<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:37+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Localization on Curved Objects Using Tactile Information</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yan-Bin</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
							<email>jia@cs.iastate.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Iowa State University Ames</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>50011-1040</postCode>
									<region>IA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Localization on Curved Objects Using Tactile Information</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>This paper offers a computational study of finger localization on 2-D curved objects using tactile data which builds on efficient numerical processing of curves. Our first algorithm localizes one rolling finger on a stationary object. It finds all boundary segments with the same arc length and total curvature computed from tactile data. The algorithm slides an imaginary segment along the object boundary by alternatively marching its two endpoints forward, stretching or contracting the segment if necessary. Through a curvature-based analysis we establish the global convergence of the algorithm to every location of such a segment and also derive the local convergence rate. The algorithm runs in time linear in the size of the discretized boundary curve domain, which is asymptotically as fast as computing the object&apos;s perimeter through numerical integration. Based on the above results, we then present a global algorithm to localize two fingers rolling on a free object. This has considerably improved over our previous local algorithm [6] using a least-squares formulation. The algorithm partitions the object boundary into segments over which related total curvature functions are monotonic. Then it combines bisection with forward marching to search for possible locations of the fingers within every pair of such segments.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>A robot grasping strategy often relies on knowledge of the exact placement of the fingers on an object. The use of tactile information combined with object geometry can facilitate the localization of the fingers relative to the object. In this paper, we investigate how one or two fingers with tactile capability can actively determine their locations on a curved object from a few contact points recorded on the fingertips.</p><p>The action taken by the fingers is rolling on the object, which is bounded by a known parametric 2-D curve with nontrivial curvature undefined at no more than a few ¡ Support for this research was provided by Iowa State University. isolated points. The kinematics of rolling together with recorded finger contacts will reduce localization to identifying curve segments on the object boundary that meet geometric requirements on arc length and total curvature.</p><p>In Section 2 we study a simple version of localization with one disk-like finger rolling on a stationary curved object. We will present a numerical algorithm with provable behavior. In Section 3 we move on to the problem of localizing two rolling fingers on a free object. The problem was studied earlier in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> but only partially solved by a leastsquares method. Built on the results in Section 2, a global algorithm is presented to find locations of both rolling fingers. Simulations will be presented in Section 4, followed by further discussions in Section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Related Work</head><p>This work is founded on contact kinematics which describe the motion of a point contact between two rigid bodies by a set of differential equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>. The special kinematics of rolling motion allow finger localization to be formulated as a purely geometric problem. <ref type="bibr">Grimson and Lozano-Pérez [5]</ref> used tactile measurements of positions and surface normals for recognition and localization of 3D polyhedra. Kriegman and Ponce <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> applied elimination theory to match curved three-dimensional objects with the shape of image contours through fitting. Rimon and Blake <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> showed how to "cage" a 2-dimensional object using two fingers but only one degree of control.</p><p>Allen and Roberts <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> deployed robot fingers to obtain a number of contact points around an object and used fitting to reconstruct the object's shape. Erdmann <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> showed that the local geometry of an object with known angular velocity can be recovered by two passive linear tactile sensors. Extending this work, Moll and Erdmann <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> applied quasi-static dynamics to reconstruct the shape of a convex object and estimate its motion from tactile readings on two palms in frictionless contact with the object.</p><p>Fischler <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> described an algorithm to locate points with extreme curvatures on planar curves and reconstruct the original curves based on these points. Mokhtarian and Mackworth <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> used inflection points (where curvatures are zero) for planar curve descriptions and matching. In the author's recent work <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, the problem of localizing two rolling fingers on a free object was presented with a least-squares solution. Nevertheless, the solution method guaranteed neither convergence nor completeness and was slow. In Section 3, we will present a global numerical algorithm to solve the same problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Localizing on a Stationary Object</head><p>We first look at how to determine the location of a finger rolling on a stationary object. Both the finger and the object can be of any shape as long as they maintain point contact. Let the object be bounded by a regular curve</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">¢ £ ¥ ¤ § ¦</formula><p>, where ¤ is the location of contact. To simplify the analysis, we assume the finger to be a disk described by¨£</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">by¨ by¨£ © " ! # $ ¦</formula><p>, where locates the contact on the disk and can be detected by its tactile sensor. See <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. Contact kinematics <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref> give the velocities of contact: </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">% ' &amp; ) (¢</formula><formula xml:id="formula_3"> £ ¥ ¤    ¦  &amp; p   w C ¢ D £ ` t u ¦ C ( t  &amp; Q (4)  £ ¥ ¤    ¦  &amp; p   w 8 £ ` t u ¦ C ¢ D £ t u ¦ C ( t  &amp;  f (5)</formula><p>Geometrically has the closed form</p><formula xml:id="formula_4"> u d © 9 © e f e £  £ @ ¤ § ¦ 6  £ `   ¦  ¦ if it is within £ I 1 h g d g i ¦</formula><p>and otherwise cannot be determined from</p><formula xml:id="formula_5"> £ @ ¤ § ¦ and  £   ¦</formula><p>alone. We need to look for numerical solutions of equations <ref type="formula">(4)</ref> and (5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Convex Boundary Curve</head><p>We begin with the case that the boundary curve </p><formula xml:id="formula_6">¢ is con- vex.</formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">¤ S X ¤ V U § T ¤ c n o f 9 f f and   S u  U §  I n o f 9 f f</formula><p>under the following rules: <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> illustrates the working of the algorithm in these two cases. For a non-unit speed curve,  </p><formula xml:id="formula_8">Case 1 l £ ¥ ¤ S ¦ h j Q q p  I r  &amp; ¤ c r 4 l £ ¥ ¤ c r s ¦ u t ¤ 9 r " v U &amp;  I r $ 1 Q f Case 2 l £ ¥ ¤ S ¦ h w Q q p  I r  &amp; ¤ c r 4 Q t  £ ¥ ¤ r " v U V  r ¦  &amp;  f</formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">s 0 t 0 s 1 s 0 t 0 t1 s 1 t1 θ a L L θ a θ b b s 0 s 0 t 0 1 s 1 s t 0 a b θ θ t1 a b L L L (a) (b)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_10"> #   u  I @     a  s  but  c   u  s s         ; (b)  9   u  s s     a    but  #   u  I s  s       .</formula><p>show by induction the following Lemma (a proof is given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>): </p><formula xml:id="formula_11">Lemma 1 In Case 1, ¤ r w q ¤ r x v U m w { holds for all  k h .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Non-Convex Boundary Curve</head><p>In this section we extend the localization procedure in Section 2.1 to an arbitrary-speed closed simple curve ¢ .  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref> illustrates the operations in the modes convex-convex and concave-convex.</p><p>Bisection will be invoked in the modes convex-concave and concave-convex. In preprocessing, we compute all points of inflection; and then in . For a detailed description of all operations, we refer the reader to <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, where the total number of numerical increments is shown to be at most  </p><formula xml:id="formula_12">£ V  G  .</formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">¥ g ¦ ' § but ¥ o ¨ ¡ © ¦ ' § . z +1 l z l z k σ( ) z k z +1 l s L t = L z k z l z l t σ ( ) −1 l+1 L s z L L (b) (a)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">µ  ¶ ¸ · ¹  º ° i  ` ² 9 ³ 9  I ² e ´ ¼ » ¤     ° i  ` ² ³ c  and  advances accordingly to ² ³ . In (b),  advances to µ  ¶ ¼ · ¹  ` ² ³ V I ° a ½ ¤  ` ² e ´ ¼ » ¤      s ° i ½ ¤  ` ² e ´ ¼ » ¤  and  advances accordingly to ² e ´ ¼ » ¤ .</formula><p>The next mode is concave-concave.</p><p>not hard to show that such a stationary point satisfies condition (4) in addition to the following condition:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">8 £ `   ¦  1 8 £ @ ¤ § ¦ &amp; p s  w 8 D £ ` $ ¦ ( ' &amp; h f<label>(6)</label></formula><p>The roles of</p><formula xml:id="formula_16"> £ ¥ ¤    ¦ , 8</formula><p>, and inflections in the marching algorithm are now replaced by</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">8 £ `   ¦ 5 1 8 £ @ ¤ § ¦ , 8 D</formula><p>, and vertices in the modified version. And the preprocessing involves computing all simple vertices n of the curve.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Localizing on a Movable Object</head><p>Now we consider that the object is no longer stationary. It moves in response to the disk rolling. We let a second identical disk with tactile capability rolling on the object, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>. Let </p><formula xml:id="formula_18">¥ V ¨ f ¦ Á § but ¥ V ¨ ¨ $ © ¦ ' § .</formula><p>except the numerators need to be replaced with the relative angular velocity . We can eliminate the object's angular velocity 2 ¾</p><p>[6]:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">% Â 1 8 £ ¥ ¤ § ¦ a C Ã D £ ¥ ¤ § ¦ C % ¤ 4 2 &amp; %  v 1 8 £   ¦ a C e Ã D £ `   ¦ C %  4 ¿ 2 g f (7)</formula><p>Let the two disks record contact positions . Integrate equation <ref type="formula">(7)</ref>  . Moreover, the arc lengths</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">over R 0 S 0 U W and R 0 S 0 n W yields  £ ¥ ¤ 9 S X ¤ V U ¦ 1  £ `   S f   U ¦  &amp;  U V (8)  £ ¥ ¤ 9 S X ¤ c n c ¦ 1  £ `   S f   I n c ¦  &amp;  n f (9)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">Q U 7 &amp;  £ @ ¤ S X ¤ V U e ¦ , Q n Y &amp;  £ @ ¤ 9 S u X ¤ c n c ¦ , Q 5 Ä &amp;  £ `   S   U e ¦</formula><p>, and  increase or both decrease. We employ an iterative procedure as illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 6</ref>.  were found by the algorithm described in Section 3. The ambiguities were eliminated with extra tactile data taken at a fourth pair of contact positions. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Domain Partitioning</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Discussion</head><p>Tactile sensing in the rolling mode reduces the localization of fingers to constraint satisfaction in multiple variables. The presented algorithms exploit curve geometry to run in time linear in the size of the discretized curve domain. This is achieved by partitioning the curve domain into intervals monotonic with respect to related functions and then by combining bisection with marching. The completeness of these algorithms distinguish themselves from a local optimization approach (based on least squares, for instance) whose success heavily relies on initial estimates.</p><p>The marching algorithm described in Section 2 can be easily generalized to find all length-Q segments on a curve, open or closed, over which the integral of a function é £ ¢ ¦ equals some constant ê . An industrial application often handles large quantities of identical parts. The precomputation of inflections and vertices is thus a one-time overhead for one part shape.</p><p>A key implementation issue is to ensure rolling contact between both fingers and the object. We are currently experimenting with one straight jaw and one passive wheel on a vertical pin.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: A disk rolling on a stationary curved object.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Two cases of marching</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Two of the four modes of the localization algorithm: (a) convex-convex, where ª F       « and ª ¡  ¬  I   i « , and its following mode (b) concave-convex, where ª ¡   e   ­ ® « and ª ¡  ¬  I    ¯ « . The function ° i    determines the ending point of a curve segment on</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Two fingers rolling on one object.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Geometrically, localization is equivalent to finding two points on ¢ at which a) the two segments of lengths Q U and Q Ä , respectively, differ by  U in total curvature, and b) the two segments of lengths Q n and Q 5 Å , respectively, differ by  n in total curvature. In the below, we will present a global numerical algorithm that finds all pairs ¤ 9 S and   S satisfying equations (8) and (9).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Iterations when both</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8: Localization of two curve segments.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>Below we present a marching algorithm that finds all curve segments on the boundary with length</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Q 

and total 
curvature 

 

. For clarity of presentation, we assume that 

¢ 

is unit-speed. But the results (including the convergence 
rate) will extend to any regular parameterization. Also we 
assume 

8 
£ 
¥ ¤ 
 § ¦ 
A j 
h 

for all 

¤ 

. Extension to 

8 
£ 
¥ ¤ 
 § ¦ 
A k 
h 

will not 
be difficult. 
Define the function 

l 
£ 
¥ ¤ 
 § ¦ 

such that 

 
£ 
¥ ¤ 

X ¤ 
4 
l 
£ 
¥ ¤ 
 § ¦ 
¦ 
m &amp; 
 

. 
Namely, 

l 
£ 
@ ¤ 
c ¦ 

is the length of the curve segment starting at 

¤ 

over which the tangent rotates by the angle 

 

. The algo-
rithm starts at location 

¤ 
S 
A &amp; 
h 

and generates two sequences 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7" validated="false"><head>Theorem 5 All segments with length Q and total curvature  can be found on a closed simple curve defined on</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>R 
h 

 
W 

up to numerical resolution in 

 
£ 
 
G 
 
¦ 

steps. 

We can directly modify the marching algorithm to find 
all stationary points of the total curvature function 

 
£ 
@ ¤ 

  
 ¦ 

over any segment of length 

Q 

along a closed curve. It is 

¤ 

A simple point of inflection satisfies 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgement</head><p>The author is grateful to the anonymous reviewers for their valuable feedback. He would also like to thank David Persky for his code used in generating cubic splines for simulation.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Haptic object recognition using a multi-fingered dextrous hand</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the IEEE Intl. Conf. on Robot. and Automat</title>
		<meeting>of the IEEE Intl. Conf. on Robot. and Automat</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="342" to="347" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the spatial motion of a rigid body with point contact</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the IEEE Intl. Conf. on Robot. and Automat</title>
		<meeting>of the IEEE Intl. Conf. on Robot. and Automat</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="686" to="695" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shape recovery from passive locally dense tactile data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Erdmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Robotics: The Algorithmic Perspective</title>
		<editor>A. K. Peters</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="132" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Locating perceptually salient points on planar curves</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fischler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Analysis and Machine Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model-based recognition and localization from sparse range or tactile data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E L</forename><surname>Grimson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lozano-Pérez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intl. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Grasping curved objects through rolling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y.-B</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the IEEE Intl. Conf. on Robot. and Automat</title>
		<meeting>of the IEEE Intl. Conf. on Robot. and Automat</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="377" to="382" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Localization and grasping of curved objects using tactile information</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y.-B</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ISU-CS-01-08</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<pubPlace>Ames, IA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>CS Dept., Iowa State University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Tech. Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On recognizing and positioning curved 3-D objects from image contours</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kriegman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ponce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Analysis and Machine Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1127" to="1137" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scale-based description and recognition of planar curves and two-dimensional shapes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mokhtarian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mackworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Analysis and Machine Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reconstructing shape from motion using tactile sensors</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Erdmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the IEEE/RSJ Intl. Conf. on Intell. Robots and Systems</title>
		<meeting>of the IEEE/RSJ Intl. Conf. on Intell. Robots and Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The kinematics of contact and grasp</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Montana</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intl. J. Robot. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Caging 2D bodies by 1-parameter two-fingered gripping systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rimon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Blake</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the IEEE Intl. Conf. on Robot. and Automat</title>
		<meeting>of the IEEE Intl. Conf. on Robot. and Automat</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1458" to="1464" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
