<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:37+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Bound Analysis of Closed Queueing Networks with Workload Burstiness</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Giuliano</forename><surname>Casale</surname></persName>
							<email>casale@cs.wm.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of William and Mary Department of Computer Science Williamsburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>23187-8795</postCode>
									<region>VA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ningfang</forename><surname>Mi</surname></persName>
							<email>ningfang@cs.wm.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of William and Mary Department of Computer Science Williamsburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>23187-8795</postCode>
									<region>VA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Evgenia</forename><surname>Smirni</surname></persName>
							<email>esmirni@cs.wm.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of William and Mary Department of Computer Science Williamsburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>23187-8795</postCode>
									<region>VA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Bound Analysis of Closed Queueing Networks with Workload Burstiness</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>C4 [Performance of Systems]: Modeling techniques General Terms Algorithms</term>
					<term>Performance</term>
					<term>Theory Keywords Queueing networks</term>
					<term>closed systems</term>
					<term>bound analysis</term>
					<term>burstiness</term>
					<term>nonrenewal service</term>
					<term>temporal dependence</term>
					<term>Markovian arrival pro- cesses</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Burstiness and temporal dependence in service processes are often found in multi-tier architectures and storage devices and must be captured accurately in capacity planning models as these features are responsible of significant performance degradations. However, existing models and approximations for networks of first-come first-served (FCFS) queues with general independent (GI) service are unable to predict performance of systems with temporal dependence in workloads. To overcome this difficulty, we define and study a class of closed queueing networks where service times are represented by Marko-vian Arrival Processes (MAPs), a class of point processes that can model general distributions, but also temporal dependent features such as burstiness in service times. We call these models MAP queueing networks. We introduce provable upper and lower bounds for arbitrary performance indexes (e.g., throughput, response time, utilization) that we call Linear Reduction (LR) bounds. Numerical experiments indicate that LR bounds achieve a mean accuracy error of 2%. The result promotes LR bounds as a versatile and reliable bounding methodology of the performance of modern computer systems.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Capacity planning of modern computer systems requires to account for the presence of nonrenewal features in workloads, such as Permission to make digital or hard copies of all or part of this work for personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGMETRICS'08, June 2-6, 2008, Annapolis, Maryland, USA. Copyright 2008 ACM 978-1-60558-005-0/08/06 ...$5.00.</p><p>short-range or long-range temporal dependence which significantly affect performance <ref type="bibr">[23-25, 31, 33]</ref>. A typical example of temporal dependence is workload burstiness, where the jobs processed by the system are not independent, e.g., the arrival of a short job is much more likely to be followed by the arrival of another short job (and vice versa for long jobs). Time-varying workloads of this type are naturally modeled as nonrenewal workloads with temporal dependence among consecutive requests.</p><p>Because of the complexity of their analysis, only small nonrenewal models based on one or two queues have been considered in the literature, mostly in matrix analytic methods research <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[28]</ref>. We address the current lack of more general modeling techniques for systems with nonrenewal workloads by introducing and analyzing a new class of closed queueing networks which can account for temporal dependence in their service processes. Our analysis enables for the first time the analytical performance evaluation of complex environments with nonrenewal workloads and immediately finds application in the capacity planning of multi-tier architectures and storage systems.</p><p>Capacity planning based on product-form queueing networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> has been extensively used in the past, since these models enjoy simple solution formulas and low computational cost of exact and approximate algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">22]</ref>. Queueing networks with general independent (GI) service <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">32]</ref> have been proposed as a solution, but although much more accurate than product-form networks, they remain insufficient for robust performance predictions if the service process is nonrenewal. That is, because they completely ignore temporal dependence between service times, they cannot be used to predict performance correctly in systems with nonrenewal workloads. This paper overcomes the limitations of existing modeling techniques by providing a bound analysis methodology for queueing networks with nonrenewal workloads. We study a class of closed queueing networks where service times are modeled by Markovian Arrival Processes (MAPs). We call these models MAP queueing networks. MAPs are a family of point processes which can easily model general distributions and nonrenewal features such as autocorrelation in service times <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[28]</ref>. Efficient fitting schemes for MAP parameterization from measurements are available, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">20]</ref>, and the resulting MAPs can approximate effectively long-range dependence <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>Because of the well-known difficulty of extending exact solution formulas outside the product-form case, we study bound analysis techniques for MAP networks. With the exception of the general ABA bounds <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[27]</ref> which provide good estimates only for very low or very high population values, no bounding techniques for nonrenewal networks exist and this is due to the lack of exact results which are usually needed to prove the bounding property. In this paper, we show that it is possible to obtain provable bounds on performance indexes also in non-product-form models.</p><p>Our nonrenewal bounds derive from the analysis of the Markov process underlying the MAP queueing network. Because of the state space explosion, its equilibrium behavior cannot be determined exactly, but we argue that it can still be bounded accurately by describing the system with "reduced" state spaces (which we call marginal state spaces). This state space transformation captures the behavior of the network conditioned on a given queue being busy or idle. The number of states in these marginal spaces grows linearly with the number of jobs in the network; thus, the proposed approach remains computationally tractable also on models with large populations. We derive exact balance equations for the equilibrium behavior of the reduced state spaces and illustrate how these formulas can be combined with linear programming <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">26]</ref> for the computation of bounds on mean value indexes. Because the number of reduced states grows linearly with the number of jobs in the network, we call these bounds Linear Reduction (LR) bounds.</p><p>The main contribution of this paper is to present a new methodology for the efficient analytic solution of queueing networks with nonrenewal workloads. This methodology automatically applies to queueing networks with renewal workloads as well. The stated contributions and outline of this work are as follows.</p><p>• We provide evidence that existing GI approximations and decomposition methods show unacceptably large errors on queueing network models with temporal dependence in the service process (Section 2).</p><p>• We define MAP queueing networks as a generalization of existing queueing networks that can model nonrenewal workloads (Section 3).</p><p>• We develop the LR bounds on performance indexes for nonrenewal MAP queueing networks that are based on a new marginal state space reduction (Sections 4 and 5).</p><p>• We present an extensive set of representative case studies showing that the LR bounds capture very well mean performance indexes such as response times or utilizations (Section 6).</p><p>We stress that MAP queueing networks are a superset of existing non-product-form networks with GI workloads. Therefore, the presented analytic methodology has a wide applicability. The LR bounds are corroborated by extensive numerical validation, where we show that they achieve a mean accuracy error of approximately 2% on a set of 10, 000 random models, promoting MAP queueing networks as versatile models of modern computer systems. We conclude the paper by outlining model generalizations and extensions in Section 7. The AMPL specification <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> of the LR bounds is available at http://www.cs.wm.edu/MAPQN/.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">PREVIOUS WORK</head><p>In Section 2.1, we review previous work on non-product-form queueing network models with FCFS queues and GI service <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. These models are the renewal specialization of the MAP queueing networks introduced in Section 3. In Section 2.2, we evaluate the applicability of approximation algorithms for models with GI service to models with nonrenewal service. Due to limited space, we point the reader to <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">22]</ref> for general background on queueing network modeling and Markov processes. Throughout this paper we assume that service time distributions are modeled by the method of phases <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Analysis of Models with Renewal Service</head><p>Closed networks of FCFS queues enjoy a product-form solution if all service times are exponentially distributed <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. If one or more servers have renewal (also called general independent (GI)) service, such as hyperexponential or Coxian <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, the product-form theory does not apply and approximate methods are used for evaluating performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</p><p>An approximation based on Markov renewal theory is developed by Reiser in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[29]</ref>. For each queue, the MVA arrival theorem <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[30]</ref> is generalized to include the coefficient of variation (CV) of the GI service process. Experiments in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref> show that this approach, although simple, is prone to large approximation errors.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[32]</ref>, Zahorjan et al. obtain an approximate mean value analysis (AMVA) by decomposition-aggregation <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. The underlying Markov process of the network is decomposed according to the active phases at the GI servers. Each partition is evaluated in isolation by Mean Value Analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[30]</ref> and the results are weighted to approximate the GI network. Validation results of the AMVA decomposition-aggregation show good accuracy.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, Eager et al. improve the results in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[29]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[32]</ref>. The response time at the GI queue used in Reiser's method is replaced by a more effective interpolation which also accounts for the response time at the other queues. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> also improves the decomposition method in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[32]</ref> and makes it compatible with the iterative AMVA framework to achieve lower computational costs on networks with several queues.</p><p>Marie's method, the diffusion approximation (DA) method, and the maximum entropy method (MEM) assume a product-form for the equilibrium state probabilities of the GI network and approximate the model accordingly <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. DA and MEM rely on formulas involving only the mean and the coefficient of variation; Marie's method is more general and uses specialized relations for Coxian distributions. Marie's method provides good accuracy in models with GI servers although its convergence properties have not been assessed <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>; DA and MEM are typically less accurate.</p><p>Finally, the Chandy-Herzog-Woo (CHW) method <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">22]</ref> replaces an arbitrary subsystem by a flow equivalent server which preserves the mean throughput of the original subsystem in each feasible state. If the subsystem includes GI servers, CHW is known to be less accurate than Marie's method <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Applicability to Nonrenewal Service</head><p>To the best of our knowledge, no results are available for analyzing closed networks with nonrenewal service, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[28]</ref> for related work in single queue systems. In this section, we establish the applicability of the methods described in Section 2.1 to closed networks with nonrenewal service.</p><p>We consider identically distributed service processes which are characterized by temporal dependence. The temporal dependence of a nonrenewal processes can be approximately modeled by the autocorrelation function ρ k which captures the similarity in magnitude of samples spaced by k lags <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. As an example, a service process can have hyperexponentially distributed samples without being necessarily renewal; that is, the usual terminology "hyperexponential service" implicitly refers to the renewal version of the process, but in general nonrenewal processes with hyperexponential distribution can be defined. These are immediately obtained by changing the order of the samples without altering their distribution, which results in temporal dependence.</p><p>A simple case of nonrenewal closed network is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig- ure 1</ref>. We use this simple model to evaluate the applicability of methods for GI queueing networks to models with nonrenewal service. Queue 1 is exponential with rate µ1 = 1; queue 2 has MAP(2) is an exponential process with rate µ 1 at queue 1, at queue 2 is a possibly nonrenewal two-phase Markovian Arrival Process (MAP(2)) <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[28]</ref>.</p><p>service <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> which can exhibit autocorrelation in service time samples and thus be a nonrenewal process. In a MAP(2), the lag-k autocorrelation ρ k geometrically decays to zero with rate 1 γ2 according to the relation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. In this example we choose γ2 = 0.75, the MAP(2) is 33% faster than the exponential queue (i.e., mean rate µ2 = 1.33), has CV = 5, and skewness 15; the process is obtained by the moment and autocorrelation matching algorithm in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The results discussed below are qualitatively similar for other models.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">ρ k = γ k 2 ` 1 − 1/CV 2 ´ /2,</formula><p>Using the model in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, we have observed that several of the methods considered in Section 2.1 cannot be applied to models with nonrenewal workloads; we distinguish two groups:</p><p>Non-applicable methods. This group includes Reiser's approximation, the AMVA methods in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">32]</ref>, Marie's method, DA, and MEM. Intuitively, these methods cannot apply for the following reasons. For the considered example, all these methods depend only on the mean, the CV, and the probability of starting service in one of the two phases. For instance, Marie's method applies corrections based on the two-phase Coxian renewal process model that is completely specified by these three parameters <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The information about the order of sampling, that is fundamental to nonrenewal service, is given only by the underlying Markov process which is not directly evaluated by these methods. Since these techniques ignore the order of sampling of the service times, they cannot account for the temporal dependence and therefore produce identical results if ρ k ≡ 0, k ≥ 1, or in the nonrenewal case ρ k 񮽙 = 0, for some k ≥ 1. Yet nonrenewal models can have performance that is extremely different from their renewal counterpart <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">25]</ref>; therefore these methods are unfit for the analysis of nonrenewal models.</p><p>Applicable methods. Decomposition-aggregation <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> can instead be used for the analysis of models with nonrenewal service. Since this method requires to evaluate all or part of the underlying Markov process, it is not limited to statistical moments of the service time distribution, but can account for changes in the phase transition rates of the MAP which result in autocorrelated samples. Decomposition-aggregation can be easily applied to the underlying process by aggregating states with identical active MAP phases; methods similar to those in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">32]</ref> can be defined based on this partitioning.</p><p>However, we have found that decomposition-aggregation can frequently exhibit severe errors if used in networks with nonrenewal service. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> show the predicted utilization of decomposition (dashed line) versus the actual utilization (solid line) for the bottleneck queue 1 in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. The actual utilization is obtained by solving the underlying Markov process by global balance, therefore it is exact. The ABA bounds, which apply to general models <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">27]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> The value γ 2 is in a MAP(2) the second largest eigenvalue of the Markov chain embedded at arrival instants <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> compared with the ABA bounds <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">27]</ref> and the decomposition-aggregation approximation <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. Although accurate in renewal models, in nonrenewal models the decomposition is often unable to capture the trend of performance indexes such as the utilization shown here. The saturation of the approximation is due to the saturation of the underlying product-form models used in the decomposition. Also the ABA bounds, which apply to general networks, are inaccurate.</p><p>are also depicted. We recall that other classes of bounds such as the popular balanced job bounds (BJB) apply only to product-form networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[22]</ref>. Although decomposition is very accurate in the renewal case, its application to the nonrenewal case results in increasingly large approximation errors for larger populations. Cases similar to the one plotted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> are easy to find for different values of the model parameters. The low quality of the results in the nonrenewal case is due to the quick saturation of the productform models used in these approximations, which reach maximum utilization for lower loads than the nonrenewal model.</p><p>The observations of this section indicate that the analysis of nonrenewal workloads cannot be performed accurately with existing techniques for models with GI service times. Due to the large approximation uncertainty and the lack of an exact product-form solution, bounding techniques are desirable. In order to address this limitation, in the following sections we introduce a bound analysis methodology for nonrenewal networks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">MAP QUEUEING NETWORKS</head><p>We introduce the class of MAP queueing networks supporting nonrenewal service which is studied in the rest of the paper. A summary of the main notation is given in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Model Definition</head><p>We consider a closed network with single-server queues, which serve jobs according to a MAP service time process and under work-conserving FCFS scheduling. The service process is independent of both the job allocation across the queues and the state of other service processes. The network is composed by M queues and populated by N statistically indistinguishable jobs (single class model), which proceed through the queues according to a stateindependent routing scheme. That is, upon departure from a server i, a job joins queue j with fixed probability pi,j. Without loss of generality, the average visit ratio at j with respect to the number of visits at queue 1 is Vj, thus V1 = 1.</p><p>The service process at queue i is modeled by a MAP with Ki ≥ 1 phases. General service can be approximated accurately by a MAP <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. If Ki = 1, then the MAP reduces to an exponential distribution, otherwise it generates service time samples that B k j states ( n, k) where j is busy in phase k C k j (i) mean queue-length of queue i within B k j ei vector of zeros with a one in the i-th position h, k, u, k * phase indexes i, j, m queue indexes</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">I k j states ( n, k) where j is idle in phase k J k j (i, h) utilization of queue i in phase h within B k j ∪ I k j ki active phase at queue i in k Ki number of phases in queue i's MAP Kmax maximum Ki, 1 ≤ i ≤ M k</formula><p>phase vector, i.e., active phases M number of queues in the network µi mean service rate of queue i µ k,h i completion rate of queue i, phase k → h N number of jobs in the network ni number of jobs at queue i in n n population vector, i.e., job allocation pi,j routing prob. from queue i to queue j π( n, k)   <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. It should be nevertheless remarked that MAP fitting can be still a challenging problem if the data has an irregular temporal dependence structure, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[20]</ref> for a review. We point to <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> for a new technique, called Kronecker Product Composition (KPC), that can provide MAP fitting of higher-order moments and temporal dependence structure of arbitrary processes. The transition from phase k to phase h for the MAP service process of queue i has rate φ k,h i and produces a service completion with probability</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">prob. of state ( n, k) π k j (ni, h) prob. of ni jobs in queue i in phase h within B k j ¯ π k j (ni, h) prob. of ni jobs in i in phase h within I k j q k,h i,j rate ( n, k) → ( n − ei + ej, k ′ ), ki = k, k ′ i = h Qi</formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">t k,h i ; if h = k then t k,k i = 1 according to the MAP definition. We define µ k,h i = t k,h i φ k,h i</formula><p>to be the rate of job completions in phase k that leave the MAP in phase h; is in row k and column h of D0. We point the reader to <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[20]</ref> and references therein for background on MAPs and MAP fitting.</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">v k,h i = (1 − t k,h i )φ k,h i , k 񮽙 = h is</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Underlying Markov Process</head><p>General MAP service requires to maintain information at the process level on the current service phase at each queue. A feasible network state in the queueing network underlying Markov process is a tuple ( n, k), where n = (n1, n2, . . . , nM ), 0 ≤ ni ≤ N , P M i=1 ni = N , describes the number of jobs in each queue, and k = (k1, k2, . . . , kM ), 1 ≤ ki ≤ Ki, specifies the active phase for each service process. According to this space, the Markov process transitions have rate q k,h i,j from state ( n, k)</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">to ( n − ei + ej, k ′ ), ki = k, k ′ i = h,</formula><p>where et is a vector of zeros with a one in the t-th position; the rate is computed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">q k,h i,j = ( pi,jµ k,h i , i 񮽙 = j, v k,h i + pi,iµ k,h i , i = j and k 񮽙 = h.<label>(1)</label></formula><p>In <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(1)</ref>, q k,h i,j is for i 񮽙 = j the rate of departures from i to j triggering a phase transition in i's service process from phase k to h; otherwise it accounts for the background transitions v k,h i and the rate of the self-looping jobs pi,iµ k,h i . Note that the case for i = j and k = h is not explicitly accounted since it corresponds to the diagonal of the infinitesimal generator of the Markov process. This diagonal is computed to make each row sum to zero.</p><p>The size of the infinitesimal generator corresponds to the cardinality of the related global balance equations and is of the order of`N+M of`of`N+M −1</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">N ´` Kmax+M −1</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Kmax´,</head><p>Kmax´ Kmax´, where Kmax is the maximum of Ki, 1 ≤ i ≤ M ; this size quickly becomes computationally prohibitive.</p><p>As a summarizing example, the MAP network in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref> with routing probabilities p1,1, p1,2, p1,3 = 1 − p1,1 − p1,2 at the first queue and p2,1 = 1, p3,1 = 1, at the remaining queues has underlying Markov process as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>. The state space description is given in the caption. For p1,1 = 0.1 and p1,2 = 0.7 the network reduces to Balbo's model used in the numerical experiments in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>; throughout the paper we illustrate some of the proposed techniques using this model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">STATE SPACE REDUCTION</head><p>General approximation techniques for non-product-form models, such as decomposition, are reviewed in Section 2. These approaches often start from the idea of applying a state space transformation to reduce model complexity. For instance, approximate lumping is used in decomposition to partition the state space into macrostates that can be evaluated in isolation <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</p><p>However, existing state space reductions introduce approximation errors that cannot be bounded in sign or in magnitude. This leaves a high degree of uncertainty on the final approximation accuracy. In this section we develop a new family of state space reductions that does not introduce any degree of approximation, while still simplifies model analysis. The proposed reduction is therefore exact, but because of several differences from exact lumping, the transformation cannot be reduced to lumping or to any method presented in previous work. <ref type="bibr">200</ref>  1 and µ 2 ≡ µ 1,1 2 , respectively; the third queue is a MAP with</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">µ 2 µ 2 µ 2 µ 2 µ 2 µ 2 µ 1 p 1,2 µ 1 p 1,2 µ 1 p 1,2 µ 1 p 1,2 µ 1 p 1,2 µ 1 p 1,2 v 1,2 3 v 1,2</formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">K 3 = 2 phases having µ k,h 3 = 0 for k 񮽙 = h, that is a MMPP(2) process.</formula><p>(002, 1) indicates that the exponential queues are idle and the MAP queue has two jobs and is in phase 1; in (110, 2), the phase 2 is the phase left active by the last served job.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Busy Condition Reduction</head><p>We introduce a state space reduction that scales linearly with the population size. We use the term "busy condition" to identify the set of states where a given queue is busy in a certain phase, which is intuitively similar to a conditional state space. For each model we generate the following O(K 2 max M 2 ) reduced state spaces with dimension O(N ) as follows.</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">DEFINITION 1 (MARGINAL STATE SPACES). Let the busy con- dition subspace B k j = {( n ′ , k ′ ) : n ′ j ≥ 1, k ′ j =</formula><p>k} be the set of states of the MAP network where queue j is busy and in phase k. The marginal state space of queue i in phase h within B k j is the state space describing the observation within B k j of queue i's queuelength while its phase is h, 1 ≤ h ≤ Ki, (the cases i = j and h = k are both considered).</p><p>Since in a non-product-form network the state of a queue implicitly depends also on the activity of the rest of the network, the marginal state spaces allow to explore in a compact way the mutual relations between any two queues i and j. A probabilistic definition of marginal state space is given later in Section 4.1.1. Two example marginal spaces for the model in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> obtained for the busy condition subspace B 1 3 are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 5</ref>. Figures 5(a)-(b) are obtained by observing the exponential queue i = 2 in its only phase h = 1 within B 1 3 . Since queue 3 is always busy in B <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> 3 , it has queue-length n3 ≥ 1 and the queue-length of queue 2 can only be n2 = 0 or n2 = 1. Note that the rate of transitions from n2 = 1 to n2 = 0 depends only on queue 2's service rate µ2; the rate from n2 = 0 to n2 = 1 depends instead on job completions at the other queues and in the original state space is equal to π(101, 1)p1,2µ1 which is unknown 2 without the equilibrium probability π(101, 1). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 5</ref>(b) similarly describes the queue-lengths of queue 3 in phase 1 within B <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> 3 , which can be only n3 = 1 or n3 = 2 since queue 3 is busy. The unknown transition rate is in this case π(101, 1)p1,3µ1.</p><p>Figure 5 clearly shows that our approach differs from an exact lumping or a decomposition-aggregation for at least three reasons: the latter techniques are applied to the entire state space and not to busy subspaces only, the aggregates are always non-overlapping <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> We henceforth assume that global balance solutions for MAP network is prohibitively expensive, therefore the equilibrium probabilities are all unknown.   <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> that are implicitly accounted for in the marginal state spaces for queue 2 and for queue 3 in phase 1 depicted in figure (b) and (d), respectively. Note that the reduction is not a lumping or a decomposition-aggregation since we are completely ignoring the transition from/to the busy condition subspace that are present in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>; also some rates would require the equilibrium probability of the state (101, 1) in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> which is unknown, and therefore the marginal state space cannot be solved in isolation.</p><p>(two busy subspaces instead can overlap, e.g., B3,1 and B2,1), and the aggregates result in a reduced state space where all rates are known so that it is later analyzed by other techniques (e.g., decomposition solves each macrostate in isolation by global balance or mean value analysis).</p><p>The main idea motivating the busy condition reduction is as follows. Even if some rates are unknown, we can obtain balance equations both for the equilibrium inside each marginal space or between the probabilities of multiple marginal spaces. We show in Section 5 how the busy condition reduction can be used to define the LR performance bounds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.1">Marginal Probabilities</head><p>The marginal probability π k j (ni, h) of having ni jobs in queue i during phase h, 1 ≤ h ≤ Ki, while queue j is busy in phase k, 1 ≤ k ≤ Kj , completely characterizes the marginal state spaces. Each marginal probability can be computed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">π k j (ni, h) = P {( n ′ , k ′ )∈B k j :n ′ i =n i ,k ′ i =h} π( n ′ , k ′ ),</formula><p>where B k j is the busy condition subspace of queue j in phase k.</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">By definition, it is π k j (ni = N, h) ≡ 0 for i 񮽙 = j, π k j (nj = 0, k) ≡ 0, π k j (nj , h) ≡ 0 for h 񮽙 = k, and π k j (nj , k) ≥ P K i h=1 π h i (nj, k) for j 񮽙 = i, nj ≥ 1.</formula><p>The last inequality follows immediately by observing that π k j (nj , k) accounts for all states in P K i h=1 π h i (nj, k) plus the states within B k j where i is idle. Because any event in the underlying Markov process involves at most two-phases and two queues, that is, source and destination queues for job departures with a possible phase transition at the source queue, the marginal probabilities π k j (ni, h) still capture all departures and phase changes in the model. Therefore, the knowledge of all π k j (ni, h)'s is sufficient to compute all mean performance indexes of interest in the original state space, including: the utilization of queue i, i.e., Ui = P K i k=1 U k i , where we denote by U k i the utilization of i in phase k, that is</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">U k i = P N nt=0 P Kt h=1 π k i (nt, h)<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where t, 1 ≤ t ≤ M , is an arbitrary queue since the summation is always equal to the probability of the busy subspace B k i ; the throughput which by the Utilization Law <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[22]</ref> is</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">X = K 1 X k=1 K 1 X h=1 M X j=1 q k,h 1,j U k 1 = U1µ1/V1,</formula><p>that is the mean rate of jobs flowing out of queue 1 assumed as reference for network completions and where µ1 denotes the mean rate of the MAP service process at queue 1; the mean queue-length of queue i is Qi = P K i k=1 Q k i , with</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">Q k i = P N n i =1 ni π k i (ni, k)<label>(3)</label></formula><p>being the mean queue-length of i in phase k. Note that these indexes are also sufficient to compute response and residence times by Little's Law, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[22]</ref>. In particular, the response time is R = N/X.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.2">Single Busy Subspace of a Single Queue</head><p>We characterize the equilibrium reached at steady state by marginal spaces. We focus on the marginal state spaces which describe a single busy subspace B k j and use the population constraint P M i=1 ni = N . Although an obvious condition, it is impossible to impose it if the state space is transformed in such a way to hide some of the ni's, as in the marginal state spaces. We therefore define a new population constraint for the busy condition subspace.</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">THEOREM 1. Define C k j (i) = P N n i =1 P K i h=1 niπ k j (ni, h),<label>(4)</label></formula><p>as the mean queue-length of i in the busy condition subspace</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">B k j , thus C k j (j) = Q k j . Then within B k j the C k j (i) sum to N U k j , i.e., P M i=1 C k j (i) = N U k j ,<label>(5)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_18">1 ≤ k ≤ Kj.</formula><p>PROOF. Using (2) and the population constraint we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">N U k j = P M i=1 ni P N nt=0 P Kt h=1 π k j (nt, h</formula><p>) and choosing the arbitrary queue t equal to i</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">N U k j = P M i=1 P N n i =1 P K i h=1 niπ k j (ni, h) = P M i=1 C k j (i).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.3">Multiple Busy Subspaces of a Single Queue</head><p>We obtain a constraint for multiple busy subspaces which resembles the global balance equations of the MAP service process considered in isolation. THEOREM 2. The utilizations of queue i in its Ki phases are in equilibrium, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">P M j=1 K i P h=1 h񮽙 =k if j=i q k,h i,j U k i = P M j=1 K i P h=1 h񮽙 =k if j=i q h,k i,j U h i ,<label>(6)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">for all 1 ≤ i ≤ M , 1 ≤ k ≤ Ki.</formula><p>PROOF. (Sketch of the proof, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> for a complete derivation.) Consider the cut separating the group of states G i k where queue i is in phase k from the complementary set of states C i k where queue i is in phase h 񮽙 = k. The outgoing probability flux from G i k is the left hand side of (6) and must be balanced at steady state by an equal incoming flow generated by the phase change transitions in C i k . This probability flux is exactly the right hand side of <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">(6)</ref>, which completes the proof.</p><p>The derived equation imposes that the MAP in isolation and the MAP observed in the busy subspaces of queue i have the same stochastic properties, which is expected if the service process of queue i is independent of the job allocation across the network and of the service processes of the other queues.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.4">Marginal Balance Conditions</head><p>Compared to the previous balances which only involve means such as queue-lengths or utilizations, the balances described in this section, called marginal balances, are more informative as they relate individual marginal probabilities.</p><p>We have found that there exists a form of partial balance between marginal state spaces, although the class of models considered in this paper is non-product-form. This new class of balances, called marginal balances, shows that MAP service imposes an equilibrium between the departure and the arrival process of queue i in groups of states belonging to different busy subspaces. Marginal balance derives from global balance, but characterizes only the set of marginal queue-length probabilities which makes it always computationally tractable. The balance is expressed as follows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>THEOREM 3 (MARGINAL BALANCE). The arrival rate at queue</head><p>i when its queue-length is ni jobs, 1 ≤ ni ≤ N − 1, is balanced by the rate of departures when the queue-length is ni + 1, that is,</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">P M j=1 j񮽙 =i P K j k=1 P K j h=1 P K i u=1 q k,h j,i π k j (ni, u) = P M j=1 j񮽙 =i P K i k=1 P K i h=1 q k,h i,j π k i (ni + 1, k),<label>(7)</label></formula><p>for all 1 ≤ i ≤ M . In the case ni = 0 the marginal balance specializes to the more informative relation</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">P M j=1 j񮽙 =i P K j k=1 P K j h=1 q k,h j,i π k j (ni = 0, u) = P M j=1 j񮽙 =i P K i k=1 q k,u i,j π k i (ni = 1, k),<label>(8)</label></formula><p>which holds for each phase u,</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">1 ≤ u ≤ Ki, with 1 ≤ i ≤ M .</formula><p>PROOF. (Sketch of the proof, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> for a complete derivation.) The statement is a consequence of the state partitioning that separates the states where i has no more than ni enqueued jobs from the states where the queue-length is at least ni + 1 jobs. Their exchanged probability flux must be balanced at steady state. The flux from the partition for states ni to the partition for state ni + 1 is equal to the rate of a job completed anywhere in the network being routed to queue i. This is the left hand side of <ref type="formula" target="#formula_23">(7)</ref>, which also accounts for all possible phases of the job's departing queue j and the destination queue i. The opposite flux from ni + 1 to ni has rate equal to the right hand side of <ref type="formula" target="#formula_23">(7)</ref>, which is the set of all possible departures from i that are not routed to i itself.</p><p>Following the proof of the marginal balance conditions, we obtain an additional balance between marginal probabilities. COROLLARY 1. Let k * , 1 ≤ k * ≤ Ki, be a phase of queue i; the following balance holds for each queue-length ni, 1 ≤ ni ≤ N − 2,</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">P M j=1 j񮽙 =i P K j k=1 P K j h=1 (q k,h j,i π k j (ni + 1, k * ) + P K i u=1 u񮽙 =k * q k,h i,j π k j (ni, u)) + P K i k=1 k񮽙 =k * q k * ,k i,i π k * i (ni + 1, k * ) = P M j=1 j񮽙 =i (q k * ,k * i,j π k * i (ni + 2, k * ) + P K i k=1 k񮽙 =k * (q k,k i,j π k i (ni + 1, k) + q k,k * i,j π k i (ni + 2, k) + P K i h=1 h񮽙 =k q k,h i,j π k i (ni + 1, k))) + P K i k=1 k񮽙 =k * q k,k * i,i π k i (ni + 1, k),<label>(9)</label></formula><p>for all 1 ≤ i ≤ M . For ni = N − 1 the balance reduces to</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">P K i k=1 k񮽙 =k * q k * ,k i,i π k * i (ni + 1, k * ) + P M j=1 j񮽙 =i P K j k=1 P K j h=1 P K i u=1 u񮽙 =k * q k,h i,j π k j (ni, u) = P M j=1 j񮽙 =i P K i k=1 k񮽙 =k * (q k,k i,j π k i (ni + 1, k) + P K i h=1 h񮽙 =k q k,h i,j π k i (ni + 1, k)) + P K i k=1 k񮽙 =k * q k,k * i,i π k i (ni + 1, k),<label>(10)</label></formula><p>for all 1 ≤ i ≤ M . PROOF. The proof follows similarly to the proof of Theorem 3 by now considering the set of states where i has no more than ni enqueued jobs except for phase k * , 1 ≤ k * ≤ Ki, where its population can be no more than ni + 1. The theorem follows imposing the equilibrium at the interface with the set of states where the marginal queue-length is at least ni + 1 and in phase k 񮽙 = k * and at least ni + 2 and in phase k * .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Idle Condition Reduction</head><p>This state space reduction can be regarded as the complementary of the busy condition reduction described in the previous section. We consider the idle condition subspace I k j where queue j is empty and the last served job has left the MAP process at j in phase k, 1 ≤ k ≤ Kj. We obtain a set of O(KmaxM 2 ) reduced state spaces with dimension O(N ) by describing the evolution within I k j of the queue-length of i during phase h, 1 ≤ h ≤ Ki. The related marginal probability function is</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">¯ π k j (ni, h) = P ( n ′ , k ′ )∈ ¯ S k j (n i ,h) π( n ′ , k ′ ),<label>(11)</label></formula><p>where the marginal space is</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">¯ S k j (ni, h) = {( n ′ , k ′ ) ∈ I k j : n ′ i = ni, k ′ i = h}, the idle subspace is I k j = {( n, k) : nj = 0, kj = k}.</formula><p>Further, by the given definitions, ¯ π k j (nj , h) ≡ 0 if nj ≥ 1 or h 񮽙 = k and similarly to the busy condition reduction π k j (nj , k) ≥ P K i h=1 ¯ π h i (nj , k) for j 񮽙 = i, nj ≥ 1. Note that from the complementarity of π k j (ni, h) and ¯ π k j (ni, h), the total state space probability is immediately obtained as</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">P K i h=1 P N n i =0 (π k j (ni, h) + ¯ π k j (ni, h)) = 1,<label>(12)</label></formula><p>for all 1 ≤ i ≤ M . Moreover, let the utilization of queue i in phase</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">h within B k j ∪ I k j be J k j (i, h) = P N n i =1 (π k j (ni, h) + ¯ π k j (ni, h)).<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where by definition the second term in the summation may be rewritten as</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">P N n i =1 ¯ π k j (ni, h) = π h i (nj = 0, k),<label>(14)</label></formula><p>which similarly to (12) relates the busy and idle reductions. Balances similar to those given for the busy condition reduction can be derived for the idle time reduction. For instance, following the proof of (5) one immediately obtains the population constraint</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">P M i=1 ¯ C k j (i) = N ¯ π k j (nj = 0, k),<label>(15)</label></formula><p>where ¯ π k j (nj = 0, k) is the probability of I k j and</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">¯ C k j (i) = P N n i =1 P K i h=1 ni ¯ π k j (ni, h)<label>(16)</label></formula><p>is the mean queue-length of i in phase h within I k j . The balance equations obtained for the idle reduction are often redundant with the balances of the busy ones. Therefore, we are not interested in developing a comprehensive characterization of this reduction. We point out two relations deriving from manipulations of the global balance equations which characterize B k j ∪ I k j where j is in phase k; these formulas cannot be expressed within the probability space of the busy subspace only.</p><p>THEOREM 4. The sum of mean queue-lengths during the subspace</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">B k i ∪ I k i satisfies P M t=1 (C j k (t) + ¯ C j k (t)) ≥ N P K i h=1 J k j (i, h),<label>(17)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_36">for all 1 ≤ i ≤ M , 1 ≤ j ≤ M , 1 ≤ k ≤ Kj . PROOF. Letting P B k j ∪I k j ≡ P ( n, k)∈B k j ∪I k j , we have N P B k j ∪I k j π( n, k) = P M t=1 P B k j ∪I k j ntπ( n, k) = P M t=1 ( P B k j ntπ( n, k) + P I k j ntπ( n, k)) = P M t=1 (C j k (t) + ¯ C j k (t)),</formula><p>where the last passage follows by definition of C j k (t) and ¯ C j k (t) as mean queue-lengths in B k j and I k j . Starting from the same term we also have</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">N P B k j ∪I k j π( n, k) ≥ N P K i h=1 J k j (i, h)</formula><p>since the utilization of any queue i, 1 ≤ i ≤ M , during B k j ∪ I k j cannot be greater than the sum of the probabilities of all states of</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">B k j ∪ I k j .</formula><p>THEOREM 5. The performance indexes in busy and idle subspaces are related by the following equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">P K i h=1, h񮽙 =k P M j=1 q k,h i,j Q k i + P M j=1, j񮽙 =i P K i h=1 q h,k i,j U h i = P M j=1, j񮽙 =i P K j h=1 P K j u=1 q h,u j,i J k i (j, h) + P K i h=1, h񮽙 =k P M j=1 q h,k i,j Q h i ,<label>(18)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_40">for all 1 ≤ i ≤ M , 1 ≤ k ≤ Ki.</formula><p>PROOF. (Sketch of the proof, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> for a complete derivation.) The proof follows similarly to that of Theorem 2 by weighting the contribution of each group of states by ni. We point to the technical report <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> for an extensive derivation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">LINEAR REDUCTION BOUNDS</head><p>We obtain the LR bounds using the results for the busy and the idle condition reductions. We determine the values of the marginal probabilities</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">π = {π k j (ni, h), ∀ i, j, k, h, ni} ∪ {¯ π k j (ni, h), ∀ i, j, k, h, ni} fmin = min f (π)</formula><p>subject to: /* preliminary definitions */ eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">(2)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_15">(3)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_16">(4)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(13)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(16)</ref>;</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">C k j (j) = Q k j ; π k j (nj, k) ≥ P K i h=1 π h i (nj , k), if nj ≥ 1, i 񮽙 = j; π k j (nj, k) ≥ P K i h=1 ¯ π h i (nj , k), if nj ≥ 1, i 񮽙 = j; π k j (nj, h) = 0, if nj = 0; π k j (nj, h) = 0, if h 񮽙 = k; π k j (ni, h) = 0, if ni = N , i 񮽙 = j; ¯ π k j (nj, h) = 0, if nj ≥ 1; /* exact characterization */</formula><p>eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_17">(5)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">(6)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_23">(7)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_24">(8)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_26">(9)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(10)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(15)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(17)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(18)</ref>; /* reduction constraints */ eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(12)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(14)</ref>; so that the linear function f (π) is a bound on a performance metric fexact ≡ f (πexact), where πexact is the set of exact equilibrium probabilities of the MAP network. In the case of lower bounds fmin ≤ fexact, the values of the marginal probabilities in π can be determined using linear programming <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> as follows. The last proposition generalizes immediately if the linear program is reformulated to compute an upper bound (LR Upper Bound) fmax = max f (π) ≥ f (πexact); therefore the same constraints in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref> can be used both for upper and lower bounds and only the objective function has to be modified.</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">/* feasibility of results */ π k j (ni, h) ≥ 0, for all π k j (ni, h) ∈ π. ¯ π k j (ni, h) ≥ 0, for all ¯ π k j (ni, h) ∈ π.</formula><p>The accuracy of the LR bounds is validated in the Section 6. The computational costs of the LR technique are indeed feasible for practical applications, e.g., we have solved the linear program for a model with 10 MAP(2) queues and N = 50 jobs using an interior point solver in approximately four minutes; for N = 100 the solution of the same model is found in approximately ten minutes suggesting good scalability. In general, the complexity of computing bounds with the linear program in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref> grows as O(lp(M 2 Kmax + M N, K 2 max M 2 N )), where lp(r, c) is the computational cost of solving a linear program with r rows and c columns. The number of rows is either dominated by the number of possible marginal balances for the case ni ≥ 1 that is O(M N ) or by the number of inequalities <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(17)</ref>    <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 2</ref> compares the number of states in the marginal state spaces with the original state space size in models with larger population and number of queues. The reduced spaces have cardinality that can be several orders of magnitude smaller than the original state space.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Discussion</head><p>The balances obtained in the Section 4 provide a rich characterization of the underlying Markov process of the MAP network. However, the number of exact relations remains much smaller than the number of the marginal probabilities π k j (ni, h) and ¯ π k j (ni, h). We stress that our exact characterization is in general underdetermined and describes a family of possible equilibria for the underlying Markov process, among which we cannot distinguish the real one. The linear programming approach allows to select the equilibrium that provides a worst-case or best-case bound on a given performance metric.</p><p>Because of the complexity of the feasibility region described by (2)-(18), it is also very hard to establish the relative importance of each equation with respect to the others, as well as determining analytical linear independence conditions among the balance equations. In our experiments, we have frequently observed that removing either equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_23">(7)</ref> or <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(18)</ref> reduces significantly the quality of the bounds. Conversely, we have found that (9) and (10) improve accuracy only on certain models. Standard sensitivity analysis of linear programs <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> may be used as a tool for investigating the relative importance of a certain balance for the model under study in order to minimize the size of the linear program.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">ACCURACY VALIDATION</head><p>We assess the accuracy of the LR bounds using the following methodology. We use both randomly-generated models and representative case studies, see <ref type="table">Table 3</ref> for a description of the employed input parameters. In order to assess the accuracy of the LR bounds, we evaluate their maximal relative error with respect to the exact solution of the MAP network computed by global balance. Due to the state space explosion, the experimentation using exact global balance solutions is often prohibitive for MAP networks with more than three queues and population N ≥ 100. Given its mean, CV, skewness, and autocorrelation decay rate γ2, a MAP(2) is generated using the exact moment and autocorrelation matching formulas in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.  <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>: Input parameters used in the validation study.</p><p>For each model, we use the linear program in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref> to compute upper and lower limits Xmax and Xmin on the mean throughput f (π) = X. Then, using Little's Law we get the response time bounds Rmin = N/Xmax and Rmax = N/Xmin which are used to compute absolute relative errors from the exact response time R. We do not report errors on other measures due to lack of space, but we remark that they are typically in the same range as those of response time. We used the GNU Linear Programming Kit <ref type="bibr">[19]</ref> to solve the linear program on an Intel Xeon 3.73Ghz using an AMPL specification <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> of the linear program in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref>. The AMPL specification is available for download at <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Random Models</head><p>In order to evaluate the general quality of the LR bounds, we evaluate 10, 000 random models. The models are generated according to the specifications in <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>. Each random model is solved for all feasible populations and the following absolute value of the maximal relative error is computed</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">∆ bnd = max N ˛ ˛ ˛ ˛ R bnd (N ) − Rexact(N ) Rexact(N ) ˛ ˛ ˛ ˛ ,</formula><p>where Rexact(N ) is the response time of the exact solution computed for the network considered with population N and R bnd (N ) is the LR bound evaluated with the same population, either Rmax(N ) or Rmin(N ). We stress that the ∆ error function is a conservative estimator since it returns the maximum error of R bnd over all evaluated populations. The converge of the bounds to the exact asymptotic value is not accounted by this metric and only the worst case error is measured. We see that the variability in the routing matrix makes it possible to evaluate different levels of balancing in the mean service demand at the queues. <ref type="table">Table 4</ref> indicates that the proposed bounds perform extremely well also for this class of models. The mean error is 1 − 2% for both bounds with a standard deviation of 0.02; the median is less than the mean, indicating that the asymmetry of the error distribution is more concentrated on small errors. The maximum error is found to be 14.2% for the response time upper  <ref type="table">Table 4</ref>: Results of Random Experiments Absolute maximal relative error (0 ≡ 0%, 1 ≡ 100%) over 10, 000 random queueing networks for the response time R = N/X (R min =lower LR bound, Rmax=upper LR bound). E.g., the mean of the error ∆ is 1.3% for Rmax and 2.2% for R min .</p><p>bound and 12.6% for the lower bound. We have inspected carefully these cases and found that models with more than 10% error in at least one of the two bounds account for only the 1% of the total number of experiments. The burstiness in these cases increases the response times at the autocorrelated station in a way that cannot be easily captured. Furthermore, the lower bound seems to be more sensitive to increased variability and autocorrelation than the upper bound, where the worst case error is for a MAP with moderate burstiness. The difference in sensitivity to MAP parameters is a positive property of the LR bounds, because large inaccuracies in one bound can be compensated by the relative accuracy of the other. Detailed numerical sensitivity of the two bounds with respect to the model parameters supporting these intuitions is discussed in the next subsection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Representative Case Studies</head><p>We consider six representative case studies illustrating the accuracy properties of the LR bounds; the results presented in this sections are typical of the actual bound accuracy as we have shown in the random model validation section.</p><p>Depending on the experiment, the MAP can be either an Erlang-2 (E2), a renewal two-phase hyperexponential (H2), a Poisson process (M ), or a nonrenewal MAP(2) (M AP ). As we show in Case 3, the bounding is more difficult for increasing values of CV; therefore we consider the E2 process with CV &lt; 1 only in Case 1. To focus on the effects on accuracy of the most important moments (i.e., mean and CV), we also fix in the case studies the skewness to 30. In the random experiments, we have spanned all feasible skewness values for the considered MAPs (range <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr">250]</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.1">Case 1: Sensitivity to Renewal and Nonrenewal Service Processes</head><p>The network is composed by two queues in series. The service process can be E2, M , H2 or M AP . For all processes, the mean rate is µ1 = 1 at the bottleneck queue 1, µ2 = 2 at the nonbottleneck queue 2. The MAP has CV = 5 and autocorrelation decay rate (γ2 = 0.5); the H2 has the same moments of the MAP, but being renewal ρ k ≡ 0, for all lags k ≥ 1.</p><p>Results. <ref type="table">Table 5</ref> reports the maximal relative error on response times for all possible combinations of service processes. It is found that: (1) nonrenewal models are significantly more difficult to evaluate than renewal models, e.g., on the most difficult renewal case, the H2/H2 model, the LR bounds progressively converge to the exact as N increases, while on the MAP/MAP case the error remains at 10% also for N = 100; (2) hyper-exponential CVs are typically more difficult to approximate than hypo-exponential CVs; (3) the error of Rmin is no greater than 4% and is quite insensitive to the service process type; (4) Rmax is more sensitive to nonrenewal service where it achieves a worst-case error of 11%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.2">Case 2: Sensitivity to Network Routing</head><p>We evaluate the impact on accuracy of network routing, showing the counter-intuitive fact that nonrenewal balanced networks are difficult to approximate. We consider the three queue model in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref> with the mean service rates considered in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, i.e., µ1 = 1/0.028, µ2 = 1/0.04, and µ3 = 1/0.28. We evaluate the accuracy of the LR response time bounds in the case where the network is perfectly balanced (p1,1 = 0.2, p1,2 = 0.7, p1,1 = 0.1), partially unbalanced (i.e., queue 3 is bottleneck, queue 1 and queue 2 are balanced, p1,1 = 0.1, p1,2 = 0.7, p1,1 = 0.2, this case corresponds to Balbo's model in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>), or unbalanced (queue 3 is bottleneck, queue 2 is slower than queue 1, p1,1 = 0.33, p1,2 = 0.33, p1,3 = 0.34). The MAP queue 3 has CV = 4 and γ2 = 0.5.   Results. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 7</ref> shows the LR bounds on response times and queue 3 utilization in the balanced and partially unbalanced cases; the utilization bounds follows immediately from the response time bounds by Little's Law and the Utilization Law <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[22]</ref> and are useful to evaluate the LR bound accuracy as a function of the bottleneck queue congestion level. We have found that the unbalanced case is extremely similar to the partially unbalanced and therefore is not plotted. It is found that: (1) the LR bounds of both utilization and response times are very close to the exact value on most populations; (2) both bounds progressively converge to the asymptotic exact, a feature that is not always found in standard bounds for queueing networks (e.g., the ABA lower utilization bound never converges asymptotically if M ≥ 2); (3) the slower asymptotic convergence in the balanced case makes the approximation more challenging, but the maximal error remains less than 11% of response time and 12% of bottleneck utilization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.3">Case 3: Sensitivity to Service Variability and Autocorrelations</head><p>We consider the nonrenewal MAP/MAP model in the last row of <ref type="table">Table 5</ref> and we vary the CV and the autocorrelation decay rate γ2 for the two identical MAPs.</p><p>Results. <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">Table 6</ref> reports the maximal relative error on response times. It is found that: (1) the error of Rmin is loosely sensitive to CV and γ2; (2) the error of Rmax is proportional to both CV and γ2, but decreases with the population size; (3) the maximum error of Rmax (13%) is compensated by the minimum error of Rmin (0%). Note that the errors are higher than in the random models since we are now considering two MAPs instead of one.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.4">Case 4: Applicability to Real Workloads</head><p>We illustrate the applicability to real workloads evaluating the model in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref> using Balbo's partially unbalanced configuration (p1,1 = 0.1, p1,2 = 0.7, p1,1 = 0.2) and considering at queue 3 the nonrenewal MMPP(16) fitted in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> from the classic long-range-dependent (LRD) Bellcore-pAug89 trace of <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[23]</ref>. This trace is often considered in the literature as representative of many long-range dependent processes found in modern computer, communication, and multimedia systems. We scale the mean of the MMPP(16) so that µ3 = 1/0.28; CV, skewness and autocorrelations are unchanged (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> for details on this MMPP(16) and its autocorrelations ρ k ).</p><p>Results. <ref type="table" target="#tab_11">Table 7</ref> illustrates results for different populations. We consider N = 50 instead of N = 100 because global balance    <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> by a MMPP(16). Absolute value of the maximal relative error (0 ≡ 0%, 1 ≡ 100%) on the response time R = N/X for the network in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref> with the MMPP(16) at queue 3 (∆ min =lower bound error, ∆max=upper bound error).</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">N = 10 N = 25 N = 100 CV γ 2 ∆ min ∆max ∆ min ∆max ∆ min ∆max 2</formula><p>is prohibitively expensive in the second case. The results indicate that: (1) the maximal error is of 5% and the accuracy improves with the population size. This result is consistent with the accuracy levels in the other case studies and indicates the applicability of the LR bounds also with models of real workloads; (2) because of the large order of the MMPP, the experiment also illustrates the low sensitivity of accuracy to changes in the number of phases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.5">Case 5: Sensitivity to Multiple MAP Queues</head><p>We consider a closed network with three queues in series. The mean service rate at queue i is µi = i. Service is either exponential or MAP(2) with CV = 4 and γ2 = 0.5. During the i-th experiment, 0 ≤ i ≤ 3, the first i queues are exponential, while the remaining M − i are MAP <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>.</p><p>Results. <ref type="table">Table 8</ref> reports results of the four experiments. It is found that: (1) the worst case error of 11% is achieved when all three queues are MAP(2); (2) both LR bounds are sensitive to the increase in the number of MAP queues; (3) with zero or one MAP <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">(2)</ref> the bounds yet converge asymptotically to the exact value; (4) the same conclusion is not immediate for the other cases, but computing Rmin and Rmax for N = 250, 500 reveals (not shown in the table) that at N = 250 the gap between the bounds is Rmax/Rmin− 1 ≈ 11%, while for N = 500 it drops to ≈ 6% suggesting convergence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.6">Case 6: Sensitivity to Network Size</head><p>In general, we have observed that for large models with dense routing matrices the linear constraining of the inevitably very small marginal probabilities may lead to numerically difficult problems.  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref>. The unbalanced case (not depicted) is qualitatively similar to the partially unbalanced, but shows a quicker convergence to the saturation.   In these cases, interior point algorithms perform better than the simplex algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, but the numerical corrections of the linear solver can inflate computational times. However, if the model is large and the routing is sparse, the numerical conditioning is usually much improved, and models up to 15-20 queues and hundreds of jobs can be evaluated efficiently.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MAPs</head><p>In this example, we study a distributed system composed by a farm of J Web servers. Each Web server serves directly static object requests (e.g., pictures) and communicates with a local database for the generation of HTML pages. Each local subsystem of Web server and database server is modeled as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">Figure 8</ref> similarly to the model of a real J2EE Web application defined and validated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[21]</ref>. We use the values found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[21]</ref> for the parameterization of the service times at the Web servers (µ −1 W S = 12.98ms), at the DB servers (µ −1 DB = 10.64ms), and for the local communication (µ −1 W S−DB−Comm = 1.12ms). The ratio between static object requests and Web pages requests is set to 9.15 : 1 as measured in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. We fix the routing probability from the communication link to each subsystem to 1/J. We use the median file size measured in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> which is approximately three packets. The mean, variance, skewness and lag-1 autocorrelation of inter-arrival times between packets is set as in the real workload used in Section 6.2.4. With these parameters, the fitted MAP at the communication links is a MAP(2) with rates v 1,2 Net = 0.8074, v 2,1 Net = 0.2107, µ 1,1 Net = 14.5809, µ 1,2 Net = 0.0, µ 2,1 Net = 0.0, and µ 2,2 Net = 131.7814.</p><p>Results. Since, due to the state space explosion, exact global balance solutions are prohibitive for M ≥ 4, we report in <ref type="table" target="#tab_15">Table  9</ref> the relative gap Rmax/Rmin − 1 between LR upper and lower response time bounds for different value of J. According to the model definition, the number of queues M is equal to 3J +1, where the additional queue is representative of inbound/outbound traffic. As J increases, there is little impact on the accuracy of the method which remains acceptable on all populations. In particular, as the population increases the error decreases below 10% on models with large populations.</p><p>To summarize, we have provided numerical evidence that the LR bounds provide accurate estimates using an extensive set of experiments. Sensitivity analysis to the different parameters has been conducted to identify the major sources of inaccuracy for the LR bounds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">CONCLUSIONS AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>Recent workload characterizations have shown that nonrenewal service processes are good abstractions of real systems' workloads, especially of those found in storage systems and Web servers <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">31]</ref>. We have shown that existing queueing network models, which always consider renewal service processes and do not account for nonrenewal features such as autocorrelation in service times, grossly overestimate or underestimate actual system performance.</p><p>We have presented a solution to this problem by studying a new class of MAP closed networks that supports nonrenewal service. We have introduced a class of exact state space reductions that are  Relative gap Rmax/R min − 1 of upper and lower bounds (0 ≡ 0%, 1 ≡ 100%) on the response time R = N/X (R min =lower bound, Rmax=upper bound).</p><p>computationally tractable and allow the efficient computation of upper and lower linear reduction (LR) bounds on arbitrary MAP network performance indexes, such as utilizations, throughputs, response times, and queue-lengths. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first time that bounds for queueing networks with MAP service are obtained. The LR bounds AMPL specification together with additional resources on MAP queueing networks are available at http://www.cs.wm.edu/MAPQN/. Experiments indicate that the LR bounds are extremely accurate, showing on average a 2% relative error on the response time with a maximum error of 14% (for 99% of the random models the maximum error is also found to be less than 10%). We also remark that if the objective function f used in the program in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref> is a nonlinear function of π, our result immediately generalizes to the nonlinear case provided that the results are global optima.</p><p>An important extension of this work is the optional inclusion of delay servers into the MAP network. Since the service rates of a delay are load-dependent, this requires a generalization of our work to the load-dependent case. It may be also interesting to extend the presented class of MAP networks to include additional scheduling disciplines or multiclass workloads in order to fully subdue the class of product-form queueing networks. Finally, it may be interesting to compare our bounds with standard diffusion or asymptotic approximations.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Example model with nonrenewal service. The service</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 : Exact global balance solution of the nonrenewal model in</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Exact global balance solution of the nonrenewal model in Figure 1 compared with the ABA bounds [22, 27] and the decomposition-aggregation approximation [13]. Although</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>mean queue-length at queue i Q k i mean queue-length at queue i in phase k Ui mean utilization of queue i U k i mean utilization of queue i in phase k v k,h i background trans. rate of queue i, phase k → h Vi mean visit ratio at queue i (V1 = 1) X mean throughput (measured at queue i = 1)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the complementary rate of tran- sitions not associated with job completions that only change the MAP active phase (background transitions). In this representation of queue i's MAP, µ k,h i is the element in row k and column h of the D1 matrix; v k,h i</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 : Example network composed by two exponential queues and a MAP queue.</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Example network composed by two exponential queues and a MAP queue. In the case where the MAP is a renewal two-phase hyperexponential process, this reduces to Balbo's model considered in the validation of approximations for GI service [8].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 : Underlying Markov process of the network in Fig- ure 3 in the simple case when the MAP is a MMPP( 2 ) process; the job population is N = 2 .</head><label>422</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Underlying Markov process of the network in Figure 3 in the simple case when the MAP is a MMPP(2) process; the job population is N = 2. Two queues are exponential with rates µ 1 ≡ µ 1,1 1 and µ 2 ≡ µ 1,1 2 , respectively; the third queue is a MAP with K 3 = 2 phases having µ k,h</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 : Example of marginal state spaces for the model in Figure 4 .</head><label>54</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Example of marginal state spaces for the model in Figure 4. Figures (a) and (c) show the observation of either queue 2 or queue 3 in phase 1 during the busy subspace B 1 3 of queue 3 in phase 1. The dashed ovals indicate states in the original state space in Figure 4 that are implicitly accounted for in the marginal state spaces for queue 2 and for queue 3 in phase 1 depicted in figure (b) and (d), respectively. Note that the reduction is not a lumping or a decomposition-aggregation since we are completely ignoring the transition from/to the busy condition subspace that are present in Figure 4; also some rates would require the equilibrium probability of the state (101, 1) in Figure 4 which is unknown, and therefore the marginal state space cannot be solved in isolation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 : Linear program determining a lower bound on an arbitrary linear performance</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Linear program determining a lower bound on an arbitrary linear performance index fexact = f (πexact). For instance, fexact can be either a mean index such as a throughput or a more detailed descriptor such as a marginal probability π k j (n i , h).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>PROPOSITION 1 (</head><label>1</label><figDesc>LR LOWER BOUND). The program in Fig- ure 6 returns a lower bound fmin ≤ f (πexact). PROOF. All the relations in the linear program are exact as we have proved in the previous sections; therefore π = π exact is a feasible solution. Since linear programming always returns an op- timum min f (π) = min{f (π) | feasible π}, we conclude that min f (π) ≤ f (π exact ) because π exact is a fea- sible value of π.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>5 : Case 1 -Sensitivity to Renewal/Nonrenewal Service Processes.</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Absolute value of the maximal relative error (0 ≡ 0%, 1 ≡ 100%) on the response time R = N/X of two queues networks (∆ min =lower bound error, ∆max=upper bound error).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Case 2 -Sensitivity to Network Routing. Analysis of utilization and response time in the balanced and partially unbalanced cases of the network in Figure 3. The unbalanced case (not depicted) is qualitatively similar to the partially unbalanced, but shows a quicker convergence to the saturation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>8 : Case 5 -</head><label>85</label><figDesc>Sensitivity to Multiple MAP Queues. Absolute value of the maximal relative error (0 ≡ 0%, 1 ≡ 100%) on the response time R = N/X for the MAP/MAP network in Table 5 (∆ min =lower bound error, ∆max=upper bound error). The notation k/3, k = 0, 1, 2, 3, used in the MAPs column indicates the number of nonexponential MAPs used in the model; the remaining M − k queues have exponential service.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 8 : Case 6: Distributed Web System.</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8: Case 6: Distributed Web System. Web farm composed by J Web servers. Bursty inbound/outbound traffic is modeled by a MAP server with temporal dependent service. Incoming requests are dispatched to a given Web server with fixed probability 1/J.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Summary of main notation 

are phase-type (PH) distributed [28]. That is, hyperexponential, 
hypoexponential, Erlang, and Coxian are all allowed service time 
distributions; nonrenewal service is also supported, e.g., Markov 
Modulated Poisson Process (MMPP), Interrupted Poisson Process 
(IPP) </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>which grows as O(M 2 Kmax);</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>total states 
total states 
M 
N 
Kmax 
marginal spaces original space 
3 
50 
2 
1.84 · 10 3 
5.30 · 10 3 
3 
100 
2 
3.64 · 10 3 
2.06 · 10 4 
3 
200 
2 
7.24 · 10 3 
8.12 · 10 4 
5 
50 
2 
5.10 · 10 3 
1.27 · 10 6 
5 
100 
2 
1.01 · 10 4 
1.84 · 10 7 
5 
200 
2 
2.01 · 10 4 
2.80 · 10 8 
10 
50 
2 
2.04 · 10 4 
5.03 · 10 10 
10 100 
2 
4.04 · 10 4 
1.71 · 10 13 
10 200 
2 
8.04 · 10 4 
7.04 · 10 15 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>State Space Reduction Effectiveness. Comparison of the 

total number of states in the marginal state spaces with the original state 
space of the queueing network. All queues have MAP service times with 
Kmax phases. The number of states in the marginal state spaces grows 
linearly in the population size, whereas the growth for the original state 
space is combinatorial. 

the number of columns is O(K 2 
max M 2 N ) because the cardinality 
of π is upper bounded by 2K 2 
max M 2 N . 
To appreciate the reduction of the state space, </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><head>Network Param .</head><label>Param</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Case Studies 
Random Models 
M 
2 − 3 
3 
pi,j 
variable 
random [0, 1] 
N 
10, 25, 100 
all in [10, 1000] 
# of nonren. MAPs 
1, 2, 3 
1 
MAP(2) Param. 
Case Studies 
Random Models 
mean 
variable 
random [0, 1] 
CV 
0.5, 2, 4, 8 
random [0.5, 10] 
skewness 
30 
random [2, 250] 
γ2 
[.00, .99] 
random [.00, .99] 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8" validated="false"><head>Table</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10" validated="false"><head>Table 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Case 3 -Sensitivity to Burstiness and Autocorrelations. 

Absolute value of the maximal relative error (0 ≡ 0%, 1 ≡ 100%) on the 
response time R = N/X for a MAP/MAP network (∆ min =lower bound 
error, ∆max=upper bound error). 

N ∆ min ∆max 
1 
0.00 
0.00 
2 
0.05 
0.03 
10 
0.03 
0.02 
25 
0.01 
0.01 
50 
0.00 
0.01 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11" validated="false"><head>Table 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Case 4 -Applicability to Real LRD Workloads. We 

use the Bellcore-Aug89 trace [23] fitted in </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13" validated="false"><head>Table</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15" validated="false"><head>Table 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Case 6 -Sensitivity to Network Size. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> v 1,2 3 v 2,1 3 v 2,1 3 v 2,1 3 µ 1 p 1,3 µ 1 p 1,3 3 µ 1,1 3 µ 1,1 µ 1 p 1,3 µ 1 p 1,3 3 µ 2,2 3 µ 2,2 µ 1 p 1,3 3 µ 1,1 µ 1 p 1,3 3 µ 2,2 Busy condition subspace of queue 3 in phase 1 Busy condition subspace of queue 3 in phase 2</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgement</head><p>This work was supported by the National Science Foundation under grants ITR-0428330 and CNS-0720699. The authors thank Gianfranco Balbo, Jeff Buzen, Larry Dowdy, Giuseppe Serazzi, Murray Woodside, Qi Zhang, and the SIGMETRICS reviewers for detailed comments which greatly helped in improving the quality of this paper.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Markovian approach for modeling packet traffic with long-range dependence</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE JSAC</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="719" to="732" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Web server workload characterization: The search for invariants</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Arlitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ACM SIGMETRICS</title>
		<meeting>of ACM SIGMETRICS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="137" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Workload characterization of the 1998 world cup web site. TR HPL-1999-35R1, HP Labs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Arlitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marked point processes as limits of Markovian arrival streams</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Asmussen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Koole</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. App. Prob</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="372" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open, closed, and mixed networks of queues with different classes of customers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Baskett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chandy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Muntz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Palacios</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="260" />
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction to Linear Optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bertsimas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tsitsiklis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Athena</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Queueing Networks and Markov Chains</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bolch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Greiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>De Meer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Trivedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of service-time variability in a closed network of queues</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bondi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Whitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perf. Eval</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="234" />
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Bound analysis of closed queueing networks with nonrenewal workloads</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Casale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Smirni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>TR WM-CS-2008-03</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>College of William and Mary</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An efficient algorithm for the exact analysis of multiclass queueing networks with large population sizes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Casale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of joint ACM SIGMETRICS/IFIP Performance</title>
		<meeting>joint ACM SIGMETRICS/IFIP Performance</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="180" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Interarrival Times Characterization and Fitting for Markovian Traffic Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Casale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Smirni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>TR WM-CS-2008-02</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>College of William and Mary</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parametric analysis of queueing networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chandy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Herzog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Woo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IBM J. Res. Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decomposability, instabilities, and saturation in multiprogramming systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Courtois</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">CACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="371" to="377" />
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Statistical Analysis of Series of Events</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A W</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1966" />
			<publisher>John Wiley and Sons</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<ptr target="http://www.cs.wm.edu/MAPQN/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MAP Queueing Networks Webpage</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AMVA techniques for high service time variability</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Eager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sorin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Vernon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ACM SIGMETRICS</title>
		<meeting>of ACM SIGMETRICS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="228" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Markov-Modulated Poisson Process (MMPP) cookbook</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Meier-Hellstern</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perf. Eval</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">AMPL -A Modeling Language for Mathematical Programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fourer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kernighan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Markovian modeling of real data traffic: Heuristic phase type and MAP fitting of heavy tailed and fractal like samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Horváth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Telek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Performance Evaluation of Complex Systems: Techniques and Tools, IFIP Performance 2002</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2459</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="405" to="434" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance modeling and evaluation of large-scale J2EE applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kounev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Buchmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the 29th International Conference of the Computer Measurement Group (CMG)</title>
		<meeting>of the 29th International Conference of the Computer Measurement Group (CMG)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="283" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quantitative System Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lazowska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zahorjan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sevcik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the self-similar nature of ethernet traffic</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Leland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Taqqu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Willinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM T. Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long range dependence and heavy tail distributions (special issue)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perf. Eval</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2-3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance impacts of autocorrelated flows in multi-tiered systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Riska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Smirni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Riedel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perf. Eval</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1082" to="1101" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New linear program performance bounds for closed queueing networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Morrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Discrete Event Dynamic Systems: Theory and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="317" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymptotic properties of closed queueing network models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Muntz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Ann. Princeton Conf. on Inf. Sci. and Sys</title>
		<meeting>Ann. Princeton Conf. on Inf. Sci. and Sys</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="348" to="352" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Neuts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Structured Stochastic Matrices of M/G/1 Type and Their Applications. Marcel Dekker</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A queueing network analysis of computer communication networks with window flow control</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE T. Comm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1199" to="1209" />
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mean-value analysis of closed multichain queueing networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lavenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="312" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-range dependence at the disk drive level</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Riska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Riedel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 3rd Conf. on Quantitative Eval. of Systems (QEST)</title>
		<meeting>of 3rd Conf. on Quantitative Eval. of Systems (QEST)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="50" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A decomposition approach to modelling high service time variability</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zahorjan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lazowska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Garner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perf. Eval</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance-Guided Load (Un)Balancing Under Autocorrelated Flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Riska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Smirni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE T. on Parall. and Distrib. Sys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="652" to="665" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
