<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Enabling Contribution Awareness in an Overlay Broadcasting System</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yu-Wei</forename><surname>Sung</surname></persName>
							<email>sungy@purdue.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Purdue University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Bishop</surname></persName>
							<email>bishopma@purdue.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Purdue University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sanjay</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
							<email>sanjay@purdue.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Purdue University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Enabling Contribution Awareness in an Overlay Broadcasting System</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>C24 [Computer- Communication Networks]: Distributed Systems General Terms: Algorithms</term>
					<term>Design</term>
					<term>Experimentation Keywords: Overlay multicast</term>
					<term>Multi-tree</term>
					<term>Incentive</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We consider the design of bandwidth-demanding broadcasting applications using overlays in environments characterized by hosts with limited and asymmetric bandwidth, and significant heterogeneity in outgoing bandwidth. Such environments are critical to consider to extend the applicability of overlay multicast to mainstream Internet environments where insufficient bandwidth exists to support all hosts, but have not received adequate attention from the research community. We leverage the multi-tree framework and design heuristics to enable it to consider host contribution and operate in bandwidth-scarce environments. Our extensions seek to simultaneously achieve good utilization of system resources , performance to hosts commensurate to their contributions , and consistent performance. We have implemented the system and conducted an Internet evaluation on Planet-Lab using real traces from previous operational deployments of an overlay broadcasting system. Our results indicate for these traces, our heuristics can improve the performance of high contributors by 10-240% and facilitate equitable band-width distribution among hosts with similar contributions.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>In the last few years, application-level overlay multicast has emerged as a key alternative to enable broadcasting applications on the Internet. In this scheme, participants in the broadcast self-organize into efficient overlays where video content is disseminated by the broadcast source without support from the network. There has been significant effort in recent years devoted to validating the architecture <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21]</ref>, designing protocols <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">27]</ref>, and deploying real systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">25]</ref>.</p><p>Much success with overlay broadcast deployments has been</p><p>Permission to make digital or hard copies of all or part of this work for personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGCOMM'06, <ref type="bibr">September 11-15, 2006</ref> restricted to homogeneous university environments, and broadcasts involving scientific conferences and lectures. For example, a recent work on experience with an overlay broadcasting system <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> indicates substantial success in achieving good performance in university-based environments, but highlights several performance issues when mainstream environments are considered. In this paper, we seek to enable overlay broadcast in environments characterized by two key properties. First, we consider highly heterogeneous environments where hosts make unequal contributions to the overlay. Such heterogeneity may arise due to different node outgoing capabilities (Ethernet vs. DSL) or different willingness to contribute bandwidth resources. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> reports the fraction of resource-poor hosts (i.e. with low outgoing bandwidth) in several real broadcast deployments range from 43% to 81%. Second, the bandwidth resources contributed by all hosts may be insufficient for everyone to receive the full source rate.</p><p>We present the design of an overlay broadcast system targeted at these environments. Our primary goal is to enable hosts to receive different levels of performance based on their contributions while effectively utilizing the bandwidth resources available in the system. To achieve this, our system leverages the multi-tree framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> to enable application-level adaptation. In our system, the source delivers data along multiple overlay trees. Each node subscribes to all trees but is only entitled to a subset of them. The number of trees a node is entitled to depends on the amount of bandwidth it contributes. This in turn determines the bandwidth, and consequently quality, it receives. While the multi-tree framework was originally proposed to improve resiliency, our focus is on using multiple trees to enable application-level adaptation and differential treatment.</p><p>We enforce bandwidth distribution policies where a node must contribute more than it is entitled to receive. Such policies are shown to better utilize bandwidth of resourcerich hosts and offer better performance to resource-poor hosts than naive bit-for-bit policies <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. They facilitate the "contribution-aware" policy: the more a node contributes, the more it is entitled to receive. To support this policy in a distributed manner, we design distributed heuristics for monitoring of overall system resources, differential and equitable distribution of bandwidth resources, and applicationlevel adaptation to changes in host contribution. While our system framework is motivated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>, we go substantially beyond these works by presenting a comprehensive contribution-aware design and implementation experience on an operational overlay broadcasting system <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p><p>We have conducted an evaluation of our contributionaware broadcasting system on PlanetLab using traces from real overlay broadcast deployments. Our results show that our heuristics offer differential and equitable resource distribution when compared to a contribution-agnostic system. In particular, the 10th-percentile performance of high contributors (nodes contributing more than 175% of the source rate) is increased by 10-240% and variation of bandwidth received among nodes with similar contributions is reduced across our set of traces. Achieving these improvements does incur a 20 − 38% decrease in the time between quality changes seen by a host, but achieves a 10-fold reduction in average time to recover from these changes for high contributors.</p><p>Section 2 discusses our assumptions and motivations in detail. Section 3 presents the design of contribution-aware heuristics. Section 4 describes the broadcasting system our implementation is based on and the process of integrating the multi-tree framework into this system. Section 5 discusses our evaluation methods and metrics. Evaluation results are presented in Section 6. Based on these results, we draw conclusions on our contribution-aware heuristics in heterogeneous, resource-scarce environments in Section 7.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">ASSUMPTIONS AND MOTIVATIONS</head><p>In this section, we describe the assumptions made on user behavior in Section 2.1. Section 2.2 introduces the multitree overlay we leverage to achieve differential resource distribution to nodes of diverse contribution levels. Section 2.3 presents a bandwidth distribution policy which we leverage to distribute bandwidth among peers. We discuss the goals of our contribution-aware system design in Section 2.4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Broadcast User Model</head><p>To simplify our design, we make certain assumptions about the behavior of broadcast participants. Although we believe our conclusions may be generalized past some of these assumptions, we limit our discussion to this user model. A peer i in the broadcast is capable of both receiving and forwarding data. Without loss of generality, we assume that every peer is capable of receiving the full source rate S in the event the system is capable of providing it to them. This is reasonable, given many "broadband" users today have asymmetric connections with a reasonably large downloading capacity. Most DSL hosts would easily be able to receive S but not forward one full-rate video stream. In academic or business environments, symmetric connections (eg: Ethernet) are more common. Such hosts frequently would be able to receive and forward several times more than S.</p><p>We do not assume a homogeneous forwarding bound, but consider different levels of actual contribution. A peer i's actual contribution fi is bounded by either ability or willingness. We assume that this forwarding bound Fi is determined by user willingness and is never over-estimated by the user (i.e. willingness ≤ ability). We assume that Fi is known only to the user and is non-zero -every peer will contribute some bandwidth upon request. We believe this is realistic since all Internet hosts have some upstream bandwidth. fi may vary over the course of i's stay in the system due to changes in the number of children i supports. Therefore, we target our design to react to users' actual contribution.</p><p>An important assumption is users are not strategic. While we offer incentives to encourage users to increase willingness to contribute, we do not model users who attempt to con- tribute minimum possible in order to achieve their desired performance. Instead, a peer i only ensures fi does not exceed Fi when adopting a new child. Therefore, we assume heterogeneity in Fi will be reflected by heterogeneity in fi.</p><p>Lastly, we assume hosts honestly report their fi, inferred by the number of children they currently support, and the bandwidth received from parents. However, we believe our heuristics can be easily integrated with recent research in distributed auditing and rating of nodes <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref> to verify the claimed contribution of nodes. With these assumptions in mind, our goal is to encourage a host i to relax its Fi, particularly under resource-scarce operating environments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Multi-tree-based Data Dissemination</head><p>Our system is targeted at regimes where insufficient resources are present in the system for all hosts to receive the full source rate. While we have assumed that all hosts contribute some outgoing bandwidth, we do not assume that everyone can forward the full source rate. In resource-scarce environments, we must also utilize any outgoing bandwidth which is less than the source rate. Therefore, we require a means by which hosts may receive and contribute graduated levels of bandwidth and transition smoothly as available resources change. To realize these goals, we leverage the multi-tree data delivery framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>. Although it was first introduced in the context of protocols based on Distributed Hash <ref type="table">Table (DHT)</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>, the multi-tree framework is not dependent on the use of DHT overlays.</p><p>In this framework, participants self-organize into a forest of T trees rooted at a source. The source encodes video with source rate S evenly into T stripes of size S/T , each distributed along one tree. The quality that a host gets depends on the number of stripes that it receives. Typically, a layered codec based on Multiple Description Coding (MDC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref> is used to realize this goal. The trees are interior-disjoint; that is, a host i allocates Fi to only one tree but attempts to connect to all of the T trees. When Fi is normalized by S, we call the resulting value the degree of host i. For example, if Fi = 300kbps and S = 400kbps, i's degree is 300/400 = 0.75. We also define the tree-degree to be degree * T , which is the maximum number of children a host can support in the tree it contributes. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> illustrates how broadcast content is delivered with T = 2. Host A and B both have a degree of 1 and allocate their bandwidth in Tree2 and Tree1, respectively, where each can support two children (i.e. tree-degree of 2). C receives S/2 each from A and B to reconstruct the original content. While this multi-tree framework was originally proposed to improve resiliency <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>, we use it as a convenient building block and focus on issues regarding heterogeneity and resource allocation mechanisms. This framework meets our needs, because it allows nodes to connect to a subset of trees and contribute in smaller bandwidth increments (i.e. stripes). Any node having a degree greater or equal to 1/T (i.e. tree-degree ≥ 1) is able to contribute. By setting T properly, we allow resourcepoor nodes with limited outgoing bandwidth to contribute, thereby spreading the forwarding load across all peers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Bandwidth Distribution Policies</head><p>A key design consideration is the selection of policies for distributing bandwidth in the broadcast among participating hosts based on their contributions. Assuming there are N hosts, and host i forwards bandwidth fi, our heuristics determine the bandwidth ri each host is entitled to receive.</p><p>The multi-tree framework enables us to consider settings where hosts can obtain different video qualities based on the bandwidth they are entitled to, by connecting to a subset of trees at a high priority. Note that the granularity is limited by the number of trees, T , in the forest. Having a larger T enables greater granularity, however one potential cost is an increased overhead due to the MDC coding.</p><p>Our heuristics do not prescribe any particular bandwidth distribution policy; however, it is designed with the goal of providing a framework that can enable the implementation of a range of policies. One simple bit-for-bit policy is to require each node to forward as much as it receives, that is, ri = fi. Under this policy, it is straightforward for each node to determine the bandwidth it should receive, as the decision is easy to compute locally. However, this policy is restrictive in two ways. First, it does not account for the fact that nodes may contribute less bandwidth than the source rate. Further, it does not provide any incentive to a node to donate more than the source rate even if it is capable of doing so. This is an issue in Internet environments today. Consider the fact that Internet broadcasts typically involve a source rate of 300-400 kbps, with a majority of hosts behind DSL and Ethernet. Hosts behind DSL can receive the source rate, but are not capable of forwarding it. Hosts behind Ethernet are capable of contributing much more than the source rate, and a policy such as ri = fi neither utilizes the bandwidth, nor incentivizes them to contribute more. On the other hand, arbitrarily sophisticated policies may be extremely difficult to implement in a distributed fashion.</p><p>Instead, we will consider a generic cost function of the form proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> to provide differential distribution:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">ri = 1 t * fi + t − 1 t * 񮽙 i fi N (1)</formula><p>ri is the bandwidth peer i is entitled to receive, fi is the bandwidth i contributes to the system. N is the number of participating peers. t is the "tax rate", which specifies a peer must contribute t * ri units of bandwidth to receive ri unit of entitled bandwidth. t must be greater than 1. If t = 1, we have a simple bit-for-bit policy. If t ≤ 1, no surplus exists and some peers will not receive their entitled bandwidth. ri is the sum of two terms. The first term represents the minimum bandwidth a peer is entitled to receive by contributing fi, and the second term is the average leftover bandwidth per node. By using a tax rate greater than 1, we are assured extra bandwidth in the system. For example, if t is 2, a peer i which contributes 2S will consume S from the system. The leftover resource S contributed by i is excessive. We aim to distribute all such excessive resources evenly among all peers, and this is represented by the second term. Since every byte of bandwidth received by a peer must be contributed by another peer(s). We can easily confirm that bandwidth is conserved by summing up both side of Equation <ref type="formula">(1)</ref>  </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">È i ri = È i fi.</formula><p>For our later evaluation, we pick a tax rate of 2.</p><p>We will focus on (1), as it lends itself to implementation in a distributed fashion. Section 3.1.1 describes a distributed way to obtain system-wide estimates such as È i fi and N .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Design Criteria</head><p>There are some criteria we wish to address in the design of our system. These criteria are targeted to offer good application performance, but also to improve user experiences while preferentially treating high-contributing nodes. Good Utilization: Given sufficient resource, users should receive bandwidth close to the source rate. While it is not possible for all users to receive the full rate in resource-scarce environments, the bandwidth provided to them should be optimized by making good use of available resources, and there should ideally be no untapped bandwidth. Each node should contribute to the extent of its ability and willingness. Equitable Distribution: When allocating bandwidth resources among hosts with similar contribution levels, they should receive similar performance. Differential Distribution: The allocation of bandwidth should favor those which make greater contributions. We also wish to offer some minimum performance to low contributors and give them improved performance if possible. Stability: Performance should be consistent over time. We expect that a node which sees performance improvements retains them and a node which sees a performance dip recovers quickly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">SYSTEM DESIGN</head><p>To differentially treat a node based on its contribution in the multi-tree framework, we consider the following problem: given a peer i, we wish to obtain a direct mapping between the actual amount of bandwidth, fi, i contributes and the amount of bandwidth, ri, the system should offer in return. Recall that i allocates its entire bandwidth Fi to only one tree, called i's Contributor Tree, but attempts to receive from all of the T trees. Extra bandwidth, if any, should be distributed evenly among participants once all of them get their deserved bandwidth. Equation (1) helps us obtain such mapping in a distributed fashion. We refer to ri as the Entitled Bandwidth of i. The natural solution is to have i simply receive ri by subscribing to 񮽙 r i S/T 񮽙 trees as an Entitled Node. These trees are the Entitled Trees of i. However, there are two reasons why this may not suffice. First, each node can only be entitled to an integral number of trees. If ri is not an integral multiple of the stripe rate, S/T , the fractional portion of the ri becomes superfluous. Second, there may be nodes whose Entitled bandwidth ri is larger than S, and they will not consume all of ri entitled to them. Consequently, not all bandwidth is used by nodes entitled to it, and there exists some additional bandwidth in the system remained to be utilized. When a node's Entitled bandwidth is lower than the source rate S, it may utilize some of these additional bandwidth available in trees they are not entitled to. We refer to the additional bandwidth that nodes are not entitled to but utilize to reach the source rate as Excess Bandwidth, and nodes looking for or utilizing this bandwidth as Excess Nodes.</p><p>In summary, a broadcast participant may assume two "main" classes in the forest, that is, it may be an Entitled node in some trees and an Excess node in some other trees. To treat different types of nodes with a better granularity, our system further classifies them and assigns them different priorities. When distributing system resources, our goal is to favor Entitled nodes over Excess nodes and evenly distributes the Excess bandwidth among all participants until they receive the source rate or no more resources remain.</p><p>Before presenting our design details, we want to make an important distinction between two concepts used in our multi-tree design: join/subscribe and receive/connect. A node joins/subscribes to a tree if it is aware of its participation within the tree, whether connected or disconnected, and a node connects to/receives in a tree if it has attached to a parent in that tree and is receiving the data forwarded by the tree. We also define a slot as an allocated bandwidth of size S/T by a parent. A slot can be in one of three states: (i) occupied by an Entitled node, (ii) occupied by an Excess node, or (iii) unused. We next show how to distribute Entitled and Excess bandwidth and how nodes are prioritized based on whether they are Entitled or Excess nodes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Determining Number of Entitled Trees</head><p>To enable a node i to compute its Entitled bandwidth ri using Equation (1), our system includes distributed mechanisms to periodically approximate the total resources utilized (i.e. È i fi) and the number of peers N . We then determine the number of trees i is required to join to receive ri. However, these global parameters may change any time due to group and network dynamics, leading to fluctuation of ri. This may reduce the stability of the system because hosts overreact to system states. Therefore, our system includes a way to smooth out the impacts sudden changes in ri have on the number of Entitled trees.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1">Distributed System Sampling</head><p>Collections of various system-wide parameters, for example, È i fi and N , are necessary to compute ri using Equation (1) and for some of our heuristics. We accomplish this by having each node in a tree periodically obtain the state of the subtree rooted at it and passing such information up the tree to the source. The source collects the state from each tree, generates system-wide information by aggregation, and propagates it down each tree to keep participating nodes informed about the system states in order to make cooperative decisions. To minimize message overhead while attempting to maintain a reasonable estimate of the transient system states, we choose a sampling period of 10 seconds.</p><p>Every 10 seconds, a node i informs its parent in each tree: (i) the bandwidth it is currently receiving from the tree, (ii) the total bandwidth received by its descendants, and (iii) the number of its descendants in each node class. The parent assembles these information from its children, aggregates with its own performance, and continues the process of passing information further up the tree. The source gathers the most recent updates every 10 seconds from its children in each tree, processes them, and sends along each tree a control update containing a monotonically increasing sequence number and the following system states: (i) the total contribution of the forest, È i fi, by summing up the bandwidth received by all nodes in the forest (ii) the total number of participants, N , measured by the total number of Contributors in the system (since each peer contributes in exactly one tree), and (iii) the number of Excess nodes connected to each tree. Since a host may receive control updates at different times from different trees it connects to, it will extract data from the update with the greatest sequence number.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">Computing Number of Entitled Trees</head><p>After joining the multi-tree system, a host i periodically (every 3 seconds) computes the number of trees it should be entitled to using the three-step process below: a. Determine Ti sample : A host i computes ri based on Equation (1), using the most recent sample of system states. To convert ri to a raw computation of Entitled trees Ti sample for peer i, we normalize it by the size of a single stripe:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Ti sample = ri S/T</formula><p>The computation occurs more frequent (once every 3 seconds) than sampling (once every 10 seconds) because fi is a transient value. Keeping the computation frequent enough enables a node to quickly adapt to the dynamics of its children and the system as a whole. b. Smoothing Ti sample : Since ri can change abruptly at any time with fi and N , it is advisable to implement some form of smoothing on Ti sample to prevent the host from overreacting to peer and network dynamics. There are two transitions that could occur: Ti sample may either increase or decrease. It will increase either if more resources are utilized per node in the system, or if the node's contribution has increased. In either case, the change is likely to be relatively long-lived and should be quickly responded to. In contrast, the value will decrease with a drop in system resources or with the departure of i's children. Children departures may be considered transient, as another child will be acquired quickly in resource-scarce environments.</p><p>Thus, we have implemented a smoothing scheme which tracks immediate increases in Ti sample , but only gradually responds to decreases. That is, we optimistically assume that reductions are transient and improvements persist. To achieve this, i calculates its estimated number of Entitled trees, Ti est , in this way:</p><p>If Ti sample &lt; Ti sample−old ,  <ref type="bibr">[1, T ]</ref> and the resulting value is the number of trees to which i is entitled. It is lower-bounded by 1 since a host is always entitled to its Contributor Tree and upper-bounded by T because when Ti ef f is greater than the total number of trees, i will simply be entitled to all trees.</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Ti est = (1 − α) * Ti est−old + α * Ti sample<label>(2)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Locating Excess Bandwidth</head><p>Since having a tax rate greater than 1 enforces each node to contribute more than its Entitled bandwidth, there will be leftover bandwidth in the system after nodes get their Entitled bandwidth. However, given the system does not know the bandwidth Fi a node i is willing to forward, it is difficult to determine the amount of theses leftover resources and where they are located until they are found and utilized. Thus, we choose to have a host i periodically explore for free slots in trees where it is not entitled, as an Excess node, until successfully connected. We call these trees Excess Trees of i. Any successful connection represents a slot which is not currently used to satisfy demands from Entitled nodes and becomes a part of system's Excess bandwidth.</p><p>Having nodes actively probe for Excess bandwidth has an additional benefit. When a node joins the system, its contribution level is not known. A node cannot contribute without any demand for resources, but in a steady state this demand would not exist until it begins to contribute. In order to accelerate this bootstrap process, there must be an ongoing demand for bandwidth to enable under-utilized nodes to raise their actual contribution. However, such aggressive probing by Excess nodes may not be fruitful under resource-constrained environments, as many of them may often compete with other nodes, including Entitled nodes, for the same slot, which may destabilize the tree structure. Thus, our system proposes a backoff scheme, in which an Excess node adaptively adjusts the aggressiveness of probing based on feedbacks received from the tree. Backoff in Excess Trees: When an Excess node actively explores for Excess bandwidth, there exists a possibility that the attempt will fail due to (i) an inherent lack of resources (no free slots nor preemptable children, will be clear later) in the tree, or (ii) resources exist but the node is not able to locate them. In either case, the node presumes that the tree is saturated and will enter a phase of exponential backoff in which it waits for t backof f seconds before retry. Consecutive failures will result in an exponential increase in the backoff timer, which is computed as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">t backof f = t base * rand(β k + Ti excess )<label>( 3 )</label></formula><p>where t base is the backoff base, β is the backoff factor, k is the number of consecutive failures, and Ti excess is node i's overall number of connected Excess trees. rand(x) returns a random number in <ref type="bibr">(0, x]</ref>. Currently, t base and β are set to 5 and 2, respectively. Since our results show that the average reconnection time for low-contributing nodes is around 1 minute, our choice of parameter values allow an Excess node to successfully connect in 3-4 attempts. This backup algorithm improves system stability since there is less contention for slots in a tree. A node attempts to connect to its Excess trees at a low priority level, implying it may take longer to connect to the tree, and even if it does, chances are it will quickly be displaced by a higher priority node. In addition, the heuristic scales the delay based on Ti excess to improve stability further because it biases Excess nodes connecting to fewer Excess trees, which have a higher priority than those connecting to more Excess trees. We confirm this benefit in Section 6.5.2. The prioritization policy will be explained in detail in the next section. Finally, to prevent nodes from repeatedly contending for the same slot(s) in the future, we use a rand function to inject some randomness in the backoff computation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Contribution-Aware Node Prioritization</head><p>In order to provide differential treatment to nodes forwarding at different levels, we introduce the notion of a class-based design. In this design, we further distinguish an Entitled node by whether it contributes or not. A node in a given tree belongs to one of three classes, in decreasing order of priority: Entitled Contributor (Contributor): A Contributor is entitled to the tree and forwards its received stripe to its children based on its forwarding bound Fi. Entitled Non-Contributor (Entitled-NC): An Entitled-NC is entitled to the tree but contributes no bandwidth. Excess: An Excess node is not entitled to the tree and contributes no bandwidth. It actively explores for a slot in the tree and is able to connect only if free slots or slots of lower priorities are available.</p><p>A host subscribes to multiple trees, but it may assume a different class in each tree. At any time, a peer joins one tree as a Contributor. This allows all hosts, regardless of its contribution level, to be entitled to at least one stripe upon entering the system, which in turn guarantees them with some minimum quality.</p><p>To assign priorities by class, we have implemented a classbased prioritization, summarized in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 1</ref>. In this scheme, when a disconnected node of higher class cannot find an empty slot, it will displace/preempt a node of a lower class. That is, when disconnected, Contributors may displace noncontributors, whether Entitled-NC or Excess, and EntitledNCs may displace an Excess node. Further, when a parent chooses between two Entitled nodes of the same class, the node with a higher contribution level fi in its Contributor tree is chosen. When choosing between two Excess nodes, the node with fewer overall connected Excess trees is chosen. This preference is only given for a difference of more than one Excess tree, since otherwise a displaced node could immediately reclaim its position and destabilize the tree structure. This provides incentives, since those nodes who contribute more will reach the full source rate with fewer connected Excess trees, and receive higher priorities over other Excess nodes. This type of preemption aims to allow each host to connect to the same number of Excess trees.</p><p>Finally, to offer more stability/protection to nodes with higher priorities, in the case a node can not find an empty slot, it will preempt, among nodes it knows, the one with the lowest priority. Thus, Excess nodes with more connected Excess trees than others are most likely to be displaced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Multi-Tree Join Management</head><p>Upon joining the multi-tree broadcast, a host i contacts the broadcast source and retrieves the following information about the system: (i) the number of trees T , (ii) the source rate S, (iii) the total number of participating hosts N , (iv) the total contribution in the system È i fi, and (v) the number of Excess nodes in each tree. i will select, with higher probability, the tree containing fewer Excess nodes as its Contributor Tree. Without any knowledge of i's willingness to contribute (i.e. Fi), balancing the non-entitled resources (i.e. Excess and unused slots) across each tree at join-time is difficult. Our join mechanism strives to keep each tree balanced in resources by encouraging new hosts to contribute in the tree with fewer Excess slots, which implies a shortage of resources in the tree. In Section 6.5.3, we show that using this join mechanism maintains trees in reasonable balance. At this point, i does not know how many trees it is entitled to since it has not begun to contribute. An optimistic decision could provide the host with more opportunities initially than it deserves. Thus we permit the host to initially join the remaining T − 1 trees as an Excess node.</p><p>Note that the effective number of Entitled trees Ti ef f computed by a host i may change upon every computation period. In case of an increase, among i's Excess trees, it picks one with the most Excess nodes and upgrades its class to Entitled-NC. On the other hand, in case of an decrease, among trees in which i is an Entitled-NC, it picks one with the fewest Excess nodes and downgrades its class to Excess. These processes repeat until i is entitled to Ti ef f trees.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>To evaluate our heuristics on a real system, we have chosen to implement them on the ESM Broadcasting System <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. ESM is a functional overlay broadcast application that has been used in academic conferences and workshops. The code for the ESM client is approximately 43,000 lines. Having this code base available provided a well-structured platform to experiment with our contribution-aware heuristics. The original ESM protocol uses a single-tree overlay to delivery broadcast content. The rest of the section summarizes ESM and describes how we extend it to use multiple overlay trees.</p><p>The ESM protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> relies on a gossip-based group membership process to create a single overlay broadcast tree among participating peers. For each node, knowledge about other members is seeded by the source at join-time and augmented through ongoing contact with other nodes. A node periodically sends information about a subset of members it knows to another node picked at random. The member receiving this message will then update its knowledge about other members. When a node i is disconnected from the tree, it starts the parent selection process by probing a random subset of the nodes it knows to inquire whether they could accept it as a child. Each probed node responds with information about whether it has a free space or a preemptable child (a node with a lower priority than i). After a timeout, the node evaluates potential parents, picks the best one based on some configurable metrics and requests addition as a child. An acceptance of this request means a parent node will begin forwarding data to the node, while a rejection causes i to restart the parent selection process. We employ a minimalist approach in adapting the code base to the multi-tree framework. In our multi-tree implementation, we have added a layer called the Multi-Tree Agent (MA) which contains an array of Single-Tree Protocol Agents (SPA, the single-tree protocol is ESM in our case) as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>. Each SPA is associated with one tree in the forest. The MA maintains global states, makes global decisions, multiplexes and de-multiplexes outgoing and incoming messages for a given tree to the associated SPA. Each tree operates independently and in parallel, interacting with the MA but not with the other SPAs. Finally, we incorporate our contribution-aware heuristics introduced in Section 3 into the Multi-tree ESM Broadcasting System.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">EXPERIMENTAL EVALUATION</head><p>We have evaluated our contribution-aware heuristics with a view to answering the following questions:</p><p>• How effective are they in ensuring good overall performance by utilizing the heterogeneous nature in the outgoing bandwidth of nodes in the system?</p><p>• How effective are they in offering differential and equitable performance to nodes based on their contributions?</p><p>• How stable is the resulting system, in terms of frequency of changes in the number of connected trees?</p><p>To answer these questions, we have conducted experiments on PlanetLab employing real traces of join/leave dynamics to compare the following two systems: Cont-Agnostic: This system refers to multi-tree ESM without any contribution-aware heuristics (e.g. no backoff). When distributing bandwidth, it does not consider nodes' contribution. The only possible preemption is that a Contributor can preempt an Entitled-NC or Excess node. This system is very similar to SplitStream <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> and CoopNet <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. Cont-Aware: This system refers to multi-tree ESM with our contribution-aware heuristics described in Section 3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Performance Metrics</head><p>We evaluate our system based on the following metrics:</p><p>• Bandwidth: For each node, we measure the mean application throughput in kbps over its lifetime. To maximize quality of the received video stream, this metric should be as close to the source rate as possible.</p><p>• Time Between Tree Reductions: This metric measures the impact of our heuristics on the stability of the system using the average time between reductions in the number of connected trees a node experiences. The implicit assumption is that the user perceived quality is dictated by the number of trees a node is connected to so each reduction degrades the user perceived streaming quality. We require they not be frequent so this metric should be as large as possible, or application performance will be inconsistent. However, we should be careful while interpreting this metric as it does not distinguish different types of reductions. For example, in a forest of four trees, a reduction from four to three trees is treated the same as a reduction from one to zero trees. Thus a reduction does not necessarily mean a user sees bad quality.</p><p>• Reconnection Time: When a node is disconnected from a tree, it should be able to reconnect quickly. This may entail preempting nodes of lower priority or locating a unused slot. Time between tree reductions measures how frequently a user experiences a dip in performance; this metric describes how long such dip persists.</p><p>• Utilization: Computed as the total bandwidth consumed by all hosts over the total forwarding limits of the hosts at a given time, the metric indicates what fraction of the system resources are being correctly located and leveraged.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Experimental Methodology</head><p>Our study is conducted based on real-world traces obtained from previous operational deployments of the ESM Broadcasting System <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Each trace lasts for several hours, and it is clearly not feasible to emulate the full duration. Thus, for each trace, we select a twenty-minute segment with characteristics shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 2</ref>. The high-speed and lowspeed hosts are generally behind Ethernet and asymmetric DSL/cable connections, respectively. The traces include the join/leave patterns of different nodes, as well as estimates of the outgoing bandwidth of each node. To quantify the resources available in these traces, we introduce Resource Index (RI) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, defined as the total forwarding capacity in the system divided by the bandwidth required for all hosts to receive the full source rate. We classify traces with an RI above one to be resource-rich and resource-scarce otherwise.</p><p>The primary trace we use for evaluation is the Slashdot trace, which is from a resource-scarce broadcast to an interest-group where the majority of hosts are behind DSL. SIGCOMM2002 and SOSP2003 are broadcasts of conferences, and thus have a much larger fraction of hosts behind high bandwidth university machines; as such, they represent resource-rich environments for comparison. GrandChallenge is a broadcast of a vehicular competition, and Rally refers to a broadcast of an election campaign. These traces represent resource-scarce environments. We focus our evaluation on the Slashdot trace and use other traces to study how sensitive our systems are to various operating environments. <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> shows RI as a function of time for the five trace segments. We emulate the traces by mapping each client to a PlanetLab host and use the same client join/leave patterns as in the trace segments to drive the experiment. Furthermore, we emulate DSL/cable and Ethernet hosts with a degree of 0.25 and 2, respectively.</p><p>For each experiment, four multicast trees are formed. Although one could improve the granularity of bandwidth distribution by using more trees to produce smaller stripes, the network and video-codec overheads increase with the number of trees. We consider four trees small enough to be efficient, while large enough to provide reasonable flexibility in varying the bandwidth. We use a source data rate of 400 kbps, a typical size of streaming videos on the Internet <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. The source streams a stripe of 100 kbps to each tree. The clients already present before the start of the segment join the broadcast in a burst and begin contributing in the their respective Contributor trees. We allow them 2 minutes to reach a steady state, after which the rest of the clients follow the join/leave patterns in the trace for the next 20 minutes, and experimental data is collected over that period.</p><p>We consider hosts with mean contributions greater than 700 kbps to be High Contributors (HC) and those with mean contributions between 75 and 100 kbps to be Low Contributors (LC). This splits hosts with various contribution levels into two groups and helps us evaluate them separately. Each result is aggregated or averaged over three runs with a consistent set of PlanetLab machines. When presenting results in the next section, we filter out hosts which stay for less than 2 minutes to highlight the results for hosts which participate for a reasonable amount of time. We will study the impact of node stay time in Section 6.2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS</head><p>We begin by showing the behavior of a typical host under the Cont-Aware system in a resource-scarce environment using the Slashdot trace in Section 6.1. Next, under the same setting, we compare the performance and average time between reductions in the number of trees of hosts in ContAware to those in Cont-Agnostic in Section 6.2 and Section 6.3, followed by a detailed evaluation of various key design components in Section 6.5. Section 6.6 explores how Cont-Aware behaves in different operating environments. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref> shows the performance of a typical high contributor in our system. The node begins by making zero contribution and connecting to its Contributor tree. Over the next minute, the number of children the node supports goes from zero to eight. As the number of adopted children increases, the number of successfully connected trees also increases quickly, as the node becomes entitled to them. The actual performance fluctuates due to the fact that ESM uses non-blocking TCP to transfer data across each overlay link, leading to burstiness on the received bandwidth.  Note that because we smooth away transient drops in contribution, the sudden loss of children between 255 and 300 seconds does not impact performance, and the node quickly acquires new children. The node is briefly disconnected from one tree at 250 seconds as shown by a 100 kbps dip of the solid line. This is due to the departure of the node's parent. However, because the node is contributing significantly to the system, the recovery time is very brief -the node finds a new location in the tree in under 6 seconds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Results with a Typical Run</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">System Performance</head><p>In this section, we would like to evaluate how well ContAware leverages the system resources and distributes them based on the contribution of each host as compared to ContAgnostic. In particular, hosts with similar contributions should see similar performance; hosts with higher contributions should see equal or better performance than those with lower contributions. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref> plots the cumulative distribution of the mean session bandwidth of high contributors for the two schemes: Cont-Aware and Cont-Agnostic. There are two curves, each corresponding to one scheme. The y-axis is the CDF and the x-axis is the mean bandwidth ranging from 0 to 400 kbps (i.e. source rate). The more a curve is toward the right, the better the overall performance is. Cont-Aware significantly improves the performance of high contributors with 80% of them receiving the source rate of 400 kbps. Cont-Agnostic however allows only 20% of high contributors to receive the source rate. Furthermore, almost all high contributors un- der Cont-Aware obtain bandwidth greater than 350 kbps whereas Cont-Agnostic does much worse, with only half of high contributors receiving more than 350 kbps. By prioritizing high contributors, Cont-Aware allocates about two more stripes to each high contributor than Cont-Agnostic.</p><p>While <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref> plots the mean bandwidth CDF for high contributors alone, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 6</ref> plots the same type of graph, but for low contributors. We see that with Cont-Agnostic, almost all low contributors receive anywhere from 100 kbps up to the source rate. Cont-Aware reduces this spread to 200-350 kbps, bringing the performance of all low contributors toward the mean. This shows Cont-Aware enables nodes contributing similarly to receive similar bandwidth. To quantify this observation, we compute the mean and standard deviation of both curves and find that although low contributors in both schemes receive a mean bandwidth around 300 kbps, with Cont-Aware, the standard deviation significantly drops from 80.5 to 34.8.</p><p>When looking at <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref> and 6 together, we see ContAgnostic gives high and low contributors a similar allocation pattern while Cont-Aware treat high contributors more favorably. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref> also suggests Cont-Aware reduces the performance spread for high contributors. Furthermore, all low contributors under Cont-Aware receive at least one stripe of 100 kbps. Thus we conclude that our contribution-aware heuristics achieve equitable and differential distribution of bandwidth based on nodes' contributions while offering some minimum guarantee on performance for low contributors. This offers incentives to nodes to contribute more and keep low contributors stay interested in the broadcast.</p><p>One question is whether it is possible to make the distribution among low contributors in Cont-Aware even more equitable, in which case most of them should receive closer to the average bandwidth of 300 kbps -for example, 8% of the low contributors receive less than 250 kbps. We see various reasons for this. First, we are limited by the granularity imposed by the multi-tree framework, and more equality could result if more trees are created. Second, some clients are limited by the bandwidth near them -further, there are issues related to our experimental artifact as several clients may be mapped to the same PlanetLab machine and compete for incoming bandwidth, causing them to under-perform. Third, there are convergence issues: short-lived low contributors do not remain in the system long enough to connect to their Excess trees, and due to the distributed nature of the system, resources are not always quickly located. In an extreme case, an Excess node which fails frequently on consecutive connection attempts may work up to a large backoff time, meaning they may never attempt to acquire a parent before they leave the system. <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref> further studies the convergence issues. Each curve corresponds to the performance for low contributors staying longer than X minutes, with X being 0, 2, and 5 minutes. The middle curve is the same as the Cont-Aware curve in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 6</ref>. As we can see, there is a minor improvement in the performance of the tail when longer-lived nodes are considered, however the impact of stay time on performance is negligible overall.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3">Time between Tree Reductions</head><p>We wish to show a node's received bandwidth is not frequently interrupted by measuring the time between reductions in the number of connected tree. <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref> shows the CDF of time between reductions in the number of connected trees for all nodes. We truncate the x-axis at 600 seconds, since nodes with fewer than one reduction in 10 minutes are considered stable. The higher the curve, the less stable the system is, since a greater percentage of nodes experience a smaller time between reductions in the number of connected tree. Although Cont-Aware appears to produce less consistent performance for all nodes, it does not necessarily imply users see bad performance due to two reasons.</p><p>First, the curve does not distinguish between different types of reductions. For example, a reduction from four to three trees is treated the same as a reduction from two to one trees. <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 3</ref> shows a breakdown of different types of reductions in the number of connected trees. We see that for Cont-Aware, only 2.5% of reductions are from two to one  trees and virtually none from one to zero trees whereas for Cont-Agnostic, almost 8% of reductions are of these types. We can also observe that almost all reductions high contributors in Cont-Awareexperience are from four to three trees, which have very little impact on application performance. In contrast, such preferential treatment for high contributors is not obvious under Cont-Agnostic. Second, we find that 90% of reduction result from preemptions rather than from parent departures, and Cont-Aware allows preempted nodes to reconnect much faster. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 9</ref> shows a breakdown of average reconnection time after preemptions. We see that by considering node contribution, the reconnection time for both groups of nodes are reduced, and the reconnection time for high contributors is much shorter than low contributors. In particular, the reconnection time of high contributors in Cont-Aware is only 1/11 of that in Cont-Agnostic. In ContAgnostic, a node which is preempted cannot preempt another node. In contrast, since Cont-Aware establishes finer prioritization levels among nodes, a preempted node can often quickly find a new location in the tree, and the cost of preemption is much cheaper.</p><p>To further understand why Cont-Aware reduces the reconnection time, <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">Table 4</ref> compares different types of preemptions that may occur based <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 1</ref> and how long the preempted node remains disconnected. In particular, there are three types of preemptions:</p><p>• EN by EN: An Entitled node may be preempted by another Entitled node of higher priority. Such type of preemption improves the tree structure by accepting a node which contributes more. The preempted node is also entitled to the tree and should reconnect quickly.</p><p>• EX by EN: An Entitled node may preempt an Excess node. This type of preemption is not quickly recovered from, but since the node was not entitled to the tree in which it was preempted, the loss of performance is less significant.</p><p>• EX by EX: An Excess node may be preempted by another Excess node. They take place in order to effect equitable performance. An Excess node receiving many Excess trees will be preempted by an excess receiving few, thereby equalizing their bandwidth. If a preempted excess was receiving too many trees, these preemptions should not recover quickly.</p><p>In <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">Table 4</ref>, we see that the reconnection time following each type of preemption are consistent with our predictions. An Entitled node reconnects quickly after a preemption. An Excess node preempted by an Entitled node does not quickly reconnect. An Excess node which is receiving in too many trees and is preempted does not recover quickly at all. We have also observed that most preemptions among high contributors are of the first type, since they are entitled to all four trees most of the time. These preemptions occur when few Excess nodes exist in the system. In this case, a Contributor sometimes will preempt an Entitled-NC. With a reconnection time under 6 seconds, such types of preemption are acceptable. We also see that some high contributor preemptions take place while the high contributor is an Excess in a tree; this situation primarily occurs at the beginning of the high contributor's lifetime, before it begins to contribute.</p><p>Most preemptions are of the second type, since under resource-scarce environments like Slashdot, most Entitled nodes are required to connect by preempting other nodes. Since an Entitled node prefers to preempt an Excess node rather than anther Entitled node, the more trees a node is entitled to, the more stable it will be. This ensures nodes are generally connected in their Entitled trees for an extended period of time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.4">Utilization</head><p>In resource-scarce Slashdot environment, Cont-Agnostic utilizes 95% of the resources in average, whereas the utilization of Cont-Aware is about 93%, demonstrating that our heuristics does not adversely impact the efficiency of ESM in locating and leveraging the available resources despite with numerous backoffs and preemptions taking place.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.5">System Dissection</head><p>In this section, we evaluate the impact of various heuristics in Cont-Aware. We wish to demonstrate the value added by each heuristic and better understand its contribution to the improved performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.5.1">Smoothing Schemes</head><p>The goal of smoothing is to enable hosts to experience less frequent reductions in the number of connected trees by not overreacting to global and local transients. In this section, we study three smoothing policies: No-Smooth, Smooth, and SmoothDown-Only, and explain why our heuristics pick SmoothDown-Only over the other two schemes to compute the estimated number of Entitled trees, Ti est . Using the notations defined in Section 3.1.2, we first define each policy:</p><p>• No-Smooth: No smoothing at all (i.e. Ti est = Ti sample ), regardless of how abruptly Ti sample changes.</p><p>• Smooth: Always smooth by using Equation (2) to calculate Ti est whenever Ti sample changes. • SmoothDown-Only: Smooth by using Equation (2) to calculate Ti est only when Ti sample decreases.</p><p>Our results show that, regardless of the smoothing schemes used, low contributors see similar low time between reductions in the number of connected trees. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref> plots CDF of the average time between reductions in the number of connected trees for high contributors. We see that No-Smooth does not perform well because Ti est fluctuates with Ti sample whereas Smooth is as bad because it does not quickly reward nodes whose contributions go up. SmoothDown-Only significantly increases the stability for high-contributors over the other two scheme because many decreases in Ti sample are caused by transient situations, such as a child departure, in which case another child will be acquired quickly in highlyutilized resource-scarce environments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.5.2">Backoff Schemes</head><p>In this section, we first justify why we incorporate the backoff mechanism in Cont-Aware. Then we investigate why it is beneficial to adding the scaling factor, Ti excess , in the computation of the backoff timer. We first define three variations of backoff policies:</p><p>• No-Backoff: No backoff at all. A disconnected Excess node immediately attempts to reconnect.</p><p>• Backoff: When failing to connect, backoff using the timer computed by Equation (3).</p><p>• Backoff w/o Ti excess : When failing to connect, backoff using timer computed by Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">(3)</ref> with Ti excess removed. Benefit of Backoff: We now examine whether Excess nodes should backoff when they are unable to connect by comparing two systems: Backoff and No-Backoff. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref>, we observe that although No-Backoff improves the overall performance slightly, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12</ref> shows that Backoff significantly improves system stability. Since the environment we consider is resource-scare, Excess nodes are very likely be preempted. By trying less frequently to connect to an Excess tree unless more resources are available, an Excess node is less likely to be quickly preempted, leading to less frequent reductions in the number of connected trees. Consider Ti excess in Backoff Timer: In Backoff, in addition to double the backoff timer after each consecutive failure in connection attempts for an Excess node, the backoff time is scaled by the number of Excess trees the node is currently connected, Ti excess . <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12</ref> compares the stability of Backoff w/o Ti excess with Backoff. We see that Backoff leads to a more stable system than Backoff w/o Ti excess by forcing peers receiving in more Excess trees to wait longer before the next reconnection attempt because even if they get connected, they are likely to be immediately preempted by other Excess nodes with a lower Ti excess .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.5.3">Load Balancing</head><p>We believe that choosing to balance the number of Excess nodes in each tree would approximately balance the resources in each tree in resource-scarce environments. the resources each tree have remain close to perfect balancing for the most of the duration. Thus, we conclude that our heuristics maintain trees in reasonable balance in resourcescarce environments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.6">Sensitivity to Trace</head><p>In this section, we evaluate our contribution-aware heuristics under environments with varying resource levels by using five different traces. We include Slashdot among these for comparison to results in previous sections. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 14</ref> shows the 10th-percentile performance of the entire set of nodes and high contributors across each trace for Cont-Aware and Cont-Agnostic. That is, 90% of all nodes see better performance than the numbers presented here. The traces are ordered based on their resource indices, with the lowest RI on the very left. The three traces on the left are resource-scarce whereas the two on the right are resource-rich. Each trace has 4 bars, with 2 bars for high contributors and 2 bars for all nodes in Cont-Aware and Cont-Agnostic. For resource-scarce traces, our heuristics offer improved tail performance for all nodes and high contributors alone. The significant improvement for high contributors confirm that they are prioritized for resources in Cont-Aware whereas improvement for all nodes implies their received bandwidth is pulled toward the mean. For resource-rich traces, we see similar performance -everyone successfully receives the source rate.</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 15</ref>, we examine the sensitivity of the average time between reductions in the number of connected trees to different traces by comparing the median value of all nodes. Notice that for resource-scarce traces, Cont-Aware causes nodes to experience reductions more frequently. In resourcerich environments, reductions are infrequent for both as most nodes can connect to empty slots. Finally, we compare the reconnection time after preemptions in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 16</ref>. Note that for all resource-scarce environments our heuristics significantly improve reconnection time for both high and low contributors. In resource-rich environments, we offer substantially similar recovery time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">SUMMARY</head><p>In this paper, we present the design and implementation experience of an overlay broadcasting system targeted at environments where not all nodes can receive the source rate and node contributions are heterogeneous. To incenvitizes nodes to increase their contributions, the system is contribution-aware: it distributes more bandwidth to nodes which contribute more. We have conducted a detailed evaluation of the system on PlanetLab using traces from real broadcasts, which helps demonstrate the benefits of the heuristics we introduce. When compared with contribution-agnostic system, our results indicate that in resource-scarce environments, our contribution-aware system can improve the 10th-percentile performance of all nodes and high contributors alone by 2-35% and 10-240%, respectively. The system also distributes the available bandwidth more equitably among nodes of similar contributions. For example, in one trace, bandwidth received by 90% of low contributors is within 100 kbps of the mean. Although nodes in our system suffer tree reductions a little more frequently, they require only 70% as much time to recover. We believe these results are promising and display the potential to extend overlay broadcasting toward ubiquitous deployment in mainstream Internet.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: A multi-tree broadcast with two trees.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 : Original vs Multi-tree implementation.</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Original vs Multi-tree implementation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 : Resource Indices for real-world traces in a 20 -minute segment. Traces with an RI above 1 are con- sidered resource-rich and resource-limited otherwise.</head><label>320</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Resource Indices for real-world traces in a 20-minute segment. Traces with an RI above 1 are considered resource-rich and resource-limited otherwise.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 : Behavior of a typical high contributor under Cont-Aware. The top curve shows the bandwidth con- tributed, the solid curve shows the Entitled bandwidth, and the dashed line shows the actual bandwidth received</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Behavior of a typical high contributor under Cont-Aware. The top curve shows the bandwidth contributed, the solid curve shows the Entitled bandwidth, and the dashed line shows the actual bandwidth received.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Cumulative distribution of average received bandwidth for high contributors.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Cumulative distribution of average received bandwidth for low contributors.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 : Cumulative distribution of received band- width for LC staying for more than 0 Figure 8 : Cumulative distribution of time between tree reductions for all nodes.</head><label>708</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Cumulative distribution of received bandwidth for LC staying for more than 0, 2, and 5 minutes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9: Average post-preemption reconnection time in seconds for nodes in different contribution levels.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 10 : Comparison of time between tree reduc- tions for high contributors under different smooth- ingFigure 11 : Cumulative distribution of received band- width for all nodes under different backoff schemes.</head><label>1011</label><figDesc>Figure 10: Comparison of time between tree reductions for high contributors under different smoothing schemes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 12 : Cumulative distribution of time between tree reductions for all nodes under different backoff schemesFigure 13 : Comparison of resource indices in each tree as compared to perfect load balancing.</head><label>1213</label><figDesc>Figure 12: Cumulative distribution of time between tree reductions for all nodes under different backoff schemes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 14 : 10th-percentile of received bandwidth for high contributors and all nodes in each traceFigure 15 : Median of average time between tree reduc- tions for all nodes in each trace.</head><label>1415</label><figDesc>Figure 14: 10th-percentile of received bandwidth for high contributors and all nodes in each trace.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 16 :</head><label>16</label><figDesc>Figure 16: Average post-preemption reconnection time for high contributors and all nodes in each trace.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>over all nodes, leading to</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>Else , Ti est = Ti sample When the current sample, Ti sample , is less than its previous sample, Ti sample−old , we smooth the sample using Equation (2) where Ti est is a weighted combination of Ti est−old , the previous value of Ti est , and Ti sample .around an integral tree value. The greater the threshold is, the more damping is imposed on Ti est . The output of this processor is the effective number of Entitled trees, Ti ef f . For example, if the last Ti est calculated was 2.8, the current Ti est must exceed 3.1 to have a Ti ef f of 3. Finally, we restrict Ti ef f to the range</head><label>Else</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>To put more weights on 
recent samples than on old samples, we set α to be 0.125, 
which from our experience has worked well. We call this 
particular smoothing scheme SmoothDown-Only. We have 
also evaluated other possible smoothing methods, and the 
results are presented in Section 6.5. 
c. Calculate Ti ef f : To further ensure the number of trees 
entitled to a node depends on the node's immediate history, 
Ti est is fed through a hysteresis processor, with a thresh-
old of ±0.1 </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>Table 1 :trees</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Preemption Matrix: Can a disconnected 
node A displace/preempt a connected node B? 

A | B 
Contributor (C) 
Entitled-NC (ENC) 
Excess (EX) 
C 
By contribution 
Yes 
Yes 
ENC 
No 
By contribution 
Yes 
EX 
No 
No 
By # Excess </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="true"><head>Table 2 : Constitution of hosts in a 20-minute segment for each real-world trace.</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Broadcast 
Avg 
Low 
High 
Total 
Peak 
Event 
RI 
Speed 
Speed 
Group 
Group 
100Kbps 
10Mbps 
Size 
Size 
SIGCOMM2002 
1.32 
34% 
66% 
88 
78 
SOSP2003 
1.31 
47% 
53% 
95 
51 
Rally 
0.96 
73% 
27% 
401 
239 
Slashdot 
0.87 
66% 
34% 
328 
156 
GrandChallenge 
0.51 
88% 
12% 
281 
149 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="true"><head>Table 3 : Breakdown of different types of reductions in the number of connected trees.</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Reduction 
Cont-Agnostic 
Cont-Aware 
from→to 
LC 
HC 
LC 
HC 
1 → 0 trees 
0.8% 
0% 
0% 
0.1% 
2 → 1 trees 
4.0% 
3.1% 
2.1% 
0.3% 
3 → 2 trees 
15.6% 
13.8% 
31.6% 
2.5% 
4 → 3 trees 
29.6% 
33.1% 
16.3% 
47.1% 

80.82 

65.26 

69.83 

7.1 

53.08 

48.35 

0 

10 

20 

30 

40 

50 

60 

70 

80 

90 

HC 
LC 
OVERALL 

Average Reconnection Time (seconds) 

Cont-Agnostic 
Cont-Aware 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="false"><head>Table 4 : Breakdown of number of preemptions for each preemption type and the average reconnection times fol- lowing each type of preemption.</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Type 
HC 
LC 
Overall 
Avg Recon Time 
EN by EN 
164 
307 
508 
5.95 
EX by EN 
86 
1449 
1591 
50.51 
EX by EX 
19 
735 
784 
71.44 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scalable Application Layer Multicast</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Banerjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kommareddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A robust reputation system for p2p and mobile ad-hoc networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Buchegger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Boudec</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Economics of Peer-to-Peer Systems</title>
		<meeting>the Second Workshop on Economics of Peer-to-Peer Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SplitStream: High-bandwidth Content Distribution in Cooperative Environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Druschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kermarrec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nandi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rowstron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SOSP</title>
		<meeting>SOSP</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scribe: A Large-Scale and Decentralized Application-Level Multicast Infrastructure</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Druschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kermarrec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rowstron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Layered Multiple Description Coding</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Padmanabhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Packet Video Workship</title>
		<meeting>Packet Video Workship</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Early Experience with an Internet Broadcast System Based on Overlay Multicast</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ganjam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S E</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sripanidkulchai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of USENIX</title>
		<meeting>USENIX</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Case for End System Multicast</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM Sigmetrics</title>
		<meeting>ACM Sigmetrics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The design of a distributed rating scheme for peer-to-peer systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dutta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Govindan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the First Workshop on Economics of Peer-to-Peer Systems</title>
		<meeting>the First Workshop on Economics of Peer-to-Peer Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Esm broadcast system</title>
		<ptr target="http://esm.cs.cmu.edu/" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Yoid: Extending the Internet Multicast Architecture</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple Description Coding: Compression Meets the Network</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Goyal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Processing Magazine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A case for taxation in peer-to-peer streaming broadcast</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">PINS &apos;04: Proceedings of the ACM SIGCOMM workshop on Practice and theory of incentives in networked systems</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="212" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overcast: Reliable Multicasting with an Overlay Network</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jannotti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gifford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kaashoek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W O</forename><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Fourth Symposium on Operating System Design and Implementation (OSDI)</title>
		<meeting>the Fourth Symposium on Operating System Design and Implementation (OSDI)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bullet: High Bandwidth Data Dissemination Using an Overlay Mesh</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kostic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Albrecht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vahdat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SOSP</title>
		<meeting>SOSP</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differentiated admission for peer-to-peer systems: Incentivizing peers to contribute their resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C.-H</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the First Workshop on Economics of Peer-to-Peer Systems</title>
		<meeting>the First Workshop on Economics of Peer-to-Peer Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application-layer Multicast with Delaunay Triangulations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liebeherr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nahas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Globecom</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Globecom</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributing Streaming Media Content Using Cooperative Networking</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Padmanabhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sripanidkulchai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of NOSSDAV</title>
		<meeting>NOSSDAV</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ALMI: An Application Level Multicast Infrastructure</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Pendarakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Verma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Waldvogel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 3rd Usenix Symposium on Internet Technologies &amp; Systems (USITS)</title>
		<meeting>3rd Usenix Symposium on Internet Technologies &amp; Systems (USITS)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application-level Multicast using Content-Addressable Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ratnasamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Handley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Karp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of NGC</title>
		<meeting>NGC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pastry: Scalable, Distributed Object Location and Routing for Large-Scale Peer-to-Peer Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rowstron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Druschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IFIP/ACM International Conference on Distributed Systems Platforms (Middleware)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Feasibility of Supporting Large-Scale Live Streaming Applications with Dynamic Application End-Points</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sripanidkulchai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ganjam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Maggs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chord: A Scalable Peer-to-Peer Lookup Service for Internet Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stoica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Karger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kaashoek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Balakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overlay Optimizations for End-host Multicast</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Helder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jamin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Fourth International Workshop on Networked Group Communication (NGC)</title>
		<meeting>Fourth International Workshop on Networked Group Communication (NGC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DONet/CoolStreaming: A Data-driven Overlay Network for Live Media Streaming</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T.-S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Yum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Tapestry: An Infrastructure for Wide-area Fault-tolerant Location and Routing. U. C</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kubiatowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Joseph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>UCB//CSD-01-1141</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Berkeley Technical Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayeux: An Architecture for Scalable and Fault-Tolerant Wide-Area Data Dissemination</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Zhuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kubiatowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Joseph</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of NOSSDAV</title>
		<meeting>NOSSDAV</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
