<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Completion Time Minimization and Robust Power Control in Wireless Packet Networks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chris</forename><forename type="middle">T K</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02139</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Muriel</forename><surname>Médard</surname></persName>
							<email>medard@mit.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02139</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Asuman</forename><surname>Ozdaglar</surname></persName>
							<email>asuman@mit.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02139</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Completion Time Minimization and Robust Power Control in Wireless Packet Networks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>A wireless packet network is considered in which each user transmits a stream of packets to its destination. The transmit power of each user interferes with the transmission of all other users. A convex cost function of the completion times of the user packets are minimized by optimally allocating the users&apos; transmission power subject to their respective power constraints. It is shown that, at all ranges of SINR, completion time minimization can be formulated as a convex optimization problem and hence can be efficiently solved. When channel knowledge is imperfect, robust power control is considered based on the channel fading distribution subject to outage probability constraints. The problem is shown to be convex when the fading distribution is log-concave in exponentiated channel power gains; e.g., when each user is under independent Rayleigh, Nakagami, or log-normal fading.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Power control plays a crucial role in the operation of a wireless network, as it strives to provide maximum benefits to the users within the confines of available resources. In particular, in a wireless network, each user's transmit power interferes with the transmission of all other users; therefore, power allocation has a significant impact on the quality-ofservice (QoS) experienced by the network users. The user benefits derived from a given power allocation assignment can be characterized by different performance metrics. Traditionally, a common performance metric is a utility function of the rates of the users.</p><p>However, maximizing a concave utility function over the feasible rate region in a wireless network is not necessarily a convex optimization problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>- <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. In the high signal to interference-plus-noise (SINR) regime, rate utility maximization can be approximately formulated as a convex optimization problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, and hence it can be efficiently solved. For voice or video applications that need to maintain at least a moderate minimum rate, the high-SINR regime is often an appropriate assumption. On the other hand, in wireless sensor networks This material is based upon work under subcontract #069145 and #060786 issued by BAE Systems National Security Solutions, Inc. and supported by the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) and the Space and Naval Warfare System Center (SPAWARSYSCEN), San Diego under Contract Nos. N66001-08-C-2013 and N66001-06-C-2020; and under ITMANET subcontract # 18870740-37362-C issued by Stanford University and supported by the DARPA. Chris T. K. Ng is supported by a Croucher Foundation Fellowship.</p><p>or delay-insensitive data applications, a user may wish to transmit at arbitrarily low rates (i.e., at low SINRs) depending on the channel conditions. At medium to low SINR, rate utility maximization are handled by iterative approximation methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. In this paper, we study a different network performance metric that is motivated by data applications. In particular, we consider the scenario where each user transmits a stream of packets to its destination, and we wish to minimize a convex cost function of the user packet completion times. We show that completion time minimization and the corresponding optimal power allocation can be formulated as a convex optimization problem at all ranges of SINR.</p><p>Moreover, we consider imperfect channel knowledge due to channel fading, and formulate the minimization as a stochastic programming problem. The channel gains are modeled as random variables: an outage event occurs when the SINR realization falls below the transmitter's SINR target. Robust power control is considered where each user is subject to an outage probability constraint. We show that for a wide class of commonly used channel fading distributions, e.g., Rayleigh, Nakagami, and log-normal, robust power control can be posed a convex optimization problem.</p><p>Optimal power control in wireless networks is studied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>; it shows that maximizing concave rate utility functions can be formulated as geometric programming (GP) problems in the high-SINR regime, which are convex and hence their solutions can be computed efficiently. In the medium-to low-SINR regime, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> describes an iterative approximation method to maximize a concave rate utility function by solving a series of GPs, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> proposes an algorithm to maximize a linear function of the rates by approximating the feasible SINR region by a series of polyblocks. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, sufficient conditions are presented for the convexity of the feasible QoS region, with optional constraints on the allocation of user power. Utility maximization through joint optimization of adaptive modulation, rate allocation, and power control is investigated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> power control is studied in frequency-selective Gaussian interference channels. Outage probabilities corresponding to different fading distributions for network users and interferers are derived in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. For interference-limited wireless networks, optimal power control is considered in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> under Rayleigh fading subject to outage probability constraints.</p><p>The rest of the paper is organized as follows. Section II describes the channel model and the optimization framework. In Section III, minimizing a cost function of the completion times is posed as a convex optimization problem. Section IV explains how the completion time region and its corresponding rate region are related. Section V considers robust power control against imperfect channel knowledge subject to outage probability constraints. Conclusions are presented in Section VI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. SYSTEM MODEL</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Wireless Channels</head><p>Consider the scenario in which M users are communicating in a wireless packet network. Each user i consists of a transmitter i and a corresponding receiver i, where i = 1, . . . , M . Transmitter i wishes to send a stream of equal-length packets to receiver i, where each packet has L i bits. We assume the complex baseband additive white Gaussian noise (AWGN) channel model between the transmitters and receivers:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Y i = M j=1 H ij X j + Z i ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where Y i is the observed signal at receiver i, X j is the signal sent by transmitter j, H ij is the channel power gain from transmitter j to receiver i, and Z i is independent Gaussian noise with power N i . We consider coherent detection: thus H ij may be assumed real as detection is unaffected by phase change in the received signal. In the subsequent sections, we consider different channel knowledge assumptions where H ij 's may represent known constants or random variables. Suppose transmitter i has transmit power constraint ¯ P i . When transmitter i transmits at a power level of P i ≤ ¯ P i , in the capacity limit, the transmission rate R i (bits per channel use) achieved by user i is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">R i = log(1 + S i ),<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where log is base 2, and S i is the signal to interference-plusnoise ratio (SINR) at receiver i. When the interference from the other transmitters is treated as noise, the SINR at receiver i is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">S i = H ii P i N i + j񮽙 =i H ij P j .<label>(3)</label></formula><p>We assume each user has a sufficient number of packets backlogged at the transmitter so that it is always transmitting, and we assume L i is sufficiently large to allow transmission close to the channel capacity limit. The completion time (number of channel uses) of the transmission of each of user i's packet is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">T i = L i /R i .<label>(4)</label></formula><p>For example, an AWGN wireless packet network with M = 2 users is illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Completion Time Cost Function</head><p>We consider the problem of minimizing a convex cost function of the completion times T 1 , . . . , T M by optimally choosing the users' transmission power subject to the power constraints:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">0 ≤ P i ≤ ¯ P i , i = 1, . . . , M . Let J(T) be the completion time cost function, where T T 1 . . . T M T</formula><p>, and other vectors are denoted similarly in this paper. We assume J(T) is jointly-convex in T 1 , . . . , T M ; the convexity penalizes overlong completion times. For example, the following completion time cost functions are convex <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">J r (T) = T [1] + · · · + T [r] (5) J p (T) = (T 1 ) p + · · · + (T M ) p 1/p , p ≥ 1.<label>(6)</label></formula><p>In <ref type="formula">(5)</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. PACKET COMPLETION TIME MINIMIZATION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Perfect Channel Estimation</head><p>We first consider the scenario where the channel power gains H ij 's can be accurately estimated and they are known by all users:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">H ij = G ij , i = 1, . . . , M, j = 1, . . . , M,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where G ij 's are known constants. In this case, the minimization of the completion time cost function J(T) can be mathematically formulated as the following optimization problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">minimize J(T) (8) over T i , R i , P i subject to T i ≥ L i /R i (9) R i ≤ log 1 + G ii P i N i + j񮽙 =i G ij P j (10) 0 ≤ P i ≤ ¯ P i ,<label>(11)</label></formula><p>where i = 1, . . . , M , and the problem data</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">G ij ∈ R + , ¯ P i , N i , L i ∈ R ++ are given. The constraint (10) in the optimization problem is not convex [1]-[3]</formula><p>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. However, we show in the next section (8)-(11) can be transformed into a convex optimization problem, and hence its solution can be efficiently computed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Convex Optimization</head><p>To formulate the the completion time minimization problem given in (8)-(11) as a convex optimization problem, we first rewrite the constraints (9), (10) as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">T i ≥ L i log(1 + S i ) , i = 1, . . . , M<label>(12)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">S i ≤ G ii P i N i + j񮽙 =i G ij P j , i = 1, . . . , M.<label>(13)</label></formula><p>Next we apply the change of variables:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">˜ S i ln S i , ˜ P i ln P i , i = 1, . . . , M,<label>(14)</label></formula><p>where ln is the natural logarithm. The completion time minimization in (8)-(11) then becomes:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">minimize J(T)<label>(15)</label></formula><p>over</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">T i , ˜ S i , ˜ P i subject to T i ≥ L i log 1 + exp( ˜ S i )<label>(16)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_14">ln exp( ˜ S i − ˜ P i − ln G ii + ln N i ) + j񮽙 =i exp( ˜ S i − ˜ P i + ˜ P j − ln G ii + ln G ij ) ≤ 0<label>(17)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_15">˜ P i ≤ ln ¯ P i ,<label>(18)</label></formula><p>where i = 1, . . . , M . Note that the constraint in (17) follows from rewriting (13) as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">S i P −1 i G −1 ii N i + j񮽙 =i S i P −1 i P j G −1 ii G ij ≤ 1,<label>(19)</label></formula><p>and taking logarithm on both sides after applying <ref type="bibr">(14)</ref>. The change of variables is similar to the transformation techniques in geometric programming (GP) problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. In particular, the log-sum-exp function in constraint <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(17)</ref> is convex <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. The convexity of (16) can be verified from its second-order conditions, as the right-hand side of (16) is twice-differentiable and its second derivative is positive:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">d 2 dx 2 log(1 + e x ) −1 = e x ln 2 2e x − ln(1 + e x ) (1 + e x ) 2 ln(1 + e x ) 3 (20) &gt; 0,<label>(21)</label></formula><p>which follows from the inequality y &gt; ln(1 + y) for y &gt; 0. Note that the transformation in (14) does impose a slight loss of generality as we assume P i 񮽙 = 0. Nevertheless, the formulation in (15)- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(18)</ref> is otherwise valid for all ranges of SINR, and its solution can be efficiently computed by standard numerical methods in convex optimization <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Note that we may consider additional linear or convex constraints on T, and sum power constraints on subsets of P: they can be readily incorporated in the optimization problem without violating its convexity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Fading Channels and Power Adaptation</head><p>In this section we consider fading channels, i.e., the channel gains H ij 's in (1) experience random variations. In particular, we assume the channel gains can be characterized by a set of s ∈ {1, . . . , S} discrete fading states:</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">H =        G (1) with probability p 1 . . . G (S) with probability p S , S s=1 p s = 1,<label>(22)</label></formula><p>where H ∈ R M×M + H ij is the channel power gain matrix, and G ∈ R M×M + G ij is defined similarly. For example, the discrete states may represent a finite set of quantized channel estimates. We consider slow fading where the duration of a fading state is long compared to the packet completion times. We assume the channel state s can be accurately estimated and it is known by all users.</p><p>We first consider the case where each user can adapt its transmission power level according to the fading state. Suppose user i transmits at power level P (s) i in fading state s, subject to the average power constraints:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">E[P i ] S s=1 p s P (s) i ≤ ¯ P i , i = 1, . . . , M.<label>(23)</label></formula><p>To minimize a cost function of the expected completion times, the optimization problem can be formulated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">minimize J(E[T 1 ], . . . , E[T M ])<label>(24)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">over E[T i ], T (s) i , S (s) i , P (s) i subject to E[T i ] = S s=1 p s T (s) i<label>(25)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">T (s) i ≥ L i log 1 + S (s) i<label>(26)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">S (s) i ≤ G (s) ii P (s) i N i + j񮽙 =i G (s) ij P (s) j<label>(27)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_24">0 ≤ P (s) i<label>(28)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_25">S s=1 p s P (s) i ≤ ¯ P i ,<label>(29)</label></formula><p>where s = 1, . . . , S; i = 1, . . . , M . The optimization in (24)-(29) can then be transformed into a convex optimization problem by similar techniques as described in Section III-B. Note that to minimize the expected value of the cost function, it can be handled similarly by replacing the objective function in (24) by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">E[J(T)] = S s=1 p s J(T (s) 1 , . . . , T (s) M ),<label>(30)</label></formula><p>where convexity is preserved in the nonnegative weighted sum of convex functions.</p><p>In the case where the user cannot adapt its transmission power level to the fading state (i.e., the transmitter is under a short-term power constraint), the optimization problem is similar to (24)-(29), but with the average power constraint in (29) replaced by separate power constraints for each fading state:</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">P (s) i ≤ ¯ P i , s = 1, . . . , S, i = 1, . . . , M.<label>(31)</label></formula><p>Note that under the short-term power constraints of <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(31)</ref>, minimizing the expected cost function (30) decomposes into S independent optimization problems: i.e., each of</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">J(T (s) 1 , . . . , T<label>(s)</label></formula><p>M ), for s = 1, . . . , S, can be minimized separately.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. RELATIONS TO RATE REGION</head><p>In general, in a wireless network as defined in <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(1)</ref>- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(4)</ref>, minimizing a convex cost function J(T) of the completion times T 1 , . . . , T M is not equivalent to maximizing a concave utility function U (R) of the rates R 1 , . . . , R M . In particular, maximizing U (R) over the rate region is in general nonconvex <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>: at high SINR it can be approximately formulated as a GP, and in the medium-to low-SINR regime there are iterative approximation methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Suppose the cost function J + (T) is convex and nondecreasing in each argument T i , then completion time minimization is a special case of rate utility maximization where the optimization problem can be formulated as convex. To see that minimizing J + (T) can be posed as a rate utility maximization problem, we define the corresponding rate utility function:</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">U T (R) −J + (L 1 /R 1 , . . . , L M /R M ).<label>(32)</label></formula><p>Note that minimizing J + (T) is equivalent to maximizing U T (R), and the utility function U T (R) is concave in R as prescribed by the convexity composition rules <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Nevertheless, in the converse, some rate utility maximization problems can be formulated as minimizing convex functions of the completion times. Suppose we minimize a positively weighted sum of the completion times:</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">J w (T) = w 1 T 1 + · · · + w M T M , w 0, 1 T w = 1, (33)</formula><p>where denotes component-wise inequality, then it is equivalent to maximizing:</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">U d (R) = − w ′ 1 R 1 − · · · − w ′ M R M ,<label>(34)</label></formula><p>where U d (R) is the utility function that corresponds to minimum potential delay fairness <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, with w ′ i = w i L i , i = 1, . . . , M . In addition, minimizing J w (T) in (33) is also equivalent to maximizing the weighted harmonic mean of the rates:</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">U h (R) = w ′ 1 R 1 + · · · + w ′ M R M −1 .<label>(35)</label></formula><p>Note that by applying Jensen's inequality on the convex function 1/x for x ∈ R ++ , we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">1 w ′ 1 R 1 + · · · + w ′ M R M ≤ w ′ 1 R 1 + · · · + w ′ M R M ,<label>(36)</label></formula><p>which implies:</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">w ′ 1 R 1 + · · · + w ′ M R M ≥ U h (R).<label>(37)</label></formula><p>Hence maximizing U h (R) provides a lower bound to max w ′ 1 R 1 + · · · + w ′ M R M , which represents a weighted throughput of the wireless network. In particular, the bound is tight when R 1 = · · · = R M as equality is achieved in <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(36)</ref>; therefore, maximizing the minimum rate in (38) below can be formulated as a minimization of the convex cost function J x (T) as given in <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(39)</ref>, which corresponds to the maximum completion time:</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">U n (R) = min{R 1 , . . . , R M } (38) J x (T) = max{T 1 , . . . , T M }.<label>(39)</label></formula><p>Moreover, the entire rate region achievable under (10)-(11) can be characterized in terms of the corresponding completion time region. Specifically, the completion time region as characterized in (16)- <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(18)</ref> is convex, and its boundary are given by the minimizer of J w (T) in <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(33)</ref>  </p><formula xml:id="formula_36">¯ P = 0 0 dB, N = 0 0 dB,<label>(41)</label></formula><p>with maximum completion time constraints:</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">T i ≤ 100L i .</formula><p>The completion time region and its corresponding rate region are shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2 and Fig. 3</ref>, respectively. Note that the power constraints as given in (41) belong to the low SINR regime, where the high-SINR GP approximation does not readily apply. The completion time region is convex in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>; however, note that its rate region counterpart is non-convex as can be observed in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. ROBUST POWER CONTROL</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Outage Probability Constraints</head><p>In Section III, we assume that the channel power gains H ij 's can be accurately estimated. However, in a fading environment where the channel estimates are updated not as fast as the channels vary, the transmitters may not know the H ij 's perfectly. In this section, we consider the scenario where the channel gains are modeled as random variables: </p><formula xml:id="formula_38">H = W W ij ,<label>(42)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_39">R 1 (bits/channel use) R 2 (bits/channel use) Fig. 3. Rate region ( ¯ P 1 = ¯ P 2 = 0 dB).</formula><p>where the users know the joint probability distribution of W ij 's but do not know their realization. As in Section III-C, we assume the duration of a fading state is long compared to the packet completion times. Based on the channel distribution, each user i chooses a target SINR S i . Should the realized channel SINR fall below the target S i , the receiver cannot decode the transmitter's message, and it results in an outage event. To ensure the network operates with an acceptable level of reliability, we extend the completion time minimization framework in Section III to additionally consider constraints imposed on the permissible probability of outage. Specifically, we minimize the completion time cost function subject to a set of outage probability constraints:</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">q i ∈ [0, 1], i = 1, . . . , M ,</formula><p>where we stipulate that the probability of user i's transmission in outage not exceed q i . Incorporating the outage probability constraints q i 's, the minimization of the completion time cost function is described by the following stochastic programming <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">minimize J(T) (43) over T i , S i , P i subject to T i ≥ L i log(1 + S i ) (44) Pr P i W ii N i + j񮽙 =i P j W ij ≤ S i &lt; q i (45) 0 ≤ P i ≤ ¯ P i ,<label>(46)</label></formula><p>where i = 1, . . . , M . We show that the minimization in (43)-(46) can be posed as a convex optimization problem for a wide class of channel fading distributions commonly considered in wireless communications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Robust Convex Optimization</head><p>In terms of the transformed variables in <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(14)</ref>, we first define the reliability function as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">Φ i ( ˜ S i , ˜ P) Pr{user i not in outage} (47) = Pr˜W Pr˜ Pr˜W ii &gt; ln exp( ˜ S i − ˜ P i + ln N i ) + j񮽙 =i exp( ˜ S i − ˜ P i + ˜ P j + ˜ W ij ) ,<label>(48)</label></formula><p>where <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(48)</ref> follows from rearranging <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(45)</ref> with the additional change of variables:</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">˜ W ij ln W ij , i = 1, . . . , M, j = 1, . . . , M.<label>(49)</label></formula><p>Next, we characterize the reliability function in terms of the channel distribution. Let W i be an M -component nonnegative random vector that corresponds to the ith row of the channel matrix W:</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">W i W i1 . . . W iM T ,<label>(50)</label></formula><p>and w i ∈ R M + a realization of W i . Under (49), the transformed vectors˜Wvectors˜ vectors˜W i , ˜ w i are defined similarly. Let f Wi (w i ) denote the joint probability distribution function (pdf) of W i . Theorem 1 below describes the sufficient condition that establishs the log-concavity of Φ i ( ˜ S i , ˜ P), under which (43)-(46) can be posed as the following convex optimization problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">minimize J(T) (51) over T i , ˜ S i , ˜ P i subject to T i ≥ L i log 1 + exp( ˜ S i ) (52) ln Φ i ( ˜ S i , ˜ P) ≥ ln(1 − q i ) (53) ˜ P i ≤ ln ¯ P i ,<label>(54)</label></formula><p>where i = 1, . . . , M . Let exp(w i ) denote component-wise exponentiation of the vector w i .</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">Theorem 1. The reliability function Φ i ( ˜ S i , ˜ P) is log-concave iñ S i , ˜ P if f Wi exp(w i ) is log-concave in w i .</formula><p>The proof is given in the appendix. For example, the above condition is satisfied when each user experiences independent fading distributed as <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>: i) Rayleigh (richly scattered environments), ii) Nakagami (significant line-of-sight propagation), or iii) log-normal (shadowing due to signal attenuation). Therefore, in all these cases, completion time minimization subject to outage probability constraints can be formulated as convex optimization problem (51)-(54).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSIONS</head><p>In this paper we consider minimizing a convex function of the completion times of user packets by optimally allocating transmission power in a wireless network. We first focus on the scenario where the channel gains can be estimated accurately and are known by all users. We show that completion time minimization can be formulated as a convex optimization problem, and hence the corresponding optimal power allocation can be efficiently computed. The optimization formulation is valid for all ranges of SINR, which is especially pertinent for wireless sensor networks or delay-insensitive data applications where the users may transmit at moderate or low SINRs. Under fading channels with transmission power adaptation across fading states, an average power constraint can be incorporated into the optimization problem. We show that completion time minimization is a special case of rate utility maximization for which the optimization problem can be posed as convex. In particular, in a wireless network, although the feasible rate region is non-convex, the corresponding completion time region is shown to be convex. Finally, we consider robust power control under imperfect channel knowledge in fading channels. Completion times are minimized subject to outage probability constraints over the fading distribution, and we show that for a wide class of commonly used fading distributions, e.g., Rayleigh, Nakagami, and log-normal, robust power control can be posed as a convex optimization problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proof of Theorem 1</head><p>We first introduce, in terms of the transformed variables in (49), the notation of˜Wof˜ of˜W −i ∈ R M−1 representing the interfering channel random vector:</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">˜ W −i ˜ W i1 . . . ˜ W i i−1 ˜ W i i+1 . . . ˜ W iM T ,<label>(55)</label></formula><p>and˜wand˜ and˜w −i is a realization of˜Wof˜ of˜W −i . The pdf of˜Wof˜ of˜W −i is given by the marginal:</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">f ˜ W−i ( ˜ w −i ) = ˜ Wii f ˜ Wi ( ˜ w i ) d ˜ W ii .<label>(56)</label></formula><p>Next, conditioning oñ W −i = ˜ w −i , the reliability function in (48) is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">Φ i ( ˜ S i , ˜ P) = ˜ W−i φ i ( ˜ S i , ˜ P, ˜ w −i ) d ˜ w −i .<label>(57)</label></formula><p>For notational convenience, we write φ i ( ˜ S i , ˜ P, ˜ w −i ) as a composition of: </p><p>where F ˜ Wii ( ˜ w ii ) in (59) is the cumulative distribution function (cdf) of˜Wof˜ of˜W ii , and ¯ F ˜ Wii ( ˜ w ii ) is referred to as its complementary cdf, which is a nonincreasing function iñ w ii . Proof: In the construction of Φ i ( ˜ S i , ˜ P) in (57), with the application of Lemma 1 below, log-concavity is preserved <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> in the integration in (57), (56); multiplication in (58); complementary cdf in (59); and composition of a logarithmically concave, nonincreasing function with a convex function in (60).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 1. Under transformation (49), f ˜</head><p>Wi ( ˜ w i ) is logconcave iñ w i .</p><p>Proof: Consider the logarithm of the pdf of transformed random vector˜Wvector˜ vector˜W i :</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">ln f ˜ Wi ( ˜ w i ) = ln exp M j=1˜w j=1˜ j=1˜w ij f Wi exp( ˜ w i )<label>(61)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">= M j=1˜w j=1˜ j=1˜w ij + ln f Wi exp( ˜ w i ) ,<label>(62)</label></formula><p>where log-concavity of f Wi exp( ˜ w i ) iñ w i follows from assumption from Theorem 1.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. An AWGN wireless packet network with M = 2 users.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, T [i] denotes the ith largest component of T. Thus the cost function J r (T) is the sum of the r longest completion times. As special cases, r = 1 represents the maximum completion time: max{T 1 , . . . , T M }, and r = M represents the sum of the completion times: M i=1 T i . In (6), the cost function J p (T) is the ℓ p -norm of the user completion times.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>over all w 0, 1 T w = 1. In turn, from the monotonicity of (4), each minimal completion time vector T ⋆ = arg min J w (T) corresponds to a maximal rate vector R ⋆ on the boundary on the rate region (10)- (11), with R ⋆ i = L i /T ⋆ i , for i = 1, . . . , M . As a numerical example, we consider the following 2-user AWGN wireless packet network:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Completion time region ( ¯ P 1 = ¯ P 2 = 0 dB).</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Power control by geometric programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Palomar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>O&amp;apos;neill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Julian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2640" to="2651" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">MAPEL: Achieving global optimality for a non-convex wireless power control problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J A</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://arxiv.org/abs/0805.2675v2" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convexity of some feasible QoS regions and asymptotic behavior of the minimum total power in CDMA systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Boche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sta´nczaksta´nczak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2190" to="2197" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Log-convexity of minimal feasible total power in CDMA channels</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Symp. Personal, Indoor and Mobile Radio Commun</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Symp. Personal, Indoor and Mobile Radio Commun<address><addrLine>Beijing, China</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-09" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1456" to="1460" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimizing adaptive modulation in wireless networks via utility maximization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>O&amp;apos;neill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Goldsmith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Internat. Conf. Commun</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Internat. Conf. Commun<address><addrLine>Beijing, China</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-05" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3372" to="3377" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solving nonconvex power control problems in wireless networks: Low SIR regime and distributed algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Palomar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Globecom Conf</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Globecom Conf<address><addrLine>St. Louis, MO</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-11" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3445" to="3450" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed multiuser power control for digital subsriber lines</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ginis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cioffi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Sel. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1105" to="1115" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigations into cochannel interference in microcellular mobile radio systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y.-D</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">U H</forename><surname>Sheikh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal power control in interferencelimited fading wireless channels with outage-probability specifications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kandukuri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Vandenberghe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Convex Optimization</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Srikant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Mathematics of Internet Congestion Control. Birkhäuser</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Stochastic Programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Prékopa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles of Mobile Communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Stüber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
