<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:41+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">On the Hardness of Being Truthful</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Christos</forename><surname>Papadimitriou</surname></persName>
							<email>christos@cs.berkeley.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Computer Science Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California at Berkeley CA</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Schapira</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Computer Science Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Hebrew University Jerusalem</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="IL">Israel</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yaron</forename><surname>Singer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">University of California at Berkeley</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">On the Hardness of Being Truthful</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The central problem in computational mechanism design is the tension between incentive compatibility and computational efciency. We establish the rst significant approximability gap between algorithms that are both truthful and computationally-efcient, and algorithms that only achieve one of these two desiderata. This is shown in the context of a novel mechanism design problem which we call the COMBINATORIAL PUBLIC PROJECT PROBLEM (CPPP). CPPP is an abstraction of many common mechanism design situations, ranging from elections of kibbutz committees to network design. Our result is actually made up of two complementary results  one in the communication-complexity model and one in the computational-complexity model. Both these hardness results heavily rely on a combinatorial characterization of truthful algorithms for our problem. Our computational-complexity result is one of the rst impossibility results connecting mechanism design to complexity theory; its novel proof technique involves an application of the Sauer-Shelah Lemma and may be of wider applicability, both within and without mechanism design.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>In real networks, routing is done by routers that choose paths other than shortest, and this results in distance matrices that do not satisfy the triangle inequality.</p><p>In such a situation, it is often desirable to construct an overlay: A set of k nodes spread throughout the network and with high-quality routing between them, so that other nodes can improve the distance between them by routing through the closest overlay node. An overlay is beneecial to different nodes in different degrees, and we wish to design the overlay that maximizes total welfare. This is a typical instance of a general problem we dene, called COMBINATORIAL PUBLIC PROJECT PROB-LEM, or CPPP. There are n agents and m resources, and, for each agent i, a private valuation function v i which speciies i's value for every subset of the resources. We assume that all valuations are nondecreasing and submodular (a case that encompasses among many others the overlay network example above, see deenitions in Subsec 1.1). The objective is to nd a subset of the resources S of size k, where k is a parameter, which maximizes the social welfare, i.e., the sum of agents' values for the chosen subset Σ i v i (S).</p><p>Computationally speaking, this problem is relatively benign; while many of its special cases are NP-hard <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> it is well known <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> that the greedy algorithm achieves a constant approximation ratio (speciically, 1 − 1 e ).</p><p>But the fact that valuations are private presents us with a formidable problem: unless otherwise incentivized, agents are likely to lie, exaggerating the degree to which they prefer one alternative over another 1 , and this misrepresentation makes optimization impossible.</p><p>There is a very general method for providing incentives for the agents to reveal their true valuation, namely the Vickrey-Clarke-Groves (VCG) mechanism <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref>.</p><p>However, VCG requires that we solve exactly (typically many instances of) the CPPP  an NP-hard problem.</p><p>We could of course turn to approximation, as we always do when faced with intractability. The tragedy of this area is that approximation and truthfulness do not mix:</p><p>Running VCG with approximate solutions is, in general, not incentive compatible <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>.</p><p>In other words, efcient approximability and incentive compatibility seem to be at loggerheads. This tension underlies much of the work in algorithmic mechanism design <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. In this paper, we establish a huge gap between the quality of the solutions that can be obtained by algorithms for CPPP that are both polynomial and truthful, and by algorithms that satisfy only one of these two desiderata. We show this by proving that no truthful and computationally-efcient algorithm for CPPP can obtain any reasonable approximation ratio, speciically, a ratio better than √ m (this holds even for the case of two agents) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> . Our inapproximability result settles a long-standing open question in algorithmic mechanism design <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29]</ref>: we exhibit a problem (CPPP) that is easy from a computational perspective (a constant approximation algorithm exists), and from an economic perspective (an optimal truthful algorithm exists), but is hard (does not allow for constant approximations) if we care about both 3 .</p><p>Our result is actually made up of two complementary results  one in the communication-complexity model and one in the computational-complexity model. Technically speaking, each of these results must overcome two main challenges <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref>: First, we must provide a combinatorial characterization of truthful algorithms. Then, once we have such a characterization, we can exploit it to prove an inapproximability result.</p><p>An interesting way to view our results is the following: Over the past four decades, complexity theory has been successful in classifying optimization problems into various classes, such as P, NP, NP-hard, and APX (those problems that can be approximated within some constant factor in polynomial time). Mechanism design is about incentive-compatible optimization, in which the inputs are provided by agents who have their own objectives. In this new regime, for social-welfare maximization problems, 4 classical VCG theory implies that P, NP, and NP-hardness are preserved under truthfulness. Our computational-complexity result essentially states that APX is not preserved (our communication-complexity <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> We note that a simple truthful polynomial-time algorithm that obtains a √ m approximation ratio for CPPP shows that our result is tight in both models. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref> 3 It is known that algorithms that are both truthful and computationally-efcient might not perform (in terms of approximation ratio) as well as algorithms that only meet one of these two requirements. However, it was unclear by how much their performance is harmed. In fact, so far researchers have only been able to establish a gap of 2 between these two types of algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> See discussion about other optimization goals in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</p><p>result proves an analogous statement in the communication model).</p><p>Communication-complexity lower bound. Our rst main contribution is an exponential lower bound on the amount of communication required by any truthful algorithm that approximates the CPPP within any reasonable ratio:</p><p>Theorem: Any truthful algorithm for the CPPP that obtains an approximation ratio of O(m 1 2 − ) requires communication that is exponential in m (for every &gt; 0 and even for n = 2).</p><p>The rst step of the proof is showing that any truthful algorithm for CPPP must be an afne maximizer. An afne maximizer is an algorithm deened by a xed set of solutions, and which, given a set of valuations, picks the solution in the set that maximizes social welfare. A celebrated result by Roberts <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> essentially states that if an algorithm is truthful for all valuations, then it has to be an afne maximizer. However, this result does not necessarily hold when restricted to special settings (submodular valuations, etc.). In fact, for many restricted settings, truthful algorithms that are not afne maximizers are known (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>). In the present case, by carefully applying machinery from Roberts's (long and delicate) proof  actually, its recent interpretation by Lavi, Mu'alem and Nisan <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>  we are able to prove that any truthful algorithm for the nondecreasing submodular case of the CPPP is an afne maximizer. The proof explores the geometric and topological properties that must hold for any truthful algorithm for CPPP to prove afne maximization.</p><p>After providing this combinatorial characterization of truthfulness the second step is proving a lower bound for afne maximizers. We do this by proving a lower bound on the number of solutions in the range of the mechanism, and then exploiting afne maximization to to establish our communication-complexity lower bound.</p><p>The proof of the theorem draws ideas from works in many different elds of research (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>), and so we defer a discussion of the related work to Section 2.</p><p>Computational-complexity lower bound. Our previous result is a communication-complexity lower bound.</p><p>Informally, the agents are assumed to compute their valuations based on exponentially large data, and then it is shown that too much of this data must be exchanged for the algorithm to be truthful. However, many interesting valuations depend on very succinct data (recall the introductory overlay problem, in which the input is a distance matrix), and computational-complexity techniques would be needed to establish lower bounds for these; no such results had been known (with the possible exception of Theorem 5 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>). Our next major result does exactly this: We consider a class of nonnegative submodular (though not nondecreasing) valuations, that are succinctly described. We show that, despite the fact that a 1 − 1 e approximation exists for this class, no truthful and polynomial-time algorithm can obtain an approximation ratio (asymptotically) better than √ m. Lemma <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">33]</ref> 5 to obtain a hardness result. This result has interesting projections on complexity theory as discussed in section 3.</p><p>Organization of the paper. In the balance of this section we introduce the CPPP and the communicationand computational-complexity notions.</p><p>In the next section we prove our exponential communicationcomplexity lower bound, while in Section 3 we prove our computational-complexity lower bound. In Section 4 we discuss our results and present several open questions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Definitions</head><p>In CPPP there is a set of n agents {1, ..., n}, and a set of m resources {1, ..., m}. <ref type="bibr">Each</ref>  </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">S, T ⊆ [m] v i (S ∪ T ) + v i (S ∩ T ) ≤ v i (S) + v i (T )</formula><p>. Submodularity is known to be equivalent to the following easily veriiable property, called decreasing marginal utilities:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">For every S ⊂ T ⊆ [m], and for every j ∈ [m] such that j / ∈ T v i (S ∪ {j}) − v i (S) ≥ v i (T ∪ {j}) − v i (T ).</formula><p>Submodularity arises in many contexts  both economic <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> This lemma is closely related to the notion of the Vapnik-</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Chervonenkis (VC) dimension.</formula><p>and computational (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">35]</ref> and references therein). This paper focuses on submodular functions that are nondecreasing <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> in that S ⊆ T implies v(S) ≤ v(T ). Nondecreasing submodular functions are known to have particularly good properties; for example, they can be approximated within a ratio of 1 − 1 e (for general nonnegative submodular functions a constant approximation ratio exists <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>).</p><p>The objective in the CPPP is to nd a subset of size k, where k is a parameter of the problem, of resources which maximizes the social-welfare. That is, we wish to</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">nd T ∈ argmax S⊆[m], |S|=k Σ i v i (S).</formula><p>We are interested in algorithms (mechanisms) for CPPP satisfying three desiderata:</p><p>Quality of solution. We want our mechanisms to return a solution (set of resources) whose social welfare is as close, in terms of ratio, to the optimum as possible.</p><p>Computational effciency. Our algorithms should run in time that is polynomial in the natural parameters of the problem  m and n. However, as the input (the data enabling each agent to compute the valuation) can be exponential in m we must specify how it can be accessed. In mechanism design one often takes a black box approach (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>): We assume that valuations are computed by an oracle that can answer a certain type of queries, and we restrict algorithms to ask a polynomial number (in n and m) of such queries. There are two common types of queries:</p><p>• In the value query model a query is a subset of resources S ⊆ <ref type="bibr">[m]</ref>, and the answer is simply v i (S);</p><p>This weaker model is mainly used for designing algorithms.</p><p>• The general query model is equivalent to Yao's communication model <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref> A different approach would be to consider cases in which the input (valuations) can be concisely represented, i.e., can be encoded in a natural way that is polynomial in m and n. We follow this approach in Section 3.</p><p>Truthfulness. We want an algorithm (mechanism) A to be such that the agents are rationally motivated to truthfully answer the algorithm's queries. This is achieved by a payment function p which, for every n-tuple of valua- </p><formula xml:id="formula_4">tion functions v = (v 1 , ...v n ) ∈ V ,</formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">∀v i , v i ∈ V i , ∀v −i ∈ V −i , v i (A(v i , v −i ))−p(v i , v −i ) ≥ v i (A(v i , v −i ))−p(v i , v −i ),</formula><p>where V −i is the cartesian product of all V j 's such that  <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> (also see <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>). <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> The notion of truthfulness we consider is the standard notion of truthfulness in dominant strategies. All our results apply to the weaker notion of truthfulness in ex-post Nash.</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">j = i, (v i , v −i ) is</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">The Characterization Lemma</head><p>Let A be an algorithm for the nondecreasing submodular CPPP with m resources and parameter k. <ref type="bibr">We</ref>  </p><formula xml:id="formula_7">∀v = (v 1 , ..., v n ) A(v) ∈ argmax S∈R A [(Σ i w i v i (S)) + C S ].</formula><p>Lemma 2.3 Any truthful algorithm for the nondecreasing submodular CPPP with n = 2 is an afne-maximizer.</p><p>Remark 2.4 We note that, as we are aiming for an impossibility result, we prove the characterization lemma only for the 2-agent case. We shall later show that our inapproximability result holds even for this special case.</p><p>Proof: As is common in such proofs (see for example <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>), we study the topological structure of vectors of valuation differences. For any pair of valuation func-</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">tions v = (v 1 , v 2 ), we shall denote by v(S) − v(T ) the vector in 2 (v 1 (S) − v 1 (T ), v 2 (S) − v 2 (T )). We also deene P (S, T ) = {α ∈ 2 |∃ v s.t. A(v) = S and v(S) − v(T ) = α}.</formula><p>If A is an afne maximizer that outputs a set S for the valuation functions v = (v 1 , v 2 ) then it must hold that for every T = S in R A (for some xed agent-weights w 1 , w 2 and outcome-weights {C R } R∈R A )</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">(Σ i w i v i (S)) + C S ≥ (Σ i w i v i (T )) + C T , which implies that Σ i w i (v i (S) − v i (T )) + (C S − C T ) ≥ 0.</formula><p>Informally, observe that the inequalities above suggest that if A is an afne maximizer, then there is a line l in 2 of the form w 1 x + w 2 y = 0 such that every P (S, T ) has l as its lower boundary (possibly shifted by some constant γ(S, T ) = C S − C T from the centre of the axes). So, to prove that a truthful algorithm A is an afne maximizer, we need to show that there are weights w 1 , w 2 (and {C R } R ) that induce such a line l (the same l for all choices of S = T ∈ R A ). This is precisely what we mean to show. The reader is referred to <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> for an explanation of the geometric intuition behind the proof of Roberts' Theorem (which also underlies our proof).</p><p>Strong monotonicity.</p><p>We shall require the strong monotonicity property.  </p><formula xml:id="formula_10">v −i ∈ V −i , if A(v i , v −i ) = S and A(v i , v −i ) = T = S then it must hold that v i (S) − v i (T ) &gt; v i (S) − v i (T ).</formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">(S) − v(T ) ≤ v (S) − v (T ) (i.e., ≤ in each coor- dinate) then A(v ) = T .</formula><p>Proof: Assume, for point of contradiction, that the conditions stated in the theorem hold and</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">A(v ) = T . Let v = (v 1 , v 2 ) and v = (v 1 , v 2 ). Let α 1 = v 1 (S)−v 1 (T )</formula><p>. We shall prove the proposition for the case that α 1 ≥ 0 (the other case requires a very similar construction). Let j ∈ S \T (since all sets are of equal size such a j is guaranteed to exist). We deene a valuation function v 1 ∈ V 1 as follows (for some arbitrarily large β &gt; 0):</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">∀R v 1 (R) = α 1 |R ∩ {j}| + β|S||T | −β(|S| − |S ∩ R|)(|T | − |T ∩ R|)</formula><p>It is easy to verify that this is indeed a nondecreasing submodular function (this construction is inspired by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>). We shall now show that A(v 1 , v 2 ) = S. This is because if A(</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">v 1 , v 2 ) = Q = S then, by strong monotonicity, v 1 (S) − v 1 (Q) &gt; v 1 (S) − v 1 (Q)</formula><p>. It is easy to show that if Q = S, T then this results in a contradiction (as we can set the value of β to be as high as we like). Observe that if we set Q = T then this too results in a contradiction. Similarly, we can show that A(v 1 , v 2 ) = T . However, in this case by strong monotonicity we have that v 2 (S) − v 2 (T ) &gt; v 2 (S) − v 2 (T ).</p><p>A contradiction.</p><p>Main part of the proof.</p><p>Claim 2.7 Let α ∈ P (S, T ) for some S, T ∈ R A . Let = ( 1 , 2 ) ≥ 0. Then, α + ∈ P (S, T ).</p><p>Proof: Since α = (α 1 , α 2 ) ∈ P (S, T ) then, by deenition, there are valuation functions v = (v 1 , v 2 ) such that A(v) = S and v(S)−v(T ) = α. We prove the claim for the case α ≥ 0 (other cases are handled similarly). Let j ∈ S \ T . We deene valuation functions v = (v 1 , v 2 )</p><p>as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">∀R v 1 (R) = (α 1 + 1 )|R ∩ {j}| + β|S||T | −β(|S| − |S ∩ R|)(|T | − |T ∩ R|) ∀R v 2 (R) = (α 2 + 2 )|R ∩ {j}| + β|S||T | −β(|S| − |S ∩ R|)(|T | − |T ∩ R|)</formula><p>The use of strong monotonicity (as in the proof of Proposition 2.6) and of Proposition 2.6 itself shows that A(v 1 , v 2 ) = S. Similarly, we can then show that A(v 1 , v 2 ) = S. Observe that v (S) − v (T ) = α + . Therefore, by deenition, α + ∈ P (S, T ).</p><p>Claim 2.7 tells us something important about the structure of the different P (S, T ) sets in 2 : If a point is in P (S, T ) then so are all points above it and to the right of it. Hence, each P (S, T ) is deened by a lower boundary with a nonincreasing slope. However, we do not yet know that this nonincreasing slope is a straight line (and certainly not that it is the same straight line for all choices of S, T ). We shall require the two following technical propositions: Proposition 2.8 For any S = T ∈ R A α ∈ P (S, T ) iff −α / ∈ P (T, S).</p><p>Proof:</p><p>Let α = (α 1 , α 2 ) ∈ P (S, T ). Then, by definition, there exists v = (v 1 , v 2 ) such that A(v) = S and v(S) − v(T ) = α. Suppose, for point of contradiction, that −α ∈ P (T, S). Then, by deenition, there exists v = (v 1 , v 2 ) such that A(v) = T and v (T ) − v (S) = −α (or, v (S) − v (T ) = α). However, by Proposition 2.6 this is impossible (A(v ) cannot equal T ).</p><p>We now prove the other direction, which is equivalent to showing that if α / ∈ P (S, T ) then −α ∈ P (T, S). Since S is in R A there must be valuation</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">functions v = (v 1 , v 2 ) such that A(v) = S. Let α W = v(S) − v(W ).</formula><p>We prove the proposition for the case α ≥ 0 (other cases are handled similarly). Let j ∈ S \ T . We deene valuation functions v = (v 1 , v 2 ) as follows (we choose β to be huge, and in particular higher than the values of all coordinates of all the different α W 's):</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">∀R v 1 (R) = α 1 |R ∩ {j}| + β|S||T | −β(|S| − |S ∩ R|)(|T | − |T ∩ R|) ∀R v 2 (R) = α 2 |R ∩ {j}| + β|S||T | −β(|S| − |S ∩ R|)(|T | − |T ∩ R|)</formula><p>The repeated use of Proposition 2.6 for every W ∈ R A such that W = S, T shows that A(v 1 , v 2 ) must be in {S, T }. However, since v (S) − v (T ) = α and α / ∈ P (S, T ), it must be that A(v ) = T . Observe that v (T ) − v (S) = −α. So, by deenition of P (T, S), −α ∈ P (T, S). Proposition 2.9 For any S, T, W ∈ R A , such that no two are equal, if α ∈ P (S, T ) and α ∈ P (T, W ) then α + α ∈ P (S, W ).</p><p>Proof:</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">Let α = (α 1 , α 2 ). Let α = (α 1 , α 2 )</formula><p>. Let Y be an additive valuation function such that ∀j / ∈ S ∪ T ∪ W Y ({j}) = 0 and the two following properties hold:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">• Σ j∈S Y ({j}) − Σ j∈T Y ({j}) = α 1 • Σ j∈T Y ({j}) − Σ j∈W Y ({j}) = α 1</formula><p>Observe that because the number of variables is greater than the number of equations such a function Y exists. Since S, T, W are of equal size we can also assume that Y only assigns nonnegative values (otherwise increase the value of each j ∈ S ∪ T ∪ W by some identical large enough constant).</p><p>Similarly, let Z be an additive valuation function such that ∀j / ∈ S ∪ T ∪ W Z({j}) = 0 and the two following properties hold:</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">• Σ j∈S Z({j}) − Σ j∈T Z({j}) = α 2 • Σ j∈T Z({j}) − Σ j∈W Z({j}) = α 2</formula><p>We deene (for some huge β to be determined later) the following valuations v = (v 1 , v 2 ):</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">∀R v 1 (R) = Y (R) + β|S||T |− β(|S| − |S ∩ R|)(|T | − |T ∩ R|) ∀R v 2 (R) = Z(R) + β|S||T |− β(|S| − |S ∩ R|)(|T | − |T ∩ R|)</formula><p>Since α ∈ P (S, T ) there must be some valuations v = (v 1 , v 2 ) such that A(v) = S. The repeated use of Proposition 2.6 (as in the proof of Proposition 2.8)</p><p>shows that A(v ) ∈ {S, W }. Similarly, by taking advantage of the fact that α ∈ P (T, W ) one can show (using similar arguments) that A(v ) ∈ {S, T }. We conclude that A(v ) = S. <ref type="bibr">Observe that</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_22">v (S) − v (W ) = (v (S) − v (T )) + (v (T ) − v (W )) = α + α . Hence, by deenition of P (S, W ) α + α ∈ P (S, W ).</formula><p>We shall prove our result for the case that − → 0 = (0, 0) ∈ P (S, T ) for every S = T ∈ R A . This greatly simpliies the exposition and enables us to convey the main idea of the proof. The proof for the more general case is achievable via the exact same logic as presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> (claim 4 and the following claims in the rst proof in that paper follow from what we have proven thus far).</p><p>Corollary 2.10 For every S = T, U = W ∈ R A it holds that P (S, T ) = P (U, W ).</p><p>Proof:</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">Let α ∈ P (S, T ). As − → 0 ∈ P (T, W ), we have that α = α + − → 0 ∈ P (S, W ). We also know that − → 0 ∈ P (U, S), and so α = − → 0 + α ∈ P (U, W ).</formula><p>That is, all the P (S, T ) sets (for every choice of S, T ) are, in fact, the very same set, that we shall refer to as </p><formula xml:id="formula_24">= (α + α ) + (− α+α 2 ) ∈ X. A contradiction.</formula><p>By repeatedly using this fact, we can, for any α, α ∈ X and λ ∈ (0, 1) build a series of points that approach λα+(1−λ)α , such that any point in the series has a ball of small radius that is fully contained in X. This (and the openness of V ) sufces to prove that λα + (1 − λ)α ∈ X. Now we know that X is convex and therefore has a lower boundary in the form of a straight line l. Moreover, l goes through the origin of the axes − → 0 , as by Proposition 2.8 α ∈ X iff −α / ∈ X. So, l can be described by w 1 x + w 2 y = 0 for some positive constants w 1 , w 2 (recall that l's slope is nonincreasing). Therefore, we get that A is an afne maximizer (for agentweights w 1 , w 2 and by setting all outcome-weights to be 0). This concludes the proof of the lemma. </p><formula xml:id="formula_25">v i (S ∪ {j}) − v i (S) &gt; v i (T ∪ {j}) − v i (T )). Claim 2.14 V strict is an open domain.</formula><p>Proof: Consider some v = (v 1 , ..., v n ) ∈ V strict . Let δ be the minimal gap caused by the above strict inequalities (taken over all possible sets of resources, agents,  </p><formula xml:id="formula_26">∀S ⊆ [m] |v i (S) − v i (S)| ≤ .</formula><p>Proof:</p><p>Fix some &gt; 0 and valuation function v i that is nondecreasing and submodular. Let &lt;&lt; . Let g be a valuation function such that ∀R ⊆ <ref type="bibr">[m]</ref> g (R) = |R| − 2 |R| 2 m+1 . The reader can verify that this function is strictly nondecreasing and has strictly decreasing marginal utilities. Moreover, for any nondecreasing submodular valuation function v and for any it holds that v i = v i + g is strictly nondecreasing and has strictly decreasing marginal utilities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Lower Bound for Affine Maximizers</head><p>Let k, the number of chosen resources in the CPPP, be xed to √ m throughout this subsection. We shall now</p><p>show that any algorithm A that obtains a reasonable approximation ratio must have a range R A of exponential size. We will then exploit afne maximization to show that the size of the range is a lower bound on the communication complexity. independently with probability p = m − 1 2 + , where &gt; 0 is small and xed, and consider the valuation function v(S) = |S ∩ V |. We claim that, unless R A contains at least Ω(e m ) sets, with high probability it approximates v very poorly.</p><p>Indeed, it follows from the Chernoff bound that, for any small δ &gt; 0, with probability at least 1 − |R A | · exp(δ 2 m 1 2 + ), in this instance of CPPP the optimum |V | is at least (1 − δ)m 1 2 + , while the solution returned by the afne maximizer will be at most (1 + δ)m ). The lemma follows.</p><p>The following now concludes the proof of our main result:</p><p>Lemma 2.17 Any afne maximizer A with range R A requires Ω(|R A |) communication, even for n = 2.</p><p>Proof: (Sketch) Consider an afne maximizer A with range R A . We shall construct two submodular valuation functions which require Ω(|R A |) communication in order to achieve optimality in the range R A . Recall that A maximizes w 1 v 1 (S) + w 2 v 2 (S) + C S over all S ∈ R A ; it is easy to see that one can assume w 1 = w 2 = 1 for all S, w.l.o.g. Now, suppose that each agent i has a private set R i A ⊆ R A , which induces the following valuation function: • There is a polynomial-time algorithm for the CPPP with valuations in C that approximates the optimal social-welfare within a ratio of 1 − 1 e .</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">v i (T ) = β · (Π S∈R i A |S| − Π S∈R i A (|S| − |S ∩ T |)) ∀T ⊆ [m].</formula><p>• Any truthful and polynomial-time algorithm cannot achieve an approximation ratio better than m 1 2 − unless NP ⊆ BPP (for every &gt; 0).</p><p>We shall start by proving our lower bound for afne maximizers. We shall then show how this result can be extended to any truthful algorithm. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Lower Bound For</head><formula xml:id="formula_28">T ⊆ [m]: ∀S ⊆ [m], v F,T (S) = | j∈S R j | − |T | (max{0, |S ∩ T | − |T | 2 }) (</formula><p>for some extremely small value of ). Intuitively, for every S ⊆ [m], v F,T assigns a value that equals the number of elements in U covered by the union of the sets in F with indices in S, minus an insigniicant penalty if S has too many elements in common with T . It is easy to verify that this function is indeed nonnegative <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> and submodular (but not nondecreasing).</p><p>Observe that for any value of k, it is easy to obtain a 1 − 1 e approximation ratio for CPPP with coveragepenalty valuations (simply ignore the penalty terms in the deenitions of the v i 's and apply the 1 − 1 e greedy approximation algorithm). We shall now show that despite this fact, any afne-maximizer fails to obtain a reasonable approximation ratio:   <ref type="bibr">[m]</ref> of size Θ( m log m ) that is shattered by R A . The idea is now to embed a small, but still polynomially large, instance of an NP-complete problem in M . We shall do this for the problem in which we have a family F of t subsets of a universe U and wish to determine whether there are t 2 sets in F whose union covers the entire universe (which is known to be NP-complete). </p><formula xml:id="formula_29">f : [q] → {0, 1} there is a sub- set Z ∈ Z for which |Z ∩ Q j | = f (j) for all j ∈ [q].</formula><p>The probabilistic polynomial-time reduction from our NP-complete problem is very similar to the nonuniform reduction shown above. The key idea is nding pairwise-disjoint subsets of <ref type="bibr">[m]</ref> as in the statement of Lemma 3.4, and then associating each subset of the universe in the NP-complete problem with all elements in one of the pairwise-disjoint subsets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Connection to Complexity Theory</head><p>This technique has an interesting projection in complexity theory: Call a language L ⊆ {0, 1} * exponentially dense if there is some α &gt; 0, and some integer N , such that for any integer n &gt; N it holds that |L ∩ {0, 1} n | ≥ 2 n α . For a language L ⊆ {0, 1} * , dene SAT L to be the problem: Given a CNF, is there a truth assignment in L that satisses it? The proof technique implies that:</p><p>Theorem 3.5 Let L be any exponentially dense language. If SAT L is in P, then NP ⊆ P/poly.</p><p>Observe that we do not know how to relax the computational hardness assumption to NP ⊆ BPP (e.g., via the probabilistic version of the Sauer-Shelah Lemma).</p><p>For the problem CIRCUIT SAT, however, we can prove this stronger result via a different technique: Theorem 3.6 Let L be any exponentially dense language. If CIRCUIT SAT L is in P, then NP ⊆ BPP.</p><p>Proof: (Sketch) To solve a given CNF φ on n variables, start with a large enough N so that L contains at least 2 n 2 strings of length N . Now hash these N bits (by a circuit computing a sampled universal hashing function) into n bits. With very high probability, the 2 n 2 bitstrings in L of length N will cover, after hashing, all 2 n bitstrings of length n. Then feed these n bits into a veriier circuit for φ. It is not hard to see that, with high probability, this overall circuit, with N inputs, has a satisfying truth assignment in L if and only if φ is satissable.</p><p>It would be very interesting to extend this idea (or the ideas in the proof of Lemma 3.4) to SAT L .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Extension to All Truthful Algorithms</head><p>We is computationally intractable under weaker computational assumptions. We suspect that this is possible, but the precise way of doing this eludes us at the moment.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>As in our communication-complexity result, the proof of this result consists of two parts: Proving that any truthful algorithm must be an afne-maximizer, and proving a hardness result for afne-maximizers. The main challenge now lies in the second part (the rst part is basically derived from the characterization of truth- fulness in our communication complexity result). The heart of our proof is therefore showing the following in- approximability result for a class of succinct submodular functions we call coverage-penalty valuations: Theorem: For CPPP with coverage-penalty valua- tions there is no polynomial-time afne maximizer with O(m 1 2 − ) approximation ratio unless NP ⊆ BPP (for every &gt; 0). To establish this, we rst show, very much as in the proof of our communication-complexity result, an ex- ponential lower bound on the number of solutions, and then we use a probabilistic version of the Sauer-Shelah</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Not</head><label></label><figDesc>any truthful algorithm is necessarily strongly- monotone (and vice-versa), yet we shall prove the theo- rem for strongly-monotone algorithms. At the end of the proof we shall revisit this assumption and explain why it can be removed. The following proposition shall play a crucial role in our proofs. Proposition 2.6 Let A be a strongly monotone algo- rithm, and let v ∈ V be such that A(v) = S. If v ∈ V and v</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Removing the Strong Monotonicity and Open Do- main Assumptions. So far, the proof of the Charac- terization Lemma relied on the assumptions that the al- gorithms in question are strongly monotone and that the domain of valuations is open. Here we exploit the fol- lowing machinery to do away with these: Theorem 2.13 [16] If a domain of valuations V is open, then for every truthful algorithm A there exists an algorithm A that satisses strong monotonicity such that if A is an afne maximizer then so is A. Theorem 2.13 implies the following modus operandi: We shall focus on a rich open subdomain of the do- main of all nondecreasing submodular valuation func- tions. We shall show that all our arguments actually ap- ply to that domain. Since in that domain truthfulness is equivalent to strong monotonicity (in the sense stated by Theorem 2.13) this will conclude the proof. We now provide a way to slightly tweak all constructions of valu- ation functions in Subsections 2.1 and 2.2 to ensure that they all belong to this open domain. Speciically, we deene the strict domain V strict to be the domain of all valuations that are strictly non- decreasing (i.e., ∀S ⊂ T ⊆ [m] and ∀i ∈ [n] v i (S) &lt; v i (T )) and have strictly decreasing marginal utilities. (i.e., ∀S ⊂ T ⊆ [m], ∀j / ∈ T and ∀i ∈ [n]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>etc.).</head><label></label><figDesc>It is easy to see that = δ 3 meets the requirement in the deenition of an open domain. We now show that any nondecreasing and submod- ular valuation function can be slightly tweaked to t in V strict . Hence, we can prove our theorem for the case that all valuations ar slightly tweaked in this manner. The reader may verify that (for sufciently small choices</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>)</head><label></label><figDesc>all the arguments in this section also apply to these slightly different constructions of valuation functions. Claim 2.15 For any nondecreasing and submodular valuation function v i ∈ V i , and any &gt; 0, there exists a valuation function v i ∈ V i that is strictly nondecreasing and has strictly decreasing marginal utilities such that</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Lemma 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>16 For any algorithm A that obtains an ap- proximation ratio of m 1 2 − to the optimal social welfare it must hold that |R A | = Ω(e m ), even for n = 1. Proof: (Sketch) Consider an algorithm A with range R A . Choose a set of resources V ⊆ [m] by sampling [m]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Theorem 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>2 No polynomial-time afne maximizer for CPPP with coverage-penalty valuations achieves an ap- proximation ratio better than m 1 2 − unless NP ⊆ BPP (for every &gt; 0 and even for n = 1). Proof: (Sketch) Fix k = √ m and n = 1. Let A be an afne maximizer as in the statement of the the- orem (w.l.o.g. assume that the agent-weights are 1 and outcome-weights are 0</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>extend our lower bound to all truthful algorithms by relying on the following simple observation: All the submodular functions that are constructed as part of the proof of the Characterization Lemma (Lemma 2.3 in Section 2) are, in fact, succinctly described. We can therefore deene a class of succinctly described valua- tion functions C, that contains the families of functions constructed in Lemma 2.3 and all coverage-penalty val- uations. It is easy to see that an approximation of 1 − 1 e is achievable for the CPPP when the valuation functions are in C (this is because coverage-penalty valuations are ar- bitrarily close to nondecreasing submodular valuations and all other valuations in C are nondecreasing and sub- modular). Because of the way we deened C one can show (by carefully applying the proof of Lemma 2.3 to this case) that any truthful algorithm for the CPPP with valuations in C is an afne-maximizer. We can now use Theorem 3.2 to obtain our result. 4 Discussion and Open Problems What are the limitations of our techniques? It would be very interesting to explore for which mechanism de- sign problems one can prove characterizations similar to that shown in Lemma 2.3 (for the CPPP), thus proving unconditional lower bounds. It would also be very inter- esting to extend the proof technique of Theorem 3.2 to other succinctly described settings. We believe that such computational hardness results can be shown for many other mechanism design problems, such as combinato- rial auctions. Finally, a big computational-complexity- related open question is proving that mechanism design</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>agent has a pri- vate valuation function v i : 2 [m] → ≥0 . We de- note by V i the space of possible valuations of agent i, and by V the domain of valuations V 1 × . . . × V n . We shall assume that v i (∅) = 0. We assume that every v i is submodular, i.e., for every</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>demands a payment from each agent. p is such that no agent can increase his utility (the value of the set chosen by the algorithm minus the payment assigned to him) by misreporting his valuation 7 . Formally, for every i ∈ [n] we have that:</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>the valuations proole in which i has v i and the other agents have v −i , (v i , v −i ) is deened similarly, and A(v) is the set A outputs for the valuation proole v. 21 2 − ) requires ex- ponential communication (for every &gt; 0 and even for n = 2).</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Communication-Complexity of Mecha-

nism Design 

In this section we prove the following: 

Theorem 2.1 Any truthful algorithm for CPPP that ob-

tains an approximation ratio of O(m 

The proof proceeds in two steps: We rst establish 

(Lemma 2.3) that any truthful algorithm for the CPPP 

must be of a very restricted kind called an afne max-

imizer. We then show that any afne maximizer for 

the CPPP requires exponential communication (Lem-

mas 2.16 and 2.17). This second part uses techniques 

introduced by Dobzinski and Nisan [5] for proving com-

munication complexity lower bounds for afne maxi-

mizers. 

The Characterization Lemma is the heart of our 

proof. It establishes that the CPPP has a rich enough 

structure, and appropriately strong interaction between 

the agents, so that a subtle variant of Roberts's proof 

[28] is enabled. The line of argument used in our proof 

follows that of Roberts', as presented by Lavi, Mu'alem, 

and Nisan [17]. However, applying this machinery to 

our setting is not straightforward as we are dealing with 

a restricted domain of valuation functions (submodu-

lar, nondecreasing). Therefore, we must handle various 

technical difculties: We must ensure that the valuation 

functions we construct belong to this restricted domain. 

We must also take measures to deal with the fact that our 

valuation domain is not open (in the standard topological 

sense). Unlike Roberts' proof, our proof makes repeti-

tive use of the strong monotonicity constraint introduced 

in </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><head>deene A's range R A to be the resource subsets of size k that are output by A for some input, i.e., R A = {S| ∃v == S}. Informally, A is an afne- maximizer if it always optimizes over its entire range R A .algorithm A is said to be an afne maximizer if there exist nonnegative agent weights w 1 , ..., w n (not all equal to 0), and outcome weights {C S } S∈R A such that</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>(v 1 , ..., v n ) s.t. A(v) Deenition 2.2 ([28]) An </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="false"><head>X . We shall now prove that X is convex, thus showing that the (lower) boundary of X (which we know is non- increasing) must be a straight line 8 . Our proof for the convexity of X relies on the assumption that the domain of valuations V is open. Unfortunately, it is not true that) ∈ V , there is some &gt; 0 such that for all v =), if ∀S ⊆ M and ∀i ∈ [n], |v i (S) − v i (S)| ≤ then v ∈ V . Proposition 2.12 X is convex. Proof: We rst show that if α, α ∈ X then α+α 2 ∈ X. Suppose, by contradiction, that α, α ∈ X but α+α 2 / ∈ X. By Proposition 2.9 α + α ∈ X, and by Proposi- tion 2.8 − α+α 2 ∈ X. However, Proposition 2.9 now implies that α+α 2</head><label>X</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>the domain of nondecreasing submodular valuations is 

open. At the end of the Characterization Lemma's proof 

we revisit this assumption and show how it too can be 

removed. 

Deenition 2.11 A domain of valuations V is open if for 
each v = (v 1 , ..., v n (v 
1 , ..., v 
n </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7" validated="false"><head>Note that since β can be arbi- trarily large, w.l.o.g. we can consider the case in which C S = 0 for all S ∈ R A . Observe that if A maximizes over the range R A , it implicitly distinguishes between the case for which R 1 A and R 2 A intersect, and the case in which R 1 A ∩ R 2 A = ∅. Therefore this is a reduction from</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>the communication set-disjointness problem, establish-

ing that Ω(|R A |) communication is required. 

3 
Computational-Complexity of Mecha-

nism Design 

We now describe a simple new technique for de-

riving computational-complexity (not communication-

complexity) lower bounds for mechanism design prob-

lems, which we believe has much broader applicabil-

ity. In particular, we show that, even if agents have 

succinctly described valuations, CPPP is inapproximable 

in polynomial time by truthful algorithms, unless NP ⊆ 

BPP. Speciically, we prove the following theorem: 

Theorem 3.1 There is a class of succinctly-described, 

nonnegative and submodular valuation functions C such 

that: 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8" validated="false"><head>T is deened by a family F = R 1 , ...R m of m subsets of a universe U , and a subset</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Affine Maximiz-
ers. 

We deene a class of succinctly described valua-

tion functions called coverage-penalty valuations. A 

coverage-penalty valuation v F,</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9" validated="false"><head>). R A consists of subsets of [m] of size √ m that are assigned by A to different inputs., there is a subset Q of R of size Θ( log |Z| log |R| ) such that for each Q ⊆ Q there is a Z ∈ Z such that Q = Z ∩ R. Hence, coming back to the afne maximizer, there is a subset M of</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Exactly as in Lemma 2.16, it can be shown that R A must 
contain Ω(e m ) sets. We now recall the Sauer-Shelah 

Lemma: 

Lemma 3.3 ([30, 33]) For any family Z of subsets of a 
universe R</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10" validated="false"><head>The embedding is as follows: We construct a coverage- penalty valuation function v for which each element in M corresponds to one of the t subsets in F , and all other elements in [m] correspond to empty sets. We set the penalty set T to equal M . Now, observe that the value of the set output by the afne maximizer A equals |U | iff there are t 2 sets in F whose union covers U .(see [27, 31, 20] on the complexity of making Sauer-Shelah Lemma constructive). However, this non- uniform reduction is sufcient to show that if A obtains an approximation ratio better than m 1 2 − in polynomial time then NP has polynomial-size circuits, i.e., NP ⊆ P/poly. By using the probabilistic version of the Sauer-that is regular (i.e., all subsets in Z are of equal size) and Q ≥ 2 |R| α (for some 0 &lt; α ≤ 1). There are integers q, l (where |R|, q and l are polynomially related) such that if we randomly choose q pairwise- disjoint subsets of R, Q 1 , ..., Q q , each of size l, then</head><label>embedding</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>The above suggests a non-uniform reduction from an 

NP-hard problem to the problem of calculating the out-

put of the afne maximizer in question. The reason the 

reduction is non-uniform (and thus it does not establish 

NP-completeness) is because we do not know how to 

nd M Shelah Lemma presented by Ajtai [1] we can turn the re-

duction described above into a probabilistic polynomial-

time reduction (thus concluding the proof of the theo-

rem). 

Lemma 3.4 ([1]) Let Z be a family of subsets of a uni-
verse R , 
w.h.p., for every function </table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> According to a March 26 2008 Gallup poll, 28% of Clinton&apos;s supporters declare that they will not vote for Obama in a presidential election.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="6"> We slightly relax this assumption in Section 3.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="8"> Observe that if we deene −X = {−α| α ∈ X} then the convexity of X implies the convexity of −X. If X and −X are convex, their union is 2 , and their interiors are disjoint (by Proposition 2.8), then they must be separated by a straight line.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="9"> This may not be true if some of the R i &apos;s are the empty set. However, this is easily handled by simply adding to v F,T (S) for every S.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank Moshe Babaioff, Liad Blumrosen,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Venkatesan Guruswami, Luca Trevisan, Gregory</head><p>Valiant and Umesh Vazirani for helpful discussions. We thank the anonymous reviewers for valuable comments.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The shortest vector problem in L 2 is NP-hard for randomized reductions (extended abstract)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ajtai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">STOC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="19" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An approximate truthful mechanism for combinatorial auctions with single parameter agent</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Archer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Papadimitriou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Talwar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tardos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 14th Annual ACM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA)</title>
		<meeting>the 14th Annual ACM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incentive compatible multi unit combinatorial auctions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bartal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">TARK 03</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multipart pricing of public goods</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Clarke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Public Choice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="1971" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Limitations of VCG-based mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dobzinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">STOC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximation algorithms for combinatorial auctions with complement-free bidders</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dobzinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schapira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">STOC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An improved approximation algorithm for combinatorial auctions with submodular bidders</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dobzinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schapira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SODA 06</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On characterizations of truthful mechanisms for combinatorial auctions and scheduling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dobzinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sundararajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM conference on electronic commerce (EC)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On maximizing welfare when the utility functions are subadditive</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Feige</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">STOC 06</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A threshold of ln n for approximating set cover</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Feige</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="634" to="652" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximizing nonmonotone submodular functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Feige</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mirrokni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vondrak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">FOCS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximation algorithms for allocation problems: Improving the factor of 1 − 1/e</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Feige</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vondrak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">FOCS 06</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed algorithmic mechanism design: recent results and future directions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Feigenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">6th International Workshop on Discrete Algorithms and Methods for Mobile Computing and Communications</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incentives in teams</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Groves</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="617" to="631" />
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Communication Complexity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kushilevitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards a characterization of truthful combinatorial auctions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">FOCS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Two simpliied proofs for Roberts&apos; Theorem</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Submitted</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combinatorial auctions with decreasing marginal utilities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lehmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lehmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In ACM conference on electronic commerce</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Tight information-theoretic lower bounds for welfare maximization in combinatorial auctions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mirrokni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schapira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vondrak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Working paper</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the complexity of approximating the VC dimension</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mossel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Umans</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comput. Syst. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="660" to="671" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Setting lower bounds on truthfulness</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schapira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SODA</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An analysis of approximations for maximizing submodular set functions ii</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Nemhauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wolsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Programming Study</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The communication complexity of approximate set packing and covering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ICALP</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computationally feasible VCGbased mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ronen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Conference on Electronic Commerce</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Algorithmic mechanism design. Games and Economic Behaviour</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ronen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="166" to="196" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>A preliminary version appeared in STOC</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The communication requirements of efcient allocations and supporting prices</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Segal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JET</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On limited nondeterminism and the complexity of the V-C dimension</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Papadimitriou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yannakakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computer and System Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The characterization of implementable choice rules</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>J.-J. Laffont</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Aggregation and Revelation of Preferences. Papers presented at the 1st</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Summer Workshop of the Econometric Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="349" />
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An algorithmic game theory primer</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Roughgarden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 5th IFIP International Conference on Theoretical Computer Science (TCS)</title>
		<meeting>the 5th IFIP International Conference on Theoretical Computer Science (TCS)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>An invited survey</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the density of families of sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comb. Theory, Ser. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="1972" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deciding the Vapnik-Cervonenkis dimension is Σ p 3 -complete</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schäfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computer and System Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Inapproximability of combinatorial public projects. Working paper</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schapira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Singer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A combinatorial problem; stability and order for models and theories in innnitary languages</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shelah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Paciic J Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="247" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="1972" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Counterspeculation, auctions and competitive sealed tenders</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Vickrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Finance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="1961" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal approximation for the submodular welfare problem in the value oracle model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vondrak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">STOC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Some complexity questions related to distributive computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">-C</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="213" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
