<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:41+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Building Algorithmically Nonstop Fault Tolerant MPI Programs</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rui</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Computing Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Mathematics and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">State Key Laboratory of Computer Architecture</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">Argonne National Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Erlin</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
							<email>yaoerlin@ict.ac.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Computing Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Mathematics and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">State Key Laboratory of Computer Architecture</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">Argonne National Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mingyu</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Computing Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Mathematics and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">State Key Laboratory of Computer Architecture</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">Argonne National Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Guangming</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Computing Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Mathematics and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">State Key Laboratory of Computer Architecture</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">Argonne National Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pavan</forename><surname>Balaji</surname></persName>
							<email>balaji@mcs.anl.gov</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Computing Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Mathematics and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">State Key Laboratory of Computer Architecture</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">Argonne National Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Darius</forename><surname>Buntinas</surname></persName>
							<email>buntinas@mcs.anl.gov</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Computing Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Mathematics and Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab1">State Key Laboratory of Computer Architecture</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory" key="lab2">Argonne National Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Building Algorithmically Nonstop Fault Tolerant MPI Programs</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Nonstop</term>
					<term>Algorithm-Based Fault Tolerance</term>
					<term>High Performance Linpack</term>
					<term>MPICH</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>With the growing scale of high-performance computing (HPC) systems, today and more so tomorrow, faults are a norm rather than an exception. HPC applications typically tolerate fail-stop failures under the stop-and-wait scheme, where even if only one processor fails, the whole system has to stop and wait for the recovery of the corrupted data. It is now a more-or-less accepted fact that the stop-and-wait scheme will not scale to the next generation of HPC systems. Inspired by the previous stop-and-wait algorithm-based fault tolerance (ABFT) recovery technique, we propose in this paper a nonstop fault tolerance scheme at the application level and describe its implementation. When failure occurs during the execution of applications, we do not stop to wait for the recovery of the corrupted node; instead, we replace it with the corresponding redundant node and continue the execution. At the end of execution, the correct solution can be recovered algorithmically at a very low cost. In order to implement the scheme, some new fault-tolerant features of the Message Passing Interface (MPI) have been investigated and utilized in the MPICH implementation of MPI. We also describe a case study using High Performance Linpack (HPL) with these new features and evaluate the performance of both our new scheme and ABFT recovery. Experimental results show the advantage of our new scheme over ABFT recovery even in a small scale.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>The largest systems in the world today already scale to hundreds of thousands of cores. With plans under way for exascale systems to emerge within the next decade, we will soon have systems comprising more than a million processing elements. As researchers work toward architecting these enormous systems, it is becoming increasingly clear that, at such scales, resilience to hardware faults is going to be a prominent issue that needs to be addressed.</p><p>While the peak performance of contemporary highperformance computing (HPC) systems continues to grow exponentially, it is getting more and more difficult for scientific applications to achieve high performance because of the increasing failures in these systems. Today's long-running scientific applications typically tolerate system failures by using checkpoint-restart techniques, where the application (or the system) occasionally checkpoints the state of the executing processes to a reliable storage <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. With the increasing gap between the compute power of these systems and the capability of the storage systems, the scalability of checkpointing solutions in next-generation HPC systems is in doubt. For example, based on a balanced system model and statistics from the Computer Failure Data Repository (CFDR) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr">Gibson et al. predicted</ref> that the effective application utilization of checkpoint/restart-based fault tolerance will keep dropping to zero under current technology trends <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Such behavior has been predicted by other researchers as well <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p><p>Diskless checkpointing has been proposed to improve the scalability of checkpointing <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. However, methods such as algorithm-based fault tolerance (ABFT) recovery <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> promise even better scalability. The ABFT method has been studied in many applications, such as ScaLAPACK <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, HPL <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, preconditioned conjugate gradient (PCG) solver <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, and iterative methods in PETSc <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Unlike systemlevel checkpointing, using ABFT recovery to handle faults is not transparent to applications. However, it does have several advantages. First, this technique introduces no explicit stoppage to perform a checkpoint. The redundancy is computed synchronously with the main computing process; thus, no rollback of work is needed when failure occurs. Second, the redundancy is completely in-memory and does not rely on the capability of the storage system. Previous experimental results show that this technique has better performance than checkpointing <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</p><p>However, ABFT recovery is still based on the stop-andwait scheme, where even if only one process fails during the execution of applications, all processes alive have to stop and wait for the recovery of the failed process. According to Amdahl's law, the maximum speedup of an application is limited by its sequential proportion. Thus, the stop-and-wait scheme will affect the parallel efficiency of applications under large scale.</p><p>To ease this problem, we propose a new nonstop algorithmbased fault tolerance scheme called ABFT hot-replacement. When failure occurs during the execution of the application, we do not stop to wait for the recovery of corrupted data; rather, we replace it with the corresponding redundant data and continue the execution. At the end of execution, our scheme can recover the correct solution algorithmically at a low cost.</p><p>In order to implement this new scheme, some new fault tolerance features of Message Passing Interface (MPI) implementations are required, for which we utilized the MPICH implementation of MPI. This paper also describes a case study using High Performance Linpack (HPL) and the MPICH implementation of MPI and evaluates its performance. Together with those new features, some additional supports at application level such as message redundancy and virtual ranks are implemented, which may be addressed in future version of MPICH. Experimental results show an observable advantage of the new scheme over ABFT recovery even in a small scale.</p><p>The rest of paper is organized as follows. Section II briefly introduces the conventional ABFT method and fault-tolerant MPI implementations. Section III proposes our new algorithmbased fault tolerance scheme, ABFT hot-replacement. In Section IV, we introduce the new fault tolerance features of MPICH used to implement the proposed scheme. In Section V, we demonstrate how to incorporate fault tolerance into HPL using the proposed scheme. Section VI presents some experimental results and evaluations. Section VII concludes this paper and discusses future work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. BACKGROUND AND RELATED WORK</head><p>In this section, we first briefly introduce the conventional algorithm-based fault tolerance method. Then the background and related work of fault-tolerant MPI are given.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Conventional Algorithm-Based Fault Recovery Method</head><p>The algorithm-based fault tolerance technique first proposed by Huang and Abraham <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> uses the encoded data to detect and correct instant errors in certain matrix operations at the system level. This technique was further developed by Chen and Dongarra to tolerate fail-stop failures that occurred during the execution of HPC applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. This latter technique is also the basis of the ABFT recovery method mentioned in this paper. The idea of ABFT is to encode the original matrices using real number codes to establish a checksum type of relationship between data, and then redesign algorithms to operate on the encoded matrices in order to maintain the checksum relationship during the execution.</p><p>Assume there will be a single process failure. Since it's hard to locate which process will fail before the failure actually occurs, a fault-tolerant scheme should be able to recover the data on any process. In the conventional ABFT method, it is assumed that at any time during the computation the data D i on the ith process P i satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">D 1 + D 2 + · · · + D n = E,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where n is the total number of processes and E is data on the encoding process. Thus, the lost data on any failed process can be recovered from Eq. (1). Suppose P i fails. Then the lost data D i on P i can be reconstructed by</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">D i = E − (D 1 + · · · + D i−1 + D i+1 + · · · + D n ).<label>(2)</label></formula><p>In practice, this kind of special relationship is by no means natural. However, it is possible to design applications to maintain such a special checksum relationship throughout the computation, and this is one purpose of ABFT research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Fault-Tolerant MPI</head><p>Although fault tolerance has not been addressed by the MPI standard as of 2.2, work has been done previously to improve the fault tolerance of MPI implementations and applications using checkpoint-rollback recovery (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>) and application-level fault tolerance (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>). Checkpoint-based fault tolerance is attractive because it is provided transparently to the application. No action on the part of the application is required to detect or handle faults. However, checkpointing-based fault tolerance has drawbacks, as mentioned in Section I, and is not suitable in all situations.</p><p>To support application-level fault tolerance, the MPI implementation must itself be able to tolerate faults. Furthermore, it must provide features to allow the application to proceed in a meaningful manner after a fault has occurred. This issue has also been studied previously (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>). Collective operations in FT-MPI <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> are required, in the presence of a failed process, to complete with the same result as if there were no failed processes; otherwise the operation must abort. The fault-tolerant features we added to MPICH differ from FT-MPI in that we decided to relax the restriction on collective operations in order to reduce the overhead during failure-free operation. In our implementation, collectives will return an error code at those processes where the result may be invalid, but they also may return successfully if the result is known to be unaffected by the failure.</p><p>In MPI/FT <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> failed processes are always replaced from a pool of spare processes. When the pool of spare processes is exhausted, the application is aborted. Our implementation does not yet have the ability to restart failed processes; instead, the decision on whether to continue is left to the application. Since spare processes are not always feasible, we feel that allowing the application to decide how to continue gives the application more flexibility.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. A NONSTOP ALGORITHM-BASED FAULT TOLERANCE SCHEME</head><p>In this section, a nonstop algorithm-based fault tolerance scheme, called ABFT hot-replacement, is proposed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Hot-Replacement Scheme</head><p>For the simplicity of presentation, we assume there will be only one process failure. However, it is straightforward to extend the results here to multiple failures by simply using multilevel redundancy or regenerating the encoded data. Suppose that at any time during the computation the data D i on the ith process P i satisfies</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">D 1 + D 2 + · · · + D n = E.<label>(3)</label></formula><p>If the ith process failed during the execution, we replace it with the encoding process E and continue the execution instead of stopping all the processes to recover the lost data D i . Note that this kind of transformation can be effective only when there is an encoding relationship among the data. From the global view, the original data is</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">D = (D 1 · · · D i−1 D i D i+1 · · · D n ),<label>(4)</label></formula><p>and the transformed data (after replacement) is</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">D = (D 1 · · · D i−1 ED i+1 · · · D n ).<label>(5)</label></formula><p>We can establish a relationship between the transformed data and the original data as</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">D = D × T,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>and T can be represented as an n × n matrix in the following form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">T =             1 1 . . .</formula><p>. . .</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">1 1 1 1 1 . . . . . . 1 1             ,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where the elements omitted in the diagonal and the ith column are all 1 and the other elements omitted are 0. We can see that One can see that the encoding relationship D = D × T cannot be maintained under all HPC applications. However, for a class of them, including matrix computations involving linear transformations, such as matrix decomposition, matrix-matrix multiplication, and scalar product, the encoding relationship can be maintained. A simple example on HPL is given in the next section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. A Simple Example on HPL</head><p>HPL is a popular benchmark for supercomputing and is widely used for ranking supercomputers on Top500 <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. It is used to solve linear system</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">Ax = b (8)</formula><p>using Gaussian elimination with partial pivoting (GEPP). We assume process P i fails during the execution. After the replacement with redundancy, the linear systems becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">A y = b.<label>(9)</label></formula><p>At the end of execution, it gives the solution y as an intermediate result. Since all the operations in GEPP are linear transformations, the relationship</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">A = A × T<label>(10)</label></formula><p>can always be kept during the execution. Combining Eq. <ref type="formula">(8)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_9">(9)</ref>, and (10), we obtain the correct solution x by</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">x = T × y.<label>(11)</label></formula><p>Assume the transformation matrix T is the same as Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">(7)</ref>. Substitute Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">(7)</ref> into Eq. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_0">(11)</ref>, giving</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">x j = y i + y j , if 1 ≤ j = i ≤ q x i = y i (12)</formula><p>It shows that the cost of recomputing the solution x is O(n), whereas the cost of ABFT recovery to handle a single process failure is O(n 2 ). Because of the simplicity of T , the correct solution can be recovered algorithmically at a low cost.</p><p>In the real implementation of fault-tolerant HPL, however, the encoding of data matrix and the transformation matrix T will be more complex because of its block-cyclic data distribution. We will discuss these issues in Section V.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Advantages</head><p>Compared with ABFT recovery, ABFT hot-replacement introduces the following two advantages.</p><p>First, consider there is only one process failure in a system, say P i . With ABFT hot-replacement, the other processes in the system do not need to stop and wait for the recovery of the data on P i . This nonstop scheme improves the efficiency of large-scale systems, since the wasted CPU cycles during the stop-and-wait period increase with the system scale.</p><p>Second, since T is a very sparse matrix, the cost of recomputing the correct solution by using T can be much lower than that of the recovery of failed process directly, especially for those computation-intensive or communicationintensive applications where each process is allocated with a large set of data. This can be seen from the simple example of HPL.</p><p>In the case shown above, because of the maintenance of checksum relationship, we were able to process the lost data on any failed process without periodically checkpointing. In practice, however, this kind of special relationship is by no means natural. Nevertheless, one can design an application to maintain such a special checksum relationship throughout the computation, by using the checksum matrices of the original ones as the input matrices. To demonstrate the feasibility of the proposed ABFT hot-replacement method, we will apply it to the fault tolerance of HPL in Section V.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. FAULT TOLERANCE IN MPICH</head><p>While the MPI Forum is currently working on adding fault-tolerance features to the standard, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, the current MPI standard (2.2) does not yet define the behavior of an MPI library in the presence of process or communication failures. We have identified the minimum set of fault-tolerance features required of an MPI implementation in order to support our fault tolerant algorithm as follows.</p><p>• Node failure will not cause the entire job to abort.</p><p>• The MPI implementation should provide a mechanism to query for failed processes. • Communication operations involving a failed process will not hang and will eventually complete.</p><p>• Communication operations will return an error code when it is affected by a failed process. This is needed to determine whether to re-send or re-receive messages.</p><p>These requirements are a subset of the features proposed by the MPI Forum's fault tolerance working group. We have implemented these requirements and included them in the 1.3.2 release of MPICH2. In this section we describe the failure detection mechanism and the API to query for failed processes followed by the behavior of point-to-point and collective communication when failed processes are involved. Note that since MPI fault-tolerance features have not been standardized and are still in the process of being defined, the MPICH fault-tolerance features described here may differ from the features ultimately included in the MPI standard, and so may change in the future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Process failure detection and query</head><p>Although process failure can sometimes be inferred from communication failure by the MPI library, this is not a reliable way to detect failed processes. For instance, sending a message to a failed process may result in a timeout or an error reply from the operating system at the remote node, but a passive receiver may wait for a message which will never arrive from a failed process. For this reason, we modified the Hydra process manager to detect failed processes. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref> shows the Hydra process manager and proxies in relation to the MPI processes. When launching an application Hydra starts a proxy at each node, which, in turn, spawns the MPI processes. When an MPI process terminates, the proxy will receive a SIGCHLD signal and will then notify the process manager. If the process terminated before calling MPI_Finalize(), the process is considered to be a failed process. Hydra can be configured to abort the entire job when a failed process has been detected. This is often useful for non-fault tolerant applications in order to prevent runaway processes. For fault tolerant applications, however, when Hydra detects a failed process, it does not abort the job, but adds the process to its list of failed processes, then notifies the MPI processes by having the proxies send the processes a SIGUSR1 signal.</p><p>The MPICH library catches the SIGUSR1 signal and queries Hydra for the list of failed processes then closes all connections to the failed processes. The MPI process can get the failed process list by querying the MPICH_ATTR_FAILED_PROCESSES attribute on MPI_COMM_WORLD. The list consists of an array of integers representing the ranks of failed processes, terminated by MPI_PROC_NULL.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Point-to-point communication</head><p>When a message is sent to or a receive is posted for a message from a failed process, the send or receive function returns an MPI_ERR_OTHER error code, or, in the case of nonblocking operations, the request is completed with the error code set. Additionally, wildcard receives, i.e., using MPI_ANY_SOURCE, posted to communicators with a failed process will also be completed with an error. When notified of a failed process, MPICH scans the list of posted receives and queued sends, and completes the ones involving the failed process with an error.</p><p>Handling wildcard receives as described above requires knowing that a communicator contains a failed process. The communicator data structure has a list of every process it contains, however, to conserve memory, MPICH does not keep track of the reverse, i.e., a list of every communicator of which a particular process is a member. Determining whether a communicator contains failed processes requires scanning the list of processes in that communicator. This can be costly, especially if an application uses many communicators.</p><p>To address this, a communicator is only checked for a failed process only when a wildcard receive is encountered, either when one is posted or when scanning the list of posted receives. Each communicator has a flag which is set whenever the list of processes is scanned and it is determined that it contains a failed process. If the flag is set, then the list of processes does not need to be scanned again, since once a process fails, it cannot be repaired. However, if the flag is not set, it is possible that the communicator was not previously checked for a failed process or that a process has failed since the last time the communicator was checked. In this case, we use a timestamp to indicate the last time the list of processes was scanned. If a process failure notification has been received since the list of processes was scanned, the list is scanned again, otherwise we know that there cannot be any failed processes in the communicator. This reduces the number of communicators that need to be scanned and the number of times a particular communicator needs to be scanned.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Collective communication</head><p>Collective operations, by definition, require the participation of all processes of the communicator. The current MPI standard does not define the result of a collective communication operation when a member of the communicator has failed. Rather than try to define the result of a collective operation with missing processes, we decided first, make sure that the collective operation does not hang, and additionally, that the collective operation will return an error at all processes where the result may be invalid.</p><p>Failed processes may cause a collective operation to hang unless the collective operation has been implemented to handle process failures. Consider a broadcast operation that is implemented by logically arranging the processes in a tree and forwarding the message over the tree using point-topoint messages. If the broadcast algorithm is implemented so that when a send or receive operation returns an error, the process will immediately abort the broadcast operation, then that process's children may hang. A child process will wait trying to receive the message from its parent, but if the parent has aborted the broadcast it will never receive the message, and will not get an error because the parent has not failed. The solution we applied is to continue the collective operation even when a failure is detected. This will prevent processes from hanging, but may result in some, but not all, processes getting invalid results from the collective operation. For instance, in the broadcast operation, the ancestors of a failed process would receive an invalid message; however, the other processes will receive the message correctly.</p><p>It is important for each process of an application to tell whether a collective operation produced a valid result. Because only the processes directly receiving from or sending to the failed process will detect the failure, the other ancestors of the failed process will need to be notified that the received data is invalid. To do this we mark the messages carrying invalid data by using a different tag value. During a collective, when a receive operation fails, all subsequent send operations will set the tag to mark the message as containing invalid data. Processes will use a wildcard tag, i.e., MPI_ANY_TAG, to receive the collective messages, then check the tag to determine whether the data is valid. If a process receives a message marked as containing invalid data, the process will continue performing the collective operation, but will mark any subsequent messages it sends as containing invalid data. When a process completes the collective operation it will return an error code if a send or receive operation failed, or if it had received invalid data at any point during the operation. In this way an error code will be returned by the collective function at any process where the collective produced an invalid result.</p><p>As of MPICH2 version 1.3.2, no mechanism is provided to be able to repair a communicator, or to allow a collective operation to be performed correctly while excluding any failed processes in a communicator. Such features are currently being investigated in this paper at the application level and we expect to include them in future versions of MPICH.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. INCORPORATING FAULT TOLERANCE INTO HIGH PERFORMANCE LINPACK</head><p>With the support of the MPICH implementation of MPI, we incorporate fault tolerance into HPL using ABFT hotreplacement scheme proposed in Section III. Our implementation focuses on handling a single process failure occurred in the main part of HPL, that is factorization, row broadcast and update phases. However, it's possible to extend the result  <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. Algorithm of HPL using left-looking LU factorization.</p><p>here to multiple process failure cases by rebuilding checksum in background and maintaining multi-level redundancies.</p><p>In this section, we first present an overview of HPL. Second, we briefly introduce the encoding of matrix and how to locate a failure. Then we give a detailed presentation on the failure handling in factorization and update phases, using hot replacement and background recovery technique. For better robustness, we also describe failure handling in row broadcasting by proposing a new message broadcasting mechanism.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. High Performance Linpack Overview</head><p>The main algorithm of HPL solves Ax = b using GEPP. It first computes the LU factorization of the n × (n + 1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">coefficient matrix [A|b], producing [A|b] = [[L, U ]L −1 b].</formula><p>Then the solution x can be obtained by solving the upper triangular system U x = L −1 b. The pseudo code for HPL using left-looking LU factorization with look-ahead depth = 0 is given as follows. For better presentation, we also depict it in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. The colored part of the matrix in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> is the part that has been computed, while the uncolored part is the trailing submatrix A sub . The part of the matrix that changes color is the part that is computed by one iteration. We denote matrices in the kth iteration with a superscript (k). At the very beginning ,we assume A sub (0) = A. Then we could see that in the kth iteration, A</p><p>sub is divided into 4 submatrices: A 11 (k) , A 12 (k) , A 21 (k) and A <ref type="bibr">22 (k)</ref> . At the end of the iteration, it produces the new trailing submatrix A sub (k+1) . We could also notice that the trailing submatrix shrinks after every iteration. For more details, we refer the reader to <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>.</p><p>Each process generates its local random matrix A ; operate on each trailing submatrix A sub</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">(k) for k = 0, 1, . . .</formula><p>; factorization phase factorize A 11 (k) and</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">A 21 (k) as L 11 (k) · U 11 (k) and L 21 (k) · U 11 (k)</formula><p>; row broadcast phase broadcast L 11 (k) , L 21 (k) and pivoting information right ; update phase perform row swaps and calculate </p><formula xml:id="formula_17">U 12 (k) = L 11 (k) −1 · A 12 (k) update the trailing submatrix A sub (k+1) = A 22 (k) − L 21 (k) · U 12 (k) solve U · x = L −1 · b to obtain x</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Matrix Encoding</head><p>The encoding of the matrix is similar to that described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. In HPL, the random matrix A is distributed onto a two-dimensional P × Q process grid according to the blockcyclic scheme. To tolerate a single-process failure, we dedicate additional P processes and organize the total P × Q + P processes as a P × (Q + 1) process grid. The redundant P processes are distributed on the (Q + 1)th column of the new process grid, holding the checksum encoding, which can be obtained by adding all local matrices on the first Q process columns. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3(a)</ref> shows the original layout of a process grid with P = 2 and Q = 2. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3(c)</ref> is the corresponding process grid with redundant processes P 2 and P 5, where P 2 holds the checksum encoding of P 0 and P 1, and P 5 does similarly. We show the encoding of an example matrix with redundancy in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>(b) and denote the local matrices of each process in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3(d)</ref>. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>, we distinguish different processes in different colors. The matrix order N we use is 4 and the block size nb is 1. Based on the consideration of simple implementation, we also keep a copy of column b on the redundant processes.</p><p>Under this encoding scheme, the row checksum relationship (matrix L excluded) can be maintained during the computation, after each update phase <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Failure Location</head><p>Since failure occurrence is unpredictable, we do not know the time and the location of the failure before it actually occurs. To obtain this information, every process should query the new MPICH_ATTR_FAILED_PROCESSES attribute on MPI_COMM_WORLD after every phase. Since different processes may finish the same phase at different time, we need to do a barrier operation before the failure checking operation to make sure that all processes get the same result. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Hot Replacement Technique</head><p>If a process failure is discovered in the failure checking after a phase, all processes alive will enter a uniform entry to perform failure handling using the ABFT hot-replacement method proposed in Section III. The redundant process column will replace the dead process column, and the computation will continue. Consider the example in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>. We assume the failed process is P 3 and the failure is discovered after the first update phase, thus we replace the redundant process column with the dead one, i.e. the 1st column. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4(a)</ref> is the supposed matrix after the first update phase without failure. In our implementation, we replace the whole column rather than a single process upon process failure. Since processes inside a column need to do some row swaps during the computation, only replacing the dead process by a redundant process will make the transformation matrix T difficult to derive.</p><p>Moreover, this hot-replacement is not physical but can be done rapidly. It is implemented by exchanging the relative parameters in the data structure of process grid and does not involve any internode data transmissions.</p><p>Note that the replacement can be done only when the checksum relationship is satisfied, that is, after the update phase. Thus, if a process failure is found after a factorization or row-broadcasting phase, all processes alive should continue execution until they finish the updating. After that, the hotreplacement could be performed.</p><p>Another issue is how to update the status of communicators after the replacement. A communicator is used in MPI to denote a set of active processes. An ideal fault-tolerant MPI implementation should be able to dynamically adjust a communicator to add new or remove failed processes. In our implementation, we address this issue in the application level by designating a virtual rank to each process. Messages are sent or received by using these virtual ranks. We wrote two macros to do the mappings between the original rank of a process in MPI_COMM_WORLD and its virtual rank according to the status of the process grid.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. Background Recovery Technique</head><p>It can be inferred from <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>(c) that the matrix U we get at last will no longer be upper-triangular, since the submatrix that has been factorized before the failure occurrence is replaced by redundancy. This will make it difficult to solve U x = L −1 b. To overcome this issue, we do not replace the already factorized data but, instead, recover them onto the corresponding redundant processes. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4(d)</ref> shows the global view of the example matrix after the recovery.</p><p>We note that the factorized data is not for immediate use (only used in solving U x = b). Thus, recovering the data could be performed in background to achieve better performance. We overlap the communication needed for the recovery with the succeeding update phases, which consist mainly of matrixmatrix multiplications. We divide the data to recover into several parts according to the amount of data to be transferred in every succeeding update phase. Then we use nonblocking MPI_Isend and MPI_Irecv to overlap the communication and the computation. Note that as the calculation takes place, the data to update decreases; thus the data to send or receive during the update phase also decreases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F. Failure Handling in Row Broadcasting</head><p>The methods discussed thus far can handle failures in the factorization or update phases. But for the row broadcast phase, the procedure may be a little tricky. All row broadcasting methods provided by HPL are based on message forwarding. Thus, if a process fails during a row broadcast phase, processes that indirectly receive messages from the failed process will be blocked. For example, suppose P 1 forwards messages from P 0 to P 2 and P 0 failed. Then P 1 will get notified of the failure by the error code of a MPI receive operation while P 2 will block.</p><p>Here we need a new robust message broadcasting mechanism. It should meet the following conditions:</p><p>• None of the processes will block if a failure occurs.</p><p>• Either all nonfailed processes receive the message successfully or none of them receive the message. In this section, we present a robust message broadcasting mechanism for the commonly used row broadcast method in HPL: the increasing-2-ring-modified method (2rinM method). root P 0 to P 1 . The Q − 2 processes left are divided into two groups: processes P 2 to P (Q+1)/2−1 are in one group and processes P (Q+1)/2 to P Q−1 in another. Messages are then sent to processes P 2 and P (Q+1)/2 , which act as sources of two increasing-one rings.</p><p>In our implementation, we designate a father node for each nonroot node. The messages of a father node should be transferred ahead of its son nodes. Each nonroot node sends the error code of its MPI_Recv to its father node. If its MPI_Recv failed, it should also initiate another MPI_Recv waiting to receive re-sent messages from its father node. As a father node, it receives the error code from its corresponding son nodes and then determines whether to resend a message again. We denote in <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref> the chronological sequences of message transmissions of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>. The dashed arrows in <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref> point from son nodes to their father nodes, showing one possible father-son relationship. In this way, we can ensure that all processes will receive the messages successfully no matter which nonroot node is failed.</p><p>But what if the root P 0 fails before the first message is received successfully? If so, all processes will hang there except those that receive messages directly from the root node. To overcome this problem, we separate the first message transmission out of the row broadcast phase. The fault-tolerant mechanism presented above is performed only after the root P 0 send messages to P 1 successfully.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. EXPERIMENTAL EVALUATION AND ANALYSIS</head><p>We performed three sets of experiments to answer the following questions about our ABFT hot-replacement method:</p><p>• How does the ABFT hot-replacement method perform?</p><p>• Is the ABFT hot-replacement method correct?</p><p>• How does the timing of process failures affect performance? The experiments were performed on two different platforms. The first two sets of experiments were performed on a smaller cluster of 17 nodes. Each node of the cluster has four quadcore 2.2GHz AMD Opteron processors, connected by Gigabit Ethernet. The third set of experiments was performed on a larger cluster of 8 blades, 10 Intel Xeon X5650 processors each, 960 cores in total. In this cluster, nodes in the same blade are connected by InfiniBand, while different blades are connected with each other by a single InfiniBand cable. All nodes of the two clusters are running Linux operating systems. The MPICH package we used on both platforms is mpich2-trunk-r7834, and all the timings were measured by MPI_Wtime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Performance of Different Algorithm-Based Fault Tolerance Methods</head><p>The first set of experiments was designed to compare the performance of the two different fault tolerance methods: ABFT recovery and ABFT hot-replacement. We incorporated both of them into HPL to handle a single process failure. Process failure was simulated by killing a process at a certain period of time after HPL started running.</p><p>The order of random matrix A and the number of computation nodes used in this set of experiments are listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table I</ref>. The matrix orders we used are of 10 4 magnitude. <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table II</ref> reports the execution time of HPL using the two methods with one process failure and HPL without failure. The corresponding overheads of the two fault tolerance methods are shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>. These overheads were calculated against HPL without failure. We can see that to handle a single-process failure, the execution time of HPL using ABFT hot-replacement is about 10-200 s shorter than that of HPL using ABFT recovery. The proportion of this part is about 1-5% of the execution time of HPL without failures. It should also be noted that the overhead of ABFT methods is affected by the mappings between processes and physical cores. If processes in the same row or column are mapped to physical cores in different nodes, the communication cost will be higher than that they all mapped inside the same node. Consider the fifth experiment where the matrix order is 50,000. One process row contains 12 processes, while one node has 16 physical cores. We can infer that there must be processes in certain rows are not mapped inside the same node. This could also explain why the overhead of ABFT methods in this experiment is higher than that of the last one, though the amount of data allocated to each process in this experiment is less.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>10,000</head><p>20,000 30,000 40,000 50,000 60,000 0% </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Numerical Impact of Round-Off Errors in Different Algorithm-Based Fault Tolerance Methods</head><p>As discussed in Section II-A, ABFT techniques are based on floating-point arithmetic encodings and may therefore introduce round-off errors in HPL. Moreover, the ABFT hot-replacement method involves matrix transformation when replacing the dead process column by the redundant process column, which will make the round-off errors even greater. The experiments reported in this section were designed to measure the numerical impact of the round-off errors by checking the norm of residuals.</p><p>All experiment configurations are the same with the first one, listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table I</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 8</ref> reports the norm of residuals at the end of each computation for the two ABFT methods with a single process failure, compared with the nonfailure case. One can see that the ABFT recovery method introduces a little round-off error into HPL whereas the ABFT hot-replacement method almost doubles the norm of residuals of HPL.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Performance of HPL using Hot-Replacement at Different Time Period</head><p>The third set of experiments was designed to evaluate the performance of the HPL using ABFT hot-replacement method when failure occurs at different times. The experiments were performed on the larger cluster with 8 blades. We used 75 of the nodes, 900 cores in total. We initiated one process per core and organized the 900 processes into a 30 × 30 grid. The matrix order we used was 200,000. The time of failure occurrence were controlled by the sleep function in python Timing of the failure (s) <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref>. Execution time of HPL using the ABFT hot-replacement method while varying the timing of the failure scripts. <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref> shows the execution time of HPL using the ABFT hot-replacement method while varying the timing of the failure. We can see that after 1,000 s, the total execution time increases radically. The reason is that, with the execution, the amount of factorized data is increasing. At the same time, the amount of data to be recovered, if a failure occurs, is also increasing. When that amount becomes too large to overlap the background recovery and the succeeding update phases, the total execution time will increase. However, the execution time of HPL using ABFT hot-replacement in the worst case should approach that of HPL using ABFT recovery theoretically.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. CONCLUSIONS AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>In this paper, a new nonstop algorithm-based fault-tolerant scheme is proposed for a class of HPC applications, including matrix computations involving linear transformations. HPL has been modified to use the new fault-tolerant scheme with the support of MPICH's new fault tolerance features. Experimental results indicate that the proposed scheme is more efficient than existing algorithmic recovery methods.</p><p>Future work may include the following three directions. First, the proposed nonstop algorithm-based fault tolerance scheme should be implemented at large scale and under real circumstances, including handling multiple failures. Second, the round-off errors introduced by this fault-tolerant method when handling multiple failures at large scale should be further investigated. Third, this approach should be extended to the fault tolerance of other HPC applications.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>T is a nonsingular matrix. If operations on the data are linear transformations (e.g., matrix operations such as decomposition), the relationship D = D × T will always be kept. At the end of computation, the original correct solution based on D can be recomputed through the intermediate solution based on D . And this recomputation is actually a transformation related to T .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Logical diagram showing MPI processes, MPICH libraries and Hydra process manager and proxies</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Two-dimensional process grid with P = 2 and Q = 2 and the data distribution of an example matrix with redundancy: (a) original process grid, (b) original matrix with redundancy from global view, (c) process grid with redundancy, (d) original matrix with redundancy from distributed/local view.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Perform ABFT hot-replacement on the example matrix after P 3 failed: (a) global matrix before failure, (b) rearranged process grid after hotreplacement, (c) global matrix after hot-replacement, (d) global matrix after recovery.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 (</head><label>4</label><figDesc>b) is the rearranged grid after hot-replacement and Figure 4(c) is the corresponding global matrix. Note that the submatrix with cross lines in Figure 4 denotes matrix L.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. The way how 2rinM method works</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 illustratesFig. 6 .</head><label>56</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Message transmissions of 2rinM method with father-son relationship in chronological sequence</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Overhead of different ABFT methods (in seconds)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>TABLE I EXPERIMENT CONFIGURATIONS ON THE SMALLER CLUSTER</head><label>I</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Matrix Order 
Number 
Processes 
Process grid 
of nodes 
per node 
with redt. 
10,000 
6 
1 
2 by 3 
20,000 
1 
16 
4 by 4 
30,000 
2 
16 
4 by 8 
40,000 
4 
16 
8 by 8 
50,000 
12 
16 
16 by 12 
60,000 
16 
16 
16 by 16 

TABLE II 
HPL EXECUTION TIME (IN SECONDS) USING DIFFERENT METHODS 

Matrix Order 
No Failures 
Hot-Rep. 
Rec. 
10,000 
577.74 
591.61 
602.73 
20,000 
1608.15 
1677.14 
1723.37 
30,000 
2601.03 
2791.12 
2821.43 
40,000 
3150.11 
3358.38 
3497.08 
50,000 
3433.09 
3479.26 
3577.77 
60,000 
4708.54 
4722.44 
4858.23 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot">t = 0 t = 1 t = 2 t = 3 t = 4 t = 5</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>This research was supported partly by the National Basic Research Program of China (973) 2011CB302502; by the National Natural Science Foundation of China under grants 60925009, 61003062, and 60921002 and in part by the Office of Advanced Scientific Computing Research, Office of Science, U.S. Department of Energy, under Contract #DE-AC02-06CH11357; by the DOE grant #DE-FG02-08ER25835.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diskless checkpointing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Plank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Puening</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Parallel Distrib. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="972" to="986" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A higher order estimate of the optimum checkpoint interval for restart dumps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Daly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Future Generation Computer Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="312" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The computer failure data repository sites</title>
		<ptr target="http://cfdr.usenix.org.Lastaccessed" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding failures in petascale computers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Physics: Conference Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Failure tolerance in petascale computers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Digney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">CTWatchQuarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing checkpointing trends for applications on petascale systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Naik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Beckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">the Proceedings of the Workshop on Parallel Programming Models and Systems Software for High-End Computing (P2S2)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Vienna, Austria</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building fault survivable MPI programs with FT-MPI using diskless checkpointing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fagg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gabriel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Langou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Angskun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bosilca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dongarra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings for ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles and Practice of Parallel Programming</title>
		<meeting>for ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles and Practice of Parallel Programming</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="223" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Highly scalable self-healing algorithms for high performance scientific computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dongarra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Computers</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithm-based fault tolerance for failstop failures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dongarra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithmic Cholesky factorization fault recovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hakkarinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 24th IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium</title>
		<meeting>the 24th IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium<address><addrLine>Atlanta, GA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithm-based recovery for HPL</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Karlsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 16th ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles and Practice of Parallel Programming</title>
		<meeting>the 16th ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles and Practice of Parallel Programming</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="304" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithm-based recovery for iterative methods without checkpointing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 20th ACM International Symposium on High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing</title>
		<meeting>the 20th ACM International Symposium on High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithm-based fault tolerance for matrix operations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Abraham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Computers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="518" to="528" />
			<date type="published" when="1984-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A linear algebraic model of algorithm-based fault tolerance</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Anfinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Luk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1599" to="1604" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithm-based checkpoint-free fault tolerance for parallel matrix computations on volatile resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dongarra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 20st IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium</title>
		<meeting>the 20st IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page">76</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The LAM/MPI checkpoint/restart framework: System-initiated checkpointing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sankaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Squyres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Barrett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lumsdaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings, LACSI Symposium, Sante Fe</title>
		<meeting>LACSI Symposium, Sante Fe</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="479" to="493" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The design and implementation of checkpoint/restart process fault tolerance for Open MPI</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hursey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Squyres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Mattox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lumsdaine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Workshop on Dependable Parallel, Distributed and Network-Centric Systems(DPDNS), in conjunction with IPDPS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blocking vs. non-blocking coordinated checkpointing for large-scale fault tolerant MPI protocols</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Buntinas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Coti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Herault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lemarinier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pilard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rezmerita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cappello</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Future Generation Computer Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FT-MPI: Fault tolerant MPI, supporting dynamic applications in a dynamic world</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fagg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dongarra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Recent Advances in Parallel Virtual Machine and Message Passing Interface</title>
		<editor>J. Dongarra, P. Kacsuk, and N. Podhorszki</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin / Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">1908</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="346" to="353" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fault tolerance in message passing interface programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gropp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lusk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of High Performance Computing Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="372" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MPI/FT: A model-based approach to low-overhead fault tolerant message-passing middleware</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Batchu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Dandass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Skjellum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Beddhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cluster Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="315" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Top 500 supercomputing sites</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.top500.org.Lastac-cessed" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">MPI-Forum fault-tolerance working group</title>
		<ptr target="https://svn.mpi-forum.org/trac/mpi-forum-web/wiki/ft/runthroughusersguide.Lastaccessed" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">HPL benchmark sites</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.netlib.org/benchmark/hpl.Lastaccessed" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
