<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:34+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Self-Checking Fault Detection using Discrepancy Mirrors</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2005-06">June 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Demara</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Central Florida Orlando</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>32816-2450</postCode>
									<region>FL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Central Florida Orlando</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>32816-2450</postCode>
									<region>FL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Self-Checking Fault Detection using Discrepancy Mirrors</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">the 2005 International Conference on Parallel and Distributed Processing Techniques and Applications (PDPTA&apos;05)</title>
						<meeting> <address><addrLine>Las Vegas, Nevada</addrLine></address>
						</meeting>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2005-06">June 2005</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Manuscript</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>fault-handling</term>
					<term>concurrent error detection</term>
					<term>self-checking fault detection</term>
					<term>fault- secure circuit</term>
					<term>Xilinx Virtex FPGA</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>A method for robust detection of faults is developed based on pairwise parallel evaluation using Discrepancy Mirror logic. Discrepancy Mirrors provide coverage for the fault detector elements within the same mechanism used for the functional logic under test. The detector logic is self-testing and propagates functional outputs with adherence to a single fault-secure property so that erroneous outputs from any single fault are not propagated. Within the detector, bitwise equality comparisons are employed directly without additional data encoding/decoding schemes to determine the validity of the output. Fault handling is performed using the underlying data throughput so that additional test vectors are not required. The circuit was implemented for a Xilinx Virtex II Pro FPGA platform and fault-secure operation was verified using ModelSim-II for exhaustive stuck-at scenarios. Results indicate fault isolation in a pool of 100,000 resources using an expected value of 17.6 to 64.1 pairings when as little as one half of the inputs applied articulate the fault.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Robust fault detection is central to the problem of enhancing the fault-handling capabilities of digital circuits. A common limitation facing many fault detection schemes is that the failure detector itself may fail. A fault involving the checker may be undetectable or result in the corruption of otherwise valid outputs. Traditional approaches to fault-detection typically rely on coding-based schemes or redundancy using a single voter, comparator or error detector. Those fault checkers possess a single point-of-failure exposure involving the detector elements, or must rely upon special test-vectors or data encodings to isolate them. Detector components in the reliability path have been referred to as golden elements <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> because the fault-handling strategy relies on them to be fault-free. This paper develops an alternative approach to self-checking fault detection based on random pairings and temporal voting to reduce such exposures. <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> lists characteristics of selected fault-handling strategies. Specialized encoding schemes are often required by Concurrent Error Detection (CED) approaches as opposed to Triple Modular Redundancy (TMR) and the Discrepancy Mirror methods which do not. The number of functional logic elements required by TMR is greater than that of the other schemes. Discrepancy Mirrors provide inherent transient fault coverage with minimal detection latency. They also support finegrained resolution of the fault location, without interruption to the data throughput flow when a fault occurs. Thus, Discrepancy Mirrors offer improved detection of permanent and transient faults, with reduced time and space overheads. A detailed comparison of existing techniques is provided in Section 1.1 and Section 1.2. Section 1.2 provides the design of the discrepancy mirror approach. Results of simulations and fault location experiments are given in Section 3.1 and Section 3.2 respectively.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Special</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Concurrent Error Detection Schemes</head><p>CED schemes include a wide array of coding-based <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> [3] and redundancy-based mechanisms <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Coding-based mechanisms typically employ mathematically robust encoding and decoding schemes. Redundancy-based mechanisms generate concurrent output values using multiple instances of the functional logic which are then checked for equality. CED schemes utilize the functional throughput that realizes the output f (i) in response to input i to evaluate a diagnostic characteristic computed by an alternate yet predictable function, f d (i). The diagnostic characteristic used could be the parity of the output, conformance to specified encodings such as Berger codes <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, equality between f (i) and f d (i), or a specific m-out-of-n code. They can be generated using dedicated logic to implement f d (i) directly or parallel evaluation with a comparator realizing a bitwise XNOR equivalence logic function. The redundancy within CED schemes can be spatial, where the hardware circuit-under-test is duplicated, or temporal, where the outputs are computed in succession for later comparison.</p><p>Consider the hardware comparators capable of bitwise output comparison, such as the equality checker <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and the two-rail checker <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Equality checkers compare two input words to determine bitwise equivalence. These circuits require complemented inputs and a multi-rail representation to be verifiable as a self-testing system. A two-rail checker checks that each pair of inputs has complementary values which are used to convert n pairs of signals into one pair of signals that are complementary if and only if all of the n input pairs are complementary. It can be made testable with the addition of a test signal and two XOR gates <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Coding-based checkers detect invalid code words at the output of the circuit-under-test for at least one valid code word input to the checker.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Triple Modular Redundancy Systems</head><p>TMR approaches rely on three parallel instances of the functional logic to compute the output in triplicate and a majority voting element to determine consensus. TMR also supports correction of single faults by disregarding the incongruent output. This works satisfactorily in the case of a single-fault assumption, unless the fault induces a Common Mode Failure whereby two incorrect outputs agree using bitwise <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> or word-width voters <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. If the logic elements within the voter fail then the fault handling system can fail. The use of redundant voters is suboptimal as it does not guarantee that their consensus is computed correctly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Discrepancy Mirror Approach</head><p>The Discrepancy Mirror approach is a duplex redundancy technique that utilizes alternate physical configurations from a population of candidate designs that are functionally equivalent. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, the technique is composed of three phases, namely Selection, Detection, and Preference Adjustment. The Selection phase selects two candidates, each of which utilize mutually exclusive subsets of the resources under test. The Detection process uses the Discrepancy Mirror logic shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> to check for bit-wise equivalence between outputs of the candidates as described below. The Preference Adjustment phase utilizes the results of successive comparisons to update the pairing strategy during subsequent selections. These steps will be explained below in the context of a Field Programmable Gate Array (FPGA) based realization whereby two configurations of the functional logic are loaded in tandem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Selection Phase</head><p>Candidate designs are selected from a population developed at design time, either manually or via a CAD tool. Random pairings or an adaptive scheme based on the results of Preference Adjustment can be employed. This process is identified as Step 1 in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. The selected designs are then loaded as the active configurations during Step 2 and Step 3. Identical input operands are applied in parallel to each configuration and the outputs are redundantly computed for comparison in the next phase.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Detection Phase</head><p>As shown in Step 4 in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, the discrepancy mirror circuit is used to identify whether the outputs of the two configurations under test agree. A complete instance of the discrepancy mirror is obtained whenever two configurations are loaded, since the discrepancy detector consists of two identical sections as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. Assertion of MATCH output from the discrepancy mirror indicates the absence of a single-fault in the configurations under test, as well as the logic in the Step 5 in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>.</p><p>The inputs to the Discrepancy Mirror shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> as "Function Output A" and "Function Output B" are generated independently. If there is a fault in a resource utilized by either of these configurations, then a discrepancy is observed at the output. The truth table shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref> describes the operation of the circuit shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. Outputs from the function configurations A and B are applied as inputs to both the XNOR gates. The output from each XNOR gate acts as the ENABLE signal for the tristate buffer in the same half, as well as the input to the tristate buffer in the other half of the discrepancy mirror. The tristate buffer outputs are tied together to form a Wired-OR connection which provides the MATCH output signal. The pull-down transistors hold the signal to a logic '0' level when the tristate buffer output is in a high-impedance state. In an active-high non-inverting tristate buffer, the input is buffered at the output only when the ENABLE signal is high. When the ENABLE signal is low, the output of the buffer is in a high-impedance state.</p><p>As listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>, the response of the circuit is robust to several possible fault scenarios. If either of the XNOR gates fail, then one of the two tristate buffers will be disabled and the other will have an input of zero, thus MATCH will be a '0', signifying discrepancy. If the tristate buffers fail, producing a high impedance output, the pull down resistors in the circuit will hold the signal to '0'. The wired-OR connection reduces single points of failure to a stuck-at fault exposure for the MATCH output. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">The Preference Adjustment Process</head><p>Step 6 and Step 7 comprise the Preference Adjustment process. When the Discrepancy Mirror returns a MATCH output, alternate configurations can be loaded for testing or the resident fault-free configurations can be used. The output from the discrepancy mirror over a period of time indicates the relative fitness of the different configurations. This information can isolate the fault location and aid in regeneration of lost functionality through the identification of alternate resources. The cumulative discrepancy information from diverse pairings over time can be used in Step 7 to modify the selection preferences for the configurations in the population.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Hardware Simulation and Verification</head><p>The operation of the discrepancy mirror circuit was verified on a Xilinx Virtex-II Pro FPGA platform using ModelSim-II. The pull-down resistors were emulated using digital components as shown in the Xilinx data sheet <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. The waveform for the MATCH output was asserted whenever the inputs to the discrepancy mirror were in agreement. The simulation waveform showed a LOW signal whenever the MATCH output was a '0'. In the Xilinx Virtex-II Pro FPGA, when pull-down resistors are emulated, a LOW signal is the equivalent of a logic-0 output. The circuit was also simulated using Cadence SPICE. The entire circuit was also realized using a total of 44 p and n-channel MOS transistors using a 1.5 micron minimum width technology with a length of 600 nm. A total of 44 CMOS transistors were utilized to realize the circuit. The widths of the pMOS transistors in the XNOR circuit were selected to be thrice the widths of the nMOS transistors to shape the waveform rise and fall times, to develop the required timing characteristics. The simulation results and waveforms obtained indicated behavior conforming to <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2 and Table 3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Fault Location Experiments</head><p>Two sets of experiments were performed to analyze the fault isolation latency. Both experiments sought identify the number of iterations required to identify the faulty resource in the case of single fault. A monte carlo simulator was constructed using a C-language program for simulating the Selection, Detection, and Preference Adjustment phases. The inputs to the simulated mirror were obtained using random number generators. Random input values were applied to two configurations chosen at random from the pool of competing configurations. More formally, let U denote the set consisting of all the logic resources in the FPGA, S denote the pool of resources suspected of being faulty, and C i ⊆ U denote the set of resources used by the i th configuration. Initially, |S| = |U |. A process of m successive intersections among the subsets</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">C j C k =j (1 ≤ j, k ≤ m) are performed.</formula><p>Each successive intersection reduces |S| until after the m th intersection at time t = m eventually |S| = 1, completing the fault-location process. Each experiment was conducted with |U | = 1,000, 10,000, and 100,000. The expected number of iterations to isolate the fault are reported for the mean values observed over 100 trials of the simulator. An individual logic resource is the equivalent of a Configurable Logic Block (CLB) in an FPGA so the range of resource pool sizes reflect a realistic device scenario.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Analysis with Perpetually Articulating Inputs</head><p>In this experiment, the inputs applied consistently articulate any fault in the logic resources used by the configurations under test. Thus, a match output indicates that the logic resources used by the configurations being compared are completely fault-free. A discrepancy between the configurations' functional outputs indicates the presence of at least one resource fault. Assertion of the MATCH output exonerates all logic resources currently being used, and a de-assertion of the MATCH output implicates the subset of logic resources currently being used as suspect. The faulty resource is isolated after m pairings through a process of successive intersection. <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> shows the faulty resource can be identified using an expected value of 11.1 pairings when |U | = 1,000 and half of the resources are utilized by each configuration. When |U | = 100,000, the mean number of pairings required to locate the fault increases by much less than a factor of ten to a value of 17.6. Under more demanding parameters, when |U | =100,000, and when only 5% of the resources are being used by each configuration, a mean value of 63.7 pairings are required to isolate the faulty resource. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Analysis with Intermittently Articulating Inputs</head><p>Depending on the inputs applied, the fault in the functional logic under test may remain dormant and thus some inputs would not articulate a visible discrepancy. In this case, a match output from the discrepancy mirror cannot evaluate whether all the resources under test are fault-free. A discrepant output is a definitive indicator of the existence of a single-fault. With such Intermittently Articulating Inputs, the discrepancy mirror based scheme requires additional random pairings to isolate the single-fault. When |U | = 1, 000, with resource utilization at 45%, an expected 42 random pairings are required to uniquely identify the faulty resource. When |U | = 100, 000, the best performance is observed for a utilization of near 50%, where the expected value of random pairings is 64.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusion</head><p>The discrepancy mirror is capable of handling faults in either the functional logic or the detector. If there is a failure in either, then the output of the mirror remains de-asserted indicating the presence of at least one resource fault.It is able to isolate the faulty resources with a expected number of random pairings that is sub-linear in the number of resources under test. It does not depend upon a specific coding scheme or a pre-defined set of inputs. Random pairings of configurations perform successive intersection of the resources under test to isolate the faulty resource. <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 4</ref> show that more pairings are required to identify the faulty resource when the utilization of available resources is below 20% or above 80%. In these situations, each successive pairing implicates (or exonerates) a smaller sub-set of resources than when half of the resources are utilized. Finally, using a discrepancy mirror based approach, the number of pairings required for fault location increases sub-linearly with an increase in |U |. For example, at 50% utilization, the expected number of pairings to locate a fault within pools of 1,000, 10,000, and 100,000 resources are 11.1, 14.9, and 17.6, respectively, demonstrating the viability of the technique.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Discrepancy Mirror-based Scheme</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Fault Isolation with Perpetually Articulating Inputs</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Encoding</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Number 
of 
Elements 

Transient 
Fault 
Detection 

Detection 
Latency 

Special 
Test 
Inputs 

Fault 
Isolation 
Resolution 

Interrupt-
Free 
Testing 

Temporal 
CED 
Schemes 

Yes 
1 
Optional 
Algorithm 
Dependent 
Yes 
Sub-circuit 
Under Test 
No 

Spatial 
CED 
Schemes 

Yes 
≥ 2 
No 
Algorithm 
Dependent 
Yes 
Sub-Circuit 
Under Test 
No 

TMR 
No 
3 
No 
Minimal 
No 
Voter 
Elements 
No 

Discrepancy 
Mirrors 
No 
2 
Yes 
Minimal 
No 

Individual 
Logic 
Resources 

Yes 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table 1 : Comparison of Fault-Detection Techniques</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="true"><head>Table 2 : Discrepancy Mirror Truth Table A B XN OR A XN OR B EN B A EN B B T RI A T RI B Match</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>0 0 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 
0 1 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
1 0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
1 1 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true"><head>Table 3 : Discrepancy Mirror Fault Coverage and Response</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Component 
Fault Scenarios 
Fault-Free 
Function Output A 
Fault 
Correct 
Correct 
Correct 
Correct 
Function Output B 
Correct 
Fault 
Correct 
Correct 
Correct 
XNOR A 
Disagree(0) Disagree(0) Fault :Disagree(0) 
Agree (1) 
Agree (1) 
XNOR B 
Disagree(0) Disagree(0) 
Agree (1) 
Fault: Disagree(0) 
Agree (1) 
Buffer A 
0 
0 
High-Z 
0 
1 
Buffer B 
0 
0 
0 
High-Z 
1 
Match Output 
0 
0 
0 
0 
1 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scrubbing away transients and jiggling around the permanent: Long survival of fpga systems through evolutionary self-repair</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Garvie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 10th IEEE Intl. On-Line Testing Symposium</title>
		<editor>C. Metra, R. Leveugle, M. Nicolaidis, and J. Teixeira</editor>
		<meeting>10th IEEE Intl. On-Line Testing Symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="160" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Logic synthesis of multilevel circuits with concurrent error detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Touba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mccluskey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="783" to="789" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synthesis of low-cost parity-based partially self-checking circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mohanram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sogomonyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gossel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Touba</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">On-Line Testing Symposium, 2003. IOLTS 2003. 9th IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-07" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="40" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Which concurrent error detection scheme to choose?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mitra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mccluskey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings International Test Conference</title>
		<meeting>International Test Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page">985</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An efficient class of unidirectional error detecting/correcting codes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hartmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="879" to="882" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design techniques for testable embedded error checkers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mccluskey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE COMPUTER</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="88" />
			<date type="published" when="1990-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design of totally self-checking comparators with an arbitrary number of inputs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L A</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mccluskey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Computers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="546" to="550" />
			<date type="published" when="1984-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Reliable Computer Systems:Design and Evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Siewiorek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Swarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<publisher>Digital Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Word voter: A new voter design for triple modular redundant systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mitra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mccluskey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">18th IEEE VLSI Test Symposium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-04" />
			<biblScope unit="page">465</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Virtex-II Pro and Virtex-II Pro X Platform FPGAs : Complete Data Sheet</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Xilinx</forename><surname>Inc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
