<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:27+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A TCP with Guaranteed Performance in Networks with Dynamic Congestion and Random Wireless Losses</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stefan</forename><surname>Schmid</surname></persName>
							<email>schmiste@tik.ee.ethz.ch</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Networks Laboratory ETH Zurich</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CH-8092</postCode>
									<settlement>Zurich</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Roger</forename><surname>Wattenhofer</surname></persName>
							<email>wattenhofer@tik.ee.ethz.ch</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Networks Laboratory ETH Zurich</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CH-8092</postCode>
									<settlement>Zurich</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A TCP with Guaranteed Performance in Networks with Dynamic Congestion and Random Wireless Losses</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>It is well-known that TCP performs poorly in the presence of packet losses happening for reasons other than Internet congestion. One increasingly important source of such errors are wireless links. In this paper, networks are studied where the congestion-and thus the bandwidth available to a host-varies over time, and where in addition packets are lost at random. First, we propose a network comprising both dynamically varying congestion and random errors. Second, our model is extended with network calculus concepts in order to study bursty changes of congestion. Finally, we present the transfer protocol TCP &quot;Wichita&quot; (TCPW) which achieves a provable worst-case performance in this environment.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>TCP is the prevailing transport protocol of the Internet. It features a variety of properties such as reliable data transport or flow and congestion control. Particularly, the TCP congestion control mechanism is seen as a cornerstone of the functionality of todays Internet, as it restricts hosts to transmit their data with the maximum rate that can be handled by the Internet backbone.</p><p>The approach taken by TCP is to have each sender limit the transmission rate as a function of the perceived network congestion: If there is little congestion on the path between the sender and the destination, the sending rate will be increased, and vice versa.</p><p>In order to control the transmission rate, TCP employs a window-based scheme. Thereby, each sender maintains a send buffer called the congestion window. Basically, this window contains the packets which have already been sent, but <ref type="bibr">which</ref> have not yet been acknowledged by the receiver. Therefore, the size of this window indirectly limits the sending rate: Roughly, at the beginning of every round trip time (RTT), the sender can send a window full of packets into the connection. At the end of the RTT, the sender receives the acknowledgements (ACKs) and can fill the window with new data.</p><p>In order to avoid congestion, a TCP sender seeks to change the window's size-and thus the sending rate-according to the presently available bandwidth. However, the only feedback a sender gets about the current state of the Internet is the number of packet losses it experiences, and hence it is clear that the size of the congestion window can only approximately reflect the current bandwidth. Most TCP versions work as follows: As long as no packets are lost, the window is increased multiplicatively up to a certain threshold, after which it is increased linearly. On the other hand, if a packet is lost, the sending window is cut in half. This so-called Additive Increase -Multiplicative Decrease (AIMD) strategy has proved to be an effective means to prevent congestion collapses as they happened in the 1980s <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>: If routers start dropping packets, the different senders reduce their sending rates multiplicatively and alleviate the load in a collaborative manner.</p><p>However, the Internet has undergone many changes over the last 10 years, both in terms of its size and of its composition. Of prime importance is the evolution of wireless networking technology, which has led to a large number of mobile Internet users. A crucial difference between wireline and wireless networks is the presence of random wireless losses in the latter. Specifically, the effective bit error rates in wireless networks are significantly higher than in wireline networks: e.g., due to higher cochannel interference, host mobility, multipath fading, or disconnections because of coverage limitations, etc. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref> The higher packet error rates in wireless networks inherently lower the performance experienced by connections traversing such networks. Unfortunately, however, they cause an even more severe degradation in the throughput of connections using TCP as the transport protocol: TCP does not have any mechanisms to differentiate between congestion-induced and other losses. Consequently, when a TCP sender experiences wireless losses, it wrongly interprets such losses as congestion losses, and cuts down its window and thus the throughput of the connection.</p><p>In this paper, we introduce a network model which comprises both congestion and random losses. Thereby, the bandwidth available to a host changes over time, for instance due to the dynamic bandwidth demand of other hosts. We will assume a conservative perspective and consider worst-case changes of the available bandwidth. In particular, we apply concepts of network calculus <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref> and allow for bursty dynamics. Moreover, in our model, packets are lost at random due to wireless links, or due to intermittent faults in hardware elements (e.g., Ethernet, FDDI adapters, etc.) or incorrect handling of arriving packets by routers. We then look at a single TCP sender and investigate algorithms which achieve a provable throughput in this environment.</p><p>The rest of this paper is organized as follows. Related work is reviewed in Section II. In Section III, we describe the model and introduce our definitions. Section IV presents and analyzes our transfer protocol TCP Wichita (TCPW). We extend our model in Section V and allow for bursty changes of congestion. The average-case performance of TCPW is studied by simulation in Section VI. Finally, the paper is concluded in Section VII.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. RELATED WORK</head><p>TCP lies at the heart of today's Internet, and still many aspects of TCP are subject to active research, e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref>. Unfortunately, we can only review some of these contributions. For an overview of TCP, we refer the reader to <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, or-for a more technical introduction-to <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[27]</ref>.</p><p>With the increasing number of mobile and wireless devices populating the Internet, researchers have started studying the impact of wireless networking technologies on the different layers of the protocol stack, including physical, data-link, medium-access, network, transport, and application layers <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref>.</p><p>One of the first papers to address TCP performance under random losses is due to Lakshman and Madhow <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. The authors investigate a model where each packet is lost independently with probability q. It is shown that-even in the absence of congestion and if the available bandwidth is infinite-the TCP's throughput is roughly limited by 1/ √ q.</p><p>Many solutions have been proposed in literature to improve TCP's performance over wireless links. For a good overview on the topic, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>[24] <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>. These approaches fall into three categories <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>: Link layer approaches which enhance TCP's performance without requiring any change at the transport layer (e.g., the snoop protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>); indirect approaches which also mask the characteristics of the wireless portion of the connection, but split the TCP connection at the base station (e.g., I-TCP <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>); and end-to-end approaches which require changes of the protocol stack at both the sender and the receiver (e.g., WTCP <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref>).</p><p>Our approach is different from the papers mentioned above as we study an explicit network model. Our model is based on the work by <ref type="bibr">Karp et al. [15]</ref> who investigate several optimization problems for Internet congestion. We also consider an enhancement of this model: in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>, a novel model inspired by network calculus concepts <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref> for the congestion's dynamics has been introduced which allows for bursty changes of the available bandwidth. We extend the wireline approaches of <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref> by taking random losses into account besides dynamic congestion, seeking to shed light on the wireless case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. MODEL</head><p>In this paper, it is assumed that the routers in the Internet drop packets when the congestion increases, and that some additional packets are lost at random for other reasons, for instance due to a high bit error rate on certain wireless links. For such a network, we consider the problem of regulating the sending rate of a unicast flow from one host to another such that the throughput is maximized.</p><p>First, consider the following static model where the bandwidth available to a flow is constant, and where a host aims at choosing its sending rate x in such a way that its throughput is maximized. If there was only a constant loss probability (independently of the sending rate), the best policy would clearly be to send at the highest possible rate given the host's hardware resources and network connection. However, if we assume the losses due to congestion to increase with the host's sending rate, this may no longer be the best solution, but there may be one or more optimal operation points. Let f be a function that defines, for each sending rate x, a corresponding packet loss probability f (x). Then, if the loss probability increases monotonically-i.e., the second derivative of f is positive: ∀x : δ 2 f (x)/δ 2 x &gt; 0-there is exactly one optimal operation point. It is easy to devise transport protocols that find such a point quickly by probing different sending rates; for example, one could make use of Brent's algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> which has a logarithmic execution time.</p><p>Henceforth, however, only dynamic models are considered where the bandwidth changes over time. This paper assumes that the bandwidth available to the flow fluctuates according to the varying requirements for bandwidth of other competing flows rather than on the flow considered. Thus, in our model, the dynamics of the congestion is given externally. Additionally, there are random packet losses in the network because of wireless links.</p><p>We consider a synchronous model where time is divided into an infinite number of rounds. The duration of a round is approximately given by the round-trip-time (RTT) between the sending and the receiving host of the flow. At the beginning of each round, the sender transmits all the data in the sending window. By the end of the round, the sender has got the acknowledgments (ACKs) from the receiver and can detect whether there have been any packet losses. Based on this information, it will then increase or reduce the size of its sending window, which determines the sending rate of the next round. Recall that the sender is not able to distinguish whether packets have been lost because of congestion or because of wireless errors.</p><p>Basically, this setting can be regarded as a game: The congestion changes are controlled by an adversary ADV which, in every round t, selects the available bandwidth u t . The task of a transfer protocol ALG is to decide the rate x t with which to send in round t such that the throughput is maximal. Thereby, ALG has no knowledge about u t and not even about the old values u s for s &lt; t. All it knows is its own sending rates x s for all s &lt; t, and whether there have been packet losses in these rounds.</p><p>In order to evaluate the performance of a transfer protocol in such a game, cost or gain functions are needed. The cost function used in this paper is described next. If in round t, ALG sends with a rate x t , and if there are no losses, we say that the gain of ALG in round t is x t . That is, ALG has a gain x t if there is no congestion in round t and if there are no random errors.</p><p>We now look at the two sources for packet losses in more detail. If in round t the available bandwidth is smaller than the sending rate of the transfer protocol, i.e., u t &lt; x t , ALG cannot transmit its packets due to congestion and the gain is 0 in round t. Moreover, with probability p, a channel is unavailable to the flow in a round t regardless of the sending rate x t , and ALG cannot increase its gain either. Thus, we have gain ALG (x t , u t ) := x t , if x t ≤ u t and no random error 0, otherwise At first sight, this cost function seems to be quite severe: For instance, there is no gain at all in congested rounds and all data is lost. Although there would be many reasonable alternative cost functions, this solution takes into account that a transfer protocol usually has to start a retransmission mechanism after a time-out and therefore experiences a certain overhead. Note that our cost function also incorporates an opportunity cost: If a transfer protocol conservatively chooses too low sending rates, i.e., x t &lt;&lt; u t , the gain is small as well. The goal of ALG is therefore to use sending rates x t which are always close to, but never above u t .</p><p>Observe that with the model described so far, in the worst case, no algorithm ALG can achieve a positive gain: After ALG has decided about its rate x t , a powerful clairvoyant adversary can always choose the available bandwidth to be slightly smaller than this rate, i.e., u t = x t − ε for some arbitrary small ε &gt; 0. Thus, the sender suffers congestion in every round and the total gain of ALG is 0. However, since congestion is determined by the policies of the competing flows, and since the flows normally do not change their rates too abruptly, also congestion does not change too drastically from one moment to the other. Therefore, it is reasonable to assume certain constraints on the bandwidth's dynamics. In our case, we assume that the bandwidth can only increase by a certain percentage per round; we do not need any bound for the bandwidth's decrease. Formally, the adversary ADV is allowed to choose u t+1 from the interval [0, u t · µ]. In Section V, we will extend this model with bursts.</p><p>Having defined the gain of a transfer protocol ALG and the worst-case congestion changes controlled by ADV , it is possible to evaluate ALG's performance formally. However, quantifying the gain by an absolute number itself does not provide many insights. The approach taken here is to compare ALG's gain to the gain the best transfer protocol OP T would have achieved for the same input. Thereby, OP T knows the available bandwidth in advance, i.e., it can always choose x t := u t which clearly yields the optimal throughput. Hence, OP T is inherently more powerful than ALG: While ALG is an online algorithm and has to select x t without the knowledge of u s for s ≥ t (and only based on binary feedbacks about u s for s &lt; t), OP T can solve the optimization problem offline. Concretely, OP T only experiences random losses, but no opportunity or congestion costs, and thus its gain in round t is given by gain OP T (x t , u t ) := u t , if there is no random error 0, otherwise To quantify ALG's performance, we consider the competitive ratio <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, i.e., the worst-case ratio (over all possible executions) of the total gain achieved by OP T divided by the <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. Sample sequence: The available bandwidth u t changes over time in a limited manner. The goal of ALG is to choose xt slightly smaller than ut. The first round is a success (u 0 = x 0 ), and ALG increases its sending rate. In the next round however, there is no gain due to congestion. In rounds 4 and 5 there are random errors, and the transfer protocol shown in the figure wrongfully reduces its sending rate although the potential bandwidth is large.</p><p>total gain of ALG (cf Definition 1). The objective of ALG is to minimize this ratio.</p><p>Definition 1 (Competitive Ratio ρ): An algorithm ALG is ρ-competitive compared to an optimal offline algorithm OP T if for all input sequences I, it holds that</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">gain OP T (I) ≤ ρ · gain ALG (I) + k</formula><p>where k is a constant independent of the input. In the following, we assume that there is no loss in round 0 and x 0 = u 0 . <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> depicts an example: The available bandwidth changes multiplicatively over time, and ALG can increase its gain only if x t ≤ u t (e.g., in round 1 where x 0 = u 0 ). Moreover, there are random errors once in a while, for example in rounds 4 and 5. The algorithm shown in the figure decreases its sending rate in rounds 5 and 6, since it has wrongfully interpreted the losses as congestion losses.</p><p>Before concluding this section, we introduce some definitions. In the following, we will distinguish between good and bad rounds. Definition 2 (Good and Bad Rounds): Rounds where the probing rate x t is smaller or equal the available bandwidth u t are called good rounds. A round t where x t &gt; u t is called a bad round. Moreover, we will refer to rounds where random losses happen as loss rounds.</p><p>Definition 3 (Loss Rounds): Rounds where neither ALG nor OP T can transmit any data because of random errors are called loss rounds. Note that by our definitions, ALG may not be able to transmit any data in good rounds, because there are random losses. However, in such a round OP T cannot increase its gain either. This motivates the definition of successful and non-successful rounds.</p><p>Definition 4 (Successful/Non-successful Rounds): Good rounds where there are no losses are called successful, all other rounds are called non-successful. Thus, successful rounds are exactly those rounds where ALG successfully transmits data and hence increases its gain.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. A COMPETITIVE TCP</head><p>Having introduced the model, we now present and analyze our transfer algorithm TCP Wichita, short TCPW. 1 Basically, the idea of TCPW is to compensate wrongful rate reductions due to random errors by increasing the rate more after successful rounds. TCPW is described in Algorithm 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Algorithm 1 TCP Wichita (TCPW)</head><p>1: (* Round t *) 2: if round t − 1 successful then 3:</p><p>x t := 2µ 2 · x t−1 ; 4: else 5:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">x t := x t−1 /2; 6: end if</formula><p>The sending rate of TCPW in round t solely depends on the binary feedback as to whether the previous round was successful or not. Moreover, TCPW cuts the sending window in half after a loss. This is similar to many existing TCP versions. However, after successful rounds, TCPW increases the sending rate also multiplicatively. This increase is larger than µ-the maximal change factor of the available bandwidth-in order to compensate wrong reductions in the past.</p><p>So how does TCPW's perform in the dynamic network introduced in Section III? First, we compute the missed bandwidth in rounds where the sending rate of TCPW is too high, i.e., higher than the available bandwidth (case x t &gt; u t ).</p><p>Lemma 4.1: In the bad rounds, the gain of an optimal transfer protocol OP T is at most a factor 4µ 2 larger than the gain TCPW achieves in the good rounds, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">gain OP T (bad) ≤ 4µ 2 · gain T CP W (good).</formula><p>Proof: First, assume that there are no loss rounds, i.e., good rounds are also successful rounds, and vice versa. After having shown that the claim holds in this case, we will tackle the general case.</p><p>Consider the last good round t before a sequence of bad rounds t, t + 1, ..., t + τ for some (maybe infinite) τ &gt; 0. We have x t ≤ u t , and by the definition of TCPW,</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">x t+1 = 2µ 2 x t &gt; u t+1 , x t+2 = x t+1 /2 = µ 2 x t &gt; u t+2 , x t+3 = x t+2 /2 = µ 2 /2x t &gt; u t+3 , etc.</formula><p>Thus, OP T has to reduce its sending rate geometrically, and the gain in a sequence of bad rounds after a good round t is limited by a factor 4µ 2 times the last successful transmission of TCPW:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">2µ 2 x t · ∞ i=0 2 −i = 4µ 2 x t .</formula><p>It remains to study the case of random losses. We consider the last good and successful round t before a sequence of nonsuccessful rounds t + 1, t + 2, ..., t + τ for some τ &gt; 0. TCPW does not distinguish errors due to congestion from random errors and reduces the probing rate geometrically as observed above. But OP T can never send with a rate larger than x i for <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. In the first good round, the competitive ratio of TCPW is at most 2µ. In general, TCPW catches up by a factor of at least 2µ with probability 1 − p, and loses a factor of at most 2µ with probability p.</p><p>i ∈ [t+1, t+τ ], because in non-successful good rounds, it also experiences the random loss, and in bad rounds its sending rate is upper bounded by x i for i ∈ [t + 1, t + τ ].</p><p>The study of the competitive ratio of good rounds is more involved. By our definition, the sending rate of TCPW is lower than the available bandwidth in these rounds. Moreover, TCPW reduces its sending rate even further after loss rounds, because it assumes the loss to be due to congestion.</p><p>By modeling the situation as a Markov chain (for an introduction, cf <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>), it can be seen that if the random loss probability is sufficiently small compared to the bandwidth changes, the expected competitive ratio in good rounds is small as well, i.e., TCPW sends at rates that are almost as high as the optimal sending rate.</p><p>Lemma 4.2: If µ ≤ 1−p 4p , the expected gain of TCPW in good rounds is at most a factor 4µ smaller than the expected gain of an optimal offline algorithm OP T , i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">E[gain OP T (good)] ≤ 4µ · E[gain T CP W (good)].</formula><p>Proof: Consider the first good round t after a sequence of bad rounds. Since x t−1 &gt; u t−1 , x t = x t−1 /2, and u t ≤ µu t−1 , the competitive ratio is at most 2µ in round t. However, with probability p, round t is non-successful, and TCPW cuts its sending rate in half while the actual bandwidth increases by a factor of at most µ, yielding a new potential competitive ratio of 4µ 2 . On the other hand, if there is no random loss, TCPW catches up by a factor of at least 2µ, and the competitive ratio is 1 (or round t + 1 is bad). Now consider round t + 1 and assume that there was a random loss in round t, i.e., the TCPW's sending rate is at most a factor 4µ 2 smaller than the one of OP T . With probability p, there is yet another random loss, and the competitive ratio in round t + 2 can be as large as 8µ 3 . However, with probability 1 − p, TCPW catches up by a factor of at least 2µ since the available bandwidth increases at most by a factor µ per round. And so on.</p><p>Thus, a competitive ratio of good rounds can be modeled with the infinite, 1-dimensional Markov chain shown in <ref type="figure">Figure  2</ref>: With probability p, TCPW loses a factor of at most 2µ in each round compared to the real bandwidth, and catches up by a factor at least 2µ with probability 1 − p.</p><p>Let us refer to the states in the Markov chain of <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>from left to right-as s 0 , s 1 , etc., and let π(s i ) be the steadystate probability of state s i . We have p·π(s 0 ) = (1 −p) ·π(s 1 ), and hence π( Using the fact that the steady-state probabilities must sum up to 1, it is possible to compute π(s 0 ):</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">s 1 ) = p/(1 − p) · π(s 0 ), p · π(s 1 ) = (1 − p) · π(s 2 ) and hence π(s 2 ) = p/(1 − p) · π(s 1 ) = p 2 /(1 − p) 2 · π(s 0 ), etc. By induction, it follows that, for i &gt; 0, π(s i ) = p 1 − p i · π(s 0 )</formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">π(s 0 ) ∞ i=0 p 1 − p i ! = 1 ⇒ π(s 0 ) = 2p − 1 p − 1 .</formula><p>Knowing the probability distribution, the expected competitive ratio in the good rounds becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">E[ρ good ] ≤ ∞ i=0 π(s i )(2µ) i+1 = 2µπ(s 0 ) · ∞ i=0 2µp 1 − p i .</formula><p>As stated in the lemma, we assume that µ ≤ 1−p 4p , and the claim follows.</p><p>Lemma 4.2 requires that µ and p adhere to a certain constraint, that is, if the random loss probability p is large, the bandwidth can only change by small factors µ. Although it is possible to alleviate this restriction by using other algorithms than TCPW, it is clear that p and µ must always be correlated in some way. Moreover, the performance of such alternative transfer protocols-which can be analyzed with the same techniques as introduced for TCPW-can be significantly worse than TCPW. For example, the Markov chain of a modified TCPW which increases its bandwidth by a factor of 4µ 2 after successful rounds but which still halves the window size is depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 3</ref>. The constraints for µ and p are slacker in this case, but the competitive ratio is worse.</p><p>Finally, we can combine Lemmata 4.1 and 4.2, and get the following theorem.</p><p>Theorem 4.3: The expected competitive ratio of TCP Wichita (TCPW) is at most 4(µ 2 + µ) if µ ≤ 1−p 4p . Proof: According to Lemma 4.1, an optimal offline algorithm OP T can increase its gain by a factor at most 4µ 2 in the bad rounds following a successful round. The expected competitive ratio of good rounds on the other hand is at most 4µ (Lemma 4.2). Since we assume that x 0 = u 0 , there is a good round before every sequence of bad rounds, and the claim follows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. CONGESTION WITH BURSTS</head><p>It has been pointed out by <ref type="bibr">Willinger et al. [30]</ref> that the nature of network traffic is inherently self-similar and bursty. In this section, we extend our framework to allow for burst-like changes of the available bandwidth as proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>.</p><p>We do not give a complete introduction to network calculus here, but refer the interested reader to the book by Le Boudec and Thiran <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref>. However, we will quickly review the concept of leaky-bucket arrival curves. In Section V-B, it is then shown how these arrival curves are adapted to model bursty congestion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Leaky-Bucket Arrival Curves in Network Calculus</head><p>Network calculus introduces the notion of arrival curves which provide some deterministic limitation to the network traffic sent by sources. The idea is that if the data flows indeed adhere to these limitations, it is possible to make statements about the deterministic behavior of networks, for instance about the queue lengths at the different routers.</p><p>Arrival curves are defined as follows. Let R be a data flow, and R(t) the total number of bits R has sent until time t. Let α be an increasing function defined for all times t ≥ 0. R has an arrival curve α if and only if for all s ≤ t:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">R(t) − R(s) ≤ α(t − s)</formula><p>Thus, the total number of bits sent until time t by flow R can never exceed the amount of bits sent by R until some time s plus α(t − s). As an example, we look at a so-called leaky bucket arrival curve which is defined as α(t) = c 1 t + c 2 for some non-negative constants c 1 , c 2 . <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> visualizes the constraints imposed upon a flow R by such an arrival curve: The total number of bits sent can increase by c 2 at once and with a rate c 1 over time, unless there is a conflict with a constraint from a previous round. Informally, the total number of bits must always be less or equal the minimum constraint that arises if the curve α is attached (or added) at all points of R(t). <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>. Leaky bucket arrival curve: The number of bits sent by flow R must never exceed the constraints from earlier times (dashed lines), i.e., ∀s ≤ t :</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">R(t) ≤ R(s) + α(t − s).</formula><p>Note that such an arrival curve incorporates a limited form of amortization: If flow R only sends a few bits for several rounds, the constraints of earlier rounds get weaker and allow R to send up to c 2 bits at once in some later round. In this paper, we port this property of arrival curves to the field of congestion control.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Bursty Congestion Changes</head><p>How can the concepts of Section V-A be used to model dynamic congestion? The idea is to bound the adversarial bandwidth changes by an arrival curve. Concretely, the new adversary ADV can again increase the available bandwidth by a factor of µ in every round. However, it may also decide to accumulate some power in some rounds and then make more abrupt changes in later rounds. The goal of a transfer protocol ALG is to compete with an optimal offline algorithm OP T which knows all the bandwidth changes in advance. <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>. Visualization for the case ∀t : u t+1 ≥ ut, i.e., for an adversary which never decreases the bandwidth. The bandwidth can increase multiplicatively in every round, but it must always adhere to the constraints imposed by the previous rounds (dashed lines).</p><p>ADV has two parameters: A rate µ ≥ 1 and maximum burst factor B ≥ 1. In every round, the available bandwidth u t varies according to these parameters in a multiplicative manner. That is, ADV selects u t+1 from the interval u t+1 ∈ [ ut βtµ , u t · β t · µ]. Hence, the available bandwidth can change by a factor of at most β t µ, where β t is called the burst factor at time t. It is explained next.</p><p>On average, the available bandwidth changes by a factor at most µ per round. However, there can be times of only small changes, but consequently, the bandwidth can change by factors larger than µ in later rounds. At the beginning, β t equals B, i.e., β 0 = B. For t &gt; 0, the burst factor β t is computed depending on β t−1 and the actual bandwidth change c t−1 that took place in round t − 1. More precisely,</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">β t = min{B, β t−1 µ c t−1 } where c t := u t+1 u t , if u t+1 &gt; u t u t u t+1</formula><p>, otherwise</p><p>This means that if the available bandwidth has changed by a factor smaller than µ in round t, i.e., c t &lt; µ, the burst factor will increase multiplicatively by µ ct , and hence the potential bandwidth change is larger in the next round (and vice versa if c t &gt; µ). In other words, the adversary is allowed to save power for forthcoming rounds. This amortization is however limited as β t is upper bounded by B for all rounds t. Also note that β t ≥ 1 always holds, because c t ≤ µβ t by the definition of ADV . <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref> visualizes ADV for the case ∀t : u t+1 ≥ u t , i.e., for an ADV than only increases (but never decreases) bandwidth: The bandwidth can rise by a factor of µB in every round, unless it conflicts with a constraint from a previous round, i.e., ∀t : u t ≤ min i∈{0,...,t−1} {u i · B · µ t−i }.</p><p>In the following, we investigate the performance of TCPW. First, observe that the missed gain by TCPW in bad rounds is still upper bounded by 4µ 2 times the gain of TCPW in good rounds (cf Lemma 4.1), because the same geometric series argument applies. For the competitive ratio of good rounds, the analysis is similar as well: Over-pessimistically, a Markov chain as depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 6</ref> can be assumed. It follows that Although the main focus of this paper is on worst-case performance, in this section, we want to complete the picture by giving some simulations of the average case behavior of TCPW for random (rather than adversarial) bandwidth changes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Without Congestion Bursts</head><p>In Section IV, it has been shown that TCPW achieves an expected competitive ratio of at most 4(µ 2 + µ) if the congestion changes in a worst-case manner and without bursts, and if µ ≤ 1−p 4·p (cf Theorem 4.3). While this throughput is acceptable, our analysis was pessimistic in several respects. For instance, it is not possible that there is a sequence of bad rounds right after a good round having a high competitive ratio.</p><p>So we may ask: What is the "competitive ratio" if the bandwidth changes randomly? In the following, we select a change factor c t uniformly distributed from the interval c t ∈ R <ref type="bibr">[1, µ]</ref>. We toss a coin and increase or decrease the bandwidth with probability .5 by a factor c t accordingly.</p><p>In experimental studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref>, packet error rates ranging from 1% in microcell wireless networks up to 10% in macrocell networks have been reported. Moreover, it is reasonable to assume that the bandwidth does also change around 10% or less per round. In <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>, the competitive ratio of TCPW is shown for an error probability p = .1 as a function of the bandwidth dynamics µ. Apparently, the ratio is near linear in this range. Moreover, as expected, it is much smaller than the bound given in Theorem 4.3.</p><p>In a second experiment, we study the impact of the error probability p: <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 8</ref> plots the competitive ratio as a function of p for bandwidth changes of approximately 10% per round, i.e., µ = 1.1: After the ratio has been almost constant in the beginning, it increases abruptly if a certain threshold is exceeded. This also highlights the existence of a relationship between µ and p (e.g., µ ≤ 1−p 4p in Theorem 4.3). If the bandwidth changes randomly and if µ and p are small, TCPW performs better if it increases the bandwidth less after successful rounds, for example by a factor 1.1 · µ 2 . In the following, we will assume such a less aggressive version of TCP Wichita.</p><p>We have compared TCP Wichita to a simplified version of the well-known TCP Tahoe <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> (cf Algorithm 2). At the beginning, TCP Tahoe increases its sending rate by a factor of two (slow-start phase), but changes to linear increase after a certain threshold (congestion avoidance phase) is met. If there is an error, the new threshold becomes half the sending rate at which the loss has occurred, and the sending rate is set back to 1. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 9</ref> shows a sample execution for p = .1 and µ = 1.1. Moreover, we assume that x 0 = u 0 and that at the beginning, threshold := u 0 /2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Algorithm 2 TCP Tahoe</head><formula xml:id="formula_12">1: (* Round t *) 2: if round t − 1 successful then 3:</formula><p>if size(window) &lt; threshold then 4:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">x t := 2 · x t−1 ; 5:</formula><p>else 6:</p><p>x t := x t−1 + 1;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>7:</head><p>end if 8: else 9:</p><p>x t := 1; <ref type="bibr">10:</ref> threshold := x t−1 /2; 11: end if TCP Tahoe is in the congestion avoidance phase most of the time, as the slow starts are quite short. Moreover, with this rather high error rate of 10%, TCP Tahoe frequently experiences errors before it reaches the available bandwidth. TCP Wichita on the other hand reacts faster to the changes. It does not have any linear phases, but overshoots sometimes.</p><p>Although a comparison of different TCP versions in the average case is beyond the scope of this paper, we just give one more simulation, namely for a simplified version of TCP Reno <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, which is a newer-and more widely used-TCP x t := x t−1 + 1; 4: else</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5:</head><p>x t := x t−1 /2; 6: end if algorithm. In contrast to TCP Tahoe, TCP Reno cancels the slow-start phase after a triple duplicate ACK (but not after a time-out). The idea is that the arrival of three duplicate ACKs indicates that some packets have been received, implying that the packets may have been lost for other reasons than congestion. This modification is known as fast recovery, and it is vital to improve performance in case of random errors.</p><p>In our simulation, we assume that there are no time-outs and TCP Reno never performs a slow-start (cf Algorithm 3). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure  10</ref> depicts a sample execution. It can be seen that while TCP Reno performs better than TCP Tahoe, still many losses occur before the available bandwidth is reached.</p><p>Finally, we want to investigate the behavior of TCPW protocols for non-multiplicative bandwidth changes. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure  11</ref> shows a sample execution where the bandwidth varies according to a normal (Gauss) distribution. Thereby, the mean is given by the current bandwidth and the standard deviation is 2. For TCPW, we again use µ = 1.1, and the error probability is 10%. Although TCP Wichita's sending rate is often too high, the performance is acceptable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. With Congestion Bursts</head><p>Finally, in this section, we briefly look at bursty congestion changes <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>. The following random bandwidth changes are considered: In round t, the "adversary" selects a change factor uniformly at random from the interval c t ∈ R <ref type="bibr">[1, µ]</ref> and then increases or decreases (each with probability .5) the bandwidth by c t . Moreover, ADV saves a factor µ/c t . In a round where the product of these saved factors exceeds the maximum burst B, the congestion is changes by B ·µ, and the burst factor is set  back to 1 (cf Section V). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 12</ref> shows a sample execution for µ = 1.05, B = 1.3 and p = .05.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. CONCLUSION</head><p>This paper has introduced a model comprising both worstcase bandwidth changes and lossy links. Moreover, algorithms have been investigated which achieve provable throughputs under this model. Our results are based on the assumption that a single (selfish) sender strives for higher data rates. Of course, such a behavior (e.g., the more aggressive bandwidth increase)-if concurrently applied by many sendersmay threaten the stability of a system. However, this work has focused on a scenario where the available bandwidth is considered to be given externally, and the study of multiple TCPW flows remains to be addressed in future work. It would also be interesting to extend our model to incorporate aspects such as buffers or varying round-trip-times. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Markov chain of a modified TCPW.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Markov chain for expected competitive ratio for the case of bursty congestion changes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Competitive ratio of TCPW for µ = 1.1 as a function of p.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Sample execution of TCP Wichita and TCP Tahoe for p = .1 and µ = 1.1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Sample execution of TCP Wichita and TCP Reno for p = .1 and µ = 1.1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Sample execution of TCPW for the case of a bandwidth varying according to the normal distribution N (ut, 2), and for p = .1 and µ = 1.1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. Behavior of TCPW and TCP Reno for bursty bandwidth changes with µ = 1.05, B = 1.3 and p = .05.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> The W in Wichita stands for wireless. Moreover, in the tradition of TCP names, Wichita is also a city (in Kansas, USA).</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stochastic Modeling of TCP over Lossy Links</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Abouzeid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Azizoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Conference on Computer Communications (INFOCOM)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1724" to="1757" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of MIMD Congestion Control Algorithm for High Speed Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Altman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Avrachenkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Barakat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kherani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Prabhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="972" to="989" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Randomized Online Algorithm for Bandwidth Utilization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Arora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Brinkman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 13th Annual ACM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA)</title>
		<meeting>the 13th Annual ACM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA)<address><addrLine>Philadelphia, PA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="535" to="539" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TCP: Indirect TCP for Mobile Hosts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bakre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Badrinath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems (ICDCS)</title>
		<meeting>the International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems (ICDCS)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Comparison of Mechanisms for Improving TCP Performance over Wireless Links</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Balakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Padmanabhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seshan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="756" to="769" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving TCP/IP Performance over Wireless Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Balakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seshan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Amir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking (MOBICOM)</title>
		<meeting>International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking (MOBICOM)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Data Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bertsekas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gallager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Borodin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>El-Yaniv</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Online Computation and Competitive Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Algorithms for Minimization Without Derivatives</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
			<publisher>PrenticeHall</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bandwidth Estimation for Enhanced Transport over Wireless Links</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Casetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gerla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mascolo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Sanadidi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Westwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Annual International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking (MobiCom)</title>
		<meeting>the Annual International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking (MobiCom)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="297" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling the Throughput of TCP Vegas</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Charalampos</forename><surname>Samios</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mary</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Vernon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM SIGMETRICS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AIMD, Fairness and Fractal Scaling of TCP Traffic</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Franois</forename><surname>Baccelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dohy</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Conference on Computer Communications (INFOCOM)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Freeze-TCP: A True End-to-End TCP Enhancement Mechanism for Mobile Environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Goff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Moronski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Phatak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Conference on Computer Communications (INFOCOM)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1537" to="1545" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving TCI/IP Performance Over Wireless Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hari</forename><surname>Balakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Srinivasan</forename><surname>Seshan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Elan</forename><surname>Amir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Randy</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1st Annual International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking (MobiCom)</title>
		<meeting>the 1st Annual International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking (MobiCom)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimization Problems in Congestion Control</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Karp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Koutsoupias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Papadimitriou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science (FOCS)</title>
		<meeting>Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science (FOCS)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="74" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scalable TCP: Improving Performance in Highspeed Wide Area Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">33</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Computer Networking: A Top-Down Approach Featuring the Internet</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kurose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley Longman Publishing Co., Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boston, MA, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Performance of TCP/IP for Networks with High Bandwidth-Delay Products and Random Loss</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Lakshman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Madhow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="336" to="350" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-Y. Le</forename><surname>Boudec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thiran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Network Calculus. Springer LNCS 2050 Tutorial</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fair Scheduling in Wireless Packet Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bharghavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Srikant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="473" to="489" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MACA-A New Channel Access Method for Packet Radio</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Karn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ARRL/CRRL Amateur Radio 9th Computer Networking Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling TCP Throughput: A Simple Model and its Empirical Validation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Padhye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Firoiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Towsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krusoe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the ACM SIGCOMM Conference on Applications, Technologies, Architectures, and Protocols for Computer Communication</title>
		<meeting>the ACM SIGCOMM Conference on Applications, Technologies, Architectures, and Protocols for Computer Communication</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="314" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fundamental Challenges in Mobile Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Satyanarayanan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 15th Annual ACM Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing (PODC)</title>
		<meeting>the 15th Annual ACM Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing (PODC)<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mobile Communications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schiller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic Internet Congestion with Bursts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schmid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wattenhofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 13th Annual IEEE International Conference on High Performance Computing (HiPC)</title>
		<meeting>the 13th Annual IEEE International Conference on High Performance Computing (HiPC)<address><addrLine>Bangalore, India</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">WTCP: A Reliable Transport Protocol for Wireless Wide-Area Networks. Wireless Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sinha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Venkitaraman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Shivakumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bharghavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Implementation)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">TCP/IP</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Handbook of Wireless Networks and Mobile Computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stojmenovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MACAW: A Media Access Protocol for Wireless LANs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bhaarghavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Demers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the ACM SIGCOMM Conference</title>
		<meeting>the ACM SIGCOMM Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the Self-Similar Nature of Ethernet Traffic</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Willinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Leland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Taqqu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
