<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:49+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing the Internet Hierarchy from Multiple Vantage Points</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lakshminarayanan</forename><surname>Subramanian</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sharad</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><surname>Rexford</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Randy</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing the Internet Hierarchy from Multiple Vantage Points</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The delivery of IP traffic through the Internet depends on the complex interactions between thousands of autonomous systems (ASes) that exchange routing information using the Border Gateway Protocol (BGP). This paper investigates the topological structure of the Internet in terms of customer-provider and peer-peer relationships between ASes, as manifested in BGP routing policies. We describe a technique for inferring AS relationships by exploiting partial views of the AS graph available from different vantage points. Next we apply the technique to a collection of ten BGP routing tables to infer the relationships between neighboring ASes. Based on these results, we analyze the hierarchical structure of the Internet and propose a five-level classification of ASes. Our characterization differs from previous studies by focusing on the commercial relationships between ASes rather than simply the connectivity between the nodes.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>T ODAY'S Internet is divided into more than 10,000 Autonomous Systems (ASes) that interact to coordinate the delivery of IP traffic. An AS typically falls under the administrative control of a single institution, such as a university, company, or Internet Service Provider (ISP). Neighboring ASes use the Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> to exchange information about how to reach individual blocks of destination IP addresses (prefixes). An AS applies local policies to select the best route for each prefix and to decide whether to propagate this route to neighboring ASes, without divulging these policies or the AS's internal topology to others. In practice, BGP policies reflect the commercial relationships between neighboring ASes. AS pairs typically have a customer-provider or peerpeer relationship <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. A provider sells connectivity to the Internet as a service to its customers, whereas peers provide connectivity between their respective customers.</p><p>AS relationships and the associated routing policies have a profound influence on how traffic flows through the Internet. An understanding of the structure of the Internet in terms of these relationships facilitates a wide range of important applications. For example, consider a content distribution network (CDN) that can place replicas of a Web site in data centers hosted by different ASes. The company can identify the IP prefixes and ASes responsible for a large portion of the traffic from the site <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. With an accurate view of the connectivity and relationship between ASes, the company can identify the best locations for its replicas. As another example, consider a new re-gional ISP that wants to connect to a small number of upstream providers. An accurate view of the AS topology and relationships can help the ISP determine which ASes would provide the best connectivity to and from the rest of the Internet.</p><p>The Internet topology alone does not provide enough information to answer these questions. For example, suppose that AS B connects to two providers, AS A and AS C. An AS graph would show connectivity from A to B and from B to C; however, AS B's routing policies would not permit transit traffic between A and C. In addition to determining the relationship between AS pairs, it is useful to identify the position of individual ASes in the Internet hierarchy. For example, a growing ISP or CDN company may need to identify the set of so-called tier-1 providers to aid in selecting potential private peering relationships. This requires performing further analysis of the AS graph in terms of the commercial relationships between the various AS pairs. A classification of ASes based only on the topological structure (say, node degree) is not sufficient. For example, some ASes near the edge of the Internet may have a relatively large number of upstream providers, whereas some large ISPs may have modest node degree consisting mainly of private peering relationships. Knowing the relationships between the ASes is important for making these distinctions.</p><p>In the absence of a global registry, the AS-level structure of the Internet is typically inferred from analysis of routing data. Previous work has focused on constructing a view of the AS graph from traceroute experiments or individual BGP table dumps. Traceroute provides a view of the path from a source to a destination host at the IP level. The traceroute data must be analyzed to infer which interfaces belong to the same router and which routers belong to the same AS <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Running experiments between multiple source-destination pairs provides a larger collection of paths over time <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Other studies have extracted AS paths directly from BGP routing tables or BGP update messages <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. The routing table dump from the University of Oregon RouteViews server <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> has been the basis of several studies of basic topological properties, such as the distribution of node degrees <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. With the exception of the work in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, these studies have focused on the topological structure without considering the relationship between neighboring ASes. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> presents a heuristic for inferring the relationships from a collection of AS paths and evaluates the technique on the RouteViews data.</p><p>In this paper, we propose a technique for combining data from multiple vantage points in the Internet to construct a more complete view of the topology and the AS relationships. Each vantage point offers a partial view of the Internet topology as viewed from one source node. Due to the presence of complex routing policies, these partial views are not necessarily shortest-path trees and may, in fact, include cycles. We generate a directed AS-level graph from each vantage point and assign a rank to each AS based on its position. Then, each AS is represented by the vector that contains its rank from each of the routing table dumps. We infer the relationship between two ASes by comparing their vectors. Based on these relationships, we construct a new directed AS graph and examine the AS level hierarchy of the Internet. We present a five-level classification of ASes with a top-most level that consists of a rich set of peerpeer relationships between ¢ ¤ £ so-called tier-1 providers. The work we describe in this paper is novel in three ways. First, we analyze AS paths seen from multiple locations to form a more complete view of the graph. Second, rather than simply combining the data from the various vantage points, we propose a methodology for exploiting the uniqueness of each view to infer the relationships between AS pairs. Third, we characterize the hierarchy of ASes based on the commercial relationships, rather than simply the connectivity of the graph. We evaluate our technique on a collection of ten BGP routing tables and summarize the characteristics of the AS relationships. To validate the inferences, we check for paths that are not consistent with the routing policy assumptions underlying customerprovider and peer-peer relationships. We show that these cases account for a small proportion of the paths and that the most common inconsistencies may stem from misconfiguration or more complex AS relationships.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. PROBLEM FORMULATION</head><p>In this section, we present a brief overview of how AS relationships affect BGP export policies and formally define the Type of Relationship (ToR) problem. Then we discuss the practical challenges that arise in solving this problem and validating a potential solution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Type-of-Relationship Problem</head><p>The relationships between ASes arise from contracts that define the pricing model and the exchange of traffic between domains. ASes typically have a provider-customer or peer-peer relationship <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. In a provider-customer relationship, the customer is typically a smaller AS that pays a larger AS for access to the rest of the Internet. The provider may, in turn, be a customer of an even larger AS. In a peer-to-peer relationship, the two peers are typically of comparable size and find it mutually advantageous to exchange traffic between their respective customers.  Exporting to a customer: An AS can export its routes, routes of its customers, and routes learned from other providers and peers to its customer. Each BGP session defines a relationship between the two ASes it connects. Although two ASes may have multiple BGP sessions, the relationship between the two ASes should be uniquely defined.</p><p>BGP export policies have a direct influence on the AS paths seen from a particular vantage point in the Internet. If every AS adheres to the customer and provider export rules, then no path should traverse a customer-provider edge after traversing a provider-customer or peer-peer edge, and no path would ever traverse more than one peer-peer edge <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. To formulate these properties in mathematical terms, we denote an edge from a customer to a provider with a § © ¨ , an edge from one peer to another with a , and edge from a provider to a customer with a ¨</p><p>. Restating a result from <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> in these terms, we have:</p><p>Theorem 1: If every AS obeys the customer, peer, and provider export policies, then every advertised path belongs to one of these two types for some : 1) Type-1:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">§ © ¨ " ! # ! " ! (N times), ¨ " ! # ! " ! (M times). 2) Type-2: § © ¨ " ! # ! " ! (N times), , ¨ # ! " ! # ! (M times).</formula><p>The first stage of a Type-¨ path contains only customerprovider links (uphill portion) and the second stage contains only provider-customer links (downhill portion). The second type captures all paths which traverse exactly one peering link. The single peering link must appear in between the uphill and the downhill portions of any path. This is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, which is a Type-$ path where and are both 2. The dotted lines indicate where other paths would likely intersect this path. Note that if all the directions are reversed, another valid path will be shown.</p><p>The type-of-relationship (ToR) problem can be formulated as a graph theory optimization problem for labeling the edges of the graph with a § © ¨ , , or¨such or¨ or¨such that the observed paths obey the export policies implied by the relationships. <ref type="bibr">Given</ref>  to maximize the number of valid paths in 4 . <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> represents the entire Internet topology where each node is an AS and each edge represents a relationship between the incident pair of ASes. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> consists of all paths seen from the various vantage points. Although we believe that the ToR problem is NP-complete, we have not been able to prove this claim. We are not aware of any polynomial-time solution to the problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Practical Challenges</head><p>Identifying the commercial relationships between ASes is challenging in practice. First, peer-peer relationships are difficult to classify. Consider the path in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. Mistakenly labeling the 6 to 7 edge as a customer-provider or providercustomer edge would not result in an invalid path; rather, the Type-¢ path would appear as a Type-1 path. As such, identifying peer-peer edges requires the use of heuristics. Second, some AS pairs do not obey the BGP policy guidelines outlined in Section II-A. For example, two ASes operated by the same institution may have a sibling relationship, where each AS exports all of its routes to the other AS <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Other AS pairs may have backup relationships to provide connectivity in the event of a failure <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. Alternatively, two ASes may peer indirectly through an intermediate AS <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. Also, an AS pair may have different relationships for certain blocks of IP addresses; for example, an AS in Europe may be a customer of an AS in the United States for some destinations and a peer for others. Router misconfiguration may also cause violations in the export rules. For example, a customer may mistakenly export advertisements learned from one provider to another.</p><p>Previous work in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> proposed and evaluated an algorithm for inferring AS relationships from a collection of AS paths. For each AS path, the algorithm assumes that the node with the highest edge degree marks the boundary between the uphill and downhill portions of the path. In the uphill portion, each node provides transit service for the previous node; in the downhill portion, each node provides transit service for the subsequent node. The inferences from multiple paths are later combined to infer the relationship between the ASes. If ASes is a provider of 9 . Peer-peer edges are detected using a heuristic that considers the degree of the nodes adjacent to the top provider in the path; nodes with similar degree can be classified as peers. In the next section, we propose an alternate approach to the ToR problem based on the paths seen from different vantage points. Our inference technique does not depend on node degree and can tolerate occasional exceptions to the export rules in Section II-A. We classify edges as providercustomer or peer-peer and use the (small number of) invalid paths to identify AS pairs that have unusual relationships (e.g., sibling, backup, or misconfiguration).</p><p>Evaluating any solution for the ToR problem requires access to a large set of paths <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> . In the past few years, a number of service providers have made their BGP routing tables available to the public. Coordinated efforts such as the RouteViews project and the RIPE Routing Information Service provide BGP data from multiple locations in the Internet. Still, the publiclyavailable tables do not provide a complete view of the AS graph  <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. For example, a peer-peer edge between two universities (say, in the same city) would appear only in the BGP tables of these two ASes. A peer-peer edge between two large ISPs would not be visible from a third ISP that peers with both of them. Collecting BGP data from a large number of vantage points provides a more complete view of the AS graph and the set of AS paths, but it is difficult (if not impossible) to quantify the extent of coverage.</p><p>Verifying the results of the inference algorithm is difficult without a complete and accurate repository of the relationships between ASes. Four main approaches to verification are possible, each with its own limitations. First, the number of invalid paths provides a rough measure of the success of the algorithm. The invalid paths correspond to cases where the inference algorithm has misclassified certain edges, or certain ASes have unusual relationships. Second, the output of the algorithm can be compared with the results of other algorithms on the same input data. Third, the inferences can be compared with the routing policies archived in the Routing Arbiter Database (RADB) <ref type="bibr">[19]</ref>; however, the information in the RADB can be incomplete or out-of-date. Fourth, the inferences can be compared with proprietary data about the routing policies and commercial relationships of individual ASes. We follow the first approach to analyze the results of our algorithm in Section IV-C and plan to consider the other approaches in our future work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. INFERRING AS RELATIONSHIPS</head><p>Our algorithm for inferring AS relationships exploits the structure of partial views of the AS graph as seen from different locations in the Internet. First this section describes the properties of the graph seen from a single vantage point. Next we present a reverse-pruning algorithm that assigns a rank to each AS for each of the partial views. Then, we infer the relationship between two ASes by comparing their vectors of ranks. Rather than simply combining the data from different vantage points into a single graph, our algorithm exploits each unique perspective to help us infer the AS relationships. </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">5 C B D 5 © E ; F B 1 ; while (G I H Q P R 9 S H U T V 5 X W ` Y B b a ) c for all 8 e d e G f H g P R 9 R H U T h V 5 X W F P h i q p r V f 8 W s B F ; 9 R t B 9 u V 5 X W 0 v G I H Q P R 9 S H U T V 5 X W ; F B F 2 w 1 ; 5 x B w 5 © y   ;  for all 8 e d  9  V 5 X W set F P R i q p V f 8 W s B F ;</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. A Partial View of the AS Graph</head><p>Consider routing data from a single vantage point  from the example in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. The routing data provides a set of paths that can be used to construct a directed graph rooted at  . For example, the paths <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>(a). The key to inferring the AS relationships is to identify the boundary point between the uphill and downhill portions of the three paths.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">V I     7 e   6        W , V      W , and V I     7 e   6 W would result in the graph in</formula><p>In practice, the Internet consists of a relatively small number of large Internet Service Providers (ISPs) and a large number of smaller ASes. The routes seen by a small AS near the edge of the Internet should have roughly equal uphill and and downhill portions of non-zero lengths. A small AS must traverse one or more upstream providers to reach most of the many other small ASes, so the uphill portions of the routes should have a less diverse collection of edges than the downhill portions. For large ISPs in the core of the Internet, the routes consist mainly of downhill portions. In either case, we expect a large portion of the edges in the partial view of the AS graph to fall in a large, acyclic portion consisting of provider-customer edges. The remaining edges (if any) should fall into a connected component near the source node.</p><p>As such, a leaf node in the graph is likely to be a customer of its parent node(s). For example, in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>. At each stage, the algorithm identifies the leaf nodes, assigns them a rank, and removes these nodes (and their incident edges) from the graph. In the end, the remaining nodes (if any) form the connected component of the original graph 5 E ; these nodes are all assigned the same (highest) rank.</p><p>In the example in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>(a),  (rank 1) is a customer of  (rank 5),  (rank 1) is a customer of  (rank 2) and so on.  and  have no direct relationship regardless of their rank because they do not share an edge. When considering a partial view from a tier-1 AS that does not have any upstream providers, every path consists of zero or one peer-peer edges followed by a downhill portion consisting of provider-customer edges. In practice, we expect the provider-customer relationship to be acyclic <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. For example, if in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>  , and  . We exploit this observation in our algorithm by assigning the same rank to all of the ASes in the remaining graph with no leaves. Information from other vantage points is necessary to construct an inference for these ASes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Multiple Vantage Points</head><p>If we continue pruning in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>(a), the eventual leaf 6 will be inferred as a customer of <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> , even though the two ASes have a peer-peer relationship. Identifying the boundary point between the uphill and downhill portions of a path is tricky. The structure of the partial view of the AS graph depends on the position of the AS in the Internet hierarchy. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, the boundary is between 6 and 7 (the peer-peer relationship), not at  as suggested by this partial view in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>(a). Now consider the view from AS  in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2(</ref> Another reason for having multiple views arises when two ASes share a link in some but not all the views. In this scenario, our algorithm imposes a relative rank for these two ASes in a partial view even though they may not share an edge from this source's perspective. Consider the topology in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS</head><p>This section evaluates our inference techniques on a collection of ten publicly-available BGP routing tables. We classify the relationships between ASes and identify a small number of AS paths that are inconsistent with the relationship assignment. The most common anomalies seem to stem from recent acquisitions and mergers, suggesting that some AS pairs may have a sibling relationship. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. BGP Routing Table Data</head><p>Our inference techniques have been applied to a collection of ten BGP routing tables available from Telnet Looking Glass servers. We automated the process of contacting each server, sending "show ip bgp" to the command-line interface, and storing the resulting table. For each destination prefix the table has one or more routes with a variety of BGP attributes, including the AS path. We extract the best and alternate paths for each prefix and construct a list of all AS paths that appear in the table. For each path, we add the AS number of the router to the beginning of each path and remove duplicate AS numbers that arise from AS prepending. Then we process the paths to construct a partial view of the AS graph. After constructing the partial views, we apply the ranking algorithm and inference rules from Section III to assign a relationship to each AS pair that shares an edge in one or more of the routing tables. <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table I</ref> provides a summary of the ten tables we downloaded on April 18, 2001. The "# Edges" column shows the number of unidirectional edges in the AS paths. The entry for AS 3582 corresponds to the University of Oregon RouteViews server, which has  ¢ peering sessions with   different ASes <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The RouteViews server has an especially rich view of the AS graph, with over 23,000 edges compared to 11,000-15,000 edges for most of the other routing tables. In total, the AS paths in the ten routing tables have 24,752 unidirectional edges between 24,059 pairs of ASes.</p><p>We use the partial views from these ten routing tables to generate our inferences of the AS relationships. In Section IV-C, we validate our inferences using the AS paths from another collection of routing tables. We manually downloaded routing data from Ebone (AS #1755), MAE-West (AS #2548), KDDI Japan (AS #2516), and Cable and Wireless (AS #6893) on April 9, 2001. These four tables are available from Web Looking Glass servers that have a slightly different interface than the Telnet servers. The Web interface typically does not permit users to invoke the "show ip bgp" command. Instead, we rely on the "bgp paths" command that produces a list of AS paths, without the destination prefix or an indication of the best path. As with the "show ip bgp" data, we extract the AS paths, add the AS number of the source AS, and remove duplicate ASes. Next we use the results of our inference algorithm to assign a relationship to each unidirectional edge. Then, we look for paths that violate the two patterns identified in Section II. In <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>, we show the frequency of occurrence of edges in the BGP routing tables. We see that about ¢  h  of all edges appear in all ten tables while about 1 Q  R  appear in only one table. A similar distribution exists for the customer-provider subset. Almost all of the "unknown" edges appear in only one table. These edges may correspond to AS pairs with sibling or backup relationships. Similarly, many of the edges that we determined to be peer-peer edges appear in only one table. This is likely due to the peer export policy we described in Section II-A. If routes learned from one peer are not distributed to other peers, and if most peer-peer edges exist in the "dense core" as we show later, and if the dense core is almost a clique, it thus implies that most peer-peer edges will be visible from only one view.</p><p>The percentages of provider-customer and peer-peer relationships in <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table II</ref>   AS pairs. However, they do not explore this graph in terms of AS relationships.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Validation of Inferences</head><p>Since the peering and customer information of an ISP are proprietary information, we cannot validate our inferences against an official list of AS relationships. Instead, we determine what percentage of the AS paths actually adhere to the export rules suggested by our inferences. There are two scenarios where we may label an AS path as an anomaly: some AS in the path actually violates the export rules, or our inference of one of the edges in the path is wrong. The percentage error that is reported in this section is the sum total of these two scenarios. For our validation, we draw on the list of AS paths from two of the ten of the Telnet servers (AS numbers 1 and 7018) used to construct our original inferences, as well as the four Web servers <ref type="bibr">(AS numbers 1755</ref><ref type="bibr">(AS numbers , 2516</ref><ref type="bibr">(AS numbers , 2548</ref>.</p><p>If every AS pair has a customer-provider or peer-peer relationships, then every AS path should have one of the two patterns identified in Theorem 1. A path is an anomaly if it has any two adjacent edges having one of the following patterns:  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Common Anomaly Patterns</head><p>The last column in <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table IV lists one popular triple for each  routing table dump</ref>. We analyzed the popular anomaly patterns using the RADB whois data <ref type="bibr">[19]</ref> which identifies ASes by name and sometimes includes a list of import and export policies. We observed that many popular anomalies occur due to sibling relationships between two ASes under the same administration. For example, in the anomaly pattern (1 7176 8938), Genuity Europe (7176) and Genuity (1) exhibit a sibling behavior. This is also true with the anomaly pattern (8297 1290 174) with Teleglobe Europe (7018), PSINet UK (1290), and PSINet (174). The anomaly patterns <ref type="formula">(1239 1740 7018)</ref> and <ref type="formula">(3561 5400 5727</ref> of the edges to be siblings; her validation of a subset of these inferences on a private data set found that ¢ ¤ £ R  of these inferences were valid. We plan to explore our approach for detecting sibling relationships in more detail as part of future work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. INTERNET HIERARCHY</head><p>In addition to inferring the relationship between AS pairs, it is useful to identify the position of each AS in the Internet hierarchy. Previous work has classified ASes based on node degree <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>; ASes with a large number of neighbors are placed above ASes with small node degree. However, a simple degreebased approach may not capture the essence of the tiers in the hierarchy. Instead, we classify ASes based on the commercial relationships derived in the previous section. Typically, a customer should be at a lower level in the hierarchy than its provider(s). We represent the AS topology as a directed graph where the direction of an edge indicates the type of relationship between the two ASes. In our graph, a provider-customer relationship between . Such a graph representation has also been independently proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. An important difference between our approaches is the procedure used for determining the Internet hierarchy. The work in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> maps the Internet topology into a strict hierarchy based on provider-customer edges while our classification also uses the distribution of peering links to identify the top levels of the hierarchy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Customers and Small Regional ISPs</head><p>Customers are the easiest class of ASes that can be classified from this directed graph structure of the AS topology. Customers are those stub networks which are origins and sinks of traffic and which do not carry any transit traffic. From the very definition of the direction of edges in our graph, we can infer the customer ASes to be the leaves of this directed graph. In a directed graph, a leaf is a node with out-degree <ref type="bibr">£</ref> . Since an undirected graph makes no distinction between out-degree and in-degree, customers with multiple providers would have a degree more than <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> and hence would not appear as leaves of the graph. Modeling the topology as a directed graph provides a more precise characterization of the bottom-most level in the AS hierarchy. In the directed graph constructed from the ten BGP dumps,</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">¡   ¡ h  ¡ of the 1 Q £     1 Q </formula><p>ASes are leaf nodes. The rest of the graph contains just 1 " ¡  u R  of the ASes. Once we identify the customers and remove these nodes, the resulting graph has a new set of leaves. These leaves represent small regional ISPs that have one or more customers. We can continue the process of pruning the leaves of the graph until we reach a point where the graph has no leaves. This involves applying a reverse pruning algorithm similar to <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref> in Section III-B. We define the set of nodes removed by this process as small regional ISPs. Since every peering relationship is represented as a loop of two edges in the graph, no ASes with peering relationships are included in this level. Applying the reverse pruning algorithm to our graph reveals  S  S 1 small regional ISPs. We define the remainder of the graph as the core, consisting of a connected component with just </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Dense Core</head><p>The set of ASes that remain after the pruning process represent the core of the Internet. Given the nature of the reverse pruning process, we can infer that for every AS present in the core, all of its peers and its provider should also be present in the core. The core of the graph should include the small number of so-called tier-1 providers. In practice, the term "tier-1 provider" is loosely defined as a "large" AS or as an AS that does not have any upstream provider. We could identify these ASes by looking for all provider-free nodes. However, this approach would be sensitive to a small number of missing edges or misclassified relationships in our AS graph. From our BGP tables and relationship inferences, there are 98 ASes with no provider. Such a large number of ASes unlikely form today's Internet dense core. This list includes small ISPs such as CCP Online and HutchCITY. Instead, we could exploit the observation that every provider-free AS would peer with every other provider-free AS to ensure reachability to all destinations. That is, the set of tier-1 ASes should form a clique where every AS has an edge to and from each of the other ASes. Other providerfree ASes, if they exist in our graph, would be excluded from the set of tier-1 providers.</p><p>In practice, some ASes may have complex transit or backup relationships to provide connectivity. We define a weaker notion of the dense core as the largest subset of ASes whose induced subgraph is "almost a clique." We define a directed graph of q nodes to be dense if every node in the graph has an indegree and out-degree of at least q   ¢ . q   ¢ is the smallest value of a degree of every node for which we can guarantee that the shortest path between any two nodes in the graph is at most ¢ (irrespective of the graph's structure). This can ensure that two ASes in the dense core which do not share a peering <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref>. Greedy heuristic to order the nodes relationship can potentially peer indirectly through some other intermediary AS in the dense core (the intermediary AS in the path of length ¢ ). The problem of determining the largest clique in a graph is NP-hard. Given that a clique is just one example of a dense graph, the problem of finding the largest dense subgraph of a graph becomes much harder. We have developed a greedy heuristic for identifying the ASes in the dense core.</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">compute ¤  d  9  V 5 X W with maximum out-degree;  B c g ¤  ; d  ¥ ¤ T h V  ¤ W  B 1 ¦ F B 1 ; while ( Y B 9 u V 5 X W ) c compute § m d  9 u V 5 X W 0 v  with max¨ max¨ max¨ V f §    W (selecting the § with the max out-degree)  B  ª © f c " §  ;   P h   { l i « ¨ h H " ¬ F H g H R V F W s B ¨  V f §    W ; F B F 2 w 1 ; d  ¥ ¤ T h V I § W ­ B F ; </formula><p>1) Identifying the Dense Core: First, we order the vertices based on a "greedy" notion of connectivity, following the heuristic in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Transit Core</head><p>After removing the dense core, we noticed the presence of other large national providers and hosting companies that have peering relationships with many of the ASes in the dense core. To identify these ASes, we define the notion of a transit core. Nodes in the transit core peer with each other and with ASes in the dense core, but they do not tend to peer with many other ASes. In our directed graph representation, these peering links are essentially the incoming directed edges from vertices outside this set to vertices within the set. We define such a set of edges to be the in-way cut of the graph induced by the given set of vertices. Using this property, we define the transit core as the smallest set of ASes containing the dense core which induces a weak in-way cut, that is, one having a small number of edges compared to the total number of ASes in the transit core. </p><formula xml:id="formula_5"> ½ r x ¾ V f  W Á · Á º Á ¢ .</formula><p>The problem of finding weak cuts in a graph is NP-complete and no good approximation algorithms are known for that problem. Given that the transit core is a superset of the dense core and Â The same set of ASes in <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table I</ref> were used, except for the CERFnet looking glass server which has been offline. that the dense core is derived by the greedy ordering, we apply the same ordering to find the transit core as was used to find the dense core. A natural way of using this ordering to find the transit core is to find the smallest value of p such that peering links with the ASes in the dense core. Concert, Singapore Telecommunications, UUNet European division, Teleglobe European division and KDDI Japan are some example ISPs in our transit core. We found many of the top providers in Europe and Asia to be present in our transit core.</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">Áµ  8 u ½ r ¿ ¾ V I   W Á · p   ¢ .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Outer Core</head><p>We classify all of the remaining ASes in the core as the outer core. The members of the outer core typically represent regional ISPs which have a few customer ASes and a few peering relationships with other such regional ISPs. The outer core consists of ¡  R  ASes that have ¢ ¤  peering sessions with ASes in the dense core and 1   peering sessions with ASes in the transit core. We observed that many members of our outer core are regional ISPs. Some examples include Turkish Telecomm, Williams Communications Group, CAIS Internet, Southwestern Bell Internet Services and Minnesota Regional Network. It is interesting to note that while Exodus Communications (AS 4197) is present in our outer core, Exodus.net (AS 3967) is present in the dense core.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. Summary</head><p>Table VI summarizes the number of ASes at each level in the hierarchy-dense core (level 0), transit core (level 1), outer core (level 2), small regional ISPs (level 3), and customers (level 4). Table VII summarizes the connectivity between various levels in the AS hierarchy. Each number in the table is the total number of edges from one level to another. For example, R ¢ ¤ is the total number of edges from level 0 to level 1. The tables shows several key properties of the Internet topology: <ref type="bibr">¥</ref> The ASes in dense core are very well connected. <ref type="bibr">¥</ref> As we move from the dense core toward customers, the inter-level and intra-level connectivity drops significantly.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_16">Level 0  1  2  3  4  0  312 626 1091 958 6732  1  183 850 1413 665 3373  2  29  145 1600 543 3752  3  0  0  0  212</ref>  The large number of customer ASes have their providers distributed across all the levels. The ASes in level £ support a large number of customer ASes. This indicates that the connectivity across levels is not strictly hierarchical, as also observed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. <ref type="bibr">¥</ref> The number of edges within the outer core is less than the total number of vertices in the outer core. This indicates the presence of multiple disconnected groups of ASes in the outer core; ASes in different groups communicate via ASes in the dense core and the transit core. The graph in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 6</ref> explores the relationship between node degree and the levels in the hierarchy. We define node degree as the number of neighboring ASes without regard to the relationship. The graph plots the cumulative distribution of node degree on a logarithmic scale. In general, level 0 and 1 ASes have high degree, and level 3 and 4 ASes tend to have low degree. However, this is not universally true. Some customers at level 4 have a large number of upstream providers, and some ASes in the dense core at level 0 have a relatively small number of neighbors. For example, our results suggest that AS 1833 (TeliaNet USA) has a degree of only  £ . Yet, we classify TeliaNet as part of the dense core due to its rich collection of peering relationships. A hierarchy based solely on degree distribution would not be able to make this distinction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSIONS</head><p>The relationships between ASes has a significant impact on the flow of traffic through the Internet. Our work makes two important contributions toward understanding the structure of the Internet in terms of these relationships: <ref type="bibr">¥</ref> An algorithm for inferring AS relationships from partial views of the AS graph from different vantage points ¥ A mechanism for dividing the Internet hierarchy into levels based on AS relationships and node connectivity</p><p>The complete structure of the Internet is unknown and difficult, if not impossible, to obtain. Our approach is comprised of many heuristics, with certain limitations: Multiple ASes may fall under the administrative control of a single institution, due to historical artifacts and market forces. We plan to extend our methodology to incorporate more complex routing policies that are not captured by the traditional customer-provider and peer-peer relationship. Despite these limitations, we have shown that our approach provides a detailed view of the Internet topology in terms of the relationships between ASes.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Type-2 path following export rules</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. (a) Partial view from AS</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Reverse pruning algorithm on graph  s </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>of the total number of edges in the graph. The nodes in the core have an average degree of .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Cumulative distribution of AS degree by level</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>These relationships translate directly into policies for exporting route advertisements via BGP sessions with neighboring ASes:</figDesc><table>¥ 
Exporting to a provider: In exchanging routing informa-
tion with a provider, an AS can export its routes and routes 
of its customers, but cannot export routes learned from 
other providers or peers. 
¥ 
Exporting to a peer: In exchanging routing information 
with a peer, an AS can export its routes and the routes of 
its customers, but cannot export routes learned from other 
providers or peers. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7" validated="false"><head>TABLE I TELNET LOOKING GLASS SERVERS</head><label>I</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>AS # 
Name 
# Edges 
1 Genuity 
13419 
1740 CERFnet 
14287 
3549 Globalcrossing 
13542 
3582 University of Oregon 
23136 
3967 Exodus Comm. 
19005 
4197 Global Online Japan 
13474 
5388 Energis Squared 
13534 
7018 AT&amp;T 
14160 
8220 COLT Internet 
11282 
8709 Exodus, Europe 
15519 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8" validated="false"><head>TABLE II INFERRED RELATIONSHIPS FOR 23,935 AS PAIRS</head><label>II</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Relationship 
# AS pairs Percentage 
Provider-customer 
22,621 
94.51% 
Peer-peer 
1,136 
4.75% 
Unknown 
178 
0.74% 

0 

10 

20 

30 

40 

50 

60 

70 

80 

90 

1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
% of Edges 

# of Dumps 

Unknown Edges 
Peer Edges 
Cust-Prov Edges 
All Edges 

Fig. 4. Percentage of edges that appear in 

 

of the ten tables 

B. Relationship Inferences 

Table II summarizes the results from applying our inference 
algorithm to the ten BGP tables from Table I. Our algorithm 
produces an inference for over 
 
 
 u¢ 
R  
of the edges in our AS 
graph (¢ 
 
  
  
¤  
h  
of the 
¢ 
 
  
  
 
h  
AS pairs). The vast majority of 
AS pairs appear to have a provider-customer relationship. Ap-
proximately 
 
h  
of the AS pairs have a peer-peer relationship. 
Table III highlights the role of the various inference rules in 
drawing conclusions about AS relationships. A large percent-
age of the provider-customer relationships are inferred from the 
Dominance rule. Dominance in 
q 
dimensions is a good indi-
cation of a provider-customer relationship and we can be rea-
sonably certain of 
 
h  
 u 
z  
h  
h  
of our provider-customer inferences. 
Similarly, close to 
 
¤  
R  
of the peering links are inferred from 
the Equivalence condition. The probabilistic rules account for 
 
u 
 
 
S  
of the provider-customer inferences and 
¢ 
h  
 u 
z ¢ 
¤ 
S  
of the 
peer-peer inferences. 
</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10" validated="false"><head>TABLE III DISTRIBUTION OF THE 23,757 INFERENCES</head><label>III</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Rule 
Number Percentage 
Complete dominance 
21,618 
95.57% 
Probabilistic dominance 
1,003 
4.43% 
Equivalence 
849 
74.74% 
Probabilistic equivalence 
287 
25.26% 

 
 u¡ 
S  
. The percentage of provider-customer relationships we 
infer is within 
1 
-1 
h u 
R  
of the figure reported in [10]. Her study 
drew on RouteViews data from September 1999, January 2000, 
and March 2000. The number of edges in the RouteViews dump 
has grown by over 
 
U £ 
S  
over the last 
1 
Q  
months. With the 
larger RouteViews table and the nine other tables, our collec-
tion of edges is twice as large as the graph used in her earlier 
study. Using traceroutes from 
1 
Q 
sources to 
 
£ 
h £ 
  
£ 
h £ 
£ 
destina-
tions [8] in October 2000, CAIDA constructed an AS graph 
that is slightly larger than ours. Their final graph consists of 

 
  
  

 
ASes and 
¢ 
 
  
 £ 
£ 
R  
edges. Ours contains 
1 
" £ 
  

 
h ¡ 
ASes 
and 
¢ 
¤  
  
  
 
R  
</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11" validated="false"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>violation of the export rules. This anomaly may arise from a misconfigured customer or due to a misclassified relationship where the customer AS is actually a sibling of one or both of the providers. Backup and sibling relationships can cause case ¢ and case  anomalies. Case  suggests that the path traverses two consecutive peering links, which may be permissible if the two peers have a sibling rela- tionship for some destination prefixes. Detecting these anomaly</figDesc><table>1) 
V 
l 2 
3 1 
 0 
© 1 
W 
: An AS permits transit traffic between two of 
its providers. 
2) 
V 
l 2 
3 1 
s £ 
W 
: An AS permits transit traffic from one of its peers 
to one of its providers. 
3) 
V 
I £ 
¢ 0 
© 1 
W 
: An AS permits transit traffic from one of its 
providers to one of its peers. 
4) 
V 
I £ 
 £ 
W 
: An AS permits transit traffic between two of its 
peers. 
Case 
1 
represents a serious </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12" validated="false"><head>TABLE IV QUANTIFICATION &amp; DISTRIBUTION OF PATH ANOMALIES</head><label>IV</label><figDesc>into one of four cases. The results in Table IV show that case 3 anomalies are very uncommon and case 1 arises less frequently than case 2 and case 4. KDDI ex- hibits an unusually high number of all four cases (especially case 4); further investigation is necessary to explain this fact.</figDesc><table>AS # AS Name 
# of 
Anomaly Anomaly 
Unique 
Case 1 Case 2 Case 3 Case 4 
Popular 
Paths 
Paths 
% 
Anomalies 
Anomaly 
1 Genuity 
65,383 
421 
0.65% 
83 
25 
58 
0 
155 
(1 7176 8938) 
7018 AT&amp;T 
141,283 
889 
0.63% 
82 
17 
64 
1 
185 
(8297 1290 174) 
6893 CW 
70,253 
2,050 
2.92% 
135 
27 
98 
10 
212 (3561 5400 5727) 
2548 MaeWest 115,199 
1718 
1.49% 
209 
59 
145 
5 
245 (1239 8043 6395) 
1755 Ebone 
23,469 
678 
2.89% 
116 
23 
86 
7 
207 (3300 8933 2200) 
2516 KDDI 
126,414 
10,927 
8.67% 
555 
262 
260 
33 
1051 
(209 1800 1239) 

paths provides a way to identify AS pairs that may have more 
complicated relationships. 
As shown in Table IV, the vast majority of paths are consis-
tent with the relationship assignments and the associated export 
policies. The percentage of anomalies varies between 
£ 
 u 
- 
 u£ 
R  
for five of the six routing tables. These results validate our base 
assumption that the export rules are observed by a large per-
centage of the ASes. However, KDDI (AS #2516) has a rela-
tively high percentage of anomalous paths (¡ 
 u 
£  
 
). For every 
anomalous path, we can identify an anomaly pattern consist-
ing of three adjacent ASes 
V 
I  
g  
 
  
~ 6 
W 
where the pair of edges 

V 
I  
g  
 
W 
and 
V 
  
  
~ 6 
W 
falls A small number of AS triples 
V 
I  
h  
  
  
~ 6 
W 
are responsible for the 
vast majority of the anomalies. For most of the routing tables, 
ten different AS triples were responsible for more than 
 
h £ 
R  
of 
the anomalous paths. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16" validated="false"><head>TABLE V ASES IN THE DENSE CORE</head><label>V</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>AS# 
AS Name 
AS# 
AS Name 
AS# 
AS Name 
1 
Genuity 
174 
PSINet 
1239 SprintLink 
1755 Ebone 
4200 Telia 
1833 TeliaNet 
209 
Qwest 
2548 Digex 
6453 Teleglobe 
2914 Verio 
3356 Level 3 
3549 GlobalCrossing 
3967 Exodus 
4006 Cogent 
3561 Cable&amp;Wireless 
2828 XO 
701 
UUNet 
5511 FranceTelecom 
8918 Carrier 1 
7018 AT&amp;T WorldNet 

2) Properties of the Dense Core: Applying this heuristic to 
the core of our graph, we identify a dense core consisting of 

¢ 
¤ £ 
ASes. These ASes include the large ISPs such as Genuity, 
Sprint, AT&amp;T, and UUNet, as shown in Table V. The top 
¢ 
£ 
ASes have a very dense connectivity of 
 
 1 
Q ¢ 
peering links. The 
top 
1 
Q  
of the 
¢ 
¤ £ 
ASes almost form a clique with only three 
edges missing from the clique. The largest clique we observed 
in this innermost core consisted of 
1 
Q  
ASes. The 
¢ 
¤ £ 
ASes 
have 

  
  
U  
R ¢ 
provider-customer edges to customer ASes and 
 
h  
¡ 
provider-customer edges to the small regional providers. After 
removing the dense core, the remainder of the core consists of 

1 
" £ 
R ¢ 
¤ 
ASes. 
We also obtained routing table dumps on 22 September 
2001 1 . The new dense core adds KDDI, another AT&amp;T AS, 
Reach and Korea Telecom, while removing Ebone, both Telia 
ASes, Cogent, UUNet and Carrier1. The dense core for 20 De-
cember 2001 adds TeliaNet, AOL, and Tiscali, while removing 
Digex, France Telecom, one AT&amp;T AS, and Korea Telecom. 
Most of the additions and removals came from or went to the 
transit core. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18" validated="false"><head>TABLE VI DISTRIBUTION OF ASES IN THE HIERARCHY</head><label>VI</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Level 
# of ASes 
Dense core (0) 
20 
Transit core (1) 
129 
Outer core (2) 
897 
Small regional ISPs (3) 
971 
Customers (4) 
8898 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20" validated="false"><head>TABLE VII INTER-CONNECTIVITY ACROSS LEVELS</head><label>VII</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>We are grateful to the anonymous reviewers for helping us improve the paper. We would also like to thank everyone who has made their BGP routing tables available to the research community.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Inter-Domain Routing in the Internet</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>AddisonWesley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sam</forename><surname>Halabi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Danny</forename><surname>Mcpherson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Internet Routing Architectures</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<publisher>Cisco Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>second edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interconnection, peering, and settlements</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Geoff</forename><surname>Huston</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. INET</title>
		<meeting>INET</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scalable router configuration for the Internet</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Alaettinoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE IC3N</title>
		<meeting>IEEE IC3N</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On network-aware clustering of Web clients</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Krishnamurthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heuristics for Internet map discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Govindan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tangmunarunkit</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Network topologies, power laws, and hierarchy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tangmunarunkit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Govindan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jamin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Willinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-06" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Computer Science, University of Southern California</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep. 01-746</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<ptr target="http://www.caida.org" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">CAIDA Web Site</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An analysis of inter-domain topology and route stability</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Govindan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Reddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On inferring automonous system relationships in the Internet</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Trans. Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">University of Oregon RouteViews project</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.routeviews.org/" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<ptr target="http://moat.nlanr.net/AS/Data/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BGP tables from the University of Oregon RouteViews Project</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On powerlaw relationships of the Internet topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michalis</forename><surname>Faloutsos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Petros</forename><surname>Faloutsos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Christos</forename><surname>Faloutsos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-09" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="262" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Inet: Internet topology generator</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jamin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>CSE-TR-433-00</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-09" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>U. Michigan</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the hierarchical structure of the logical Internet graph</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Figueiredo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jaiwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE ITCOM</title>
		<meeting>SPIE ITCOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inherently safe backup routing with BGP</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lixin</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Timothy</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Griffin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><surname>Rexford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stable Internet routing without global coordination</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rexford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Trans. Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="681" to="692" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On inferring AS-level connectivity from BGP routing tables</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Govindan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jamin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Willinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">IXC Buys Three ISP&apos;s</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.thedigest.com/93/93-38.html" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
