<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:49+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Schedulability Criterion and Performance Analysis of Coordinated Schedulers</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2001-09">September 2001</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chengzhi</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
							<email>chengzhi@rice.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Rice University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>6100 S Main Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>77005</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Edward</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Knightly</surname></persName>
							<email>knightly@rice.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Rice University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>6100 S Main Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>77005</postCode>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Schedulability Criterion and Performance Analysis of Coordinated Schedulers</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Proceedings of ITC-17</title>
						<meeting>ITC-17						</meeting>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2001-09">September 2001</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Inter-server coordinated scheduling is a mechanism for downstream nodes to increase or decrease a packet&apos;s priority according to the congestion incurred at upstream nodes. In this paper, we derive an end-to-end schedulability condition for a broad class of coordinated schedulers that includes CJVC and CEDF. In contrast to previous approaches, our technique purposely allows flows to violate their local priority indexes while still providing an end-to-end delay bound. We show that under a simple priority assignment scheme, coordinated schedulers can outperform WFQ schedulers, while replacing per-flow scheduling operations with a simple coordination rule. Finally, we illustrate the performance advantages of coordination through numerical examples and simulation experiments.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>In the past decade, there has been great progress in the design of packet scheduling algorithms, including service disciplines which achieve performance isolation <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref>, quality of service differentiation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref>, and scalable core-stateless implementation <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>.</p><p>Simultaneously, new theoretical tools have been devised to analyze the performance properties of such multi-class schedulers. For example, exact delay bounds for Earliest Deadline First (EDF) and Strict Priority (SP) schedulers are derived in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. Moreover, multi-node delay bounds have been developed for networks of elements characterized by service curves using "network calculus" <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21]</ref>, an approach which encompasses and generalizes previous results for networks of Weighted Fair Queueing (WFQ) servers <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> and rate-controlled servers <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref>. In general, such techniques provide schedulability conditions, i.e., constraints that, if satisfied, ensure that all packets of all flows will meet their respective delay bounds without violation or loss.</p><p>Recently, a class of schedulers has been studied which employ coordination of priorities among nodes <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28]</ref>. A scheduler that employs coordination can give a packet higher or lower priority at downstream nodes depending on whether the packet was serviced late or early at upstream nodes. This intuitively appealing concept has been applied in a number of service disciplines proposed in the literature including FIFO+ <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and Global EDF <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Moreover, such schedulers have potential applications to future multi-service networks since they can provide end-to-end services using simple, work conserving, per-node scheduling algorithms that do not require per-flow operations. Indeed, it was shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> that core stateless service disciplines such as Core-stateless Jitter Virtual Clock (CJVC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> can also be expressed by a simple coordination mechanism.</p><p>The goal is this paper is to provide a schedulability condition and analytical framework for coordinated schedulers. Our approach represents a fundamental departure from previous techniques in two ways. First, our schedulability condition allows packets to violate local per-node constraints, while still ensuring delay bounds are satisfied end-to-end, i.e., by the final hop. Allowing such local violations is crucial to exploiting the key multi-node property of coordinated schedulers. Consequently, techniques that require all packets to satisfy their local constraints at each node to ensure end-to-end schedulability cannot be applied. Second, previous techniques rely on either per-flow traffic re-shaping <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref> or per-flow scheduling <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21]</ref> (such as in WFQ) to derive multi-node schedulability conditions. In contrast, we consider a scenario of work-conserving servers with no per-flow operations, and therefore achieve the core-stateless property defined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>.</p><p>The contribution of this paper is as follows. First, we develop an end-to-end schedulability condition for a broad class of coordinated schedulers that includes Coordinated EDF (CEDF) and CJVC. Our key technique is to introduce a virtual partition of the traffic into essential, and non-essential traffic, where only the former traffic can impede a packet in meeting its delay bound. With this concept, we derive a bound on the essential traffic at downstream nodes and show that distortion of the essential traffic is confined to within a narrow range. In other words, we show that coordination limits downstream distortion analogous to the way per-flow traffic reshaping eliminates distortion.</p><p>Second, we study the problem of assigning local priority indexes. We show that with a particular assignment scheme, coordinated schedulers can achieve not only the same end-toend delay bound as WFQ, but also the tighter end-to-end delay bound than WFQ, yet without per-flow packet forwarding in the network core. In other words, we establish that any set of flows that can be scheduled in WFQ networks can also be scheduled in coordinated scheduling networks.</p><p>Finally, we illustrate and quantify the practical advantages of coordinated scheduling with a set of numerical examples and ns-2 simulation experiments. We first devise a simple example with three flows to illustrate that coordinated schedulers can achieve a lower delay bound than WFQ schedulers. We then use simulations of exponential and Pareto on-off traffic flows and a 6-node network to illustrate statistical differences between coordinated scheduling, EDF, and WFQ.</p><p>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. In Section 2, we provide background and a precise definition of inter-server coordination. In section Section 3, we develop a key tool for multi-node analysis and show how to bound the essential traffic at downstream nodes. In Section 4, we use this traffic bound to provide a global schedulability criterion for networks using coordinated scheduling. Next, in Section 5, we study priority index assignment and its relationship to WFQ. Finally, in Section 6, we compare coordinated and non-coordinated service disciplines using numerical examples and simulations, and in Section 7 we conclude.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">BACKGROUND ON INTER-SERVER COORDINATION</head><p>In this section, we provide a formal definition of coordination among servers. We then illustrate the generality of the definition by describing how service disciplines from the literature, namely CEDF and CJVC, can be characterized as examples of coordinated schedulers. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Definition and Properties Definition 1 (Coordinated Network Scheduling) Consider a server which services packets in increasing order of their priority indexes. A scheduler possesses the CNS property if</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">¢ ¡ £ ¥ ¤¦¨ ¤¦¨¤¦¨ § © ¡ £ ¡ £ § ¡ £ ! ¤¦ # " % $ &amp; ( ' ¡ £ ¥ ¤¦ ) 1 0 (1)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">£ ! ¤¦ H G I P ' £ ¥ ¤¦ R Q T S U £ ¥ ¤¦ B ' £ ! ¤¦ S U £ ¥ ¤¦ # V , W X 2 ` Y where ' £ ! ¤¦ S U £ ¥ ¤¦ Y b a .</formula><p>The key property of the CNS discipline is that the priority index of each packet at a downstream server depends on its priority index at upstream servers, which in turn depends on its entrance time into the network. Therefore, if a packet violates its priority index at an upstream server, downstream servers will increase the packet's priority, thereby increasing the likelihood that the packet will meet its end-to-end delay bound. Similarly, if a packet arrives "early" due to a lack of congestion upstream, downstream servers will reduce the priority of the packet, enabling other packets to be serviced ahead of it. Thus, even though the distributed servers operate independently, the priority index of each packet is communicated downstream via insertion of a label into the packet header (e.g., as described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>) so that the servers (virtually) coordinate to provide an end-to-end service.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">CJVC and CEDF</head><p>An example of coordinated scheduling is Core-stateless Jitter Virtual Clock. CJVC was proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> as a mechanism for achieving guaranteed service without per-flow state in the network core. CJVC uses "dynamic packet state" to store information in each packet header containing the eligible time of the packet at the ingress router and a slack variable that allows core routers to determine the local priority index of the packet. For a work-conserving variant of CJVC, the priority index of packet 2 of flow 7 at node is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">¡ £ ¥ ¤¦¨ ¤¦¨¤¦¨ § c de g f i h U p r q ¡ £ s t ¡ " % $ £ ! ¤ u $ w v y x      b § ¡ £ ¥ ¤¦ B " % $ &amp; x     ¡ £ 1 0 (2)</formula><p>where flow-7 </p><formula xml:id="formula_3">x       ¡ £ G  I P ' £ ¥ ¤¦  Q  S  £ ! ¤¦  ' £ ¥ ¤¦ S  £ ! ¤¦ B V , where ' £ ¥ ¤¦ § x   4      x     d  e   and S U £ ¥ ¤¦ § x 4     " x   d  e   .</formula><p>Thus, work-conserving CJVC is a coordinated network service discipline in which the increment of the priority index is a function of the reserved bandwidth of the corresponding flow.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>, coordination within the context of EDF was studied. We refer to such schedulers as Coordinated Earliest Deadline First (CEDF) if the priority indexes are assigned as</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">¡ £ ¥ ¤¦ § ¡ £ £ ¥ ¤ u $ £ ¥ ¤e C ) C ) C ) £ ! ¤¦ (3)</formula><p>clearly expressible in the form of Equation <ref type="formula">(1)</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Example</head><p>Consider the simple example of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> in which three packets of flow 7 arrive to the network at § a 9 respectively, and traverse two hops with</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">¡ £ ` § ' ¡ £ ¥ ¤e § ¢ ¡ .</formula><p>In the example, all packets have identical size, the link speed is 1 packet per time unit, and cross traffic exists at both hops. At the first hop, these three packets are assigned priority indexes (deadlines) of 5, 6, and 7 respectively, by both CNS and EDF. Suppose further that these three packets depart from the first hop at times 3, 4, and 10 respectively, so that the third packet misses its local deadline by 3 time units due to cross traffic with higher priority. According to the arrival times at the second hop, these three packets are assigned priority indexes of 8, 9, and 15 by EDF, whereas the indexes are 10, 11, and 12 for CNS. In the example, with further cross traffic at the second hop, the third packet has higher priority in the CNS network than the EDF network, and therefore is able to meet both its local delay bound and global delay bound. In contrast, in the EDF network, the third packet meets its local delay bound at the second hop, but is not able to "catch up", and meet its end-to-end delay bound.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="0">1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 111 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20</head><p>Packet Arrival Event</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="0">1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 111 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20</head><p>Packet Priority Index</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Packet Departure Event</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>δ = 5 msec 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20</head><p>(a) CNS and EDF at the First Hop</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="0">1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 111 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20</head><p>Packet Arrival Event msec δ = 5</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="0">1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 111 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20</head><p>Packet Priority Index</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Packet Departure Event 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20</head><p>(b) EDF at the Second Hop</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="0">1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 111 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20</head><p>Packet Arrival Event msec δ = 5</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="0">1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 111 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20</head><p>Packet Priority Index</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Packet Departure Event 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20</head><p>(c) CNS at the Second Hop This simple example illustrates how distributed servers can be forced to (virtually) coordinate priority indexes to improve the likelihood of satisfying an end-to-end delay constraint.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">TRAFFIC CHARACTERIZATION IN DOWNSTREAM NODES</head><p>In multi-node networks without traffic re-shaping, traffic characteristics are distorted at downstream nodes as compared to their properties at the network entrance. In this section, we derive a burstiness bound for arriving traffic at downstream nodes, which we use as a basis for deriving a global schedulability criterion in the next section. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Preliminaries</head><formula xml:id="formula_6">, £ ¥ ¤ u $ ¡ £ Q £ ¥ ¤ u $ ¡ ¤ £ £ ! ¡ £ # "<label>(5)</label></formula><p>We also assume that the network is stable if for  <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24]</ref>, acyclic networks or cyclic networks with ring topology are stable if Inequality (6) is satisfied.</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">$ § 9 D C ) C ) C E # % , &amp; ( ' f 0 ) 2 1 4 3 6 5 £ ( 7 9 8 A @ C B E D £ ! ¡ £ F H G B<label>(6)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Virtual Partition</head><p>Here, we define essential traffic 3 as a fundamental notion for analysis of coordinated schedulers that enables us to accurately bound the queueing delay experienced by the traffic. In particular, for a given time P , all arriving traffic of server $ arriving in I a ¤ £ can be virtually decomposed according to whether or not its priority index is larger than P . As only the portion of traffic with priority index smaller than or equal to time P affects the time when traffic with priority index P is served, we refer to this traffic as essential traffic, which we formally define as follows. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition 2 (Essential</head><formula xml:id="formula_8">  R ¨ S Q¨T   © ¨ U W V  ¡ £ "<label>(7)</label></formula><p>As an example, for the traffic with the arrival pattern described in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1 (a)</ref>, some values of its essential traffic are given as: . In other words, void time refers to the largest time less than such that there is no traffic backlogged with priority index smaller than or equal to P . Notice that for an initially idle network, the void time is guaranteed to exist.</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">£ ¥ ¤ u $ ¡ A 4 P £ § a if P G I  A 4 ¡ £ ; £ ! ¤ u $ ¡ A 4 P £ §  $ £ if P G I¡ X £ ; £ ¥ ¤ u $ ¡ A 4 P £ §  $ £  e £ if P G I Y X 4 ` £ ; £ ¥ ¤ u $ ¡ A 4 P £ §  $ £ R  e £  b a £ if P G I Y ` # c</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Burstiness Bound at the Ingress Server</head><p>To Since the essential traffic at a downstream server depends on the corresponding essential traffic at the ingress server (i.e., the network entrance), we first provide an upper bound for the essential traffic envelope at the ingress server.</p><p>Lemma 1 An essential traffic envelope of flow 7 at its first hop is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">§ £ ¥ ¤ u $ t ¡ £ § f 1 h p 3 © ¨ § 3   © ¨ 3  )  ¡ £ "<label>(10)</label></formula><p>Proof: See <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">Based on Lemma 1, we have § £ ¥ ¤ u $ ¡ a £ § &amp; ( ' f ) 2 1 § £ ¥ ¤ u $ ¡ £ Y  B " ! £</formula><p>, which will be used to derive the schedulability criterion in the next section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Downstream Servers</head><p>At the output of a multiplexer, a traffic flow's characteristics (such as its traffic envelope) are distorted. Without additional mechanisms such as per-flow re-shaping, this distortion can become more severe at each Downstream node. We now show that under coordinated network schedulers, the distortion of the essential traffic is limited due to coordination itself. That is, a flow's distortion is limited by downstream mechanisms to catch up late packets and delay early packets. Recall that we only consider stable networks, so that the queueing delay is bounded (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> at each server along its path.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">END-TO-END SCHEDULABILITY CRITERION</head><p>In this section, we derive a general end-to-end schedulability criterion for coordinated schedulers. In our approach, we allow packets to violate their local priority indexes and exploit the coordination property to obtain an end-to-end delay bound. Moreover, since priority indexes are not required to be equivalent to delay bounds, the approach provides flexibility in assignment of local priority indexes which we further exploit in the next section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">A Recursive Condition for Violating Packets</head><p>For an isolated EDF scheduler, the schedulability condition (no packet violates its priority index) has thoroughly been discussed in several papers, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>. However, when the schedulability condition can not been satisfied, it is important to know what is the bound for the amount of time by which packets miss their deadlines (priority indexes), specially for coordinated schedulers that allow packets to violate their local deadlines. Based on the key property of coordinated schedulers exploited in Lemma 2, we provide a condition for bounding the time by which packets miss their local deadlines (priority indexes).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theorem 1 If each arriving packet at server</head><p>$ has not missed its priority indexes at the previous server by more than </p><formula xml:id="formula_12">£ ¥ ¤¡ @  £ ¥ ¤£  " % $ D such that ¡ £ ¥ ¤£  " % $ £ ¥ ¤¡ @  £ ¥ ¤£  " % $ D ¡ £ ¥ ¤£</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">End-to-End Delay Bounds</head><p>Since the schedulability criterion given in Equation (12) decouples the priority index from the delay bound, the following corollary can be used to compute the end-to-end delay bound. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Corollary 1 Given the priority index increment assignments</head><p>Proof: See <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p><p>Observe that the maximum queueing delay of Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">(13)</ref> has three components. The first term has two interpretations which we illustrate by examples. If the network performs CEDF as in Equation <ref type="formula">(3)</ref>, then ¡ £ is a constant and represents the local delay bound at the ingress node. Alternatively, if the network performs CJVC, then</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">f i h U p ¡ ¡ £ 1 § f i h U p ¡ q t ¡ £ ! ¤ u $ Q ¡ £ v § f 1 h p ¡ q  ¡ £  £ @ I ¢ ¡ " % $ £ ¥ ¤ u $ Q ¡ £ V  v f 1 h p ¡  ¡ £  £ f i h U p ¡ I t ¡ " % $ £ ! ¤ u $ Q ¡ £ V </formula><p>i.e., it is the maximum packet size divided by the guaranteed rate, plus the maximum amount of time a flow-7 packet arriving before its previous packet priority index. The second term is the sum of the upper bounds of the local priority indexes from the second to final hop. The third term represents the delay by which packets are allowed to violate the priority index at the final hop. As we will show in Section 5, there is flexibility in how to assign all three of these components to obtain different end-to-end performance properties.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Leaky Bucket Flows</head><p>If the essential traffic envelopes at the ingress servers are bounded by affine functions, the schedulability criterion of Theorem 1 can be simplified. This scenario arises for both leaky bucket regulated traffic as well as virtual leaky-bucket smoothers as described in Section 5.1. Proof: See <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Corollary 2 If each flow</head><p>In the next section, we apply this simplified schedulability criterion to assign priority indexes at downstream servers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">PRIORITY INDEX ASSIGNMENT FOR END-TO-END SERVICE</head><p>In this section, we develop a particular priority index assignment scheme and show that under the scheme, coordinated schedulers can achieve the same end-to-end delay bound as WFQ.</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">¡ ! due to " % $ # &amp; % " w ( ' % w ) ' # .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">At Ingress Servers</head><p>Suppose the ingress node services packets according to the virtual clock service discipline <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref>. Then the priority index increments at the ingress server are</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">¡ £ § I ¢ ¡ " % $ £ ¥ ¤ u $ Q ¡ £ ¥ ¤ u $ V   ¡ £ £ £ (14)</formula><p>where,   , using the results in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">¥ ¤¦ Q ¡ £ ¥ ¤¦ § ¡ £ ¥ ¤ u $ Q ¡ £ ¥ ¤ u $ . Since ¡ £ ¥ ¤ u $ § ¡ £ ¥ ¤ u $ ¡ £ § f i h U p q ¡ £ ¥ ¤ u $ ¡ " % $ £ ¥ ¤ u $ v x  ¡  is</formula><formula xml:id="formula_18">If 5 ¦ 7 8 A @¡ @  £ ¥ ¤ u $ D h D £ ¦ G ¡@  £ ¥ ¤ u $ D , then according to Theorem 2 in [10], ¢ ¡ £ ¥ ¤ u $ ¢ ¡ £ ¥ ¤ u $ &amp;  B ! £ £ G ¡ ¦ @£ ! ¤ u $ D 2 § 9 C ) C ) C<label>(15)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_20">¢ ¡ £ ¥ ¤ u $ Q ¡ £ ¥ ¤ u $ § ¡ £ ¦ £ £ £ "<label>(17)</label></formula><p>Notice that in this case,  ¡  bounds the first term of the end-to-end delay bound of Corollary 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">At Downstream Servers</head><p>At downstream servers and Y 9 , we assign the priority index increments as: </p><formula xml:id="formula_21">' ¡ £ ¥ ¤¦ §  B ! £ £ £  B ! £ £ G ¡@  £ ¥ ¤¦ B " % $ D<label>(18)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_22">¢ £ ! ¤£  § ' £ ¥ ¤£  Q £ ¥ ¤¡ @  £ ¥ ¤£  " % $ D .</formula><p>This assignment is simpler than CJVC <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> and VTRS <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> because it does not require a slack variable or virtual time adjustment term for each packet. The coordination property allows us to avoid this term and consequently, to simplify the service discipline as well as obtain a tight end-to-end delay bound.</p><p>We next show that with the above priority index assignment scheme, coordinated scheduling achieves the same end-to-end delay bound as WFQ.</p><p>Theorem 2 Consider the priority index increment assignment defined by <ref type="bibr">Equations (14)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_21">(18)</ref>  </p><p>Proof: See <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p><p>Notice that the end-to-end delay bound in Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_23">(19)</ref> is the same as that for WFQ <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> and VC <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. It is needed to point out that, with coordination and the above simple priority index assignments, Theorem 2 plus a simple example provided in the next section is to our knowledge the first proof that core-stateless schedulers can outperform WFQ schedulers.</p><p>Finally, we observe that coordinated schedulers can employ heterogeneously allocated pernode priority assignments in order to better utilize network resources. For example, flows could allocate a less stringent priority index to heavily loaded nodes. A general assignment scheme remains an important issue for future study in coordinated schedulers as well as other service disciplines. <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> Traffic Parameters and Priority Index Assignment. flow 1 In this section we illustrate the performance advantages of inter-server coordination by comparing the CNS service discipline with non-coordinated schedulers WFQ and EDF. For rateguarantee oriented service disciplines such as WFQ and VC, we show via a numerical example that with appropriate selection of priority indexes, CNS can outperform WFQ and VC. Finally, we present a brief ns-2 simulation study to illustrate performance differences in a scenario with six nodes and cross traffic. Consider a simple system with 3 flows as described in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>. Let server 1 and server 2 have capacity C and other servers have infinite capacity, each packet has size and let</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">COORDINATION VS. NON-COORDINATION: NUMERICAL EXAMPLES AND SIM-ULATIONS</head><formula xml:id="formula_24">¡ $ §  B " ! $ § £ $ § ¢ ¡ e ¡ $ § a ' ¡ $  ¤e § ' $  ¤e § ¤ £ ¡ S t $  ¤e § S 8 $  ¤ a § a ' ¡ $  ¤ a § ' $  ¤ a</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.">Comparison of CNS and WFQ</head><formula xml:id="formula_25">$ t ¡ £ § e ¡ £ § a ¡ £ § ¡ e .</formula><p>The traffic parameters and the priority index assignments are summarized in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>.</p><p>Since each packet does not suffer the queueing delay at its first hop,</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">$  ¤¡ @$  ¤ u $ D § e ¤¡ @e ¤ u $ D § a ¤¡ @ a ¤ u $ D § a</formula><p>and the parameters that are needed when checking the scedulability for flows at server 1 are given in <ref type="table" target="#tab_18">Table 2</ref>. </p><formula xml:id="formula_27">¨ § ¡ ¡ £ Q £ £ ¢ £ ¥ ¤£ £ G Q 5 £7 § £ £ f i h U p £ ( 7 ©  B " ! £ Q G $  ¤¡ ¦ @ ! $  ¤e D G Q 5 £ ( 7 ¨ § £ £ ¢ e ¤e " (21)</formula><p>To verify flow-2 packets will miss their priority indexes at server 1 no more than Using the parameters given in <ref type="table" target="#tab_18">Table 1 and Table 2</ref>, it is easy to verify Inequalities (20) (21) <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref>. Similarly, using the parameters given in <ref type="table">Table 1 and Table 3</ref>, it is easy to verify flow-1 packets will miss their priority indexes at server 2 no more than  </p><formula xml:id="formula_28">$  ¤¡ ¦ @ ! $  ¤ a</formula><formula xml:id="formula_29">¡ $ § f i h U p ¡ ¨ $ ¡ $ ( ' $  ¤e S 8 $  ¤e ( ' $  ¤ a S 8 $  ¤ a $  ¤¡ @$  ¤ a D § £ ¢ G ¡ e § A G ¡ a § A G "</formula><p>Alternatively, for WFQ, according to results provided in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>, the end-to-end delay bound for flow 1 is given as: Hence the bandwidths (weight) reserved for flow 2 at server 1 and flow 3 at server 2 must be zero. Therefore, in this case, WFQ degenerates to the strict priority service discipline (flow 1 has the highest priority). According to the result provided in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, the minimum delay bounds guaranteed by the strict priority service discipline to flows 2 and 3 are ¢ £ ¡ .</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">¡ $ §  $  $ G G</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.">Simulation Experiments</head><p>Throughout this paper, we have focused on schedulability conditions for coordinated schedulers. Here, we use ns-2 simulations to illustrate potential performance improvements from coordination not only in the maximum end-to-end delay, but also in statistical delay properties.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Server 3 Server 4 Server 5 Server 6 Server 2 Server 1 Path for target traffic</head><p>Path for background traffic <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. Simulation Topology</p><p>We consider a simple tandem network topology as depicted in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. All link capacities are 10 Mb/sec, packet lengths are 100 bytes, and propagation delays are 0. There are several flows (varying from 25 to 60) entering the network from the first server and exiting from the last server. These flows have the longest path and are chosen to be the target class for analysis. In addition, each server also serves two classes of cross traffic consisting of 125 flows which traverse a single router and then exit the network, and 125 flows that traverse two routers and then exit. The cross traffic has the same characteristics as the target traffic.   <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>. Exponential On-Off Traffic We simulate both exponential and Pareto on-off flows with on-rate 64 Kb/sec, mean on time 312 msec and mean off time 325 msec and Pareta shape parameter 1.9. The increment of the priority index at each server is 1 msec for the target traffic, 3 msec for the cross traffic with a 2-hop path, and 6 msec for cross traffic with a 1-hop path. We compare the 99-percentile end-toend delay experienced by the target traffic for networks with CNS, EDF, and WFQ schedulers.</p><p>The simulation results are depicted in Figures 4 and 5. Each point in the figure represents the result of a 200 second ns-2 simulation run, with averages reported over multiple simulations. The figure shows the 99.9-percentile of the end-to-end delay distribution of the target traffic as a function of the number of flows passing each server.</p><p>We make two observations regarding the figures. First, coordination has reduced the 99-percentile end-to-end delay experienced by the target traffic: for example, in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>, when each server supports 295 exponential on-off traffic flows (45 target flows and 250 cross traffic flows), the end-to-end delay experienced by the target traffic is 40 msec for CNS, 66 msec for WFQ, and 51 msec for EDF. The reason for this is that in a CNS network, packets which suffer excessive queueing delays at upstream nodes have an opportunity to "catch up" at a downstream node, by having a higher (relative) priority index. In contrast, in EDF or WFQ networks, each router treats packets locally according to their arrival time, without regard to whether this arrival time is late or early.</p><p>Second, when traffic is more bursty, e.g., for Pareto on-off traffic, the advantage of CNS over WFQ or EDF is even more pronounced. For example, in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>, when each server supports 295 Pareto on-off traffic flows (45 target flows and 250 cross traffic flows), the end-to-end delay experienced by the target traffic is 52 msec for CNS, 111 msec for WFQ, and 109 msec for EDF. The reason for this is that the heavy-tailed burst durations of this traffic place a heavier burden on the scheduler during periods of overload. Through inter-server coordination, CNS can better distribute this overload among network nodes and reduce a flow's end-to-end delay. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, we derived an end-to-end schedulability criterion for a class of work conserving service disciplines termed coordinated schedulers. Exploiting the coordination property, we showed that the "essential traffic" for a flow incurs only minimal distortion at downstream nodes. Moreover, we showed that packets can be allowed to violate local priority indexes (such as local deadlines) and still satisfy an end-to-end requirement by "catching up" with higher priority downstream. We then devised a priority assignment scheme and showed that under the scheme, coordinated schedulers can outperform WFQ schedulers. Finally, we presented numerical and simulation results to quantify the performance gains of coordination.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Illustration of Coordination</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Two Server System</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 5. Pareto On-Off Traffic</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8" validated="false"><head>$ ) is given by §</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>). 

# 

To simplify notation, we assume that 

$ 

w 

&amp; % 
' 
) ( 
&amp; 0 
2 1 

= 0, if 

0 
4 3 
6 5 

; and 

$ 

w 

&amp; % 
' 
) ( 
&amp; 5 
) 1 
8 7 
@ 9 
B A 
D C 
4 E 
F 
H G 
I 
$ 

w 

&amp; % 
' 
P ( 
&amp; 0 
2 1 

. 

Lemma 2 If each flow-7 packet has not missed its priority indexes at server 
¥ 
¡ 
7 


Q 

£ 
¡ 

Y 
9 
£ 

by more than 

£ 
! ¤¡ 
@ 
 £ 
¥ ¤¦ 
# " 
% $ 
D 
, then an essential traffic envelope 

 § 

£ 
¥ ¤¦ 
¦ ¡ 

£ 
of flow 
7 
at its 

3 
6 5 
hop (server 

£ 
¥ ¤¦ 
¦ ¡ 

£ 
 § 

 § 

£ 
¥ ¤ 
u $ 
¡ 

Q 

£ ¢ 

£ 
¥ ¤¦ 
£ 

(11) 

where 

¢ 

£ 
¥ ¤¦ 
 § 
I 
P ' 
£ 
¥ ¤¦ 
Q 

£ 
¥ ¤¡ 
@ 
 £ 
¥ ¤¦ 
# " 
% $ 
D 
V 
% Q 
9 
5 

¦ 

5 

¥ ¤ 

e 
S 
 £ 
¥ ¤ 
5 
. 

Proof: See [16]. 

This lemma characterizes a key property of coordinated schedulers, namely that a flow's 
traffic characteristics are minimally distorted at downstream servers. Specifically, if 

¢ 

£ 
¥ ¤¦ 
is a 
constant for 

 § 
9 

B A 
4 
C 
) C 
) C 

B F 
£ 
, we can use the same essential traffic envelope 

 § 

£ 
¥ ¤ 
u $ 
¡ 

£ 
to evaluate 
the local queueing delay suffered by flow 
7 
</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18" validated="true"><head>Table 2 Parameters for Server 1.</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>¢ 

$ 
 ¤ 
u $ 

 § 

¢ 

$ 
 ¤e 
 § According to Corollary 2, to verify flow-1 packets will miss their priority indexes at server 1 
no more than 

$ 
 ¤¡ 
@$ 
 ¤e 
D 
 § 

¤ £ ¡ 

, we need to verify 

5 
£7 

¦ ¥ 

¡ 

£ 

5 
£ 
( 7 

¨  § 

¡ 

¡ 

£ 
Q 

£ 

£ 

¢ 

£ 
¥ ¤£ 

£ 

G 
Q 
5 
£7 

 § 

£ 

£ 

f 
i h 
U p 
£ 
( 7 

© 

 
B 


" ! £ 

Q 
G 

$ 
 ¤¡ 
¦ @ 
! $ 
 ¤e 
D 

G 
Q 
5 
£ 
( 7 

¨  § 

£ 

£ 


¢ 

$ 
 ¤e 

(20) 

and 

5 
£7 

¦ ¥ 

¡ 

£ 

5 
£ 
( 7 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic end-to-end delay bounds for earliest deadline first scheduling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE INFOCOM 2000</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM 2000<address><addrLine>Tel Aviv, Israel</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimizing end-to-end delay in high-speed networks with a simple coordinated schedule</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE INFOCOM &apos;99</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM &apos;99<address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of network calculus to guaranteed service networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Le</forename><surname>Boudec</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1087" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rainbow fair queueing: Fair bandwidth sharing without per-flow state</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Zegura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM<address><addrLine>Tel Aviv, Israel</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic priority protocols for packet voice</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Walrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Messerschmitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="632" to="643" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supporting real-time applications in an integrated services packet network: Architecture and mechanism</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM &apos;92</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM &apos;92<address><addrLine>Baltimore, Maryland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="26" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A calculus for network delay, parts I and II</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cruz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quality of service guarantees in virtual circuit switched networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cruz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1048" to="1056" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A case for relative differentiated services and the proportional differentiation model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dovrolis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ramanathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Network</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An upper bound on delay for the virtual clock service discipline</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Figueira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pasquale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="399" to="408" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient admission control for EDF schedulers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Firoiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kurose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Towsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE INFOCOM &apos;97</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM &apos;97<address><addrLine>Kobe, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-04" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="310" to="317" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Link-sharing and resource management models for packet network</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Floyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Jacobson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal multiplexing on a single link: Delay and buffer requirements</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Georgiadis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Guérin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Parekh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Information Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient network QoS provisioning based on per node traffic shaping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Georgiadis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Guérin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Peris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sivarajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="482" to="501" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coordinated network scheduling: A framework for end-to-end services</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Knightly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE ICNP &apos;00</title>
		<meeting>IEEE ICNP &apos;00<address><addrLine>Osaka, Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Schedulability criterion and performance analysis of coordinated schedulers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Knightly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.ece.rice.edu/networks/publications.html" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Technical Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exact admission control for networks with bounded delay services</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liebeherr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wrege</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ferrari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="885" to="901" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relative delay differentation and delay class adaptation in core-stateless networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nandagopal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Venkitaraman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sivakumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bharghavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM<address><addrLine>Tel Aviv, Israel</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A generalized processor sharing approach to flow control in integrated services networks: the single-node case</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Parekh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gallager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="344" to="357" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A generalized processor sharing approach to flow control in integrated services networks: the multiple node case</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Parekh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gallager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SCED: a generalized scheduling policy for guaranteeing quality-ofservice</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sariowan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cruz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Polyzos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="669" to="684" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Core-Stateless Fair Queueing: A scalable architecture to approximate fair bandwidth allocations in high speed networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stoica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM &apos;98</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM &apos;98<address><addrLine>Vancouver, British Columbia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Providing guaranteed services without per flow management</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stoica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM &apos;99</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM &apos;99<address><addrLine>Cambridge, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Any work-concerving policy stabilizes the ring with spatial re-use</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tassiulas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Georgiadis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rate-controlled service disciplines</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ferrari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of High Speed Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="412" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtual clock: A new traffic control algorithm for packet switching networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM &apos;90</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM &apos;90<address><addrLine>Philadelphia, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990-09" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="29" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtual time reference system: A unifying scheduling framework for scalable support of guaranteed services</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2684" to="2695" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Achieving end-to-end delay bounds by EDF scheduling without traffic shaping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Viniotis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE INFOCOM &apos;01</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM &apos;01<address><addrLine>Anchorage, Alaska</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
