<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:50+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Snowball: Extracting Relations from Large Plain-Text Collections</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Eugene</forename><surname>Agichtein</surname></persName>
							<email>eugene@cs.columbia.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1214 Amsterdam Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>10027-7003</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Luis</forename><surname>Gravano</surname></persName>
							<email>gravano@cs.columbia.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1214 Amsterdam Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>10027-7003</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Snowball: Extracting Relations from Large Plain-Text Collections</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Text documents often contain valuable structured data that is hidden in regular English sentences. This data is best exploited if available as a relational table that we could use for answering precise queries or for running data mining tasks. We explore a technique for extracting such tables from document collections that requires only a handful of training examples from users. These examples are used to generate extraction patterns, that in turn result in new tuples being extracted from the document collection. We build on this idea and present our Snowball system. Snowball introduces novel strategies for generating patterns and extracting tuples from plain-text documents. At each iteration of the extraction process, Snowball evaluates the quality of these patterns and tuples without human intervention, and keeps only the most reliable ones for the next iteration. In this paper we also develop a scalable evaluation methodology and metrics for our task, and present a thorough experimental evaluation of Snowball and comparable techniques over a collection of more than 300,000 newspaper documents.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Text documents often hide valuable structured data. For example, a collection of newspaper articles might contain information on the location of the headquarters of a number of organizations. If we need to find the location of the headquarters of, say, Microsoft, we could try and use traditional information-retrieval techniques for finding documents that contain the answer to our query <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. Alternatively, we could answer such a query more precisely if we somehow had available a table listing all the organization-location pairs that are mentioned in our document collection. A tuple &lt;o,񮽙&gt; in such table would indicate that the headquarters of organization o are in location 񮽙, and that this information was present in a document in our collection. Tuple &lt;Microsoft, Redmond&gt; in our table would then provide the answer to our query. The web contains millions of pages whose text hides data that would be best exploited in structured form. In this paper we develop the Snowball system for extracting structured data from plain-text documents with minimal human participation. Our techniques build on the idea of DIPRE introduced by Brin <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</p><p>DIPRE: Dual Iterative Pattern Expansion DIPRE was proposed as an approach for extracting a structured relation (or table) from a collection of HTML documents. The method works best in an environment like the World-Wide Web, where the table tuples to be extracted will tend to appear in uniform contexts repeatedly in the collection documents (i.e., in the available HTML pages). DIPRE exploits this redundancy and inherent structure in the collection to extract the target relation with minimal training from a user.</p><p>As in the rest of the paper, we focus the presentation on the organization-location scenario defined above. In this context DIPRE's goal is to extract a table with all the organizationlocation tuples that appear in a given document collection. Initially, we provide DIPRE with a handful of instances of valid organization-location pairs. For example, we may indicate that &lt;Microsoft, Redmond&gt; is a valid pair, meaning that Microsoft is an organization whose headquarters are located in Redmond. Similarly, we provide DIPRE with a few other examples, as <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> shows. In addition, the user provides a general regular expression that the entities must match. This is all the training that DIPRE requires from the user.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Organization</head><p>Location  After this initial training phase, DIPRE looks for instances of the example organizations and locations in the text documents. Then, DIPRE examines the text that surrounds the initial tuples. For example, DIPRE inspects the context surrounding Microsoft and Redmond in "computer servers at Microsoft's headquarters in Redmond" to construct a pattern "&lt;STRING1&gt;'s headquarters in &lt;STRING2&gt;." Other possible patterns are listed in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>.</p><p>A DIPRE pattern consists of a five tuple &lt;order, urlprefix, left, middle, right&gt; and is generated by grouping together occurrences of seed tuples that have equal strings separating the entities (middle) and then setting the left and right strings to the longest common substrings of the context on the left and on the right of the entities, respectively. The order reflects the order in which the entities appear, and urlprefix is set to the longest common substring of the source URL's where the seed tuples were discovered. After generating a number of patterns from the initial seed tuples, DIPRE scans the available documents in search of segments of text that match the patterns. As a result of this process, DIPRE generates new tuples and uses them as the new "seed." DIPRE starts the process all over again by searching for these new tuples in the documents to identify new promising patterns.</p><p>&lt;STRING1&gt;'s headquarters in &lt;STRING2&gt; &lt;STRING2&gt;-based &lt;STRING1&gt; &lt;STRING1&gt;, &lt;STRING2&gt; Related Work Brin's DIPRE method and our Snowball system that we introduce in this paper both address issues that have long been the subject of information extraction research. Our task, though, is different in that we do not attempt to extract all the relevant information from each document, which has been the goal of traditional information extraction systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. One of the major challenges in information extraction is the necessary amount of manual labor involved in training the system for each new task. This challenge has been addressed in different ways. One approach is to build a powerful and intuitive graphical user interface for training the system, so that domain experts can quickly adopt the system for each new task <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Nevertheless, these systems still require substantial expert manual labor to port the system to each new domain. In contrast, Snowball and DIPRE require only a handful of example tuples for each new scenario.</p><p>Another approach is to train the system over a large manually tagged corpus, where the system can apply machine learning techniques to generate extraction patterns <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. The difficulty with this approach is the need for a large tagged corpus, which again involves a significant amount of manual labor to create. To combat this problem, some methods have been proposed to use an untagged corpus for training.</p><p>[11] describes generating extraction patterns automatically by using a training corpus of documents that were manually marked as either relevant or irrelevant for the topic. This approach requires less manual labor than to tag the documents, but nevertheless the effort involved is substantial. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> describes machine learning techniques for creating a knowledge base from the web, consisting of classes of entities and relations, by exploiting the content of the documents, as well as the link structure of the web. This method requires training over a large set of web pages, with relevant document segments manually labeled, as well as a large training set of page-to-page relations.</p><p>Finally, a number of systems use unlabeled examples for training. This direction of research is closest to our work. Specifically, the approach we are following falls into the broad category of bootstrapping techniques. Bootstrapping has been an attractive alternative in automatic text processing. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref> demonstrates a bootstrapping technique for disambiguating senses of ambiguous nouns.</p><p>[5] uses bootstrapping to classify named entities in text exploiting two orthogonal features, i.e., the spelling of the entity itself (e.g., having a suffix "Corp."), and the context in which the entity occurs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> also presents a bootstrapping technique to extract patterns to recognize and classify named entities in text. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref> describes an extension of DIPRE to mining the Web for acronyms and their expansions.</p><p>[2] presents a methodology and theoretical framework for combining unlabeled examples with labeled examples to boost performance of a learning algorithm for classifying web pages. While the underlying principle of using the systems' output to generate the training input for the next iteration is the same for all of these approaches, the tasks are different enough to require specialized methodologies.</p><p>Our Contributions As we have discussed, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> describes a method for extracting relations from the web using bootstrapping. Our Snowball system, which we present in this paper, builds on this work. Our main contributions include:</p><p>• Techniques for generating patterns and extracting tuples: We develop a new strategy for defining and representing patterns that is at the same time flexible, so that we capture most of the tuples that are hidden in the text in our collection, and selective, so that we do not generate invalid tuples (Sections 2.1 and 2.2).</p><p>• Strategies for evaluating patterns and tuples: Since the amount of training that Snowball requires is minimal, it is crucial that the patterns and tuples that are generated during the extraction process be evaluated. This way, Snowball will be able to eliminate unreliable tuples and patterns from further consideration. We develop strategies for estimating the reliability of the extracted patterns and tuples (Section 2.3).</p><p>• Evaluation methodology and metrics: Evaluating systems like Snowball and DIPRE is challenging: these systems are designed to work over large document collections, so manually inspecting all documents to build the "perfect" table that should be extracted is just not feasible. We introduce a scalable evaluation methodology and associated metrics (Section 3), which we use in Sections 4 and 5 for largescale experiments over collections of training and test documents. These collections have a total of over 300,000 real documents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">THE SNOWBALL SYSTEM</head><p>In this section we present the Snowball system <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2</ref>), which develops key components of the basic DIPRE method. More specifically, Snowball presents a novel technique to generate patterns and extract tuples from text documents (Sections 2.1 and 2.2). Also, Snowball introduces a strategy for evaluating the quality of the patterns and the tuples that are generated in each iteration of the extraction process (Section 2.3). Only those tuples and patterns that are regarded as being "sufficiently reliable" will be kept by Snowball for the following iterations of the system (Section 2.3). These new strategies for generation and filtering of patterns and tuples improve the quality of the extracted tables significantly, as the experimental evaluation in Section 5 will show.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Generating Patterns</head><p>A crucial step in the table extraction process is the generation of patterns to find new tuples in the documents. Ideally, we would like patterns both to be selective, so that they do not generate incorrect tuples, and to have high coverage, so that they identify many new tuples. In this section, we introduce a novel way of generating such patterns from a set of seed tuples and a document collection.</p><p>Snowball is initially given a handful of example tuples. For every such organization-location tuple &lt; o, 񮽙 &gt;, Snowball finds segments of text in the document collection where o and 񮽙 occur close to each other, just as DIPRE does, and analyzes the text that "connects" o and 񮽙 to generate patterns. A key improvement of Snowball from the basic DIPRE method is that Snowball's patterns include named-entity tags. An example of such a pattern is &lt;LOCATION&gt;-based &lt;ORGA-NIZATION&gt;. This pattern will not match any pair of strings connected by "-based." Instead, &lt;LOCATION&gt; will only match a string identified by a tagger as an entity of type LO-CATION. Similarly, &lt;ORGANIZATION&gt; will only match a string identified by a tagger as an entity of type ORGANI-ZATION. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref> shows additional patterns that Snowball might generate, with named-entity tags.</p><p>&lt;ORGANIZATION&gt;'s headquarters in &lt;LOCATION&gt; &lt;LOCATION&gt;-based &lt;ORGANIZATION&gt; &lt;ORGANIZATION&gt;, &lt;LOCATION&gt; A key step in generating and later matching patterns like the one above is finding where &lt;ORGANIZATION&gt; and &lt;LO-CATION&gt; entities occur in the text. For this, Snowball uses a state-of-the-art named-entity tagger, The MITRE Corporation's Alembic Workbench <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. In addition to ORGANIZA-TION and LOCATION entities, Alembic can identify PER-SON entities, and can be trained to recognize other kinds of entities. (See Section 6 for further discussion.) Once the entities in the text documents are tagged, Snowball can ignore unwanted entities (e.g., PERSONs), focus on occurrences of LOCATION and ORGANIZATION entities, and analyze the context that surrounds each pair of such entities to check if they are connected by the right words and hence match our patterns.</p><p>Snowball represents the context around the ORGANIZATION and LOCATION entities in the patterns in a flexible way that produces patterns that are selective, yet have high coverage. As a result, minor variations such as an extra comma or a determiner will not stop us from matching contexts that are otherwise close to our patterns. More specifically, Snowball represents the left, middle, and right "contexts" associated with a pattern just like the vector-space model of information retrieval represents documents and queries <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. Thus, the left, middle, and right contexts are three vectors associating weights (i.e., numbers between 0 and 1) with terms (i.e., arbitrary strings of non-space characters). These weights indicate the importance of each term in the corresponding context.</p><p>Definition 1 A Snowball pattern is a 5-tuple &lt;left, tag1, middle, tag2, right&gt;, where tag1 and tag2 are named-entity tags, and left, middle, and right are vectors associating weights with terms.</p><p>An example of a Snowball pattern is a 5-tuple &lt;{&lt;the, 0.2&gt;}, LOCATION, {&lt;-, 0.5&gt;, &lt;based, 0.5&gt;}, ORGANIZATION, {}&gt;. This pattern will match strings like "the Irving-based Exxon Corporation," where the word "the" (left context) precedes a location (Irving), which is in turn followed by the strings "-" and "based" (middle context) and an organization. Slight variations of the given string will also match the pattern to a smaller extent. (We introduce a notion of "degree of match" later in this section.)</p><p>To match text portions with our 5-tuple representation of patterns, Snowball also associates an equivalent 5-tuple with each document portion that contains two named entities with the correct tag (i.e., LOCATION and ORGANIZATION in our scenario). After identifying two such entities in a string S, Snowball creates three weight vectors l S , r S , and m S from S by analyzing the left, right, and middle contexts around the named entities, respectively. Each vector has a non-zero weight for each term that appears in the respective context where the l S and r S are each limited to the w-term window to the left and to the right of the entity pair. The weight of a term in each vector is a function of the frequency of the term in the corresponding context. These vectors are scaled so their norm is one. Finally, they are multiplied by a scaling factor to indicate each vector's relative importance. From our experiments with English-language documents, we have found the middle context to be the most indicative of the relationship between the elements of the tuple. Hence we will typically assign the terms in the middle vector higher weights than the left and right vectors. After extracting the 5-tuple representation of string S, Snowball matches it against the 5-tuple pattern by taking the inner product of the corresponding left, middle, and right vectors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition 2</head><p>The degree of match Match(t P , t S ) between two 5-tuples t P =&lt; l P , t 1 , m P , t 2 , r P &gt; (with tags t 1 and t 2 ) and t S =&lt; l S , t 񮽙 1 , m S , t 񮽙 2 , r S &gt; (with tags t 񮽙 1 and t 񮽙 2 ) is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">M atch(tP , tS) = 񮽙 lP · lS + mP · mS + rP · rS if the tags match 0 otherwise</formula><p>In order to generate a pattern, Snowball groups occurrences of known tuples in documents, if the contexts surrounding the tuples are "similar enough." More precisely, Snowball generates a 5-tuple for each string where a seed tuple occurs, and then clusters these 5-tuples using a simple singlepass clustering algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, using the Match function defined above to compute the similarity between the vectors and some minimum similarity threshold τ sim . The left vectors in the 5-tuples of clusters are represented by a centroid ¯ l s . Similarly, we collapse the middle and right vectors into ¯ m s and ¯ r s , respectively. These three centroids, together with the original tags (which are the same for all the 5-tuples in the cluster), form a Snowball pattern &lt; ¯ l s , t 1 , ¯ m s , t 2 , ¯ r s &gt;.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Generating Tuples</head><p>After generating patterns (Section 2.1), Snowball scans the collection to discover new tuples. The basic algorithm is outlined in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>.</p><p>Snowball first identifies sentences that include an organization and a location, as determined by the named-entity tagger. For a given text segment, with an associated organization o and location 񮽙, Snowball generates the 5-tuple t =&lt; l c , t 1 , m c , t 2 , r c &gt;. A candidate tuple &lt; o, 񮽙 &gt; is generated if there is a pattern t p such that M atch(t, t p ) ≥ τ sim , where τ sim is the clustering similarity threshold of Section 2.1.</p><p>Each candidate tuple will then have a number of patterns that helped generate it, each with an associated degree of match. Snowball uses this information, together with information about the selectivity of the patterns, to decide what candidate tuples to actually add to the table that it is constructing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Evaluating Patterns and Tuples</head><p>Generating good patterns is challenging. For example, we may generate a pattern &lt;{}, ORGANIZATION, &lt;",", 1&gt;, LOsub GenerateTuples(Patterns) foreach text segment in corpus (1) {&lt; o, 񮽙 &gt;, &lt; ls, t1, ms, t2, rs &gt;} = = CreateOccurrence(text segment); TC = &lt; o, 񮽙 &gt;; SimBest = 0; foreach p in Patterns (2) sim = M atch(&lt; ls, t1, ms, t2, rs &gt;, p);</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">if (sim ≥ τsim) (3) UpdatePatternSelectivity(p, TC ); if(sim ≥ SimBest) SimBest = sim; PBest = p; if(SimBest ≥ τsim)</formula><p>CandidateTuples <ref type="bibr">[TC]</ref>.Patterns[PBest] = = SimBest; return CandidateTuples; CATION, {}&gt; from text occurrences like "Intel, Santa Clara, announced..." This pattern will be matched by any string that includes an organization followed by a comma, followed by a location. Estimating the confidence of the patterns, so that we do not trust patterns that tend to generate wrong tuples, is one of the problems that we address in this section. We can weigh the Snowball patterns based on their selectivity, and trust the tuples that they generate accordingly. Thus, a pattern that is not selective will have a low weight. The tuples generated by such a pattern will be discarded, unless they are supported by selective patterns.</p><p>The case for tuples is analogous. "Bad" seed tuples may generate extraneous patterns that in turn might result in even more wrong tuples in the next Snowball iteration. To prevent this, we only keep tuples with high confidence. The confidence of the tuple is a function of the selectivity and the number of the patterns that generated it. Intuitively, the confidence of a tuple will be high if it is generated by several highly selective patterns.</p><p>The pattern and tuple evaluation is the key part of our system, and is responsible for most of the improvement over the DIPRE scheme. As an initial filter, we eliminate all patterns supported by fewer than τ sup seed tuples. We then update the confidence of each pattern in Step (3) of the algorithm in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>, which checks each candidate tuple t = &lt;o, 񮽙&gt; generated by the pattern in question. If there is a high confidence tuple t' = &lt;o, 񮽙 񮽙 &gt; generated during an earlier iteration of the system for the same organization o as in t, then this function compares locations 񮽙 and 񮽙 񮽙 . If the two locations are the same, then the tuple t is considered a positive match for the pattern. Otherwise, the match is negative. Intuitively, the candidate tuple that a pattern generates for the "known" organizations should match the locations of these organizations. Otherwise, the confidence in this pattern will be low. Note that this confidence computation assumes that organization is a key for the relation that we are extracting (i.e., two different tuples in a valid instance of the relation cannot agree on the organization attribute). Estimating the confidence of the Snowball patterns for relations without such a single-attribute key is part of our future work (Section 6).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition 3 The confidence of a pattern P is:</head><p>Conf (P ) = P.positive (P.positive + P.negative) where P .positive is the number of positive matches for P and P .negative is the number of negative matches.</p><p>As an example, consider the pattern P = &lt;{}, ORGANIZA-TION, &lt;",", 1&gt;, LOCATION, {}&gt; referred to above. Assume that this pattern only matches the three lines of text below:</p><p>"Exxon, Irving, said" "Intel, Santa Clara, cut prices" "invest in Microsoft, New York-based analyst Jane Smith said"</p><p>The first two lines generate candidate tuples &lt;Exxon, Irving&gt; and &lt;Intel, Santa Clara &gt;, which we already knew from previous iterations of the system. The third line generates tuple &lt;Microsoft, New York&gt;. The location in this tuple conflicts with the location in tuple &lt;Microsoft, Redmond&gt;, hence this last line is considered a negative example. Then, pattern P has confidence Conf (P ) = 2 2+1 = 0.67. Our definition of confidence of a pattern above is only one among many possibilities. An alternative is to account for a pattern's coverage in addition to its selectivity. For this, we adopt a metric originally proposed by <ref type="bibr">Riloff [11]</ref> to evaluate extraction patterns generated by the Autoslog-TS information extraction system, and define Conf RlogF (P ) of pattern P as follows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition 4 The RlogF confidence of pattern P is:</head><p>Conf RlogF (P ) = Conf (P ) · log 2 (P.positive)</p><p>Pattern confidences are defined to have values between 0 and 1. Therefore, we normalize the Conf RlogF values by dividing them by the largest confidence value of any pattern.</p><p>Having scored the patterns, we are now able to evaluate the new candidate tuples. Recall that for each tuple we store the set of patterns that produced it, together with the measure of similarity between the context in which the tuple occurred, and the matching pattern. Consider a candidate tuple T and the set of patterns P = {P i } that were used to generate T . Let us assume for the moment that we know the probability P rob(P i ) with which each pattern P i generates valid tuples. If these probabilities are independent of each other, then the probability that T is valid, P rob(T ), can be calculated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">P rob(T ) = 1 − |P | 񮽙 i=0 (1 − P rob(P i ))</formula><p>Our confidence metric Conf (P i ) was designed to be a rough estimate of Prob(P i ), the probability of pattern P i generating a valid tuple. We also account for the cases where T has occurred in contexts that did not match our patterns perfectly. Intuitively, the lower the degree of match between a pattern and a context, the higher is the chance of producing an invalid tuple. For this, we scale each Conf (P i ) term by the degree of match of the corresponding pattern and context: Definition 5 The confidence of a candidate tuple T is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Conf (T ) = 1 − |P | 񮽙 i=0 (1 − (Conf (P i ) · M atch(C i , P i )))</formula><p>where P = {P i } is the set of patterns that generated T and C i is the context associated with an occurrence of T that matched P i with degree of match Match(C i , P i ).</p><p>Note that when we described the calculation of the pattern confidence, we ignored any confidence values from previous iterations of Snowball. To control the learning rate of the system, we set the new confidence of the pattern as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Conf (P ) = Conf new (P )·W updt +Conf old (P )·(1−W updt )</formula><p>If parameter W updt &lt; 0.5 then the system in effect trusts new examples less on each iteration, which will lead to more conservative patterns and have a damping effect. For our experiments we set W updt = 0.5. We also adjust the confidence of already-seen tuples in an analogous way.</p><p>After determining the confidence of the candidate tuples using the definition above, Snowball discards all tuples with low confidence. These tuples could add noise into the pattern generation process, which would in turn introduce more invalid tuples, degrading the performance of the system. The set of tuples to use as the seed in the next Snowball iteration is then Seed = {T |Conf (T ) &gt; τ t }, where τ t is some prespecified threshold.</p><p>For illustration purposes, <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 2</ref> lists three representative patterns that Snowball extracted from the document collection that we describe in Section 4.1.</p><p>Conf middle right 1 &lt;based, 0.53&gt; &lt;, , 0.01&gt; &lt;in, 0.53&gt; &lt;', 0.42&gt; &lt;s, 0.42&gt; 0.69 &lt; headquarters, 0.42&gt; &lt;in, 0.12&gt; 0.61 &lt;(, 0.93&gt; &lt;), 0.12&gt; </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">EVALUATION METHODOLOGY AND METRICS</head><p>The goal of Snowball is to extract as many valid tuples as possible from the text collection and to combine them into one table. As we have discussed, we do not attempt to capture every instance of such tuples. Instead, we exploit the fact that these tuples will tend to appear multiple times in the types of collections that we consider. As long as we capture one instance of such a tuple, we will consider our system to be successful for that tuple. This is different from the goal of traditional information extraction <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Traditional information extraction systems aim at extracting all the relevant information from each document as completely as possible, while our system extracts tuples from all of the documents in the collection and combines them into one table. To evaluate this task, we adapt the recall and precision metrics from information retrieval to quantify how accurate and comprehensive our combined table of tuples is. Our metric for evaluating the performance of an extraction system over a collection of documents D is based on determining Ideal, the set of all the tuples that appear in the collection D (Section 3.1).</p><p>After identifying Ideal, we compare it against the tuples produced by the system, Extracted, using the adapted precision and recall metrics (Section 3.2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Methodology for Creating the Ideal Set</head><p>For small text collections, we could inspect all documents manually and compile the Ideal table by hand. Unfortunately, this evaluation approach does not scale, and becomes infeasible for the kind of large collections over which Snowball is designed to operate. To address this problem, we start by considering a large, publicly available directory of 13,000 organizations provided on the "Hoover's Online" web site <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> . From this well structured directory, we generate a table of organization-location pairs. Unfortunately, we cannot use this table as is, since some of the organizations in it might not occur at all in our collection.</p><p>To determine the target set of tuples Ideal from the Hoover'scompiled table above, we need to keep only the tuples that have the organization mentioned together with their location in a document. To find all such instances, we identify all the variations of each organization name in the Hoover's table as they may appear in the collection, and then check if the headquarters of the test organization are mentioned nearby. We used Whirl <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, a research tool developed at AT&amp;T Research Laboratories for integrating similar textual information, to match each organization name, as it occurs in the collection, to the organization in the Hoover's table.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">The Ideal Metric</head><p>Now that we have created the Ideal table, we can use it to evaluate the quality of the Snowball output, the Extracted table. If the initial directory of organizations from Hoover's contained all possible organizations, then we could just measure what fraction of the tuples in Extracted are in Ideal (pre-1 http://www.hoovers.com cision) and what fraction of the tuples in Ideal are in Extracted (recall). Unfortunately, a large collection will contain many more tuples that are contained in any single manually compiled directory. (In our estimate, our training collection contains more then 80,000 valid organization-location tuples.) If we just calculated precision as above, all the valid tuples extracted by Snowball, which are not contained in our Ideal set, will unfairly lower the reported value of precision for the system.</p><p>To </p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Recall = 񮽙 |Join| i=0 [񮽙 i = 񮽙 񮽙 i ] |Ideal| · 100% (1)</formula><p>where [񮽙 i = 񮽙 񮽙 i ] is equal to 1 if the test value 񮽙 i matches the extracted value 񮽙 񮽙 i , and 0 otherwise. Thus, the sum in the numerator is the number of correct tuples of the Ideal set that we extracted, which we divide by the size of the Ideal table to obtain our recall. Similarly, we define Precision as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">P recision = 񮽙 |Join| i=0 [񮽙 i = 񮽙 񮽙 i ] |Join| · 100%<label>(2)</label></formula><p>An alternative to using our Ideal metric to estimate precision could be to sample the extracted table, and check each value in the sample tuples by hand. (Similarly, we could estimate the recall of the system by sampling documents in the collection, and checking how many of the tuples mentioned in those documents the system discovers.) By sampling the extracted table we can detect invalid tuples whose organization is not mentioned in the Hoover's directory that we used to determine Ideal, for example. Similarly, we can detect invalid tuples that result from named-entity tagging errors. Hence, we also report precision estimates using sampling in Section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Matching Location and Organization Names</head><p>A problem with calculating the Ideal metric above is introduced by the proliferation of variants of organization names.</p><p>We combine all variations into one, by using a self-join of the Extracted table with itself. We use Whirl to match the organization names to each other, to create the table Extracted'. We pick an arbitrary variation of the organization name, o s , as the "standard," and pick a location, 񮽙 max , from the set of matching organization-location tuples, with the highest confidence value. We then insert the tuple &lt; o s , 񮽙 max &gt; into the Extracted' table.</p><p>Similarly, we need to decide when the location extracted for an organization is correct. For example, our system might conclude that California is the location of the headquarters of Intel. This answer is correct, although not as specific as could be. Our scoring system will in fact consider a tuple &lt;Intel, California&gt; as correct. Specifically, we consider tuple &lt; o, 񮽙 &gt; to be valid if (a) organization o is based in the U.S. and 񮽙 is the city or state where o's headquarters are based; or (b) organization o is based outside of the U.S. and 񮽙 is the city or country where o's headquarters are based.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">EXPERIMENTAL SETTING</head><p>We describe the training and text collections that we used for experiments in Section 4.1. We also enumerate the different extraction methods that we compare experimentally (Section 4.2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Training and Test Collections</head><p>Our experiments use large collections of real newspapers from the North American News Text Corpus, available from LDC 2 . This corpus includes articles from the Los Angeles Times, The Wall Street Journal, and The New York Times for 1994 to 1997. We split the corpus into two collections: training and test. The training collection consists of 178,000 documents, all from 1996. The test collection is composed of 142,000 documents, from 1995 and 1997.</p><p>Both Snowball and DIPRE rely on tuples appearing multiple times in the document collection at hand. To analyze how "redundant" the training and test collections are, we report in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 3</ref> the number of tuples in the Ideal set for each frequency level. For example, 5455 organizations in the Ideal set are mentioned in the training collection, and 3787 of them are mentioned in the same line of text with their location at least once. So, if we wanted to evaluate how our system performs on extracting tuples that occur at least once in the training collection, the Ideal set that we will create for this evaluation will contain 3787 tuples. <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">0  5455  4642  1  3787  3411  2  2774  2184  5  1321  909  10</ref> 593 389 The first row of <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 3</ref>, corresponding to zero occurrences, deserves further explanation. If we wanted to evaluate the</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Organization-Location Pairs Occurrences: Training Collection Test Collection</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Evaluating Alternative Techniques</head><p>We compared Snowball with two other techniques, the Baseline method and our implementation of the DIPRE method. These two methods require minimal or no training input from the user, and hence are comparable with Snowball in this respect. In contrast, state-of-the-art information extraction systems require substantial manual labor to train the system, or to create a hand-tagged training corpus.</p><p>The first method, Baseline, is based purely on the frequency of co-occurrence of the organization and the location. Specifically, Baseline reports the location that co-occurs in the same line with each organization most often as the headquarters for this organization.</p><p>The second method is DIPRE. We did not have access to its original implementation, so we had to re-implement it and adapt it to our collections. The original DIPRE implementation uses urlprefix to restrict pattern generation and application. Since all of our documents came from just three sources, DIPRE was not able to exploit this feature. The second, more important modification had to do with the fact that DIPRE was designed to extract tuples from HTML-marked data. Without HTML tags, DIPRE could not find occurrences of the seed tuples in plain text that were surrounded by exactly the same non-empty contexts. To solve this problem, we used the named-entity tagger to pre-tag the input to DIPRE. This way, all the organizations and locations were consistently surrounded by named-entity tags. DIPRE could then generate patterns that take advantage of these tags. The results we report are not for the original DIPRE implementation, but rather for our adaptation for tagged documents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Snowball</head><p>We explored the best parameter values for Snowball by running the system on the training corpus. Parameters we experimented with include:</p><p>• Use of Punctuation: We experimented with discarding punctuation and other non-alphanumeric characters from the contexts surrounding the entities. Our hypothesis was that punctuation may just add noise and carry little content to help extract tuples. We report results for Snowball and SnowballPlain, where Snowball uses punctuation, and Snowball-Plain discards it.</p><p>• Choice of Pattern Scoring Strategies: We tried variations on the basic framework for weighing patterns, as described in Section 2, with or without using the RlogF metric of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.  Snowball on the test collection.</p><p>• Choice of Pattern Similarity Threshold (τ sim ): This parameter controls how flexible the patterns are, both during the pattern generation stage (i.e., how similar the occurrences of the example tuples have to be in order to be grouped into one cluster), as well as during the tuple extraction stage, where τ sim controls the minimum similarity between the context surrounding the potential tuple and a pattern, determining whether a tuple will be generated.</p><p>• Choice of Tuple Confidence Threshold (τ t ): This threshold determines the minimum confidence a tuple must have to be included in the seed set to start the next iteration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS</head><p>In this section, we experimentally compare the performance of Snowball and the alternative techniques that we discussed in Section 4.2. Our experiments use the training and test collections of Section 4.1. We ran experiments on the training collection to determine the optimal pattern scoring strategy, optimal values for τ sim , τ t , τ sup , and the optimal weight distribution W left , W middle , and W right for the left, middle, and right context vectors of each pattern.</p><p>As we discussed, the only input to the Snowball system during the evaluation on the test collection were the five seed tuples of <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. All the extraction patterns were learned from scratch by running the Snowball system using the operational parameters listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table 4</ref>, which worked best on the training collection. The normalized RlogF metric was used to score patterns for generating the set of seed tuples for the next iteration. The results are reported in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>. The plot shows the performance of the systems as we attempt to extract test tuples that are mentioned more times in the corpus. As we can see, Snowball performs increasingly well as the number of times that the test tuples are required to be mentioned in the collection is increased. While DIPRE has better precision than Snowball at the 0-occurrence level (72% vs. 67% for Snowball), Snowball has at all occurrence levels significantly higher recall than DIPRE and Baseline do. We also observe that punctuation matters. The recall of Snowball-Plain is significantly lower than that of Snowball. <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref> shows that Snowball's results are stable over subsequent iterations of the algorithm. In contrast, DIPRE quickly diverges, since it has no way to prevent unreliable tuples from being seed for its next iteration. We report data for only two iterations for Snowball-Plain because it converged after the second iteration (i.e., it did not produce any new seed tuples).</p><p>As discussed in Section 3.2, we complete our evaluation of the precision of the extraction systems by manually examining a sample of their output. For this, we randomly selected 100 tuples from each of the extracted tables, and checked whether each of these tuples was a valid organization-location pair or not. We separate the errors into three categories: errors due to mistagging a location and assigning it to a valid organization ("Location" error), errors due to including a nonexisting organization ("Organization" error), and errors due to deducing an incorrect relationship between a valid organization and location ("Relationship" error). These different types of errors are significant because they highlight different "culprits": the "Location" and "Organization" errors could be prevented if we had a perfect named-entity tagger, whereas the "Relationship" errors are wholly the extraction system's fault ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">Table 5</ref>).</p><p>The last column in <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">Table 5</ref> (P Ideal ) is precision, calculated by ignoring the "Organization" errors and computing the fraction of valid organizations for which a correct location was found. These values correspond to the values of precision we would have calculated if our Ideal table included all the valid organizations in the random samples. These figures, however, do not capture invalid tuples generated due to improper tagging of a string as an organization. From our manual inspection of a random sample of 100 tuples from each extracted table, we observed that DIPRE's sample contained 74 correct tuples and 26 incorrect ones. Snowball's sample contained 52 correct tuples and 48 incorrect tuples, while Baseline has a majority of incorrect tuples (25 vs. 75). As we can see from the breakup of the errors in the table, virtually all of Snowball's errors are tagging related (i.e., "Location" or "Organization" errors). If we prune the Snowball's final output to only include those tuples t with Conf (t) ≥ 0.8 = τ t , then most of these spurious tuples disappear. In effect, from a random sample of 100 tuples from this pruned table, 93 tuples are valid and only 7 are invalid. Furthermore, none of the invalid tuples are due to "Relationship" errors (third row of <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">Table 5</ref>).</p><p>So far, the results that we have reported for Snowball are based on a table that contains all the "candidate" tuples generated during Snowball's last iteration. As we saw in <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">Table 5</ref>, the precision of Snowball's answer varies dramatically if we prune this table using the tuple confidence threshold τ t . Of course, this last-step pruning is likely to result in lower recall values. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 7</ref> we explore the tradeoff between precision and recall for different values of this last-step pruning threshold. A user who is interested in high-precision tables might want to use high values for this threshold, while a user who is interested in high-recall tables might want to use lower values of the threshold. For example, by setting τ t = 0.4 and filtering the Extracted table accordingly, we estimate the absolute precision of Snowball's output to be 76% and recall   (a) (b) to be 45%, both of which are higher than the corresponding metrics of DIPRE's output.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Type of Error</head><p>In summary, both Snowball and DIPRE show significantly higher precision than Baseline. In effect, Baseline tends to generate many tuples, which results in high recall at the expense of low precision. Snowball's recall is at least as high as that of Baseline for most of the tests, with higher precision values. Snowball's recall is generally higher than DIPRE's, while the precision of both techniques is comparable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">CONCLUSIONS AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>This paper presents Snowball, a system for extracting relations from large collections of plain-text documents that requires minimal training for each new scenario. We introduced novel strategies for generating extraction patterns for Snowball, as well as techniques for evaluating the quality of the patterns and tuples generated at each step of the extraction process. Our large-scale experimental evaluation of our system shows that the new techniques produce high-quality tables, according to the scalable evaluation methodology that we introduce in this paper. Our experiments involved over 300,000 newspaper articles.</p><p>We only evaluated our techniques on plain text documents, and it would require future work to adopt our methodology to HTML data. While HTML tags can be naturally incorporated into Snowball's pattern representation, it is problematic to extract named-entity tags from arbitrary HTML documents. State-of-the-art taggers rely on clues from the text surrounding each entity, which may be absent in HTML documents that often rely on visual formatting to convey information. On a related note, we have assumed throughout that the attributes of the relation we extract (i.e., organization and location) correspond to named entities that our tagger can identify accurately. As we mentioned, named-entity taggers like Alembic can be extended to recognize entities that are distinct in a context-independent way (e.g., numbers, dates, proper names). For some other attributes, we will need to extend Snowball so that its pattern generation and matching could be anchored around, say, a noun phrase as opposed to a named entity as in this paper. In the future, we will also generalize Snowball to relations of more than two attributes. Finally, a crucial open problem is how to generalize our tuple and pattern evaluation strategy of Section 2.3 so that it does not rely on an attribute being a key for the relation.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Initial DIPRE patterns. &lt;STRING1&gt; and &lt;STRING2&gt; are regular expressions that would match an organization and a location, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: The main components of Snowball.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 : Patterns that exploit named-entity tags.</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Patterns that exploit named-entity tags.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 : Algorithm for extracting new tuples using a set of patterns.</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Algorithm for extracting new tuples using a set of patterns.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :Figure 6 : Recall (a) and precision (b</head><label>56</label><figDesc>Recall (a) and precision (b) of Baseline, DIPRE, Snowball and Snowball-Plain (test collection).) of Baseline, DIPRE, Snowball, and Snowball-Plain as a function of the number of iterations (Ideal tuples with occurrence ≥ 2; test collection).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Recall (a) and sample-based precision (b) as a function of the threshold τ t used for the last-step pruning of the Snowball tables (Ideal tuples with occurrence ≥ 1; test collection).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>User-provided example tuples for DIPRE. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>Table 2 : Actual patterns discovered by Snowball. (For each pattern the left vector is empty, tag1 = ORGANIZATION, and tag2 = LOCATION.)</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><head>address this problem we create a new table, Join, as the join of tables Ideal and Extracted ontable. Given the table Ideal and the Join table that we have just created, we can define recall and precision more formally. We define Recall as:</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>a unique key (i.e., orga-
nization). For each tuple T =&lt; o, 񮽙 &gt; in the Ideal table, we 
find a matching tuple T 񮽙 =&lt; o 񮽙 , 񮽙 񮽙 &gt; in the Extracted table 
(if any), such that o 񮽙 o 񮽙 . (We describe how to deal with vari-
ations in the organization names in Section 3.3.) Using these 
values, we now create a new tuple &lt; o, 񮽙, 񮽙 񮽙 &gt; and include it 
in the Join </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Occurrence statistics of the test tuples in 
the experiment collections. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7" validated="false"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Parameter values used for evaluating 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8" validated="false"><head>Correct Incorrect Location Organization Relationship P</head><label>Correct</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Ideal 
DIPRE 
74 
26 
3 
18 
5 
90% 
Snowball (all tuples) 
52 
48 
6 
41 
1 
88% 
Snowball (τ t = 0.8) 
93 
7 
3 
4 
0 
96% 
Baseline 
25 
75 
8 
62 
5 
66% 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9" validated="false"><head>Table 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Manually computed precision estimate, derived from a random sample of 100 tuples from each extracted 
table. 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> http://www.ldc.upenn.edu performance of our system on all the organizations that were mentioned in the corpus, even if the appropriate location never occurred near its organization name anywhere in the collection, we would include all these organizations in our Ideal set. So, if the system attempts to &quot;guess&quot; the value of the location for such an organization, any value that the system extracts will automatically be considered wrong in our evaluation.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under Grant No. IIS-9733880. We also thank Regina Barzilay, Ralph Grishman, and Vasilis Hatzivassiloglou for their helpful comments, and Eleazar Eskin for many fruitful discussions.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
				<title level="m">Proceedings of the Sixth Message Understanding Conference</title>
		<meeting>the Sixth Message Understanding Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufman</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combining labeled and unlabeled data with co-training</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Avrim</forename><surname>Blum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tom</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1998 Conference on Computational Learning Theory</title>
		<meeting>the 1998 Conference on Computational Learning Theory</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracting patterns and relations from the WorldWide Web</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sergey</forename><surname>Brin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1998 International Workshop on the Web and Databases (WebDB&apos;98)</title>
		<meeting>the 1998 International Workshop on the Web and Databases (WebDB&apos;98)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integration of heterogeneous databases without common domains using queries based on textual similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">William</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1998 ACM International Conference on Management of Data (SIGMOD&apos;98)</title>
		<meeting>the 1998 ACM International Conference on Management of Data (SIGMOD&apos;98)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unsupervised models for named entity classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yoram</forename><surname>Singer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Joint SIG-DAT Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Very Large Corpora</title>
		<meeting>the Joint SIG-DAT Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Very Large Corpora</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Learning to construct knowledge bases from the World Wide Web. Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Craven</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dipasquo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Freitag</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mccallum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nigam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Slattery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mixedinitiative development of language processing systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Day</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Aberdeen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lynette</forename><surname>Hirschman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robyn</forename><surname>Kozierok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Patricia</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marc</forename><surname>Vilain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Fifth ACL Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing</title>
		<meeting>the Fifth ACL Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Description of the UMass systems as used for MUC-6</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Soderland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mccarthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Lehnert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 6th Message Understanding Conference</title>
		<meeting>the 6th Message Understanding Conference<address><addrLine>Columbia, MD</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information Retrieval: Data Structures and Algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>William</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<publisher>PrenticeHall</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Frakes and Ricardo Baeza-Yates</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information extraction: Techniques and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ralph</forename><surname>Grishman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Information Extraction (International Summer School SCIE-97)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatically generating extraction patterns from untagged text</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ellen</forename><surname>Riloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Thirteenth National Conference on Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the Thirteenth National Conference on Artificial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1044" to="1049" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning dictionaries for information extraction by multi-level bootstrapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ellen</forename><surname>Riloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rosie</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Sixteenth National Conference on Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the Sixteenth National Conference on Artificial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Automatic Text Processing: The transformation, analysis, and retrieval of information by computer</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gerard</forename><surname>Salton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NYU: Description of the Proteus/PET system as used for MUC-7</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Roman</forename><surname>Yangarber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ralph</forename><surname>Grishman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Seventh Message Understanding Conference</title>
		<meeting>the Seventh Message Understanding Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Morgan</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unsupervised word sense disambiguation rivaling supervised methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yarowsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 33rd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</title>
		<meeting>the 33rd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics<address><addrLine>Cambridge, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="196" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mining the web for acronyms using the duality of patterns and relations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jeonghee</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Neel</forename><surname>Sundaresan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1999 Workshop on Web Information and Data Management</title>
		<meeting>the 1999 Workshop on Web Information and Data Management</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
