<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:51+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Framework for Cost-Effective Peer-to-Peer Content Distribution</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hefeeda</surname></persName>
							<email>mhefeeda@cs.purdue.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Purdue University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>47907</postCode>
									<settlement>West Lafayette</settlement>
									<region>IN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Framework for Cost-Effective Peer-to-Peer Content Distribution</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">RESEARCH DIRECTIONS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">PROMISE: Pure P2P Architecture</head><p>This section presents our solution to the problem of media streaming in a cooperative peer-to-peer environment. The solution is purely distributed. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, we proposed PROMISE: A PeeR-tO-peer MedIa StrEaming system. PROMISE architecture consists of a set of peers (end-system machines) interconnected through a P2P substrate such as Pastry, Chord, or CAN. The P2P substrate maintains connectivity among live peers, manages peers joining and leaving, and performs object lookup function. PROMISE assumes that peers exhibit quite heterogeneous characteristics and they do not offer server-like functionalities: they fail more often, offer limited capacity, and may reduce their sending rates unexpectedly. Therefore, several supplying peers may be needed to serve a requesting peer. The design of PROMISE relies on a new application level service called CollectCast. CollectCast carefully chooses the supplying peers and orchestrates them in order to yield the best quality for the receiver. Specifically, The major functions of CollectCast are: (1) it infers and leverages the underlying network topology and performance information for the selection of senders. This is based on a novel application of several network tomography techniques; (2) it selects the "best" supplying peers that will likely yield the best quality for the streaming session; (3) it adaptively assigns rate and data to suppliers based on the capacity of each supplier and the current network conditions; and (4) it monitors the status of peers and connections and transparently switches suppliers so that the full quality is maintained throughout the session.</p><p>We evaluate PROMISE through simulation and Internet experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. We show that streaming from multiple failure-prone peers in a dynamic network environment is indeed feasible. Specifically, we show that the full quality can be maintained in presence of failures and packet losses. Our simulation demonstrates that a significant gain in quality (quantified by aggregate received rate and its stability) can be achieved using our tomography-based peer selection technique. Finally, PROMISE does not burden the participating peers: we show that, on the average, a sending peer contributes less than a quarter of the required streaming rate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Hybrid Architecture</head><p>The hybrid architecture can be used as infrastructure for ondemand media streaming in environments such as distance learning (e.g., distributing lectures to students at several campuses) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>. The key ideas in this work are: (1) Network-aware peers organization, in which a two-level clustering technique is used. In the first level, nearby peers are grouped into a network-cluster. Then, in the second level, network clusters within an autonomous system (AS) are assigned to the same AS-cluster. This peers organization is validated by statistics collected and analyzed from real Internet data. (2) Leveraging peers clustering to implement network-aware searching (to locate nearby suppliers) and dispersion algorithms. The dispersion algorithms efficiently disseminate the files into the system with the objective of keeping sufficient copies of the media files as close as possible to the clients (within the cluster). Networkaware searching and dispersion yield two desirable effects: (i) reduction of the load on the underlying network, since the traffic traverses fewer number of hops, and (ii) better streaming service because the delay is shorter and less variable. (3) Making good use of peers heterogeneity: more powerful peers (super peers) do more work, they help in the searching and dispersion functions. This is why we call this architecture as a hybrid architecture.</p><p>We demonstrate the potential of the proposed architecture for a large-scale on-demand media streaming service through an extensive simulation study on large, Internet-like, topologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Starting with a limited streaming capacity (hence, low cost), the simulation shows that the capacity is rapidly increased and many clients can be served even if they come according to different arrival patterns such as constant rate arrivals, flash crowd arrivals, and Poisson arrivals. Furthermore, the simulation shows that a reasonable client-side initial buffering of 10-20 seconds is sufficient to ensure the full-quality of playback in presence of supplying peers failure and degradation.</p><p>An approximate cost-profit analysis to show the economic potential of a large-scale media streaming service built on top of a P2P infrastructure is given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Incentive-Compatible Provisioning</head><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, we identify the key economic-related research problems that need to be addressed to realize the great potential of collaborative P2P systems. One of the key problems is the P2P network provisioning. In the P2P context, we define network provisioning as the process of creating and distributing information resources among supplier peers in preparation for client requests. This definition bears some similarities with the replication problem addressed by Choen and Shenker <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. The authors propose optimal replication strategies that minimizes the expected search size in an unstructured P2P environment. They prove that replicating objects in proportion to the square-root of their query rates yields the minimum expected search size for locatable items. However, the replication strategies assume "full cooperation" from peers, in the sense that a peer voluntarily commits some of its capacity to the system and follows the prescribed protocol for replicating objects. However, nodes in P2P systems are found to be economically rational or utility-maximizing. Unless properly incentivized, nodes may deviate from the protocol or not participate at all. In the replication problem, if peers are not paid for sharing data, they may not have an incentive to cache data for subsequent sharing. If they do get paid, their decision to cache may depend on more subtle factors such as their "forecast of demand" for the cached materials. In a multi-product environment, a peer may prefer to only cache what it perceives to be the most popular and therefore the most lucrative content, even though this may not be in line with the overall system objective. Peers rationality makes the provisioning problem more challenging. To address this challenge, we are working on the following research tasks: (1) Developing models to understand peers behavior and more specifically their valuation of their own capacity, (2) Studying how the system performance depends not only on the aggregate capacity but also on the heterogenous contributions from individual peers, (3) Analyze the interaction between the provisioning algorithms and the searching algorithms, and (4) Design an incentive mechanism to integrate the above issues into a provisioning algorithm that optimizes a system-wide objective function. Our solution will be based on ideas from microeconomic theory, especially on the theory of mechanism design and its applications in computer science problems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Trustworthy P2P Systems</head><p>Security plays a critical role on the growth of a collaborative P2P system. More users become an integral part of the system when they are certain that the shared data is not corrupted and they can trust other peers for possible content sharing and exchange. Trust is of particular importance in P2P environments full of unknown entities while lack of predefined trusted relationship (e.g., trusted third parties). It is important for the supplier and the customer to establish a certain level of trust between them before the transaction is conducted. We aim to dynamically assess the trustworthiness of peers and incorporate that into the searching and dispersion algorithms. Three main research tasks are proposed: (1) Evidence identification. What may serve as an evidence in P2P systems? As an example, the fraction of time a peer actually fulfilled its commitment for serving a file or paying the price for consuming a file can be considered as an evidence, (2) Evidence collection. After identifying an evidence, how can we collect sufficient instances of this evidence to: (3) Build trust models. How to use evidences from multiple peers to construct the web of trust among them. And finally, how to integrate the web of trust with the searching and dispersion algorithms.</p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Replication strategies in unstructured peer-to-peer networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Choen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ACM SIGCOMM&apos;02</title>
		<meeting>of ACM SIGCOMM&apos;02<address><addrLine>Pittsburgh, PA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Economics of a collaborative peer-to-peer infrastructure for content distribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hefeeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Afeche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bhargava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>CS-TR 03-015</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-04" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Purdue University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A hybrid architecture for cost-effective on-demand media streaming. Revised for Journal of Computer Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hefeeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bhargava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cost-profit analysis of a peer-to-peer media streaming architecture</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hefeeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Habib</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bhargava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>TR 2002-37</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">CERIAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-06" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Purdue University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PROMISE: peer-to-peer media streaming using CollectCast</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hefeeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Habib</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Boyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bhargava</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Multimedia 2003 Conference</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>To appear</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On peer-to-peer media streaming</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hefeeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hambrusch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bhargava</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE ICDCS&apos;02</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE ICDCS&apos;02<address><addrLine>Vienna, Austria</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
