<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:56+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">MovStream: An Efficient Algorithm for Monitoring Clusters Evolving in Data Streams </title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Liang</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
							<email>tangliang@cs.scu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sichuan University Chengdu</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>610065</postCode>
									<country key="CN">P.R.China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chang-Jie</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
							<email>tangchangjie@cs.scu.edu.cn</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lei</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sichuan University Chengdu</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>610065</postCode>
									<country key="CN">P.R.China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chuan</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sichuan University Chengdu</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>610065</postCode>
									<country key="CN">P.R.China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ye-Xi</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sichuan University Chengdu</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>610065</postCode>
									<country key="CN">P.R.China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chun-Qiu</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sichuan University Chengdu</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>610065</postCode>
									<country key="CN">P.R.China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jun</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sichuan University Chengdu</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>610065</postCode>
									<country key="CN">P.R.China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Birth Defects Supervising Centre of Western China Medical School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sichuan University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>610065</postCode>
									<settlement>Chengdu</settlement>
									<region>P.R.China</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">MovStream: An Efficient Algorithm for Monitoring Clusters Evolving in Data Streams </title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Monitoring cluster evolution in data streams is a major research topic in data streams mining. Previous clustering methods for evolving data streams focus on global clustering result. It may lose critical information about individual cluster. This paper introduces some basic movements of evolution of an individual cluster. Based on the measurement of the movements, a novel algorithm called MovStream is proposed to monitor clusters&apos; evolving in data streams. The experimental results on real datasets show that our MovStream algorithm surpasses the well-known CluStream algorithm by 25-50% in accuracy and one order of magnitude in efficiency.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The evolution of data clusters in data streams can be used to analyze the trends of the continuous data streams. Recently, several data clustering algorithms for data streams have been introduced <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Most of them focus on finding the centers of clusters and building clusters. However, in many applications, the information about fashions of movements and changes on clusters is also very useful. It provides a better understanding on how and why data streams change. CluStream is a well-known clustering algorithm that can handle this information in evolving data streams <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. It proposes a new concept of pyramidal time frames and stores the properties of micro-clusters at particular time as snapshots. According to subtractive properties of the microcluster, it is convenient to get the clustering result in a past time-horizon. In the applications of detecting and monitoring data streams, the information about appearance and disappearance of clusters may not be enough. Discovering how a new cluster comes from and how an old cluster changes are interesting.</p><p>This paper proposes a new method named MovStream to monitor the data clusters in evolving data streams over the sliding windows. Previous clustering methods often use the global clustering strategy to monitor the synopsis of evolving data stream. However, each cluster has its own evolving behavior, and the behavior contains practical meanings in certain situation. The global uniform method may lose some critical information. Our method provides evolving information of each individual cluster in data streams. The evolving behavior of each cluster is treated as a movement of the cluster. Further, we introduce several measurements for basic movements. These measurements defined based on the properties of data cluster were introduced in previous literatures <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref> . We refer significant movements to movement events. There are corresponding operations to refine the clustering result when a movement event is detected. These operations include move, split, merge, stretch and delete. As the split and merge operations in B + Tree keep the balance of the indexing tree, these operations keep the accuracy of clustering result in evolving data streams.</p><p>In <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>, the position of the cluster center changes. This kind of movement is defined as drift. Suppose the data points of data streams follow a Gaussian distribution, when the mean parameter of the Gaussian model is changed, there should be a drift of movement to the cluster of these data points in data streams. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 2</ref>, two clusters are the same cluster with two time stamps. They have the same centroid, but their radiuses are different. The radius is defined as the average distance from data points to the centroid that will be introduced later. The movement comes from different radius of the cluster will be defined as expand or shrink. For example, if the cluster follows a Gaussian distribution, expand or shrink can be seen as an alteration of the variance parameter. There is also a straightforward way to increase or decrease the radius of the cluster.</p><p>Motivated by these observations, we propose a heuristic strategy to detect and monitor the actions of the clusters in evolving data streams including the movements introduced in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 2</ref>  The main contributions of this paper are summarized as follows. First, we propose the movement event with the measurement to the cluster. It provides valuable information about evolving behavior of each cluster in evolving data streams. Second, we design a novel data stream clustering method MovStream. It consists of the movement event detecting algorithm and the clustering refinement operations. The time and space complexities of movement event detecting algorithm are constant. Since the clustering refinement operations are invoked only when a movement event is triggered, the cost of these operations will be small in the situation of stable data streams.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Related Work</head><p>Data streams clustering methods require the scalability and efficiency in the data processing. Most single pass clustering approaches are under the assumption that the data points arrived in several chunks <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. Guha et al. proposed a k-means based algorithm for clustering data streams <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>. The algorithm only makes a single pass over the data stream and uses small space. It requires O(kN) time and O(N ε ) space, where k is the number of centers, N is the length of data stream, and ε &lt; 1. O'Chalaghan et al proposed the STREAM algorithm to cluster data streams <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. The algorithm is similar to Guha's. <ref type="bibr">Nasraoui et al.</ref> proposed an artificial immune system (AIS) based clustering approach TECNO-STREAMS <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</p><p>Aggarwal et al. proposed CluStream algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. It adopts micro-clusters introduced in BIRCH algorithm and uses micro-clusters to absorb arrived data points in online step. The offline step is to use kmeans <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> to cluster the micro-clusters into macroclusters. The properties of micro-clusters are subtractive, so that according to two snapshots of micro-clusters, people can get clustering result on every past time-horizon. However, when the purpose of the algorithm is monitoring clusters in data streams, previous work has two weaknesses. First, the evolving of micro-clusters cannot represent the evolving of individual natural clusters. Second, the natural clusters cannot be clustered from micro-clusters in a straightforward way. For monitoring clusters, the macro-clustering is not executed in offline step. It should be executed to monitor natural clusters every period time. So it is not efficient in this situation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Preliminaries</head><p>Previous literatures gave some preliminary concepts and terminologies of the data cluster <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. Suppose |X i -X j | stands for the distance between two given data points X i and X j . Given a cluster C of data points {X i }, where i = 1, 2…, N, the centroid X 0 , the radius R and the diameter D of the cluster are defined as follows.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">X 0 = 1 ( ) / N i i XN   (1) R = 1 2 2 1 1 ( | 0 | ) N i i XX N    (2) D = 1 2 2 11 1 ( | | ) ( 1) NN ij ij XX NN     . (3)</formula><p>where, R is the average distance from data points to the centroid. D is the average pairwise distance within a cluster. They are two alternative measures of the tightness of the cluster around the centroid. In this paper, we use these properties to monitor the changes in data streams. Given two clusters C i and C j , let X0 i and X0 j be the centroids of C i and C j . Then the mean distance of C i and C j is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">d mean (C i , C j ) = | X0 i -X0 j |.<label>(4)</label></formula><p>In our model, each cluster has a sliding window to maintain recent data points. The sliding window is implemented by a dynamic-length queue. The element of the queue contains the data point and it's time stamp.</p><p>The sum of the lengths of queues of all clusters is fixed by a constant parameter horizon time given by the user. It was introduced in previous literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. When a new arrived data point is inserted to a cluster, the oldest data point in the horizon time in one of the clusters should be popped out.</p><p>Each data point has a time stamp. There is a constraint for the sliding window. Suppose X n is the nth element in the sliding window. Two data points X i and X j with time stamp T i and T j are in one sliding window, if i &lt; j, there must be T i &lt; T j .</p><p>Notation. Given a sliding window SW of a cluster C and a time stamp t, S(SW) t denotes the set of data points X 1 … X n in SW at time stamp t, C(SW) t denotes the cluster of S(SW) t . |SW| denotes the number of data points in SW and the length of SW. LS(SW) denotes the linear sum of data points in SW, and SS(SW) denotes the square sum of data points in SW. i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">LS(SW) = 1 n i i X   , SS(SW) = 2 1 n i i X   .</formula><p>Lemma 1. Given a sliding window SW of a cluster C with time stamp t, let X 1 , X 2 …, X N be data points of SW where N = |SW| &gt; 1. The centroid, radius of cluster C can be calculated as follow:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">X0 = ( ) / LS SW N (5) R = 2 1 || ( ) / ( ( ) / ) || SS SW N LS SW N <label>(6)</label></formula><p>Due to space limitation, we omit proof here. The detail can be found in <ref type="bibr">[13]</ref>. Lemma 1 gives the method to calculate the centroid and radius according to LS and SS. When a new data point arrives at a cluster, LS(SW) and SS(SW) of the sliding window can be updated in a straightforward way, whose time complexity is O(d). So the cost of calculating the new centroid and radius of the cluster are also O(d), where d is the number of dimensions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Monitoring Clusters Evolving</head><p>As new data comes continuously, the data points in the sliding window and the cluster are always altered. Based on the properties of cluster introduced before, we define measurements for movements as follows: Definition 1 (Cluster Movement) Given a sliding window SW of a cluster C and two time stamp t and t' ,t &lt; t', if () t S SW , ' () t S SW , let R t and R t' be the radiuses of C(SW) t and C(SW) t' (R t' &gt; R t ). drift, expand, shrink from t to t' are defined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">(1) drift C (t, t') = d mean ( C(SW) t , C(SW) t' ) (2) expand C (t, t')= R t' -R t (3) shrink C (t, t')= R t -R t' = -expand C (t, t') (4) decline C (t, t')= 1-|S(SW) t' |/ |S(SW) t |</formula><p>Based on observations, only significant movements are meaningful and worth to detect in practical applications. We introduce some significant movements and refer it to movement events. To control the sensitivity of the movement event detecting, we introduce a predefined parameter set {δ i } (δ i &gt; 0) where i = 1 … 5. Definition 2 (Movement Event) Given a sliding window SW of a cluster C and two stamp t and t' (t &lt; t'), let the user-defined sensitivity parameter set be {δ i } (δ i &gt; 0) where i = 1 … 5, and R t be the radius of cluster C at time stamp t. The conditions for movement event at time stamp t' are defined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5"> Drift event: () t S SW , ' () t S SW , drift C (t, t') &gt; R t • δ 1 .  Expand event: () t S SW  , ' () t S SW  , expand C (t, t') &gt; R t • δ 2 .  Shrink event: () t S SW , ' () t S SW , shrink C (t, t') &gt; R t • δ 2 .  Die-out event: () t S SW , decline C (t, t') &gt; δ 3 .(0 &lt; δ 3 &lt; 1)</formula><p>Note that, Parameters δ 4 and δ 5 are not used in the definition of movement event. We will discuss them in sub-section 5.2. In data streams, there may be more than one movement event to trigger. The same type of movement event except die-out event may be generated several times to accomplish a large movement. The type of movement event may be not exclusive either. So that the drift event and expand event will be generated alternately during the change. Definition 3 (ClusterState) Given a sliding window SW of a cluster C, the data points in SW are X 1 , X 2 … X N with time stamps T 1 , T 2 …, T N , the cluster state of the cluster is a 6-tuple ClusterState = (SW, LS, SS, t, OX 0 , OR) defined by: Based on ClusterTable data structure and sensitivity parameter set, we propose an algorithm for detecting and refinement operations to of clusters in data streams. The refinement operations guarantee the accuracy of the clustering result.</p><formula xml:id="formula_6"> SW is</formula><p>Move The move operation is executed when a drift event occurs. For example, in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>, it revises the original centroid of the cluster to current centroid according to LS.</p><p>Split This operation is to split the cluster into two smaller clusters if the radius is larger than maximum of radius. It is executed when expand event is triggered. For example, from <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3 to Fig. 4</ref>, the cluster O 1 is split into cluster O <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> and O 4 . We use δ 4 that is one of the given sensitivity parameter set to represent the limit of maximal radius in data streams. Given two ClusterState tuples CS i = (SW i , LS i , SS i , t i , OX 0i , OR i ,) of cluster i, if OR i &gt; δ 4 then the split operation will be executed to the cluster i. The splitting method consists of two O(|SW|) steps. The first is to find out the farthest data point from the center in SW. The second step is to make the farthest data point be a seed to absorbing data points in SW. Some data points which are nearer to the seed than to the center will be assigned to the seed. Finally, the seed with its data points becomes a new cluster. New ClusterState tuple of the new cluster will be created and inserted to the ClusterTable.</p><p>Merge The merge operation is to merge two near clusters. It is executed when drift event or expand event is triggered. For example, from <ref type="figure">Fig. 3 to Fig. 5</ref>  Stretch The stretch operation is executed when shrink event or expand event occurs. This operation will update the original radius by current radius of the cluster. Current radius can be calculated by Lemma 1.</p><p>Delete The delete operation is executed when dieout event is triggered. This operation firstly distributes all the data points with their time stamps of the cluster to other cluster. Every data point will be assigned to the nearest one of other clusters. Then it deletes the ClusterState of the cluster in the ClusterTable.</p><p>Algorithm 3 describes maintaining the clusters and ClusterTable. It is an event-driven process that checks each condition of movement event and trigger corresponding operations introduced in this subsection. There are two integer parameters MaxNumCluster and MinNumCluster that limit the range of the number of clusters in data streams processing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Algorithm 3</head><p>Maintain({δ i }, MaxNumCluster, MinNumCluster) 1 for each cluster i do 2 while exist any movement event of cluster i is triggered do 3 event = the movement event triggered 4</p><p>Invoke corresponding operations to event 5</p><p>if the number of clusters &lt; MinNumCluster</p><p>Invoke split to the maximal radius cluster. 7</p><p>if the number of clusters &gt; MaxNumCluster 8</p><p>Invoke merge to the two closest clusters.</p><p>The time complexities of all refinement operations are less than O(h), where h is the constant parameter horizon time. Furthermore, the process of Algorithm 3 doesn't need to be executed when every new data points arrive in. The user can define a parameter checkinterval as the number of data points in the interval of maintaining process execution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Experimental Study</head><p>All experiments were conducted on a PC with Intel Pentium IV 3.20GHz processor and 2 GB memory, which runs Windows XP. The well-known CluStream <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> was used as the benchmark algorithm, and all algorithms were implemented in standard C++.</p><p>(1) Real datasets. In order to demonstrate the effectiveness of MovStream, the KDD-CUP'99 Network Intrusion Detection data set was used. Aggarwal et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> used the data set to evaluate the accuracy of CluStream with respect to STREAM <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. As Aggarwal and Callaghan et al. did in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, the 34 continuous attributes of total 42 attributes were selected for the experiments. (2) Synthetic datasets. To demonstrate the scalability of MovStream, we generated several synthetic dataset which follows a series of Gaussian distributions. The size of dataset varies from 100K to 400K, the number of clusters varies from 5 to 20, and the dimensionality of data points varies from 4 to 50. The mean and variance of the Gaussian distributions are changed every 10K data points. The quality of clustering on data sets is measured by the sum of square distance (SSQ), which is used in many previous literatures <ref type="bibr">[2, 3, 4, 6 and 7]</ref>. Both algorithms were executed five times and their average SSQs were calculated.</p><p>We determined 5 clusters for each algorithm in real dataset. For MovStream, the MaxNumCluster and MinNumCluster were both set to 5 so that it can output the same number of clusters as CluStream. For CluStream algorithm, the parameters were set at micro-ratio = 10, Max. Boundary Factor t = 2. Aggarwal et al. did extensive experiments and discussed that the clustering can achieve high-quality and stable in that situation <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. InitNumber for both algorithms was set to 2000. For MovStream algorithm, the ClusterTable maintaining process was invoked every 100 data points, checkinterval=100. The sensitivity parameter set was set at {1.5, 1.5, 0.95, 45500, 0.1}. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 6</ref> gives the results when horizon time is set to 1000. At time stamp 30000, the average SSQ of MovStream is about equal to that of CluStream. Both algorithms output the average SSQs every 1000 data points. We have found that the average SSQs of two algorithms are almost in a same magnitude, but most of time MovStream is a little more accurate than CluStream. <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref> shows the results when horizon is set to 5000 as <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 6</ref>. We compare the total average SSQs for all SSQs for each horizon time in data streams as showed in <ref type="figure">Fig. 8</ref>. MovStream is more accurate than CluStream about 25% to 50%. We also compare the efficiencies of both algorithms. The micro-clusters in CluStream don't represent the natural clusters in data streams, so when the purpose is monitoring natural clusters, CluStream needs to do macro-clustering for each period time. The number of data points streamed in the period time can be defined as a parameter monitor-period. Another important parameter for CluStream is micro-ratio, which is the number of micro-clusters divided by the number of natural clusters <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. As Aggarwal et al. discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, large amount of micro-clusters leads to high-quality clustering result but low-performance. We compared the efficiency of CluStream with different micro-ratio as showed in <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref>. The size of load buffer of all algorithms is set to 100000 (points), and the execution time contains the time of data reading from hard disk. The parameters are set as horizon time=2000, monitorperiod=2000. Other parameters are same as before. For example, CluStream(4.0) indicates the micro-ratio is 4.0 that the number of micro-clusters is equal to the number of natural clusters. From <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref>, we can see large amount of micro-clusters leads the performance to fall down rapidly. Considering the same clustering quality, CluStream(10.0) is slower about 10 times than MovStream. From the reports from Code Performance Profiler, we found that there are two main reasons for MovStream algorithm is s faster than CluStream. First, the number of clusters maintained in CluStream is larger than that in MovStream. CluStream need a large number of micro-clusters to achieve high-quality clustering, the cost of find and merge the suitable micro-clusters is high. Second, CluStream need kmeans algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> to cluster the micro-clusters into macro-clusters in period time. The k-means algorithm is not efficient as many single-pass data clustering algorithms <ref type="bibr">[2, 3 and 7]</ref>. Furthermore, it has to be executed in period time. <ref type="figure">Fig. 10</ref> and <ref type="figure">Fig. 11</ref> show the scalability on the number dimensions test on synthetic datasets. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.12</ref> and <ref type="figure">Fig.13</ref> show the scalability on the number of clusters to determine on synthetic datasets. The microcluster is set as 4.0. In these synthetic dataset tests, we can see MovStream has a better linear scalability than CluStream, and MovStream is also faster than CluStream. Because MovStream fits the datasets perfectly, there is no split movement or merge movement could be triggered in whole processes. Thus the efficiency of MovStream is always very high.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Conclusions and Future Work</head><p>In this paper, we have studied: (a) introducing basic movements of the cluster with the measurement for them, (b) proposing an effective and efficient cluster monitoring method named MovStream based on the measurements, and (c) giving extensive experiments to show that MovStream can achieve more accurate by 25-50% than that of highest clustering quality of CluStream..MovStream includes basic movements of cluster and operations like balance keeping operations in B + Tree. More valuable types of movement of the cluster and more precise and efficient refinement operations will be proposed in the future.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig.2 The expand to a cluster</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig.3 Two clusters</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig.6 Network Intrusion dataset (horizon time=1000)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>arrived at [t 1 , t 2 ] 

O1 

O4 

O3 

O2 

arrived at [t 3 , t 4 ] 
arrived at [t 5 , t 6 ] 
arrived at [t 7 , t 8 ] 
Fig.1 The drift to a cluster 

O1 

O2 
O3 

arrived at [t 1 , t 2 ] 

arrived at [t 3 , t 4 ] 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>the sliding window of the cluster.  LS is LS(SW) of the sliding window SW.  SS is SS(SW) of the sliding window SW.  t is the time stamp when the last cluster refinement operation be executed.  OX 0 is the original centroid of the cluster, which is the centroid at time stamp t.  OR is the original radius of the cluster, which is the radius at time stamp t. ClusterTable ClusterTable is a dynamic list data structure that stores the ClusterState tuple of each cluster in data streams. In our work, ClusterTable[i] presents the ClusterState tuple of cluster i. Algorithm 1 describes the first phase of our method. It is enlighten by the idea of k-means clustering to initialize clusters [1]. Algorithm 1 InitClusterTable (k, InitNumber) 1 Store first InitNumber data points. 2 cluster the InitNumber data points into k clustersAlgorithm 2 describes how to process the new arrived data, where X new is from data stream and X last is) 1 Find the nearest cluster i in ClusterTable to X new . 2 Add X new and X new • X new to LS and SS of ClusterTable[i] 3 Push X new in ClusterTable[i].SW 4 Find the cluster j contains X last in ClusterTable. 5 Pop out X last from ClusterTable[j].SW. 6 Subtract X last and X last • X last from LS and SS of ClusterTable[j]</head><label></label><figDesc>the oldest data point in all clusters. The time complexity of line 1 and 4 is less than O(MaxNumCluster), where MaxNumCluster is a user- defined factor that is maximal the number of clusters in ClusterTable. Algorithm 2 is a constant time complexity cost.</figDesc><table>. 
3 
for each initial cluster i do 
4 
Create the ClusterTable[i] from the cluster i. 
5 
Fill ClusterTable[i].SW. 
6 
Calculate LS, SS of ClusterTable[i]. 
7 
Calculate centroid, radius of ClusterTable[i] 
8 
ClusterTable[i]. t = 0 

Algorithm 2 ProcessNewData (X new </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>, the cluster O 1 and cluster O 2 are merged into cluster O 1 . Given two ClusterState tuples CS i = (SW i , LS i , SS i , t i , OX 0i , OR i ) of cluster i and CS j = (SW j , LS j , SS j , t 0j , OX 0j , OR j ) of cluster j, if (OR i + OR j ) •δ 5 &gt; |OX 0i -OX 0j | then the merge operation will be executed to merge cluster i and j. The sliding windows of the two clusters will be also merged by a merge sort. The time complexity of merge is O(|SW i | + |SW j |).</head><label>,</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pattern Classification and Scene Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. wiley and Sons</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Streaming-Data Algorithms for High-Quality Clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>O&amp;apos;callaghan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mishra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Meyerson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ICDE</title>
		<meeting>of ICDE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustering Data Streams: Theory and Practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Meyerson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mishra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Motwani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. on KDE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="515" to="528" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Framework for Clustering Evolving Data Streams</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Aggarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the 29th VLDB</title>
		<meeting>of the 29th VLDB</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BIRCH: An Efficient Data Clustering Method for Very Large Databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Livny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM SIGMOD Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GenIc: A Single Pass Generalized Incremental Algorithm for Clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Grossman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SIAM Conference on Data Mining</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustering data stream</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mishra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Motwani</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Challaghan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lo&amp;apos;</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the 41st annual symposium on FOCS 2000</title>
		<meeting>of the 41st annual symposium on FOCS 2000<address><addrLine>Redondo Beach, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="366" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gaber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zaslavsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Krishnaswamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Mining Data Streams: A Review. SIGMOD Record</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="26" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Nasraoui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cardona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rojas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">TECNO-STREAMS: Tracking Evolving Clusters in Noisy Data Streams with a Scalable Immune System Learning Model. ICDM 2003</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="242" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Nasraoui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rojas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Robust Clustering for Tracking Noisy Evolving Data Streams. SDM</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustering binary data streams with k-means</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ordonez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 8th ACM SIGMOD workshop on research issues in DMKD 2003</title>
		<meeting>the 8th ACM SIGMOD workshop on research issues in DMKD 2003</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="19" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Density-Based Clustering over an Evolving Data Stream with Noise</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ester</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<publisher>SDM</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
