<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T17:01+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Extracting synonymous gene and protein terms from biological literature</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hong</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Eugene</forename><surname>Agichtein</surname></persName>
							<email>eugene@cs.columbia.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Extracting synonymous gene and protein terms from biological literature</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">BIOINFORMATICS</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="340" to="349"/>
							<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btg1047</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received on January 6, 2003; accepted on February 20, 2003</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Motivation: Genes and proteins are often associated with multiple names. More names are added as new functional or structural information is discovered. Because authors can use any one of the known names for a gene or protein, information retrieval and extraction would benefit from identifying the gene and protein terms that are synonyms of the same substance. Results: We have explored four complementary approaches for extracting gene and protein synonyms from text, namely the unsupervised, partially supervised, and supervised machine-learning techniques, as well as the manual knowledge-based approach. We report results of a large scale evaluation of these alternatives over an archive of biological journal articles. Our evaluation shows that our extraction techniques could be a valuable supplement to resources such as SWISSPROT, as our systems were able to capture gene and protein synonyms not listed in the SWISSPROT database. Data Availability: The extracted gene and protein synonyms are available at</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Genes and proteins often have multiple names. As biological research progresses, additional names may be given for the same substance, or different names may be found to represent the same substance. For example, the protein lymphocyte associated receptor of death has several synonyms including LARD, Apo3, DR3, TRAMP, wsl, and TnfRSF12. Authors often use different names to refer to the same gene or protein across articles or sub-domains. Identifying these name variations would benefit information retrieval and information extraction systems. Recognizing the alternate names for the same substance would help biologists to find and use relevant literature.</p><p>Many biological databases such as GenBank † and SWISSPROT ‡ include synonyms; however, these * To whom correspondence should be addressed. † http://www.psc.edu/general/software/packages/genbank/genbank.html ‡ http://www.ebi.ac.uk/swissprot/ databases may not always be up to date. We found that even biology experts disagree with some of the synonyms that were listed in the SWISSPROT database. Furthermore, to our knowledge, lists of gene and protein synonyms and thesauri are mainly constructed by laborious manual curation and review. Therefore, it is desirable to automate this process due to the increasing number of discovered genes and proteins. The problem of extracting gene and protein synonyms from text requires first identifying gene or protein names in the text, and then determining whether these names are synonymous. In this work, we focus on the second part of the problem: namely, on extracting pairs of gene or protein names that are considered to be synonymous. We rely on existing state-of-the-art taggers for gene and protein name entity identification. Having identified the gene or protein entities in text, we apply different methods for extracting the synonymous ones.</p><p>In this study, we adapt and explore four novel complementary approaches for extracting synonymous gene and protein names from biological literature. We present an in-depth study of state-of-the-art techniques over a large collection of recent journal articles. We develop a scalable methodology for evaluating the quality of extracted synonyms. Our experimental results show that our techniques result in the extraction of novel gene and protein synonyms that are not present in the SWISSPROT database § . Our extraction techniques could be used to improve search and analysis of biological literature, and to aid human curators of biology resources.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BACKGROUND AND RELATED WORK</head><p>Extracting gene and protein synonyms from biological literature is an important problem with significant practical benefits. Synonymous gene and protein names represent the same biological substances. This might be recognized if the substances in question exhibit identical biological functions or the same gene or amino acid sequences ¶ .</p><p>Recent computational linguistics research on synonym detection has mainly focused on detecting semantically related words rather than exact synonyms, by measuring the similarity of surrounding contexts. For example, these approaches may identify 'beer' and 'wine' as related words because both have similar surrounding words such as 'drink', 'people', 'bottle' and 'make' (e.g. ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dagan et al., 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Li and Abe, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Lin, 1998))</ref>. A different approach exploited WORDNET <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Fellbaum, 1999</ref>), a large lexical database for English words, to evaluate semantic similarity of any two concepts based on their distance to other concepts that subsume them in the taxonomy <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Resnik, 1995)</ref>.</p><p>In the biomedical domain, most approaches for synonym identification appear to be restricted to the actual content of the strings in question, and ignore the surrounding context. One such approach used a semi-automatic method to identify multi-word synonyms in UMLS (the Unified Medical Language System, a large biomedical taxonomy <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Humphreys and Lindberg, 1993)</ref>), by linking terms as candidate synonyms if they shared any words <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Hole and Srinivasan, 2000</ref>). For example, the term 'cerebrospinal fluid' leads to 'cerebrospinal fluid protein assay.' The candidate synonym terms then were evaluated by human curators. A different approach employed a trigram-matching algorithm to identify similar multi-word phrases. In this study, the phrases are treated as documents made up of character trigrams. The 'documents' are then represented in the vector space model, and similarity is computed as the cosine of the angle between the corresponding vectors ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Wilbur and Kim, 2001</ref>). Several other systems (e.g. ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Liu and Friedman, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Pakhomov, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Park and Byrd, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Schwartz and Hearst, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Yoshida et al., 2000;</ref>)) applied rule-based, statistical or machine-learning approaches for mapping abbreviations to their full forms. To our knowledge, few studies have attempted to automatically identify synonymous relations among gene or protein abbreviations. In contrast, our techniques can identify synonyms of abbreviations as well as full names.</p><p>We approach the synonym extraction problem by applying information extraction and text classification techniques, where the desired structured information is the synonym pairs that are 'hidden' in the biological literature. As we describe next, machine learning techniques have been successfully used to adapt text analysis systems to new domains. The following studies provided the foundation for our current work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Information extraction and machine learning</head><p>One of the major challenges in information extraction is the large amount of manual labor involved in constructing and tuning the extraction system. Many biological information extraction systems (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Friedman et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Rindflesch et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Thomas et al., 2000;</ref>) build upon domain knowledge and domain-specific rules. To reduce manual effort, one approach is to build a powerful and intuitive graphical user interface for training the system, so that domain experts can quickly adopt the system for each new task ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Yangarber and Grishman, 1998)</ref>. This approach still needs substantial manual labor to port the system to new domains.</p><p>Machine-learning methods are becoming increasingly popular in text analysis. These methods significantly reduce required manual labor by automatically acquiring rules from labeled and unlabeled data. For example, supervised machine learning techniques such as Support Vector Machines (SVMs) were found to be highly effective for text classification <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Joachims, 1998)</ref>. In previous work, other supervised learning techniques have been applied to information extraction from unstructured and semi-structured text (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Califf and Mooney, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Kushmerick et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Muslea et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Soderland, 1999)</ref>). While supervised machine learning approaches usually need less manual labor than knowledge-based approaches, they still require significant manual effort because of their dependency on a manually labeled training corpus. Several approaches attempt to reduce manual effort in annotating the training corpus. For example, instead of tagging entire documents, one approach required only marking the documents as either relevant or irrelevant for the extraction task <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Riloff, 1996)</ref>. This approach requires less manual labor, but the effort involved is still substantial.</p><p>For this reason, the general partially-supervised approaches have become an attractive alternative. A partially-supervised system typically starts with a relatively small number of manually labeled examples and proceeds to acquire new training examples automatically. Some of the early applications of partially-supervised learning using bootstrapping include identifying word hyponyms and hypernyms in natural language text <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Hearst, 1992)</ref>, and word sense disambiguation <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Yarowsky, 1995)</ref>.</p><p>More recently, the co-training framework was proposed for combining unlabeled and labeled examples to boost performance of a learning algorithm (e.g. for web page classification <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Blum and Mitchell, 1998)</ref>). A related approach was subsequently used for classifying named entities (e.g. company names) in text ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Collins and Singer, 1999)</ref>. A different approach for named entity classification used multi-stage bootstrapping ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Riloff and Jones, 1999)</ref>. Another variation of the bootstrapping technique was applied for disambiguating gene, protein, and RNA terms in biological literature ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hatzivassiloglou et al., 2001</ref>).</p><p>Bootstrapping has also been used for extracting structured relations from text. The partially supervised DIPRE method was proposed for automatically acquiring patterns and relations from the pages on the web <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Brin, 1998</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>i341</head><p>More recently, the Snowball information extraction system <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Agichtein and Gravano, 2000</ref>) extended the basic DIPRE method by incorporating automatic pattern and tuple evaluation for extracting relations from large text collections. A similar bootstrapping-based technique was independently developed for traditional information extraction ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Yangarber et al., 2000)</ref>.</p><p>In this study, we explore four complementary approaches to extracting gene and protein synonyms from text. In the next section we describe our implementations of the unsupervised, partially-supervised, supervised, and the hand-constructed systems that we developed for extracting gene and protein synonyms from biological literature.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXTRACTING SYNONYMOUS GENE AND PROTEIN TERMS</head><p>We now present our approaches for extracting synonymous genes and proteins from biological literature. To extract these synonyms, we first need to identify, or tag, the genes and proteins as they appear in the text. This task is accomplished by pre-processing the corpus. Having identified the gene and protein entities, we can apply complementary approaches for determining which of the entities are synonyms of each other. First, we outline an unsupervised approach. Next, we describe our adaptation of Snowball, a partially-supervised information extraction system. We then present a supervised machine learning method based on a state-of-the-art automatic text classification tool. Next, we describe an extraction system that was manually constructed by a biology expert. Finally, we present a new combined system, where the output of the manually constructed system is augmented with the output of the machine learning-based systems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pre-processing: gene and protein tagging</head><p>Identifying gene or protein names in biological literature has been a rich area of research. As part of our system development we compared three alternative gene taggers: the tagger described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Fukuda et al. (1998)</ref>, the tagger described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Proux et al. (1998), and</ref><ref type="bibr">Abgene (Tanabe and</ref>). We emphasize that the purpose of our study was not to systematically evaluate gene taggers, but to identify the one that is best suited for our synonym identification task. We examined all three taggers over our training corpus and found that Abgene performed best for our extraction task. Therefore, we use Abgene as the tagger of choice for all of the subsequent experiments.</p><p>We also observed that gene or protein synonyms usually occur within the same sentence. Therefore, we segment the corpus into sentences using the publicly available SentenceSplitter system 񮽙 . After sentence segmentation, 񮽙 Available from http://l2r.cs.uiuc.edu/∼cogcomp/index research.html.</p><p>only the pairs of genes that appear within the same sentence will be considered as potential synonyms by any of the following extraction techniques. Additionally, we observed that the authors tend to specify gene and protein synonyms in the first few pages of the article. Therefore, our systems examined only the first 4Kb of text of each article for potential synonyms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Contextual similarity: an unsupervised approach</head><p>We adopted a synonym detection method-which we will refer to as Similarity-for identifying synonyms based on contextual similarity <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Dagan et al., 1995)</ref>. We chose Similarity over the others (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Li and Abe, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Lin, 1998)</ref> because Similarity has been shown to be both robust and general <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Dagan et al., 1995)</ref>.</p><p>The contextual similarity approach finds sets of words that appear in similar contexts. The main observation is that synonyms of a word t can be detected by finding words that appear in the same contexts as t. If the contexts of t 1 and t 2 are similar, then t 1 and t 2 are considered synonyms. More formally, we define the context of a term t as all words that occur within a d word window from t (e.g. d = 5) * * . In order to separate chance co-occurrence from the words that tend to appear together, the method uses mutual information to weight each word w in the context of t. The mutual information I (t, w) is defined as log 2 ( P(t,w) P(t)·P(w) ), and calculated as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">I (t, w) = log 2 񮽙 N d · f req(t, w) f req(t) · f req(w) 񮽙 ,</formula><p>where N is the size of the corpus in words, and d is the size of the window. Note that I (t, w) 񮽙 = I (w, t) because f req(t, w) (i.e. the number of times w appears to the right of t) is not symmetric. Using mutual information, we can now define the similarity Sim between two terms t 1 and t 2 , based on their respective contexts as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">񮽙 w∈lexicon min(I (w, t 1 ), I (w, t 2 )) + min(I (t 1 , w), I (t 2 , w)) 񮽙 w∈lexicon max(I (w, t 1 ), I (w, t 2 )) + max(I (t 1 , w), I (t 2 , w)) ,</formula><p>where w ranges over the complete lexicon of all of the words that appear in the respective contexts of t 1 and t 2 .</p><p>The value of the similarity Sim(t 1 , t 2 ) is used to determine whether t 1 and t 2 are synonyms. It is not feasible to compute Sim(t 1 , t 2 ) for all choices of t 1 and t 2 , since this would require O(|lexicon| 3 ) running time. We implemented a heuristic search algorithm to compute a close approximation of the set of most similar terms for a given term t 1 ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dagan et al., 1995)</ref>. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> reports some of the synonym sets extracted by Similarity from a biological journal archive. * * We distinguish the left context of t (i.e. words that appear within d words before t), and the right contexts of t because of asymmetry of English grammar. For clarity of the presentation, we omit this distinction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>i342</head><p>Extracting synonymous gene and protein terms  The original Similarity method ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dagan et al., 1995</ref>) was designed to find contextual synonyms for all words in the corpus. In contrast, we are only interested in computing synonyms of gene and protein terms. Therefore, the Similarity system uses a modification of the search algorithm to only search for contextual similarity between terms g 1 and g 2 if both g 1 and g 2 were tagged by the Abgene tagger as genes. The confidence, Conf(s), of a candidate synonym pair s(g 1 , g 2 ) is simply the value of similarity Sim(g 1 , g 2 ). We consider only the top k most similar terms for each term g 1 (we set k = 5).</p><p>While the unsupervised approach is attractive because it does not require manual training, many of the extracted gene and protein pairs are likely to be false positives. Therefore, we would like to incorporate some domain knowledge without requiring significant manual effort. With this goal in mind, we adapted a partially supervised information extraction system for our synonym identification problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Snowball: a partially-supervised approach</head><p>The Snowball system <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Agichtein and Gravano, 2000</ref>) uses a bootstrapping approach for extracting structured relations from unstructured (natural language) text. Snowball was designed to operate over large text collections and to require minimal human input. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 2</ref>, Snowball starts with a small set of user-provided seed tuples for the relation of interest, and automatically generates and evaluates patterns for extracting new tuples. In our study, the relation to be extracted is Synonym (Gene1, Gene2).</p><p>As initial input, Snowball only requires a set of userprovided seed (i.e. example) tuples in the target relation (i.e. a set of known gene or protein synonym pairs). For this problem, we extended Snowball to also make use of negative examples (i.e. co-occurring genes and protein expressions known not to be synonyms of each other). Snowball then proceeds to find occurrences of the positive seed tuples in the collection. These occurrences are converted into extraction patterns, which are subsequently used to extract new tuples from the documents, and the process iterates by augmenting the seed tuples with the newly extracted tuples.</p><p>A crucial step in the extraction process is the generation of patterns to find new tuples in the documents. Given a set of seed tuples (e.g. 񮽙g 1 , g 2 񮽙), and having found the text segments where g 1 and g 2 occur close to each other, Snowball analyzes the text that 'connects' g 1 and g 2 to generate patterns. Snowball's patterns incorporate entity tags (i.e. the GENE tags assigned by the tagger during the preprocessing). For example, a pattern would be generated from a context '񮽙GENE񮽙 also known as 񮽙GENE񮽙'. Snowball represents the left, middle, and right 'contexts' associated with an extraction pattern as vectors of weighted terms (where terms can be arbitrary strings of non-space characters). During extraction, to match text portions with patterns, Snowball also associates an equivalent set of term vectors with each document portion that contains two entities with the correct tags (i.e. a pair of GENEs).</p><p>After generating patterns, Snowball scans the collection to discover new tuples by matching text segments with the most similar pattern (if any). Each candidate tuple will then have a number of patterns that helped generate it, each with an associated degree of match. Snowball uses this information, together with information about the selectivity of the patterns, to decide what candidate tuples to actually add to the table that it is constructing. Intuitively, we can expect that newly extracted synonyms for 'known' genes should match the known synonyms for these genes. Otherwise, if the newly extracted synonym is 'unknown' (i.e. a potential false positive), the pattern is considered to be less 'selective' and its confidence is decreased. For example, if Snowball extracted a new synonym pair s = =g a , g b 񮽙, we check if there exists a set of high confidence previously extracted synonyms for g a , e.g. 񮽙g a , g 1 񮽙, 񮽙g a , g 2 񮽙. If g b is equal to either g 1 or g 2 , s is considered a positive match for the pattern, and an 'unknown' match otherwise. Note that this confidence computation 'trusts' tuples generated on earlier iterations more than newly extracted tuples. Additionally, if the pattern P matches a known negative example tuple, the confidence of P is further decreased. More formally, Snowball defines Conf(P), the confidence of a pattern P as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">񮽙 log 2 (P positive ) P positive (P positive + P unknown · w unk + P negative · w neg 񮽙 i343</formula><p>where P positive is the number of positive matches for P, P unknown is the number of 'unknown' matches, and P negative is the number of negative matches, adjusted respectively by the w unk and w neg weight parameters (set during system tuning). The confidence scores are normalized so that they are between 0 and 1.</p><p>Snowball calculates the confidence of the extracted tuples as a function of the confidence values and the number of the patterns that generated the tuples. Intuitively, Conf(s), the confidence of an extracted tuple s, will be high if s is generated by several highly selective patterns. More formally, the confidence of s is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Con f (s) = 1 − |P| 񮽙 i=0 (1 − (Con f (P i ) · Match(C i , P i ))),</formula><p>where P = {P i } is the set of extraction patterns that generated s, and C i is the context associated with an occurrence of s that matched P i with degree of match Match(C i , P i ). After determining the confidence of the candidate tuples, Snowball discards all tuples with low confidence. These tuples could add noise into the pattern generation process, which would in turn introduce more invalid tuples, degrading the performance of the system. The set of tuples to use as the seed in the next Snowball iteration is then Seed = {s|Conf (s) &gt; τ t }, where τ t = 0.6 is a threshold tuned during system development.</p><p>The original Snowball system was designed to operate with few user-provided example tuples. When many labeled examples are available, supervised methods have performed well. Next, we present our adaptation of a supervised text classification system for synonym extraction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Text classification: a supervised approach</head><p>We can use supervised machine learning to build a text classifier to identify synonymous genes and proteins. We start with the same user-provided positive and negative example gene and protein pairs as were used as the initial examples for Snowball. We then automatically create the training set of example contexts where these gene and protein pairs occur. These contexts are assigned either a positive weight of 1.0 or a negative weight of w neg (tuned as part of system development).</p><p>We can now train the classifier to distinguish between the 'positive' text contexts (i.e. those that contain an example synonym pair), and the 'negative' text contexts. Thus, a classifier would be able to distinguish previously unseen text contexts that contain synonym pairs (e.g. 'A, also known as B'), from the contexts that do not express the synonymy relation (e.g. 'A regulates B').</p><p>We chose a state-of-the-art text classification tool SVMLight (Joachims, 1998) † † which has been shown to † † Available at:</p><p>http://www-ai.cs.uni-dortmund.de/SOFTWARE/ SVM LIGHT/svm light v3.02.eng.html be effective for text classification. The resulting system, to which we refer as SVM, uses as features the same terms and term weights used by Snowball for training and prediction. We used the rbf, or the radial basis kernel function option of the SVMLight package, which performed best in our preliminary experiments over the development corpus.</p><p>After the classifier is trained, SVM examines every text context, C, surrounding pairs of identified gene and protein terms in the collection. If the classifier determines C to be an instance of the 'positive' (i.e. synonym) class, the corresponding pair of genes or proteins, s, is assigned the initial confidence score Conf 0 (s), equal to the score that the classifier assigned to C. The confidence scores are normalized so that the final confidence of the candidate synonym pair s, Conf (s), is between 0 and 1. Note that SVM does not combine evidence from multiple occurrences of the same gene or protein pair: when s occurs in multiple contexts, Conf (s) is assigned based on the single 'most promising' text context of s.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GPE: the hand-crafted extraction system</head><p>As a final-and the most labor-intensive-extraction approach, we used a previously constructed hand-crafted system called GPE ) that was built specifically for extracting synonymous gene and protein expressions. The construction of GPE begins with a set of known synonymous gene or protein names. The domain expert examines the contexts where these example gene or protein pairs occur and manually generates patterns to describe these occurrences. For example, the expert decided that the strings 'known as' and 'also called' would work well as extraction patterns. Using these manually constructed patterns, GPE scans the collection for new synonyms. For example, GPE identified the synonymous set Apo3, LARD, DR3, wsl from the sentence '. . . Apo3 (also known as LARD, DR3, and wsl). . . '. Since GPE does not use gene or protein taggers, many pairs of strings that are not genes or proteins can be extracted. To avoid such false positives, GPE uses heuristics and knowledgebased filters. After filtering, each extracted synonym pair s is assigned a confidence Conf (s) = 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The combined system</head><p>While GPE requires labor-intensive tuning by a biology expert, it can extract a small high quality set of synonyms ( ). In contrast, both Snowball and SVM induce extraction patterns automatically, allowing them to capture synonyms that may be missed by GPE. On the other hand, Snowball and SVM are also likely to extract more false positives, resulting in the lower 'quality' of the extracted synonyms. We can exploit the advantages of both the knowledge-based and machine learning-based techniques in a combined system. We now i344 Extracting synonymous gene and protein terms present our Combined system that integrates the output of Snowball, SVM, and GPE ‡ ‡ .</p><p>We can combine outputs of the individual extraction systems in different ways (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Dietterich, 2000</ref>). In our implementation of Combined, we assume that each system is an independent predictor, and that the confidence score assigned by each system to the extracted pair corresponds to the probability that the extracted synonym pair is correct. We can then estimate the probability that the extracted synonym pair s = =p 1 , p 2 񮽙 is correct as (1 − the probability that all systems extracted s incorrectly):</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Conf (s) = 1 − 񮽙 E∈Systems (1 − Conf E (s)),</formula><p>where Conf E (s) is the confidence score assigned to s by the individual extraction system E. This combination function quantifies the intuition that agreement of multiple extraction systems on a candidate synonym pair s indicates that s is a true synonym.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL SETUP AND EVALUATION METHODOLOGY</head><p>We evaluated Similarity, Snowball, SVM, GPE, and Combined over a collection of 52 000 recent journal articles from Science, Nature, Cell, EMBO, Cell Biology, PNAS, and the Journal of Biochemistry. The journal archives are maintained by the GeneWays Project ( <ref type="bibr">Fried- man et al., 2001</ref>) at Columbia University. The collection was separated into two disjoint sets of articles: the development collection, containing 20 000 articles, and the test collection, containing 32 000 articles.</p><p>System tuning The Similarity, Snowball, and the SVM systems were tuned over the unlabeled development collection articles. The tuning consisted of changing the parameter values (e.g. the size of the context window d) in a systematic manner to find a combination that appeared to perform best on the development collection. The final parameter values used for the subsequent experiments over the test collection are listed in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>.</p><p>User-provided examples Note that our machine-learning based systems do not require manually labeled articles.</p><p>Instead, approximately 650 known gene and protein synonym pairs, previously compiled from a variety of sources, were used as positive examples for the Snowball and SVM systems. Some of these did not occur in the collections, and thus did not contribute to the system training. Additionally, a set of negative examples were compiled by a biology expert by examining the contexts of some commonly co-occurring, but not synonymous, genes and proteins in the development collection. ‡ ‡ As we will discuss, Similarity did not perform well, and therefore was not included in the Combined system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Parameter</head><p>Value Description window d  <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>. Final values of the Similarity, Snowball, and SVM system parameters.</p><p>One of the goals of our evaluation is to determine whether the extraction approaches that we compare generalize to new document collections. Therefore, the only information that we retained from the tuning of the Similarity, Snowball, and SVM systems were the values of the system parameters <ref type="figure">(Fig. 3)</ref>. During the 'test' stage of our experiments, both Snowball and SVM systems were re-trained from scratch over the unlabeled articles in the test collection, by starting with the same initial example gene and protein pairs described above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Evaluation metrics</head><p>Our evaluation focuses on the quality of the extracted set of synonym pairs, S e : (1) how comprehensive is S e , and (2) how 'clean' the pairs in S e are. To compare the alternative extraction systems, we adapt the recall and precision metrics from information extraction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recall</head><p>The fraction of all of the synonymous gene and protein pairs that appear in the collection, S all , and were captured in the extracted set, S e , is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Recall = |S e ∩ S all | |S all | .</formula><p>Precision The fraction of the real synonym pairs in S e is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">Precision = |S e ∩ S all | |S e | .</formula><p>Note that all of the compared extraction systems assign a confidence score between 0 and 1 to each extracted synonym pair. It would be useful to know the precision of the systems at various confidence levels. Therefore, we calculate precision at c, where c is the threshold for the minimum confidence score assigned by the extraction system. The precision at c is then defined as the precision of the subset of the extracted synonyms with the confidence score ≥ c. We define recall at c equivalently.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>i345</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Relationship Type SWISSPROT Synonyms Context</head><p>Family Related GRPE, MGEL '. . . requires the nucleotide release factors, grpe and mge1. . . ' Fragment PS2, ALG3 '. . . sas ps-2 c-terminal 109-amino acid fragment ( alg3 ) is essential in the death process. . . ' Subunits P40, P38 '. . . baculoviruses encoding individual rf-c subunits p140, p40, p38, p37, and p36) yielded. . . ' Homologous GRIP-1, TIF2 '. . . shown that grip-1 , the murine homologous of tif2. . . ' Functionally Related CDC47, MCM2 'and cdc47 , cdc21 , and mis5 form another complex, which relatively weakly associates with mcm2.' </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Evaluation methodology</head><p>For small text collections, we could inspect all documents manually and compile the sets of all of the synonymous genes in the collection by hand. Unfortunately, this evaluation approach does not scale, and becomes infeasible for the kind of large document collections for which automatic extraction systems would be particularly useful. The problem with exhaustive evaluation is two-fold: (1) the extraction systems tend to generate many thousands of synonyms from the collection (which makes it impossible to examine all of them to compute precision), and (2) since modern collections typically contains thousands of documents, it is not feasible to examine all of them to compute recall.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Estimating precision</head><p>To estimate precision at c, for each system's output S e we randomly select 20 candidate synonym pairs from S e with confidence scores (0.0-0.1, 0.1-0.2, . . . , 0.9-1.0) § § . As a result, each system's output is represented by a sample of approximately 200 synonym pairs. Each sample (together with the supporting text context for each extracted pair) is given to two biology experts to judge the correctness of each extracted pair in the sample. Having computed the precision of the extracted pairs for each range of scores, we estimate precision at c as the average of the evaluated precision scores for each confidence range, weighted by the number of extracted tuples within each confidence score range.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Estimating recall</head><p>To compute the exact recall of a set of extracted synonym pairs S e , we would need to manually process the entire document collection to compile all synonyms in the collection. Clearly, this is not feasible. Therefore, we use a set of known correct synonym pairs that appear in the collection, which we call the GoldStandard. To create this GoldStandard, we use SWISSPROT. From this well structured database, we generate a table of synonymous gene and protein pairs by parsing the 'DE' and 'GN' § § If there are fewer than 20 extracted synonyms with the required confidence score, we select all of the ones that match. sections of protein profiles. Unfortunately, we cannot use this table as is, since some of the pairs may not occur at all in our collection. We found that synonym expressions tend to appear within the same sentence. Therefore, the GoldStandard consists of synonymous genes and proteins (as specified by SWISSPROT) that co-occur in at least one sentence in the collection, and were recognized by the Abgene tagger. We found a total of 989 such pairs.</p><p>Unfortunately, we found that we did not agree with many of these synonym pairs. We consider synonymous gene or protein names to be those that represent the same genes or proteins. However, SWISSPROT appears to consider a broader range of synonyms. For example, SWISSPROT synonyms included different genes or proteins that had a similar function, that belong to the same family, that were different subunits, and those that were functionally related <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Fig. 4)</ref>. Note that we judged the synonym pairs based solely on the information in our corpus and did not perform any biological experiments.</p><p>To create the GoldStandard, we asked six biology experts (all with PhDs in biology) to evaluate gene and protein pairs listed as synonyms in SWISSPROT, and judge whether they considered the pairs as synonyms. Each expert evaluated between 100 to 989 pairs. Each candidate synonym pair was judged by at least two experts, and was included in the GoldStandard if at least one of the experts agreed with the SWISSPROT classification ¶ ¶ . Experts disagreed with SWISSPROT on 318 pairs, and were unsure of additional 83. As a result, we included a total of 588 confirmed synonym pairs in the GoldStandard. The agreement was 0.61 among experts, 0.83 between experts and SWISSPROT, and 0.77 overall. The resulting GoldStandard is used to estimate recall as the fraction of the GoldStandard synonym pairs captured.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p>In this section we compare the performance of Similarity, Snowball, SVM, GPE, and Combined on the recall and precision metrics over the test collection described above. ¶ ¶ The evaluated synonym pairs are available at http://synonyms.cs.columbia. edu/SPROT/.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>i346</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Extracting synonymous gene and protein terms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>System</head><p>Tagging Similarity Snowball SVM GPE  The experiments were performed on a dual-CPU 1.2 Ghz Athlon machine with 2 Gb of RAM. We report the running times of each system in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 5</ref>. Note that the Tagging and preprocessing (i.e. identifying the gene and protein terms in the collection) were performed once for the complete collection, and were not required again for the subsequent experiments. <ref type="figure">Figure 6a</ref> reports recall of all systems. Similarity performs poorly, with recall less than 0.09 for all confidence scores. In contrast, Snowball and SVM have the highest recall for confidence scores below 0.4 (reaching 0.72 for Snowball and 0.38 for SVM), while GPE has the best recall (0.14) of any individual system for the higher confidence scores. Note that GPE always assigned the Conf (s) = 1 to all extracted candidate pairs, and is therefore represented by a single data point in each plot. Combined has the highest recall of all systems for all confidence scores. For example, at confidence score c = 0.4, Combined recall is more than double that of any individual system.</p><p>We report the precision of all systems for varying confidence scores in <ref type="figure">Figure 6b</ref>. Similarity has extremely low precision (less than 0.01) and therefore is not shown. Our experiments indicate that Similarity performed well for more common terms <ref type="figure">(Fig. 1</ref>), but performed poorly on identifying gene and protein synonyms as it tends to extract pairs of genes that are related, but not synonymous. Both Snowball and SVM extract synonyms with over 0.9 precision at their highest confidence scores. GPE also has the precision of 0.9. The confidence scores that both Snowball and SVM assign to their extracted pairs are correlated with the actual precision. For example, while the precision at c = 0.8 of Snowball is 0.9, precision at c = 0.1 is 0.1. Snowball has higher precision than SVM for all confidence score values. Also note that while both Snowball and SVM have sharp drops in precision between the confidence scores of 0.4 and 0.7, the Combined confidence score is more smooth, and appears to be a better predictor of the precision. <ref type="figure">Figure 6c</ref> reports the values of precision versus recall for all systems. Both Snowball and SVM clearly trade off precision for high recall. Even though Snowball is able to achieve the recall of almost 0.72, the corresponding precision is 0.07. In contrast, GPE has at most 0.14 recall. As we conjectured, combining these complementary approaches in Combined resulted in a significant gain: While Combined has the highest precision of all systems, it is also able to achieve the highest recall of 0.8.</p><p>To complement the reported recall figures, we also estimated the number of all real synonym pairs extracted by each system for each confidence score c <ref type="figure">(Fig. 6d)</ref>. These values were calculated by multiplying the number of pairs extracted by the system with the score ≥ c by the corresponding precision at c. Despite exhibiting lower precision values, Snowball and SVM extract a significantly larger set of real synonyms than GPE. Similarly, Combined extracts the largest estimated number of real synonyms. For example, we estimate Combined to have extracted almost 10,000 correct synonyms at the confidence score of 0.4, which is more than ten times the estimated number of synonyms extracted by Snowball, SVM, or GPE individually. In summary, Combined is the best performing system on all metrics, and significantly improves over the manually constructed GPE.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p>We evaluated the four different extraction approaches over a large collection of biological journal articles. Our extraction results are particularly valuable as we found that many of the synonyms that we extracted do not appear in SWISSPROT. Of the 148 extracted synonym pairs that were manually judged as correct by the experts during our evaluation, 62 (or 42%) were not listed as synonyms in SWISSPROT. This leads us to predict that out of the approximately 10 000 correct synonym pairs extracted by Combined with confidence score ≥ 0.4 <ref type="figure">(Fig. 6d)</ref>, we would find more than 4000 novel synonym pairs.</p><p>Our results show that machine learning-based approaches were responsible for the significant improvement of Combined over the manually constructed knowledgebased system. Snowball and SVM are-by design-more flexible, and therefore can detect cases on which GPE failed. For example, Snowball extracted the pair 񮽙EIF4G, P220񮽙 from the text fragment: '...eIF4G, also known as eIF4 or p220, binds both eIF4A...', which was not captured by GPE. While both SVM and Snowball contributed to the improved performance of Combined, Snowball has an additional advantage of generating intuitive human-readable patterns <ref type="figure">(Fig. 7)</ref> that can be potentially examined and filtered by a domain expert.</p><p>There are many ways to improve our system. For example, we found that the small number of negative examples significantly improved performance of Snowball. Further experiments on varying the size and composition of the initial example tuple sets may result in additional improvements. We do not differentiate between gene and protein terms with the same name, and it may be beneficial to apply the approach of ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Hatzivassiloglou et al., 2001</ref>) for disambiguation. We may also explore more ways to enhance gene and protein name entity identification, which is likely to further improve extraction quality. Our approaches extract synonyms from a collection of biological literature, and therefore the quality of the extracted relation depends in part on the collection consistency. We found some conflicting statements in our collections. For example, the following two statements are taken from two different articles in our test collection: while the first text fragment suggests that the proteins PC1 and PC3 are different substances, another article indicates that PC1 and PC3 are synonyms for the same substance:</p><p>' . . . the positive cofactors (pcs) pc1, pc2, pc3, and p15.' '. . . hydra pc1 (also called pc3) . . . '</p><p>Lacking additional information, it is difficult to make a decision whether PC1 and PC3 are synonyms. We plan to explore this problem further in our future work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>In this paper we have addressed an important problem of extracting gene and protein synonyms from biological literature. We have adapted and evaluated complementary synonym extraction approaches that span the spectrum from an unsupervised approach to a hand-crafted knowledge-based system. We performed a large-scale evaluation of the competing approaches which show that our extraction techniques can be used as a valuable supplement to resources such as SWISSPROT.</p><p>As part of our analysis, we discovered some inconsistent statements in the articles. In future work we may incorporate some of the proposed methods for resolving inconsistencies (e.g. ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Magnini et al., 2002</ref>), <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Krauthammer et al., 2002)</ref>). Additionally, we may incorporate work of <ref type="bibr">(Hatzi- vassiloglou et al., 2001</ref>) for disambiguation between genes and proteins that share the same name.</p><p>We speculate that the machine learning-based approaches for synonym identification, particularly Snowball, could be applied successfully for extracting other biological relations such as relationships between genes and proteins, small molecules, drugs, and diseases. We plan to explore this further in the future.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. The architecture of Snowball, a partially-supervised information extraction system.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Four types of apparent gene and protein relationships (with an example and literature context of each) that were designated by SWISSPROT as synonyms: Family Related, Subunits, Homologous, and Functionally Related.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Running times of Tagging, Similarity, Snowball, SVM, GPE (test collection).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 6 .Fig. 7 .</head><label>67</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Recall and precision of Similarity, Snowball, SVM, GPE, and Combined: Recall versus confidence score (a), Precision versus confidence score (b), precision versus recall (c), and the estimated number of correct synonym pairs extracted by each system versus confidence score (d).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Term t 1 List of the top ranked synonyms t 2 together with Sim(t 1 , t 2 ) multigene</head><label>t</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>superfamily (0.94) subfamily (0.92) subclass (0.89) 
definite 
unambiguous (0.94) unequivocal (0.92) rigorous(0.88) 
question 
intriguing (0.98) possibility (0.94) issue (0.90) 

Fig. 1. Some similar term sets extracted by the Similarity system 
from a biological journal archive. 

Generate Extraction Patterns 

Seed Tuples 

Generate New Seed Tuples 
Tag Entities 

Augment Table 

Find Occurrences of Seed Tuples 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Snowball: extracting relations from large plain-text collections</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Agichtein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gravano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the ACM International Conference on Digital Libraries</title>
		<meeting>the ACM International Conference on Digital Libraries</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combining labeled and unlabeled data with co-training</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Blum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ICML</title>
		<meeting>ICML</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracting patterns and relations from the WorldWide Web</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the SIGMOD Workshop on the Web and Databases (WebDB)</title>
		<meeting>the SIGMOD Workshop on the Web and Databases (WebDB)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relational learning of patternmatch rules for information extraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Califf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mooney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the AAAI Symposium on Applying Machine Learning to Discourse Processing</title>
		<meeting>the AAAI Symposium on Applying Machine Learning to Discourse Processing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unsupervised models for named entity classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Singer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Joint SIGDAT Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Very Large Corpora</title>
		<meeting>the Joint SIGDAT Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Very Large Corpora</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Contextual word similarity and estimation from sparse data. Computer, Speech and Language</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Dagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Marcus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Markovitch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ensemble methods in machine learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Dietterich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">LNCS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">WordNet: an Electronic Lexical Database</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fellbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genies: a natural-language processing system for the extraction of molecular pathways from complete journal articles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Friedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krauthammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rzhetsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward information extraction: identifying protein names from biological papers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fukuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tsunoda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Takagi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</title>
		<meeting>the Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="707" to="718" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disambiguating proteins, genes, and RNA in text: a machine learning approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Hatzivassiloglou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Duboue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rzhetsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="106" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic acquistion of hyponyms from large text corpora</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hearst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of COLING</title>
		<meeting>COLING</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovering missed synonyms in a large concept-oriented metathesaurus</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Srinivasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the AMIA Symposium</title>
		<meeting>the AMIA Symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="354" to="358" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The UMLS project: making the conceptual connection between users and the information they need</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Humphreys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lindberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bull. Med. Lib. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="170" to="177" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Making large-scale support vector machine learning practical</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Joachims</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Kernel Methods: Support Vector Machines</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Of truth and pathways: chasing bits of information through myriads of articles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krauthammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Iossifov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gomez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hripcsak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Hatzivassiloglou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Friedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rzhetsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="257" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wrapper induction for information extraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kushmerick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Weld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Doorenbos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI)</title>
		<meeting>the International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Word clustering and disambiguation based on co-occurrence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Abe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of COLING</title>
		<meeting>COLING</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic retrieval and clustering of similar words</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACL</title>
		<meeting>ACL</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mining terminological knowledge in large biomedical corpora</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Friedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</title>
		<meeting>the Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is it the right answer? exploiting web redundancy for answer validation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Magnini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Negri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Prevete</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tanev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACL</title>
		<meeting>ACL</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">STALKER: learning extraction rules for semistructured web-based information sources</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Muslea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Minton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Knoblock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of AAAI-98 Workshop on AI and Information Integration</title>
		<meeting>AAAI-98 Workshop on AI and Information Integration</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semi-supervised maximum entropy based approach to acronym and abbreviation normalization in medical text</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pakhomov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACL</title>
		<meeting>ACL</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hybrid text mining for finding abbreviations and their definitions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Byrd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of EMNLP</title>
		<meeting>EMNLP</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detecting gene symbols and names in biological texts: a first step toward pertinent information extraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Proux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rechenmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Julliard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Pillet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jacq</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Workshop on Genome Informatics</title>
		<meeting>Workshop on Genome Informatics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using information content to evaluate semantic similarity in a taxonomy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Resnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 14th International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI)</title>
		<meeting>the 14th International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatically generating extraction patterns from untagged text</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Riloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Thirteenth National Conference on Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the Thirteenth National Conference on Artificial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1044" to="1049" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning dictionaries for information extraction by multi-level bootstrapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Riloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Sixteenth National Conference on Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>the Sixteenth National Conference on Artificial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EDGAR: extraction of drugs, genes and relations from the biomedical literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Rindflesch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tanabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hunter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</title>
		<meeting>the Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple algorithm for identifying abbreviation definitions in biomedical text</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hearst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</title>
		<meeting>the Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning information extraction rules for semistructured and free text</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Soderland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Machine Learning</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page">34</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tagging gene and protein names in biomedical text</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tanabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wilbur</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1124" to="1132" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic extraction of protein interactions from scientific abstracts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Milward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ouzounis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pulman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</title>
		<meeting>the Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flexible phrase-based query handling algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wilbur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the ASIST</title>
		<meeting>the ASIST</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NYU: description of the Proteus/PET system as used for MUC-7</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yangarber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Grishman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Seventh Message Understanding Conference</title>
		<meeting>the Seventh Message Understanding Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unsupervised discovery of scenario-level patterns for information extraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yangarber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Grishman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tapanainen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Huttunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing ANLP-NAACL</title>
		<meeting>Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing ANLP-NAACL</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unsupervised word sense disambiguation rivaling supervised methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yarowsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the ACL</title>
		<meeting>the ACL</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PNAD-CSS: a workbench for constructing a protein name abbreviation dictionary</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yoshida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fukuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Takagi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping abbreviations to full forms in biomedical articles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Friedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hripcsak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Amer. Med. Inform. Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="262" to="272" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic extraction of gene and protein synonyms from medline and journal articles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Hatzivassiloglou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Friedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rzhetsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wilbur</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the AMIA Symposium</title>
		<meeting>the AMIA Symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="413" to="423" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
