<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T17:01+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">FGS+: OPTIMIZING THE JOINT SNR-TEMPORAL VIDEO QUALITY IN MPEG-4 FINE GRAINED SCALABLE CODING</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Raj</forename><forename type="middle">Kumar</forename><surname>Rajendran</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mihaela</forename><surname>Van Der Schaar</surname></persName>
							<email>mihaela.vanderschaar@philips.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Philips Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Shih-Fu</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
							<email>sfchang@ee.columbia.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Columbia University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">FGS+: OPTIMIZING THE JOINT SNR-TEMPORAL VIDEO QUALITY IN MPEG-4 FINE GRAINED SCALABLE CODING</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>To enable video transmission over heterogeneous wireless networks, a highly scalable compression and streaming framework that can adapt to large and rapid bandwidth variations in real-time is necessary. MPEG-4 Fine Grained Scalability (FGS) provides fine-grained SNR and temporal scalabilities, but these scalabilities are implemented and performed independently, thereby neglecting the gains that can be made from making joint SNR-temporal decisions to maximize quality. In this paper, a novel Fine Grained SNR-Temporal scalability framework called FGS+ that provides a new level of performance by considering SNR and temporal scalability jointly is presented. This new solution uses the results of our subjective tests, which indicate the levels to which SNR-quality needs to be enhanced before motion-smoothness should be improved. The study also reveals that these SNR-temporal tradeoff points vary among videos, and depend on the characteristics of the video. Based on these observations, our solution uses reference frames, enhanced relative to FGS, for prediction, improving visual quality over MPEG-4 FGS by up to 1.5 dB.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Real-time streaming of audiovisual content over wireless networks (GPRS, UMTS, WLANs etc.) is emerging as an important technology area in multimedia communications. Due to the wide variation of available bandwidth over short intervals in wireless sessions, there is a need for scalable video coding methods that allow streaming to flexibly adapt to changing network conditions in real-time. One such technique is MPEG-4 Fine-Granular Scalability (FGS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, which can adapt in real-time to bandwidth variations while using the same pre-encoded stream.</p><p>The key advantages of the MPEG-4 FGS framework -resilience and flexibility-come at the expense of lower video quality. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, the FGS performance is compared to a set of non-scalable streams coded at discrete bit-rates covering the same bandwidth range. The results obtained indicated a decrease in coding efficiency of up to 2-3 dB for FGS <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> .</p><p>In this paper, a novel scalable video-coding framework called FGS+ that improves the FGS coding efficiency is introduced. The basis of this new scheme lies in the realization that in the FGS framework, the SNR and temporal scalabilities are implemented and performed independently, neglecting that SNR-temporal tradeoffs should be made jointly for improved visual quality. First, we present the results of a subjective study that allows us to <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Although this type of comparison may seem to be unfair to FGS -the non-scalable streams are optimized for particular bit-rates whereas FGS covers the same range of bandwidth with a single enhancement-layer -this comparison provides insight into the theoretical limits of the FGS ratedistortion performance if the base-layer and enhancement-layer are independently coded and optimized. determine the optimal division of bits between SNR and temporal layers at different bit-rates. Based on this analysis, we conclude that to optimize overall visual quality, certain tradeoffs between the bandwidths allocated to spatial and temporal layers need to be established. For instance, at low transmission bit-rates, the SNRquality requires relatively larger improvement before motionsmoothness is improved (i.e. at low bit-rates, more bandwidth should be allocated to SNR-quality instead of temporal-quality). We then present an enhanced FGS scalability solution called FGS+ that uses these relationships to produce up to 1.5 dB gain compared with the MPEG-4 FGS framework. We tabulate the gains for various video sequences at different bit-rates.</p><p>The paper is organized as follows. Section 2 briefly describes MPEG-4 FGS scalability. Section 3 presents the results of our subjective study on FGS SNR-temporal-quality. Sections 4 and 5 present two variants of the improved FGS+ framework that include performance results and comparisons with MPEG-4 FGS. Section 6 outlines how FGS+ parameters for unseen videos can be chosen, and Section 7 draws conclusions. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">MPEG-4 FGS SNR-TEMPORAL SCALABILITY</head><p>This section briefly presents the MPEG-4 FGS framework (the user is referred to <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> for details) whose structure is portrayed in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1A</ref>. Under this framework, video content can be compressed to cover any bandwidth range [R min , R max ] by the use of two streams: a base-layer (BL) stream that is always transmitted and an enhancement-layer (EL), which is transmitted only as bandwidth allows. The base-layer bit-rate R BL is chosen for coding the baselayer (BL) such that the available bandwidth is almost certainly lower than R min at all times (i.e. R BL ≤ R min ). The FGS enhancement-layer (EL), which is progressively coded using a finegrained approach based on bit-plane DCT coding, improves upon the base-layer video, and supports both SNR and temporal scalability through a single pre-encoded stream. MPEG-4 FGS scalability therefore provides flexibility in supporting <ref type="figure">(Fig 1B)</ref>:</p><p>• Temporal scalability by increasing only the frame-rate.</p><p>• SNR scalability while maintaining the same frame-rate.</p><p>• Both SNR and temporal scalabilities.</p><p>However, no automatic mechanism for performing the optimal SNR-temporal tradeoff is standardized in MPEG-4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">JOINT SNR-TEMPORAL FGS+ ENCODING</head><p>As mentioned in the previous section, the MPEG-4 FGS server has two degrees of freedom: the temporal-quality or the SNRquality can be enhanced at each transmission bit-rate. However, SNR and temporal-quality are just two components of the overall video quality, and hence, only certain combinations of SNR and temporal quality will lead to maximal overall quality (as depicted in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2A</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fig. 2: (A) SNR-Temporal tradeoffs at various bit-rates. (B) SNRtemporal tradeoff for video-classes based on BL data</head><p>Since no standardized objective measure for determining the overall (SNR-temporal) quality of a coded sequence exists, we conducted a subjective quality assessment for evaluating the performance of various FGS SNR-temporal tradeoffs at four transmission bit-rates R t = (200,300,500,1000kbps) 2 for four 10-second CIF sequences from the MPEG-4 test suite. The four sequences were selected to cover a wide range of video characteristics. Their relative motion-vector magnitudes (MV) and I-frame TM-5 image-complexity values (Xi) are shown in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Foreman</head><p>Stefan  <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>: Relative values of motion-vectors and TM-5 complexity in the four videos used in testing</p><p>At each bit-rate R t , four videos with different frame-rates (5, 7.5, 10, 15 fps) and corresponding 3 SNR-quality were produced. The videos were synchronized and shown simultaneously to the twelve viewers who, at each bit-rate, selected the encoding perceived to have the best overall quality. The results, representing the average frame-rate chosen at each bandwidth are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.  3</ref>. The following conclusions can be drawn from the figure:</p><p>1. Until the SNR-quality improves to an acceptable level, the users prefer that the additional bandwidth be used to enhance the SNR-quality. Once SNR-quality has improved adequately, the preference is for improved temporal-quality (i.e. motionsmoothness). The curves vary substantially for different videos, and are correlated to the texture-complexity and motion-vector magnitude of the videos. For instance, spatially complex sequences such as Mobile require more bits to produce an image of satisfactory SNRquality, while videos with large motion-magnitude, such as Coastguard, require more temporal-quality at a lower bandwidth. Since the study indicates a clear preference for a specific allocation of bandwidth between SNR and temporal-quality at each bit-rate, the server can make optimal rather than ad-hoc choices about bandwidth allocation. Additionally, since this allocation path is pre-determined for a particular video, the encoder/transmitter and decoder/receiver can follow the same path in the SNR-temporal plane ( <ref type="figure">Fig. 2A)</ref> and will know the exact number of bits allocated to each frame at any bandwidth, as depicted in <ref type="figure">Fig.2B</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">FGS+ FOR B-FRAMES</head><p>This section describes our enhanced FGS+ framework, which uses the results of the study in Section 3 to provide "extended" reference frames for temporal B-frames in the enhancement-layer (EL).</p><p>Recall that in MPEG-4 FGS, the EL frames are solely predicted from the base-layer. This ensures that complete reference-frames are always received at the decoder, independent of bandwidth. However, these small references-frames reduce coding efficiency as temporal correlation between frames is only minimally exploited. In our schemes, the path the transmitter will take in the SNR-temporal-quality plane is known a-priori ( <ref type="figure">Fig. 2A)</ref>  </p><note type="other">EL stream Original Video Base Layer (BL) Encoder FGS Enhancement Layer (EL) Encoder BL stream</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MVs XIs</head><p>TrainedVideo Classifier</p><p>Tradeoffcurve (B) ChoosingTradeoff-C the second temporal B-frame, introduced at a higher bandwidth R t uses reference frames extended by a larger number of bits. Subsequently, this section answers the two questions that need to be addressed in implementing the GFS+ framework:</p><p>• At which bandwidths R k should temporal-frames be introduced (i.e. the frame-rate be increased)? • When a temporal-frame is introduced, what should be the optimal size of the extended-reference?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Introducing temporal-frames</head><p>We illustrate the procedure for introducing temporal-frames through an example. Assume that the base-layer frame-rate is F BL and that for the video being transmitted, the SNR-temporal subjective study has indicated that users prefer videos with framerates of F i until each enhancement-layer frame improves to a quality corresponding to B i bits (R i -R BL =B i *F i ), followed by frame-rates of F i+1 until each frame improves to B i+1 bits etc., where F 0 =F BL and R 0 =R BL 4 . Let us examine what happens when the current bandwidth changes to R N when the system is operating at a bandwidth R C corresponding to a frame rate of F C and a quality of B C bits/frame. In the MPEG-4 FGS scheme <ref type="figure">(Fig. 1B)</ref>, at the bandwidth R N , the transmitter can choose the best SNR-quality of (R N -R BL /F BL bits/frame, the best temporal-quality (determined by the number of FGS-temporal frames compressed at encoding time) or make any other SNR-temporal tradeoff in between. However, in the enhanced scheme <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Fig. 4A)</ref>, the transmitter takes a predetermined path with respect to dividing additional bandwidth between SNR and temporal-quality. When the bandwidth changes to R N , the transmitter first identifies k, such that F k *B k &lt; R N -R BL &lt; F k+1 *B k+1 and allocates (R N -R BL )/F k bits to each enhancement-layer frame. If F k &gt; F C , the transmitter will introduce new frames to increase the frame rate from F C to F k . <ref type="bibr">5</ref> . For instance, if R N for the Coastguard video changes to 300kbps, based on the results depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3</ref>, F N should be changed from 5 fps to 8 fps, yielding B N = (R N -R BL )/F N = 25 kb given R BL = 100kbps.</p><p>Note that in the new scheme, at frame-rate F k , the encoder and decoder are aware 6 that all frames have qualities corresponding to at least B k , such that the newly introduced temporal frames do not need to be predicted solely from the base-layer, but can be predicted from the extended reference frames of size B BL +B k . Adopting higher quality extended reference frames for FGS+ leads to an improved compression efficiency as will be shown in Section 4.3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Determining the size of the reference</head><p>The user-study indicates the bandwidths at which temporalquality should be improved by introducing new B-frames. However we do need to determine the optimal amount of extendedreference B BL +B i to use at each bandwidth R i . One approach to determine these optimal B BL +B i is empirical: plot the compression performance as a function of the extended-references B i at each bandwidth R i , and choose the extension B OPT that provides the best performance.</p><p>The compression performance (PSNR) of the encoded video for the Coastguard sequence is presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 2</ref>. It tabulates the PSNR improvement of each frame as a consequence of using varying amount of extended-references. At each bit-rate R i , the performance improves as we extend the reference-frames by adding more EL bit-planes (BP). However, if we use too many bit-planes as reference, the performance starts degrading because at that point, not all the additional bits used in enhancing the reference are transmitted; thus the decoder makes predictions based on incompletely constructed references. As R i increases, the number of bit-planes than can be used to improve the reference without a loss in performance increases. This is clearly seen in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 2</ref>, where at 300 kbps performance peaks at 2 bit-planes while at 1500 kbps performance falls off only after 4 bit-planes. So, for this video sequence, at a R i of 300 kbps, the optimal performance improvement is obtained by using 2 bit-planes of enhancement, while at a R i of 1000 kbps, the optimal choice is 3 bit-planes.  The SNR in dB for the Coastguard video as a function of the bit-rate and the number of bit-planes used as reference.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Kbps</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Performance</head><p>The improvement in performance of the B-frame only FGS+ scheme over traditional MPEG-4 FGS is presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 3</ref>. The videos had a base-layer bandwidth R BL or approximately 100 kbps, and contained one B-frame per P-frame <ref type="bibr">7</ref>   The maximum improvement in performance at different bit-rates for the B-frame case.</p><p>The number of FGS bit-planes used to enhance the base-layer was chosen by the empirical method outlined above and is given in parenthesis. The performance improvement ranges from 0.19 dB to 1.28 dB. Note that at low bit-rates spatially simple videos such as Coastguard benefit the most, while at higher bit-rates the spatially most complex sequence such as Mobile derive the largest improvement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">FGS+ FOR ALL-FRAMES</head><p>In the scheme depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 4B</ref>, only the temporal B-frames in the enhancement-layer use extended-reference for prediction. However, performance can be further improved by additionally using extended-references for the base-layer P-frames <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Fig. 5A)</ref>. Unlike the B-frame only case, depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 4A</ref>, the subjective study does not provide a guideline for the amount of enhancement to be used for P-frames prediction, as base-layer P-frames are present at all bandwidths. Therefore, we need a different approach to determine the amount of extended-reference to use for the P-frames. If we choose the amount of enhancement to be B T bits/frame corresponding to a bandwidth R T , there are always B T bits available for each I and P frame at bandwidths higher than R T . The performance at bandwidths higher than R T is enhanced due to the larger references used in predicting the P-frames, while at bandwidths lower than R T , performance degrades, as all B T bits are not transmitted resulting in incomplete references. This problem is compounded by prediction-drift, where the error in a P-frame is transmitted to all subsequent P-frames within the GOP and stops only at the next I-frame <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Hence, the advantages and drawbacks of choosing an enhancement of B bits/frame must be balanced, as illustrated in <ref type="figure">Fig</ref> One solution to finding the optimum R T is to calculate the probable magnitude of improvement given the choice of transmission bandwidth R T , and probability of transmission at bandwidth r to be p(r). Namely we maximize the expectation of quality improvement by choosing the optimal reference frame.</p><p>[ ]</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">            − = ∑ r old new T r PSNR r PSNR r p T F ) ( ) ( ) ( ) ( max</formula><p>After an optimum R T and the corresponding enhanced-reference level B T for the P-frames is chosen, all P-frames are predicted from BL frames enhanced to B T bits by the addition of EL bit-planes as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 5A</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Performance</head><p>The additional improvement in performance gained by using 3 bit-planes of enhanced references for the P-frames is shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table 4</ref>. For the complex sequence Mobile, the performance degrades marginally at low bit-rates indicating that all 3 additional bit-planes used in creating the enhanced-reference were not transmitted at 300 kbps. Note also that the complex sequences Stefan and Mobile benefit the most at high bandwidths. The results show that at 3 bit-planes the P-frame scheme adds -0.03 dB to 0.59 dB over the B-frame only scheme. Thus using both the B-frame and all-frame schemes result in overall improvements of 0. <ref type="bibr">16</ref>   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">CHOOSING PARAMETERS</head><p>The bandwidths R i at which new temporal frames are introduced, the number of bit-planes B i to use in enhancing the EL temporal references, and the number of bit-planes B T to use in enhancing the BL P-frame references vary, depending on the characteristics of a video. The characteristics that influence R i significantly are TM-5 complexity (Xi) and motion-vector magnitude (MV), while Xi largely influences the choice of B i and B T . Good choices of these values for unseen videos can be made by classifying videos based on values such as Xi and MV, then using the characteristic value of the class. Since Xi and MV are calculated in the BL by the encoder and decoder, no additional cost is incurred in this process (see <ref type="figure">Fig 2B)</ref>.</p><p>More detailed algorithms for choosing the appropriate parameters based on observing many video characteristics will be presented in future work. We will adopt content-based classification methods that predict adequate parameter classes based on the video features (such as MV &amp; Xi). Similar approaches have been used in predicting video traffic classes on rate-distortion curves in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>This paper has presented a fine-grained scalable encoding scheme referred to as FGS+ that produces gains of up to 1.5 dB over MPEG-4 FGS. In introducing fine-grained scalability MPEG-4 FGS paid a 2-3 dB cost. We show how more than half of that loss can be regained through an innovative view of video quality: we consider SNR-temporal-quality jointly rather than independently and determine their optimal combination at each bandwidth through a subjective study. This new solution uses the results of our subjective tests, which indicate the levels to which SNR-quality needs to be enhanced before motion-smoothness should be improved for optimal visual quality. Based on this observation, our solution uses improved base-layer frames to predict temporal-scalability frames instead of the base-layer frames in the original FGS scheme. Furthermore, the study revealed that different SNR-temporal tradeoffs videos should be made based on sequence characteristics at various transmission bit-rates. Since our tradeoff experiment is resolution dependent, we plan to conduct further studies that include resolution scalability along with temporal and SNR scalabilities.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>The</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 1. The FGS SNR-temporal scalability structure (A) and examples of its usage in supporting joint SNR-temporal scalability in a finegranular way (B).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 : SNR-Temporal preference curves for different videos.</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3: SNR-Temporal preference curves for different videos.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 : (A) The proposed scheme using optimized reference and (B) SNR-quality as bandwidth</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4: (A) The proposed scheme using optimized reference and (B) SNR-quality as bandwidth increases This path pre-determines the level to which the quality of each frame is improved before a new temporal-enhancement frame is introduced. Therefore, the newly introduced temporal frame can use extended-frames as reference, thereby producing smaller residues and improving compression efficiency. MPEG-4 FGS and the FGS+ scheme are illustrated in Fig. 1B and Fig. 4A. Note that while the temporal B-frames introduced first in FGS+ use reference frames extended by a small fraction of the bits present in the EL,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 : (A) All-frame scheme. (B) Effect on performance of choice of reference bandwidth T</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: (A) All-frame scheme. (B) Effect on performance of choice of reference bandwidth T</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Enhanced-reference 
scheme 

Scheme using fixed 
reference rate 

(B) SNR quality of enhanced-scheme 

Bandwidth 

SNR dB 

2T fps 
T fps 

4T fps 

3T fps 

Reference for 
2 nd B-frame 

Reference for 
1 st B-frame 

I 
P 

(A) B-FRAME ONLY SCHEME 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7" validated="false"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>The improvement in performance in SNR dB of the All-
Frame FGS+ over B-frame only FGS+ when 3 EL bit-planes are used 
to enhance the reference 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> The base-layer bit-rate RBL was 100 kbps. 3 Bits were divided among frames to maintain uniform SNR-quality.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> Note that for the base-layer, a different number of bits BBL is used for each frame to ensure constant quality among frames. 5 If frame-rates are changed abruptly, there will be a vertical drop in SNRquality rather than the horizontal change depicted in Fig 4(B). 6 If the SNR-temporal tradeoffs made by the encoder at different bit-rates are not known at the decoder, the encoded stream needs to indicate the size of the reference frames used for FGS+ prediction.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="7"> It should be noted that the P-frame performance does not change in this scheme, so the average B-frame improvement in performance is twice what is shown in Table 3.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The MPEG-4 FineGrained Scalable Video Coding method for Multimedia Streaming over IP</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Radha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Van Der Schaar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. on Multimedia</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A hybrid temporal-SNR FineGranular Scalability for Internet Video</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Van Der Schaar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Radha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. on CSVT</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motion-Compensation based Fine-Granular Scalability (MC-FGS)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Van Der Schaar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Radha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">MPEG-4 Contribution M6475</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Principles and Applications of Content-Aware Video Communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S.-F</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bocheck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE ISCAS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
