<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T17:01+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">PROMISE: Peer-to-Peer Media Streaming Using CollectCast</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><surname>Hefeeda</surname></persName>
							<email>mhefeeda@cs.purdue.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Purdue University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>47907</postCode>
									<settlement>West Lafayette</settlement>
									<region>IN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ahsan</forename><surname>Habib</surname></persName>
							<email>habib@cs.purdue.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Purdue University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>47907</postCode>
									<settlement>West Lafayette</settlement>
									<region>IN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Boyan</forename><surname>Botev</surname></persName>
							<email>botevbi@cs.purdue.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Purdue University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>47907</postCode>
									<settlement>West Lafayette</settlement>
									<region>IN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dongyan</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Purdue University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>47907</postCode>
									<settlement>West Lafayette</settlement>
									<region>IN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Bharat</forename><surname>Bhargava</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Purdue University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>47907</postCode>
									<settlement>West Lafayette</settlement>
									<region>IN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">PROMISE: Peer-to-Peer Media Streaming Using CollectCast</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>C25 [Computer-Communication Networks]: Local and Wide- Area Networks-Internet</term>
					<term>C24 [Computer-Communication Net- works]: Distributed Systems-Distributed Applications</term>
					<term>H35 [In- formation Storage and Retrieval]: Online Information Services- Data Sharing General Terms Design, Measurements, Performance Keywords Peer-to-Peer Systems, Multimedia Streaming</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present the design, implementation, and evaluation of PROMISE, a novel peer-to-peer media streaming system encompassing the key functions of peer lookup, peer-based aggregated streaming, and dynamic adaptations to network and peer conditions. Particularly, PROMISE is based on a new application level P2P service called CollectCast. CollectCast performs three main functions: (1) inferring and leveraging the underlying network topology and performance information for the selection of senders; (2) monitoring the status of peers and connections and reacting to peer/connection failure or degradation with low overhead; (3) dynamically switching active senders and standby senders, so that the collective network performance out of the active senders remains satisfactory. Based on both real-world measurement and simulation, we evaluate the performance of PROMISE, and discuss lessons learned from our experience with respect to the practicality and further optimization of PROMISE.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Peer-to-peer (or P2P) systems have gained tremendous momentum in recent years. In a P2P system, peers communicate directly with each other for the sharing and exchange of data as well as other resources such as storage and CPU capacity. Paralleling research in other aspects of P2P, such as lookup <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>, storage <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28]</ref>, and multicast <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32]</ref>, we in this paper focus on P2P real-time media streaming. Different from general P2P file sharing, P2P media streaming poses more stringent resource requirements for real-time media data transmission. However, as first addressed in our earlier work <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, for a media file of playback rate R0, a single sending peer may not be able or willing to contribute an outbound bandwidth of R0. Moreover, downloading the entire media file before playback is not the best solution, due to the potentially large media file size and thus long download time. As our solution, we propose a P2P media streaming model that involves multiple sending peers in one streaming session.</p><p>Despite recent research results of ours and others, a number of challenges intrinsic in P2P media streaming have not been addressed. In this paper, we present our solution to the following challenge: in a highly diverse and dynamic P2P network, how to select, monitor and possibly switch sending peers for each P2P streaming session, so that the best possible streaming quality can be maintained? The dynamics and diversity are reflected in both peers and network connections between peers: (1) a sender may stop contributing to a P2P streaming session at any time, (2) the outbound bandwidth contributed by a sender may change, (3) the connection between a sender and the receiver may exhibit different end-to-end bandwidth, loss, and failure rate, and more importantly (4) the underlying network topology determines that the connections between the senders and the receiver are not independent of each other, with respect to their loss and failure rate. As a result, the quality of a P2P streaming session depends on judicious selection of senders, constant monitoring of sender/network status, and timely switching of senders when the sender or network fails or seriously degrades. Unfortunately, previous works in P2P media streaming do not provide a systematic solution to the above challenge. For example, some previous works simply assume that a receiver receives media data from only one sender <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">9]</ref>. For the works that do assume multiple senders for one receiver <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>, there is no study on the selection of the best senders.</p><p>In this paper, we present the design, implementation, and evaluation of PROMISE, a novel and comprehensive peer-to-peer media streaming system. In designing PROMISE, we have developed a novel P2P service called CollectCast, which operates entirely at the application level but infers and exploits properties (topology and performance) of the underlying network. CollectCast has a pattern of "one receiver collecting data from multiple senders". Unlike other multiple-to-one network services such as concast <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>, each CollectCast session involves two sets of senders: the standby senders and the active senders. Members of the two sets may change dynamically during the session. CollectCast reflects the P2P philosophy of dynamically and opportunistically aggregating the limited capacity of peers to perform a task (streaming) traditionally performed by a dedicated entity (a media server). CollectCast realizes the functions of sender selection, monitoring, and switching, so that the receiver will observe minimum fluctuation of media streaming quality. We have performed both real-world measurements and simulations of PROMISE. Our results show that CollectCast-based P2P streaming achieves better performance than P2P streaming based only on end-to-end network performance information.</p><p>The rest of the paper is organized as follows. An overview of PROMISE is given in Section 2. The following three sections provide the details of PROMISE: peer selection in Section 3, rate and data assignment in Section 4, and dynamic switching in Section 5. We evaluate PROMISE through simulation in Section 6, and Internet experiments in Section 7. Section 8 discusses the related work. Finally, Section 9 concludes the paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">PROMISE: AN OVERVIEW</head><p>The PROMISE architecture consists of a set of peers interconnected through a P2P substrate <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 1</ref>). The P2P substrate maintains connectivity among peers, manages peer membership, and performs object lookup. PROMISE operations are independent of the underlying P2P substrate. Therefore, PROMISE can be deployed on top of P2P substrates such as Pastry <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, Chord <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, and CAN <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. We note that each of these P2P substrates returns only one peer for an object lookup request, if the object exists in the system. In our prototype, we have modified Pastry to return multiple peers for each lookup request. We used Pastry because it has been implemented <ref type="bibr">[14]</ref> and the code is written in Java with good portability.</p><p>Notations. We use bold symbols (e.g., p) to represent random variables and regular symbols (e.g., Rp) to represent constant values. An edge from node i to node j is denoted by i → j. A path with one or more edges from node x to node y is denoted by The playback rate of the media file is referred to as R0.</p><p>Peer characteristics. PROMISE assumes that peers exhibit heterogeneous characteristics and they do not have server-like capability: they contribute limited capacity, and may fail or reduce their sending rates unexpectedly. Therefore, multiple sending peers may</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Receiver Side</head><p>1. CAND ← P2PSubstrateLookup(fileId); 2. T ← BuildTopology(CAND, receiverId); 3. ACTV ← SelectPeers(T ); 4. while the session is not over do 5.</p><p>Connect(ACTV); /* Establish the streaming session */ 6. SendControlPackets(ACTV); 7.</p><p>needToSwitch ← false; 8.</p><p>while needToSwitch == false do 9.</p><p>needToSwitch ← ReceiveSegment(); 10.</p><p>end while 11.</p><p>T ← UpdateTopology(T , newMeasuredValues); 12.</p><p>ACTV ← SelectPeers(T ); 13. end while </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sender Side</head><p>1. /* Wait for a control packet */ 2. while this peer is an active supplier do 3.</p><p>ctrPkt ← ReceiveControlPacket(); 4.</p><p>rate ← GetAssignedRate(ctrPkt); 5.</p><p>dataToSend ← GetAssignedData(ctrPkt); 6. do 7.</p><p>SendData(dataToSend, rate); 8.</p><p>UpdateStatistics(); 9.</p><p>while no control packet received; 10. end while</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 3: CollectCast: Sender side</head><p>be needed to serve a requesting peer at any time. In order to capture the heterogeneous characteristics of peers, we associate each peer p with two parameters: offered rate Rp and availability p.</p><p>The offered rate is the maximum sending rate that a peer can (or is willing to) contribute to the system. A lower bound on the offered rate (R min p ) is imposed by the system to limit the maximum number of peers required to serve a request. This limits the number of concurrent connections (and hence the control overhead) that the requesting peer needs to maintain. The availability is the fraction of time a peer is available for serving. We represent the availability of peer p as a binary random variable p, with 1.0 indicating 'available for streaming' and 0.0 otherwise. The rate and availability information is collected by a daemon running in each participating peer. The rate could be a parameter set by the user during initial set up. The availability can either be set by the user or measured by collecting statistics during the regular operation of the peer. Statistics on how long a peer stays connected to the Internet and how much bandwidth used are easy to collect.</p><p>CollectCast and PROMISE. The design of PROMISE relies on a novel application level P2P service called CollectCast. CollectCast judiciously chooses the sending peers and orchestrates them in order to yield the best quality for the receiver. Specifically, CollectCast encompasses a number of techniques for: (1) selecting the best sending peers, (2) inferring and monitoring the characteristics of the underlying network, (3) assigning streaming rates and data segments to the sending peers, and (4) deciding when a change of the sending peers is needed. Details of each technique are given in subsequent sections. The functions of CollectCast are divided into receiver-side ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>) and sender-side <ref type="figure">(Figure 3</ref>) functions. The receiver plays the leading role in CollectCast. PROMISE operation. A streaming session in PROMISE is established as follows. A peer requesting a movie runs the receiver procedure shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>. The procedure first issues a lookup request to the underlying P2P substrate, which will return a set of candidate peers who have the movie. The candidate set typically contains 10 to 20 peers. The protocol then constructs and annotates the topology connecting the candidate peers with the receiver. Using the annotated topology, the selection algorithm determines the active sender set. The active set is the best subset of peers that is likely to yield the best quality for this streaming session. The rest of the candidate peers are kept in a standby sender set, from which replacement peers will substitute failed or degraded peers from the active set. Once the active set is determined, the receiver establishes parallel connections with all peers in the active set. Two connections are established with each peer. A UDP connection for sending the stream packets, 1 and a TCP connection for sending control packets. The receiver assigns a sending rate to each of the active senders based on the sender's offered rate and the goodness of the path from that sender to the receiver. The streaming session continues as far as there is no need to switch to a different active sending set. A switch is needed if a peer fails or the network path becomes congested. At which time, the topology is updated with new values measured passively during streaming and a new active set is selected. The sender role is simple: upon receiving a control packet, the sender determines the rate and the subset of data it is supposed to send. The sender keeps sending till a new control packet arrives with new assignment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">SELECTING BEST PEERS</head><p>The searching step returns a set of candidate peers from which the receiving peer chooses the active set to start streaming the movie. Three selection techniques are possible: random, end-to-end, and topology-aware. The random technique randomly chooses a number of peers that can fulfill the aggregate rate requirement, even though these peers may have low availability and share a congested path. The end-to-end technique estimates the "goodness" of the path from each candidate peer to the receiver. Based on the quality of the individual paths and on the availability of each peer, the technique chooses the active set. The end-to-end technique does not consider shared segments among paths, which may become bottlenecks if peers sharing a tight segment are chosen in the active set. In 1 Adjusting the rate of the UDP connection to compete fairly with TCP traffic of other applications is discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. contrast to the end-to-end technique, the topology-aware technique infers the underlying topology and its characteristics and . considers the goodness of each segment of the path. Thus, it can make a judicious selection by avoiding peers whose paths are sharing a tight segment.</p><p>Illustrative example. Consider the example shown in Figures 4 and 5. The lookup step returns peers P1, P2, . . . , P6 as a candidate set to the receiving peer Pr. The random technique may choose P1, P3, P4 as the active set, even though some of these peers have low availability (P1), and others share a congested path (P3, P4). The end-to-end technique considers the goodness of individual paths and the availability of peers. Therefore, it selects peers P3, P5, P6. It is not, however, aware of the shared segment between the two paths P5 ¡ Pr and P6 ¡ Pr, which can not afford the aggregate rate from P5 and P6. Finally, the topologyaware technique makes an informed decision, using the annotated topology, and selects the best set: P2, P3, P6.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Topology-Aware Selection</head><p>This section presents the details of the topology-aware selection technique. We first define the goodness topology and how it is annotated by network performance metrics (e.g., available bandwidth and loss rate) and peers characteristics (e.g., offered rate and availability). Then, we use the goodness topology to estimate the peer goodness for the session being established. Finally, we state the peer selection problem, formulate it as an optimization problem, and present an algorithm to solve it.</p><p>Goodness topology T . It is a directed graph that interconnects the candidate peers and the receiving peer ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>). Each edge (hereafter called a path segment, or simply a segment) i → j ∈ T is annotated with a goodness random variable i→j . Each leaf node represents a peer p from the set of candidate peers ¡ and has two attributes: a fixed offered rate Rp and a random variable p that describes the availability of p for streaming.</p><p>The goodness topology is built in two steps. In the first step, network tomography techniques are used to infer the approximate topology and annotate its edges with the metrics of interest, e.g., loss rate, delay, and available bandwidth. This is called the inferred topology. A segment in the inferred topology may represent a sequence of links with no branching points in the physical topology. This hides unnecessary details and yields a compact representation of the physical topology. We assume that routes from candidate peers to the receiver do not change during the course of the streaming session. This indicates that the inferred topology is a tree-structured graph rooted at the receiver. Previous studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">10]</ref> adopted the same assumption, which is backed by Internet measurement studies. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> indicates that the end-to-end Internet paths often remain stable for a significant period of time. More details on building the inferred topology are given in Section 3.3. The second step transforms the inferred topology to the goodness topology. The transformation process is basically computing a "logical" goodness metric for each segment from its properties.</p><p>Segment goodness. The segment goodness i→j is, in general, a function of one or more properties of the segment i → j, depending on the feasibility and ease of measuring these properties segment-wise. Segment properties may include loss rate, delay, jitter, and available bandwidth. In PROMISE, we represent the segment goodness as a function of the loss rate and available bandwidth because these two metrics: (1) can be measured segmentwise <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, and (2) are the most influential on the receiving rate, and hence on the quality. A segment with high available bandwidth and low loss is unlikely to introduce high jitter or long queuing delay. The goodness of segment i → j is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">i→j = wi→j ¢ i→j ,</formula><p>where wi→j is a weight that depends on the available bandwidth and level of sharing on segment i → j, and ¢ i→j is a binary random variable that depends on the loss rate.</p><p>¢ i→j is defined in terms of the packet loss rate as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">¢ i→j = 1, if a packet is not lost on i → j 0, otherwise (1)</formula><p>If the average loss rate on segment i → j is</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">¡ i→j , then the mean of ¢ i→j is: E[¢ i→j ] = ¢ i→j = 1 × (1 − ¡ i→j ) + 0 = 1 − ¡ i→j .</formula><p>The weight wi→j is determined by the available bandwidth on segment i → j (denoted by bi→j) and the aggregate rate from peers sharing this segment if they are selected in the active set. The segment weight is a per-peer metric, that is, the weight of segment i → j (and hence, its goodness) could differ for two peers sharing segment i → j. The weight of segment i → j for a peer p is denoted by w (p) i→j and is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">w (p) i→j = min ¢ 1, max(0, (bi→j − £ s∈S,i→j∈s¤ r Rs)/Rp)¥ , (2)</formula><p>where S is the set of peers selected to be in the active set thus far, and s ¡ r is the path from the sending peer s to the receiving peer r. The intuition behind this formulation is that, if a segment has a bandwidth equal to or higher than the aggregate rate contributed from peers sharing this segment, then this segment will not throttle this aggregate rate, and hence its weight is set to 1. Otherwise, the weight is a fraction proportional to the shortage in the bandwidth if peer p along with peers in S are chosen to serve. The example given later in this section explains numerically how to compute these weights.</p><p>Peer goodness. We define the goodness of a peer p, Peers with high expected goodness values (close to 1) indicate that these peers are likely to provide good and sustained sending rate. This is because they are unlikely to stop sending packets and these packets will be transmitted through network paths of low dropping probability.</p><p>Best active peers set. This is the subset of peers that are likely to provide the "best" quality to the receiver. The perceived quality is quantified by the aggregated receiving rate. We are now ready to state the selection problem:</p><p>Active Peers Selection Problem. Given the annotated goodness topology T , find the set of active peers ¡ actv ⊆ ¡ that maximizes the expected aggregated rate at the receiver, provided that the receiver inbound bandwidth is not exceeded.</p><p>Mathematically, this can be phrased as: find</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">¡ actv that Maximizes E ¨ © £ p∈ actv ¦ pRp (4) Subject to R l ≤ £ p∈ actv Rp ≤ Ru,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>where ¦ p and Rp are the goodness and offered rate of peer p, respectively, and R l , Ru are the lower and upper rate targets. Section 4 shows how R l , Ru are determined.</p><p>Selection algorithm. Given the problem formulation above, finding the best active set ¡ actv is straightforward. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 6</ref> describes an algorithm to determine ¡ actv given the goodness topology T . The algorithm determines the expected aggregated rate for all possible active sets and selects the one with the highest rate. There are several code optimization possibilities which are not discussed for the sake of clarity.</p><p>Complexity. The selection algorithm enumerates all possible sets that satisfy the constraints in (5). However, the input (the candidate set) to the algorithm is fairly small (10 to 25 peers from which we choose 3 to 5 active peers). Checking the constraints in (5) is a matter of adding a few numbers and comparing with the bounds. Many sets will be disqualified by the constraint. For the remaining qualified sets, selecting the best among them is also a simple computation. In addition, the selection algorithm is invoked only a few times: at the beginning of the session and when a peer switching is needed. In our implementation, PROMISE calls the selection algorithm no more than five times during a 60-minute streaming session, and each call takes a few tens of milliseconds on a reasonable PC. Therefore, although designing more efficient selection algorithms is possible, we believe that the payoff will not be significant.</p><p>Complete example. This examples shows the details of selecting the best peers in the topology shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>. To simplify the discussion, we set R l = Ru = R0 and the loss rate in all path segments to 0, that is, ¢ i→j = 1, ∀i, j. The playback rate R0 is 1 Mb/s. The possible active sets that satisfy the constraints in 5 are: {P4, P6}, {P3, P5, P6}, {P2, P5, P6}, {P1, P5, P6}, {P3, P4, P5}, {P2, P4, P5}, {P1, P4, P5}, {P1, P3, P4}, {P2, P3, P4}, {P2, P3, P6}, {P1, P3, P6}, {P1, P2, P4}, {P1, P2, P6}, and {P1, P2, P3, P5}. The expected aggregated rate is then computed for every set. For instance, the expected aggregated rate for {P3, P5, P6} is 1 × .8 + 1 × .8 + .25/.50 × .9 = 2.05. P5 and P6 have a shared segment (5 → 3) of bandwidth .5. If we assign w (P 5 ) 5→3 = 1 (because the available bandwidth on the path is greater than P5's offered rate), P6 will get a left-over bandwidth of 0.25, which makes the weight w (P 6 ) 5→3 = 0.25/0.50. If we assign the w (P 6 ) 5→3 = 1, P5 gets a weight of 0 because no bandwidth is left for this peer on the shared segment. We consider all combinations of ordered peers in a particular peer set to maximize the expected rate. The expected rate of all possible sets are 1.4, 2.05, 1.95, 1.45, 1.85, 2.0, 1.5, 1.75, 1.25, 2.4, 1.9, 1.2, 1.6, and 2.3, respectively. The highest aggregate rate comes from the set {P2, P3, P6}.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Selection Algorithm</head><p>1. Enumerate all possible sets that satisfy constraints in (5): </p><formula xml:id="formula_5">¡ 1 , ¡ 2 , . . . , ¡ M . 2. ¡ actv = null; maxE = 0 3. for each ¡ m , 1 ≤ m ≤ M do 4. Set difi→j = bi→j , ∀i → j ∈ T 5. E = 0 6. for each p ∈ ¡ m do 7. Gp = p 8. for each segment i → j ∈ p ¡ r do 9. Gp = Gp × min(1, ¢ i→j × difi→j /Rp) 10. difi→j = max(0, difi→j − Rp) 11. endfor 12. E = E + Gp</formula><note type="other">13. endfor 14. if E &lt; maxE then 15. maxE = E 16.</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">End-to-End Selection</head><p>Instead of building the underlying topology, the end-to-end technique uses the end-to-end path bandwidth and loss rate in addition to peer availability. It exploits no information about the path segments shared among peers and therefore imposes less overhead than the topology-aware selection. However, as our evaluation shows (Section 6), while better than random selection, it does not perform as well as the topology-aware selection. We can formulate the endto-end selection as a special case of the topology-aware selection as follows. Instead of writing the peer goodness as in Equation <ref type="formula">(3</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_6">wp¤ r = 1, Rp ≤ bp¤ r Rp−bp¡ r Rp , otherwise<label>(6)</label></formula><p>Using this formulation, the expected rate maximization problem can be solved in a way similar to the one in Section 3.1.</p><p>Example. The parameters in this example are the same as in the example in Section 3.1. Thus, the possible active sets are also the same. The end-to-end selection utilizes the availability of peers and the path available bandwidth to calculate the expected rate. For example, the expected rate of the set {P3, P5, P6} is 1 × .8 + 1 × .8 + 1 × .9 = 2.5. The corresponding expected rate of all possible sets are 1.4, 2.5, 2.4, 1.9, 2.1, 2.0, 1.5, 2.0, 1.5, 2.4, 1.9, 1.4, 1.8, and 2.5, respectively. The maximum expected rate is 2.5, which is supplied by peer sets {P3, P5, P6} and {P1, P2, P3, P5}. Either of them can be taken, but we prefer the set with fewer peers to reduce the overhead of maintaining multiple concurrent connections.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Topology Inference</head><p>In this section, we describe our approach to inferring an approximate topology just sufficient for peer selection. Discovering the interior characteristics of the network by probing only from its end points is called network tomography <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref>. Our approach is a mix of a number of modified versions of known techniques. Our modifications significantly reduce the overhead and lead to a much shorter convergence time. We first construct the logical topology, and then we annotate it with the available bandwidth and loss rate. More details can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</p><p>Building the logical topology. This is a straightforward step in which a tool like traceroute is used to build the physical topology. Traceroute is performed in parallel from all the candidate peers to the receiver. Then, consecutive links with no branching points are merged together into one segment, resulting in the logical topology. We note that some routers do not support traceroute. This, however, does not severely harm the technique because we are not interested in the exact topology, but in the shared segments among peers.</p><p>Annotating the topology with available bandwidth. Let us first precisely define the end-to-end available bandwidth of a path. As spelled out by <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, it is the maximum rate that the path can provide to a flow, without reducing the rate of other traffic. The link with the minimum available bandwidth (i.e., the tight link) determines the path available bandwidth. Measuring the path available bandwidth is costly: one should keep increasing the probing traffic rate till at least it reaches (probably exceeds) the available bandwidth on the tight link. Measuring the available bandwidth on individual path segments is even more costly. Our approach trades-off the unnecessary accuracy of available bandwidth for far less overhead. It accomplishes this through three ways: (1) instead of measuring the path available bandwidth, we test whether a path can accommodate the aggregated rate from peers sharing this path. This rate is at most R0. R0 is typically less than 1 Mb/s, (2) we conservatively label all segments of a path with the value of its tightest segment, and (3) we construct the probing packets from the actual data (i.e., data from the media file that will be sent anyway).</p><p>Jain and Dovrolis <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> show that the one-way delay differences of a periodic packet stream is a good indication of the available path bandwidth between two nodes. The idea is that if the streaming rate is higher than the available bandwidth, the one-way delay difference will show a trend of increase. This is because packets will be queued at the tight link. On the other hand, if the streaming rate is lower than the available bandwidth, the one-way delay difference will be zero. Then, to measure the bandwidth, the sender sends a stream of packets with a specific rate. The receiver measures the trend in the delay difference and decides whether the next stream rate should be increased or decreased by a factor of 2. The procedure continues till the available bandwidth is estimated within the desired range of accuracy. We make two adaptations to the basic procedure. First, we set the initial stream rate as the minimum possible offered rate (R min p ) from a peer. And we terminate whenever the stream rate reaches the minimum of R0 and the aggregate rate from peers sharing the path. Second, since one peer may not be able to send at rate R0, we coordinate the probing from multiple peers to get the same effect as probing from one sender.</p><p>Annotating the topology with loss rate. Instead of explicitly probing for segment-wise loss rates, we leverage the information obtained during available bandwidth measurements. The receiver assigns the sending rate to each of the sending peers. It also determines which data packets should be sent by each peer. Therefore, it is easy to determine the loss rates on individual end-to-end paths. To compute the segment-wise loss rates, we use the recently proposed Bayesian inference using Gibbs sampling method <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. The method models the network tomography (for segment-wise loss rates) as a Bayesian inference problem. Then, using the measured data and an assumed initial distribution for the segment losses, the method iteratively computes the posterior distribution of the segment losses <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</p><p>Overhead estimation. We consider two types of overhead: processing and communication. The communication overhead is due to the probing packets. However, as noted above, we send actual data packets as probes. Thus, effectively, we do not introduce communication overhead. The receiver, though, needs a larger buffer (in the order of seconds) to store these data packets for later use. The processing overhead is mainly due to topology inference and peer selection. This is not much of a concern, given that the topology will typically be very small (10 to 20 nodes). Finally, we note that building the topology and determining the best active set will increase the start up delay, which is the initial time before starting playing back the media file. However, it is still in the order of seconds.</p><p>Discussion. Ideally, CollectCast will leverage some public Internet measurement facilities, if they are widely deployed. CollectCast can query the measurement facility about the network conditions of the paths connecting the candidate peers with the receiver. The measurement facility will be utilized by many users and applications. Therefore, more accurate measurements can be performed and the overhead will be amortized over all applications. Recently, Internet measurement facilities have started to appear in the literature, see for example <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">RATE AND DATA ASSIGNMENT</head><p>In this section, we first explain the role of FEC in our system. Then, we describe how the rate and data are assigned to each peer in the active set.</p><p>Forward Error Correction (FEC) in PROMISE. We use erasure codes (also known as FEC in the network community) to tolerate packet losses due to network fluctuations and limited peers reliability. The media file is divided into equal-length data segments. Each segment has a size of ∆ original packets and is protected using FEC separately. Several FEC techniques such as Reed-Solomon codes and Tornado codes <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> can be used. We use Tornado codes because they are faster to encode/decode, albeit with little decoding inefficiency <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. We use the notation F EC(α) to indicate that the system can tolerate up to (α − 1)% packet loss rate. For instance, F EC(1.25) means that a data segment will be successfully reconstructed even if 25% of the sent packets were lost. α is the parameter that defines the current (packet) loss tolerance level in the system. α has two bounds: αu, α l , which are the maximum and minimum loss tolerance levels, respectively. These bounds impact the selection of active peers determined by solving the maximization problem (Section 3.1) because the bounds (R l , Ru) in the constraints (5) are computed as: Ru = αuR0 and R l = α l R0.</p><p>Data segments stored at peers are pre-encoded using F EC(αu). A segment of ∆ packets is encoded into ∆/(2 − αu) packets. For instance, F EC(1.25) on a segment of size 120 packets results in a 160 encoded packets, from which any 120 can reconstruct the original segment. Even though data segments are pre-encoded with αu, we do not send at aggregated streaming rate of αuR0 all the time. Rather, we send at αR0, α l ≤ α ≤ αu. α is estimated based on the current expected aggregated loss rate ¢ ¡ using: </p><formula xml:id="formula_7">α = max(α l , 1 + min(αu, 1 + ¡ )).<label>(7)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_8">Rp = αR0 £ x∈ actv Rx Rp.<label>(8)</label></formula><p>Data assignment. The active peers collectively send the media file segment by segment: they all cooperate in sending the first segment, then the second one, and so on. Note that, since the active peers send at rate αR0, they send only ∆/(2 − α) packets out of the stored ∆/(2 − αu) packets. Each peer p is assigned a number of packets Dp to send in proportion to its actual streaming rate:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">Dp = £ ∆ (2 − α) Rp αR0 ¤ .<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Example. Let α l = 1.0625, and αu = 1.25. Assume that the media file is divided into segments each with 120 packets. Encoding with F EC(αu = 1.25), each encoded segment will have 160 packets. Suppose that the current active set has three peers P1, P2, P3 with offered rates RP 1 = R0/2, RP 2 = R0/4, RP 3 = R0/2, respectively. Assume that the current estimated α is 1.125. Therefore, the assigned rates are:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">RP 1 = 0.45, RP 2 = 0.225, RP 3 = 0.45.</formula><p>The number of packets that need to be sent is 138, and the data assignment is: DP 1 = 55, DP 2 = 28, DP 1 = 55. Peer P1 sends packets with sequence numbers from 1 to 55, peer P2 from 56 to 83, and peer P3 from 84 to 138.</p><p>Discussion. Packet losses in the Internet is known to be bursty, which has a negative effect on the FEC techniques: during a loss burst, the number of lost packets may exceed what FEC can recover. However, authors of <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> have shown that streaming from multiple senders, as in our case, alleviates the effect of loss burstness on FEC. In our usage of FEC, the number of redundant packets sent is proportional to the current loss rate. If loss rate is low (which is a typical case), only a small number of extra packets will be sent, saving network bandwidth. Finally, we note that the data is pre-encoded. Therefore, senders will not have to encode them on the fly. The receiver decodes them on the fly. Tornado codes are quite fast (order of millisecond for decoding), especially when the segment size is small.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">DYNAMIC SWITCHING</head><p>During a long streaming session the environment may change: peers may fail or network paths may become congested. To maintain good streaming quality on the receiver side, we need to adapt to these changes. During the session, the receiver collects statistics on the loss rate and streaming rate contributed from each sending peer. These statistics are used to update the goodness topology, which is then used to adjust the active set.</p><p>Peer failure. A peer failure is detected in two ways: (1) from the TCP control channel established between the receiver and each of the sending peer (e.g., connection reset), and (2) if the rate coming from this peer is degraded. Once a failure is detected, the active set is adjusted by replacing the failed peer with new one(s). We choose the replacement peers using the topology-aware selection (Section 3.1), provided that the currently good peers are part of the new active set. This may not yield a globally optimal solution, but it is more practical for two reasons. First, the newly chosen set can be totally different from the old one, which will require tearing down all of the old connections and establishing new ones. Second, notice that the topology is partially updated, since for the standby peers, we use the information gathered at the beginning of the streaming session. Thus, it is better to keep peers that are currently doing well. After determining the new active set, the receiver sends a control packet to each peer in the set. The control packets contain the rate and data assignment, computed as explained in Section 4, for each peer.</p><p>Network fluctuations. The receiver procedure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Figure 2</ref>) makes a switching decision after receiving each segment of the media file. A  segment is in the order of few seconds. Switching means one of two actions: (1) assigning new rates for the currently active peer set, or (2) adjusting the active set by adding or replacing peers. After receiving a segment, the receiver computes γ = (R¡ − R0)/R0, where R¡ is the aggregate rate measured during the last segment. A value of γ &lt; 0 means that the network is dropping more than the current loss tolerance level α allows. In this case, the receiver tries to increase α to reach the desired R0. It computes a new value for α using the updated topology. If the new α exceeds the upper bound αu, a new active set is selected using the topology-aware selection. Otherwise, a new rate and data assignment is computed using the new α. If γ is positive but less than a threshold (e.g., 0.1), we do nothing: the current setting is good to achieve the target rate with a reasonable FEC overhead. If γ is larger than the threshold, a decrease in α is appropriate. A new smaller α is computed and used to assign rate and data to peers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">EVALUATION</head><p>In this section, we evaluate the performance of PROMISE using extensive simulations. Results from Internet experiments are presented in Section 7.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Simulation Setup</head><p>Hierarchical topology. The topology used in the simulation has three levels. The highest level is composed of transit domains, which represent large Internet Service Providers (ISPs). Stub domains; which represent small ISPs, campus networks, moderatesize enterprise networks, and similar networks; are attached to the transit domains on the second level. Some links may exist among stub domains. At the lowest level, the end hosts (peers) are connected to stub routers. The first two levels are generated using  the GT-ITM tool <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>. We then, probabilistically add hosts to stub routers. Each experiment was run on several different topologies. The topologies used in the experiments have, on average, 600 routers and 1,000 hosts (peers). Simulation parameters. Imposing cross traffic over such a large topology is not feasible. Instead, we approximate the effect of cross traffic by: (1) attaching a stochastic loss model to the links, and (2) randomly setting the links bandwidth to capture the available bandwidth on them. We use the two-state Markov loss model (aka Gilbert model), which was shown to model the Internet packet losses with a reasonable accuracy <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>. In this model, the loss process is modeled as a Markov chain with two states: good and bad. In the good state, the probability of losing a packet is very small and typically assumed to be zero. In the bad state, the probability of losing packets is assumed to be 1.0. The model has two parameters, which are the transition probabilities between the good and bad states.</p><p>The available bandwidth on each link is chosen uniformly at random in the range [0.25R0, 1.5R0]. Peers' parameters are chosen to reflect the diversity in the P2P community <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. The availability of peers ( No peer can support more the R0/2 and many of them provide a small fraction of R0. The streaming session lasts for 60 minutes and the streaming rate R0 is 1 Mb/s. Every experiment is performed 100 times with different seeds, and the results are averaged over all runs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Performance of the Topology-Aware Selection</head><p>A streaming session is simulated as follows. First, we randomly select a number of candidate peers (e.g., 20 peers) and a receiver from the the 1,000-peer community. Then, we select the active peer set using either the random, end-to-end, or topology-aware selection (Section 3). Each session is run three times with the same parameters, albeit each run with a different peer selection algorithm. Peers in the active set start streaming till a switching is needed. The loss tolerance level αu is set to 1.2. We are interested in measuring two metrics: the aggregated loss rate and the aggregated streaming rate perceived by the receiving peer. These two metrics are important since they determines the media playback quality.</p><p>Results with no peer failures. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 7</ref> depicts the aggregate loss rate seen by the receiver for the three selection techniques. The topology-aware selection achieves lower loss rate (13%) than those of end-to-end (17%) and random (18%) selection. The aggregated loss rate is high in this experiment because we set the available bandwidth on the links in the range [0.25, 1.5] Mb/s. We do that to stress the selection techniques. The aggregated rate perceived by the receiver is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 8</ref>. The topology-aware technique yields a steady aggregated rate of 1.0 Mb/s, which achieves full playback quality. The end-to-end technique performs better than the random technique. However, neither of them can achieve full playback rate. This shows the importance of supplying peer selection under the same peer and network conditions. Similar results have also been obtained under other topologies and different loss rate and available bandwidth.</p><p>Results with peer failures. During the streaming session, a peer may fail with a probability that is inversely proportional to its availability. We simulate peer failures as follows. We schedule a fixed number of failure trials at random times throughout the streaming session. At each failure trial, a peer is selected randomly from the active set and we fail it probabilistically according to its availability: we generate a random number between 0 and 1. If this number is greater than the peer's availability, the peer is failed. Otherwise, the peer remains active and the session continues normally till the next failure trial. The intuition behind this failing method is that if we have many failure trials, each peer will get enough trials to be tested. The fraction of the 'no-failure' trials will approximately be its availability.</p><p>Figures 9 and 10 show the aggregated loss rate and the aggregated streaming rate, respectively, in the presence of peer failures. The topology-aware selection still performs better than the other two techniques, achieving a lower loss rate and maintaining full playback quality. Note that, in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref>, the aggregated rate is slowly decreasing as the session progresses. This is because as the time elapses, more peers fail and the selection technique is left with fewer peers in the standby set to choose from. This suggests that if we expect many peer failures, the candidate set should be large enough in order to maintain full playback quality, and the size of the candidate set should be chosen properly.</p><p>Size of candidate set. In this experiment, we estimate the size of the candidate set for different values of peers availability. We vary the average availability of peers from 0.1 to 0.9. A total of 25 failure trials are scheduled during each streaming session. If a failure trial is successful (i.e., we fail a peer), a replacement peer (or peers) will be chosen. We run the simulation 10 times for each value of peer availability and count the total number of peers that are needed to complete the session. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref> shows the impact of peer availability on the size of candidate set. The figure shows the average number of successful failure trials (out of 25) and the minimum, mean, and maximum number of peers required in the candidate set as the average availability grows from 0.1 to 0.9, over the 10 simulation runs. For example, for an average peer availability of 0.6, we need an average of 11 peers in the candidate set, and a maximum of 14 will guarantee that we will not run of out peers in the candidate set. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref> shows that as the availability increases, the number of peers needed in the candidate set decreases. We are deriving a more rigorous and generic relation between the size if candidate set and peer availability based on streaming session duration, peer failure model, and network failure model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">INTERNET EXPERIMENTS</head><p>A prototype of PROMISE has been implemented and tested in both local and wide area environments. We have modified Pastry (code obtained from <ref type="bibr">[14]</ref>) to support multiple peer lookup. PROMISE is implemented in Java. The code runs as an agent in each participating peer.</p><p>We install several PROMISE agents on remote sites located in North America and Europe. Due to space limitation, we present a sample of the experimental results. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12</ref> shows an experiment in which multiple failure-prone peers serve a streaming session. The receiver is located at Purdue University. Six candidate peers were chosen for this streaming session: purdue1 and purdue2 at Purdue University but in two different subnets, uconn at University of Connecticut, gatech at Georgia Institute of Technology, uiuc at University of Illinois, and toronto at University of Toronto. The active set initially has four peers: purdue1, purdue2, uconn, and gatech. The aggregate streaming rate is 450 Kb/s. After 385 seconds, we fail purdue2. PROMISE detects the failure and purdue2 is replaced by uiuc. The switching is fast and it does not affect the aggregated rate. Another failure is scheduled at time 780. This experiment, although simple, serves as a proof of concept: streaming from multiple heterogeneous and unreliable peers is feasible and high streaming quality can be achieved.</p><p>We are currently testing PROMISE on PlanetLab <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, a largescale wide area overlay infrastructure. Initial results are available in the extended version of this paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">RELATED WORK</head><p>In the last few years, the P2P paradigm has received tremendous attention from researchers. Two main categories of research can be identified: research on protocols and algorithms ( such as searching and replication), and research on building P2P systems. The first category aims at building scalable and efficient P2P infrastructure (substrate), which could be used for systems in the second category. Lookup (or routing) protocols such as CAN <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, Chord <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, and Pastry <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> guarantee locating the requested object within a logarithmic number of steps, if the object exists in the system. However, network locality has not been amply exploited (except Pastry). Examples of P2P systems include CFS <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref> on top of Chord <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, and PAST <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> on top of Pastry <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. Another example is Pixie <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>: a P2P content exchange architecture. Pixie aggregates requests from multiple peers and multicasts content to the requesting peers. These systems do not target media streaming. Therefore, unlike PROMISE, they do not consider real-time and sending rate requirements for P2P data transmission.</p><p>Application level multicast (ALM) is proposed to overcome the limited deployment of IP multicast. Each ALM-based system has its own protocol for building and maintaining the multicast tree. For example, both NICE <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> and Zigzag <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> adopt hierarchical distribution trees and therefore scale to a large number of peers. Narada <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref>, on the other hand, targets small scale multi-sender multi-receiver applications. Narada maintains and optimizes a mesh that interconnects peers. The optimized mesh yields good performance but it imposes maintenance overhead. SpreadIt <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref> constructs a distribution tree rooted at the sender for a live media streaming session. A new receiver joins by traversing the tree starting at the root till it reaches a node with sufficient remaining capacity. CoopNet <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> supports both live and on-demand streaming. It employs multi-description coding and constructs multiple distribution trees (one tree for each description) spanning all participants. SplitStream <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref> provides a cooperative infrastructure that can be used to distribute large files (e.g., software updates) as well as streaming media. SplitStream is built on top of Scribe <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref>, a scalable publish-subscribe system that employs Pastry <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> as the lookup substrate. The content in SplitStream is divided into several stripes, each is distributed by a separate tree. Different from these systems, PROMISE is proposed for the streaming of media data from multiple senders to one receiver. And CollectCast is another P2P service complementing the ALM service.</p><p>Many P2P data sharing and distribution systems implicitly assume that a sending peer is capable of supporting one or more receiving peers. However, it has been shown that peers are heterogeneous in their capability and/or willingness to contribute resources to other peers <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. Few systems have considered the problem of selecting multiple supplying peers (senders) for a receiver, based on peer heterogeneity as well as network topology and conditions. PROMISE addresses this problem.</p><p>The distributed video streaming framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20]</ref> shows the feasibility and benefits of streaming from multiple servers to a single receiver. The receiver uses a rate allocation algorithm to specify the sending rate for each server in order to minimize the total packet loss. This specification is based on estimating the end-to-end loss rate and available bandwidth between the receiver and each server. However, the framework is not explicitly designed for P2P environments. Therefore, it does not address the selection and dynamic switching of senders.</p><p>Finally, Rodrigues and Biersack <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> show that parallel download of a large file from multiple replicated servers achieves significantly shorter download time. The subsets of a file supplied by each server are dynamically adjusted based on the network conditions and the server load. This work targets bulk file transfer, not real-time media streaming. Moreover, it does not consider sender selection nor does it leverage network tomography techniques.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>This paper presents a novel and comprehensive P2P media streaming system, PROMISE. The most salient features of PROMISE include: (1) it accounts for peer heterogeneity, reliability, and limited capacity, (2) it matches a requesting peer with a set of supplying peers that are likely to achieve the best streaming quality, (3) it dynamically adapts to network fluctuations and peer failure, and (4) it performs (2) and (3) by inferring and leveraging the underlying network conditions. These features are brought into PROMISE via a new application level P2P service called CollectCast. Through simulations and Internet experiments, we show that streaming from multiple failure-prone peers in a dynamic P2P environment is indeed feasible. Specifically, we show that the full quality can be maintained in the presence of failures and losses. Our simulations demonstrate that significant gain in streaming quality can be achieved by our topology-aware peer selection technique.</p><p>PROMISE can be extended in several directions. First, CollectCast can be tuned to compete fairly with TCP traffic and react to congestion in the network. Second, large-scale testing of PROMISE will demonstrate its practicality and may hint several refinements and adjustments of the CollectCast functions. Initial results on these issues can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. Finally, CollectCast can be extended beyond the physical network characteristics and streaming applications. For example, CollectCast may take peers' social properties such as credibility and trustworthiness into consideration. One can imagine a graph showing the topology formed by the candidate suppliers and the receiver, but the links are labeled with trust-related metrics. This will enable security-sensitive applications to choose the best peers that will supply the most trusted data or service.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 : PROMISE architecture: Peers are interconnected through a P2P substrate (e.g., Pastry, Chord). For each ses- sion, multiple sending peers cooperate to serve a requesting peer. Senders are chosen based on the current network con- ditions and the reliability of peers to render the best quality.</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: PROMISE architecture: Peers are interconnected through a P2P substrate (e.g., Pastry, Chord). For each session, multiple sending peers cooperate to serve a requesting peer. Senders are chosen based on the current network conditions and the reliability of peers to render the best quality.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The expectation of a random variable ¢ is denoted by ¢ .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: CollectCast: Receiver side</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 : Topology-aware selection. It constructs an approxi- mate topology and considers shared segments.</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4: Topology-aware selection. It constructs an approximate topology and considers shared segments.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 : End-to-end selection. It does not not consider shared segments.</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: End-to-end selection. It does not not consider shared segments.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6 : Pseudo code for selecting the best active peers set.</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6: Pseudo code for selecting the best active peers set.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>), we write it as: ¦ p = pwp¤ r ¢ p¤ r , where wp¤ r is the path weight and ¢ p¤ r is the binary random variable that depends on the end-to-end path loss rate. The mean of ¢ is: ¢ p = 1− ¡ p¤ r , where ¡ p¤ r is the average end-to-end path loss rate. Computing the path weight is much easier in this case and is given by:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 7 : Aggregated loss rate perceived by the receiver: no peer failures.</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Aggregated loss rate perceived by the receiver: no peer failures.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 8 : Aggregated streaming rate at the receiver: no peer failures.</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8: Aggregated streaming rate at the receiver: no peer failures.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 9 : Aggregated loss rate perceived by the receiver: with peer failures.</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9: Aggregated loss rate perceived by the receiver: with peer failures.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 10 : Aggregated streaming rate at the receiver: with peer failures.</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10: Aggregated streaming rate at the receiver: with peer failures.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The offered rate (Rp) is also distributed uniformly in the range [0.125R0, 0.5R0].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 11 : Size of the candidate peers set required for different average peer availability values. The mid-point is the mean, the lower point is the minimum, and the top point is maximum number of peers required in the candidate set.</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Figure 11: Size of the candidate peers set required for different average peer availability values. The mid-point is the mean, the lower point is the minimum, and the top point is maximum number of peers required in the candidate set.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 12 : Streaming from multiple peers. Two supplying peers failed at times 385 and 780. PROMISE detects and re- places the failed peers.</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Figure 12: Streaming from multiple peers. Two supplying peers failed at times 385 and 780. PROMISE detects and replaces the failed peers.</figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> For the feasibility of the analysis, we are making a reasonable assumption: the quality of individual segments of the path is independent from each other and from the availability of the peer.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>The authors would like to thank Dr. Ketan Mayer-Patel, our paper's shepherd, and the anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments and suggestions. This research is sponsored in part by the National Science Foundation grants ANI-0219110 and IIS-0209059.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scalable application layer multicast</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Banerjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kommareddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Varghese</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ACM SIGCOMM&apos;02</title>
		<meeting>of ACM SIGCOMM&apos;02<address><addrLine>Pittsburgh, PA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="220" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Deshpande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Garcia-Molina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Transience of peers and streaming media. First Workshop on Hot Topics in Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inference and labeling of metric-induced network topologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bestavros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Byers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Harfoush</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE INFOCOM&apos;02</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE INFOCOM&apos;02<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A digital fountain approach to reliable distribution of bulk data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Byers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Luby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mitzenmacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rege</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
				<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGCOMM&apos;98</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM&apos;98<address><addrLine>Vancouver, British Columbia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="67" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling Internet topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Calvert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Doar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Zegura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Communications Magazine</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="160" to="163" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Concast: Design and Implementation of an Active Network Service</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Calvert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Griffioen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mullins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sehgal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Journal on Selected Area in Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="426" to="437" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SplitStream: High-bandwidth content distribution in a cooperative environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Druschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kermarrec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nandi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rowstron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 2nd International Workshop on Peer-to-Peer Systems (IPTPS &apos;03)</title>
		<meeting>of 2nd International Workshop on Peer-to-Peer Systems (IPTPS &apos;03)<address><addrLine>Berkeley, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SCRIBE: A large-scale and decentralized application-level multicast infrastructure</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Druschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kermarrec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rowstron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communication (JSAC)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1489" to="1499" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A case for end system multicast</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seshan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications (JSAC)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1456" to="1471" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximum likelihood network topology identification from edge-based unicast measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Coates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nowak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGMETRICS</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGMETRICS<address><addrLine>Marina Del Rey, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Internet tomography</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Coates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nowak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Processing Magazine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wide-area cooperative storage with CFS</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Dabek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kaashoek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Karger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stoica</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ACM SOSP</title>
		<meeting>of ACM SOSP</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Streaming live media over peer-to-peer network</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Deshpande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Garcia-Molina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Stanford University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">PROMISE: peer-to-peer media streaming using CollectCast</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hefeeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Habib</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Boyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bhargava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>CS-TR 03-016</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-08" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Purdue University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
	<note>Extended version</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">End-to-end available bandwidth: Measurement methodology, dynamics, and relation with TCP throughput</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dovrolis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ACM SIGCOMM&apos;02</title>
		<meeting>of ACM SIGCOMM&apos;02<address><addrLine>Pittsburgh, PA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="308" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simulation and analysis of packet loss in user datagram protocol transfers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Markovski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Xue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Trajkovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Supercomputing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="196" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A routing underlay for overlay networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nakao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Peterson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bavier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGCOMM&apos;03</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM&apos;03<address><addrLine>Karlsruhe, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed video streaming over Internet</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zakhor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of Multimedia Computing and Networking (MMCN02)</title>
		<meeting>of Multimedia Computing and Networking (MMCN02)<address><addrLine>San Jose, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed video streaming with forward error correction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zakhor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Int&apos;l Packetvideo Workshop (PV&apos;02)</title>
		<meeting>Int&apos;l Packetvideo Workshop (PV&apos;02)<address><addrLine>Pittsburgh PA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Server-based inference of Internet link lossiness</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Padmanabhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Qiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE INFOCOM&apos;03</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE INFOCOM&apos;03<address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributing streaming media content using cooperative networking</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Padmanabhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sripanidkulchai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of NOSSDAV&apos;02</title>
		<meeting>of NOSSDAV&apos;02<address><addrLine>Miami Beach ,FL, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Page</forename><surname>Planetlab Home</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.planet-lab.org/" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A scalable content-addressable network</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ratnasamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Handley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Karp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ACM SIGCOMM&apos;01</title>
		<meeting>of ACM SIGCOMM&apos;01<address><addrLine>San Diego, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic parallel access to replicated content in the Internet</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Biersack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Networking</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="455" to="465" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pixie: A jukebox architecture to support efficient peer content exchange</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rollins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Almeroth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ACM Multimedia</title>
		<meeting>of ACM Multimedia<address><addrLine>Juan Les Pins, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pastry: Scalable, distributed object location and routing for large-scale peer-to-peer systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rowstron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Druschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 18th IFIP/ACM International Conference on Distributed Systems Platforms</title>
		<meeting>of 18th IFIP/ACM International Conference on Distributed Systems Platforms<address><addrLine>Heidelberg, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Storage management in past, a large-scale, persistent peer-to-peer storage utility</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rowstron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Druschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 18th ACM Symposium on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP&apos;01)</title>
		<meeting>of 18th ACM Symposium on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP&apos;01)<address><addrLine>Chateau Lake Louise, Banff, Canada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A measurement study of peer-to-peer file sharing systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Saroiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gummadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gribble</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of Multimedia Computing and Networking (MMCN02)</title>
		<meeting>of Multimedia Computing and Networking (MMCN02)<address><addrLine>San Jose, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scriptroute: A public Internet measurement facility</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Spring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wetherall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 4th USENIX Symposium on Internet Technologies and Systems (USITS&apos;03)</title>
		<meeting>4th USENIX Symposium on Internet Technologies and Systems (USITS&apos;03)<address><addrLine>Seattle, Washington, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chord: A scalable peer-to-peer lookup service for Internet applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stoica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kaashoek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Balakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ACM SIGCOMM&apos;01</title>
		<meeting>of ACM SIGCOMM&apos;01<address><addrLine>San Diego, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Zigzag: An efficient peer-to-peer scheme for media streaming</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Do</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE INFOCOM&apos;03</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE INFOCOM&apos;03<address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On peer-to-peer media streaming</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hefeeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hambrusch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bhargava</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE ICDCS&apos;02</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE ICDCS&apos;02<address><addrLine>Vienna, Austria</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measurement and modeling of the temporal dependence in packet loss</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yajnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Moon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kurose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Towsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE INFOCOM&apos;99</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE INFOCOM&apos;99<address><addrLine>York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-03" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="352" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the constancy of Internet path properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Duffield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Paxon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ACM SIGCOMM Internet Measurement Workshop</title>
		<meeting>of ACM SIGCOMM Internet Measurement Workshop<address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
