<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T17:03+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Automatic extraction of synonyms in a dictionary</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Vincent</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Blondel</surname></persName>
							<email>blondel@inma.ucl.ac.be</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Applied Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Computer Science DepartmentÉcole Department´DepartmentÉcole</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Louvain Avenue Georges Lemaitre</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>normale supérieure 45 rue d&apos;Ulm F</addrLine>
									<postCode>4 B-1348, 75230</postCode>
									<settlement>Louvain-la-Neuve, Paris cedex 05</settlement>
									<country>Belgium, France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pierre</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Senellart</surname></persName>
							<email>pierre.senellart@ens.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Applied Mathematics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Computer Science DepartmentÉcole Department´DepartmentÉcole</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Louvain Avenue Georges Lemaitre</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>normale supérieure 45 rue d&apos;Ulm F</addrLine>
									<postCode>4 B-1348, 75230</postCode>
									<settlement>Louvain-la-Neuve, Paris cedex 05</settlement>
									<country>Belgium, France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Automatic extraction of synonyms in a dictionary</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We propose a method for automatic synonym extraction in a dictionary. Our method is based on an algorithm that computes similarity measures between vertices in graphs. This algorithm can be thought of as a generalization of Kleinberg&apos;s web search algorithm to structure graphs that are more general than the hub-authority graph used by Kleinberg. We use the 1913 Webster&apos;s Dictionary and apply our method on four synonym queries. The results obtained are analyzed and compared to those obtained with two other methods.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>In this paper, we propose a method for automatic synonym extraction in a dictionary (our goal is not exactly the same as that of automatic thesaurus generation techniques: for a given word, we only want a list of good synonyms or nearsynonyms). Our method uses a graph constructed from the dictionary and is based on the assumption that synonyms have many words in common in their definitions and are used in the definition of many common words. Our method is based on an algorithm that generalizes an algorithm initially proposed by Kleinberg for searching the web <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[8]</ref>.</p><p>Starting from a dictionary, we first construct the associated dictionary graph G; each word of the dictionary is a vertex of the graph and there is an edge from u to v if v appears in the definition of u. Then, associated to a given query word w, we construct a neighborhood graph G w which is the subgraph of G whose vertices are those pointed by w or pointing to w. Finally, we look in the graph G w for vertices that are similar to the vertex 2 in the structure graph 1 −→ 2 −→ 3 and choose these as synonyms. For this last step we use a similarity measure between vertices in graphs that was introduced in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">6]</ref> and is described in Section 2.</p><p>The problem of searching synonyms is similar to that of searching similar pages on the web; a problem that is dealt with in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[8]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[5]</ref>. In these references, similar pages are found by searching authoritative pages in a subgraph focused on the original page. Authoritative pages are pages that are similar to the vertex "authority" in the structure graph hub −→ authority.</p><p>We ran the same method on the dictionary graph and obtained lists of good hubs and good authorities of the neighborhood graph. There were duplicates in these lists but not all good synonyms were duplicated. Neither authorities nor hubs appear to be the right concepts for discovering synonyms.</p><p>In the next section, we describe our method in some detail. In Section 3, we briefly survey two other methods that will be used for comparison. We then describe in Section 4 how we have constructed a dictionary graph from the Webster's dictionary. In a last section we compare all methods on the following words chosen for their variety: disappear, parallelogram, sugar and science.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">A generalization of Kleinberg's method</head><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[8]</ref>, Jon Kleinberg proposes a method for identifying web pages that are good hubs or good authorities for a given query. For example, for the query "automobile makers", the home pages of Ford, Toyota and other car makers are good authorities, whereas web pages that list these home pages are good hubs. In order to identify hubs and authorities, Kleinberg's methods exploits the natural graph structure of the web in which each web page is a vertex and there is an edge from vertex a to vertex b if page a points to page b. Associated to any given query word w, the method first constructs a "focused subgraph" G w analogous to our neighborhood graph and then computes hub and authority scores for all vertices of G w . These scores are obtained as the result of a converging iterative process. Initial hub and authority weights are all set to one, x 1 = 1 and x 2 = 1. These initial weights are then updated simultaneously according to a mutually reinforcing rule: the hub scores of the vertex i, x 1 i , is set equal to the sum of the authority scores of all vertices pointed by i and, similarly, the authority scores of the vertex j, x 2 j , is set equal to the sum of the hub scores of all vertices pointing to j. Let M w be the adjacency matrix associated to G w . The updating equations can be written as</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">񮽙 x 1 x 2 񮽙 t+1 = 񮽙 0 M w M T w 0 񮽙 񮽙 x 1 x 2 񮽙 t t = 0, 1, . . .</formula><p>It can be shown that under weak conditions the normalized vector x 1 (respectively, x 2 ) converges to the normalized principal eigenvector of</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">M w M T w (respectively, M T w M w ).</formula><p>The authority score of a vertex v in a graph G can be seen as a similarity measure between v in G and vertex 2 in the graph</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">1 −→ 2.</formula><p>Similarly, the hub score of v can be seen as a measure of similarity between v in G and vertex 1 in the same structure graph. As presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">6]</ref>, this measure of similarity can be generalized to graphs that are different from the authority-hub structure graph. We describe below an extension of the method to a structure graph with three vertices and illustrate an application of this extension to synonym extraction. We then briefly describe the situation for arbitrary structure graphs.</p><p>Let G be a dictionary graph. The neighborhood graph of a word w is constructed with the words that appear in the definition of w and those that use w in their definition. Because of this, the word w in G w is similar to the vertex 2 in the structure graph (denoted P 3 )</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">1 −→ 2 −→ 3.</formula><p>For instance, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref> shows a part of the neighborhood graph of likely. The words probable and likely in the neighborhood graph are similar to the vertex 2 in P 3 . The words truthy and belief are similar to, respectively, vertices 1 and 3. We say that a vertex look like the vertex 2 of the preceding graph if it points to vertices looking like the vertex 3 and if it is pointed to by vertices looking like the vertex 1. This mutually reinforcing definition is very similar to Kleinberg's definitions of hubs and authorities.</p><p>The similarity between vertices in graphs can be computed as follows. To every vertex i of G w we associate three scores (as many scores as there are vertices in the structure graph) x 1 i , x 2 i and x 3 i and initially set them equal to one. We then iteratively update the scores according to the following mutually reinforcing rule: the scores x 1 i are set equal to the sum of the scores x 2 j of all vertices j pointed by i; the scores x 2 i are set equal to the sum of the scores x 3 j of vertices pointed by i and the scores x 1 j of vertices pointing to i; finally, the scores x 3 i are set equal to the sum of the scores x 2 j of vertices pointing to i. At each step, the scores are updated simultaneously and are subsequently normalized;</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">x k ← x k /񮽙x k 񮽙 (k = 1, 2, 3)</formula><p>. It can be shown that when this process converges, the normalized vector score x 2 converges to the normalized principal eigenvector of the matrix</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">M w M T w + M T w M w .</formula><p>Thus, our list of synonyms can be obtained by ranking in decreasing order the entries of the principal eigen-</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">value of M w M T w + M T w M w .</formula><p>The algorithm described above can be generalized to arbitrary structure graphs. Let G 1 = (V 1 , E 1 ) and G 2 = (V 2 , E 2 ) be two given graphs. We think of G 2 as a "structure graph" and wish to quantify the similarity between the vertex v 1 in G 1 and the vertex v 2 in G 2 . It is shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">6]</ref> how similarity scores can be obtained from the principal eigenvector of the matrix</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">M 1 ⊗ M 2 + M T 1 ⊗ M T 2</formula><p>where ⊗ denotes the Kronecker tensorial product, and M 1 and M 2 are the adjacency matrices associated to G 1 and G 2 . When  </p><formula xml:id="formula_8">M 2 = 񮽙 0 1 0 0 񮽙</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Other methods</head><p>In this section, we briefly describe two synonym extraction methods that will be compared to our method on a selection of 4 words.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">The distance method</head><p>One possible way of defining a synonym distance is to declare that two words are close from being synonyms if they appear in the definition of the same words and have the same words in their definition. A way of formalizing this is to define a distance between two words by counting the number of words that appear in one of the definitions but not in both, and add to this the number of words that use one of the words but not both of them in their definition. Let A be the adjacency matrix of the dictionary graph, and i and j be the vertices associated to two words. The distance between i and j can be expressed as</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">d(i, j) = 񮽙(A i,· − A j,· )񮽙 + 񮽙(A ·,i − A ·,j ) T 񮽙</formula><p>where 񮽙 · 񮽙 is the l 1 vector norm (sum of all entries magnitudes). For a given word i we may compute d(i, j) for all j and sort the words according to increasing distance.</p><p>Unlike the other methods presented in this paper, we can apply this algorithm directly to the entire dictionary graph rather than on the neighborhood graph. This does however give very bad results: the first two synonyms of sugar are pigwidgeon and ivoride. We will see in Section 5 that much better results are achieved if we use the neighborhood graph.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">ArcRank</head><p>ArcRank is a method introduced by Jan Jannink and Gio Wiederhold for building a thesaurus <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[7]</ref>; their intent was not to find synonyms but related words. We did not implement their method but have used instead the online version available at http://skeptic.stanford.edu/data/ (this online version also uses the 1913 Webster's Dictionary and the comparison with our results is therefore meaningful).</p><p>The method is based on the PageRank algorithm, used by the web search engine Google and described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[4]</ref>. PageRank assigns a ranking to each vertex of the dictionary graph in the following way. All vertices start with identical initial ranking and then iteratively distribute it to the vertices they point to, while receiving the sum of the ranks from vertices they are pointed by. This process converges to a stationary distribution corresponding to the principal eigenvector of the adjacency matrix of the graph. ArcRank assigns a ranking to each edge according to the ranking of its vertices. If |a s | is the number of outgoing edges from vertex s and p t is the page rank of vertex t, then the edge relevance of (s, t) is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">r s,t = p s /|a s | p t</formula><p>Edge relevances are then converted into rankings. Those rankings are computed only once. When looking for words related to some word w, one select the edges starting from or arriving to w which have the best rankings and extract the corresponding incident vertices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Dictionary graph</head><p>Before proceeding to the description of our experiments, we describe how we constructed the dictionary graph. We used the Online Plain Text English Dictionary <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref> which is based on the "Project Gutenberg Etext of Webster's Unabridged Dictionary" which is in turn based on the 1913 US Webster's Unabridged Dictionary. The dictionary consists of 27 HTML files (one for each letter of the alphabet, and one for several additions). These files are available from the web site http://www. gutenberg.net/. In order to obtain the dictionary graph several choices had to be made.</p><p>• Some words defined in the Webster's dictionary are multi-words (e.g., All Saints', Surinam toad). We did not include these words in the graph since there is no simple way to decide, when the words are found side-byside, whether or not they should be interpreted as single words or as a multi-word.</p><p>• Some head words of definitions were prefixes or suffixes (e.g., un-, -ous), these were excluded from the graph.</p><p>• Many words have several meanings and are head words of multiple definitions. For, once more, it is not possible to determine which meaning of a word is employed in a definition, we gathered the definitions of a word into a single one.</p><p>• The recognition of derived forms of a word in a definition is also a problem. We dealt with the cases of regular and semi-regular plurals (e.g. daisies, albatrosses) and regular verbs, assuming that irregular forms of nouns or verbs (e.g., oxen, sought) had entries in the dictionary.</p><p>• All accentuated characters were replaced in the HTML file by a \ (e.g, proven\al, cr\che). We included these words, keeping the \.</p><p>• There are many misspelled words in the dictionary, since it has been built by scanning the paper edition and processing it with an OCR software. We didn't take these mistakes into account.</p><p>Because of the above remarks, the graph is far from being a precise graph of semantic relationships. For example, 13, 396 lexical units are used in the definitions but are not defined. These include numbers (e.g., 14159265, 14th) and mathematical and chemical symbols (e.g., x3, fe3o4). When this kind of lexemes, which are not real words, are excluded, 12, 461 words remain: proper nouns (e.g., California, Aaron), misspelled words (e.g., aligator, abudance), existing but undefined words (e.g., snakelike, unwound) or abbreviations (e.g., adj, etc). We also decided to exclude too frequent words in the construction of neighborhood graphs, that is words who appeared in more than L definitions (best results were obtained for L ≈ 1, 000 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Results</head><p>In order to be able to compare the different methods and to judge their relevance, we will examine the first ten results given by each of them for four words, chosen for their variety:</p><p>1. disappear: a word with various synonyms such as vanish. We have also included lists of synonyms coming from two hand-made sources: WordNet <ref type="bibr">[2]</ref> and the dictionary of synonyms of Microsoft Word 97. The order of appearance of the words for these two last sources is arbitrary, whereas it is well defined for the distance method and for our method. The results given by the Web interface implementing ArcRank are two rankings, one for words pointed by and one for words pointed to. We have interleaved them into one ranking. We have not kept the query word in the list of synonyms, since this has not much sense except for our method, where it is interesting to note that in every example we have experimented, the original word appeared as the first word of the list (a point that tends to give credit to the method).</p><p>In order to have an objective evaluation of the different methods, we asked a sample of 21 persons to give a mark (from 0 to 10, 10 being the best one) to the lists of synonyms, according to their relevance to synonymy. The lists were of course presented in random order for each word. <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Tables 1, 2, 3 and 4</ref> give the results. Concerning disappear, the distance method and our method do pretty well: most of the words given by hand-made dictionaries (vanish, cease, fade, die, pass) appear (one must not forget that verbs necessarily appear without their postposition). Other words such as dissipate or faint are relevant too. However, some words like light or port are completely irrelevant, but they appear only in 6th, 7th or 8th position. If we compare these two methods, we observe that our method is better: an important synonym like pass takes a good ranking, whereas port or appear go out of the top ten words. It is hard to explain this phenomenon, but we can say that the mutually reinforcing aspect of our method is apparently a positive point. On the contrary, ArcRank gives rather poor results with out of the point words like eat, instrumental or epidemic.</p><p>Because the neighborhood graph of parallelogram is rather small (30 vertices), the first two algorithms give similar results, which are not absurd: square, rhomb, quadrilateral, rectangle, figure are rather interesting. Other words are less relevant but still are in the semantic domain of parallelogram. ArcRank which also works on the same subgraph does not give as interesting words, although gnomon makes its appearance, since consequently or popular are irrelevant. It is interesting to note that hand-made dictionaries are less rich, because they focus on a particular aspect (quadrilateral for Wordnet, rhomb for Microsoft Word).</p><p>Once more, the results given by ArcRank for sugar are mainly irrelevant (property, grocer, ...). Our method is again better than the distance method: starch, sucrose, sweet, dextrose, glucose, lactose are highly relevant words, even if the first given near-synonym (cane) is not as good. Its given mark is even better than for the two handmade dictionaries. The dictionary of synonyms of Microsoft Word amusingly focuses on a very specific aspect of the word.</p><p>The results for science are perhaps the most difficult to analyze. The distance method and ours are comparable. ArcRank gives perhaps better results than for other words but is still poorer than the two other methods. Once again, the dictionary of synonyms of Word gives very few words, though highly relevant ones.</p><p>As a conclusion, the first two algorithms give interesting and relevant words, whereas it is clear that ArcRank is not adapted to the search for synonyms. The variation of Kleinberg's algorithm and its mutually reinforcing relationship demonstrates its superiority on the basic distance method, even if the difference is not obvious for all words. Of course, the obtained relevance cannot be reasonably compared with those of hand-made lists. Still, these automatic techniques show their interest, since they present more complete aspects of a word than handmade dictionaries. They could profitably be used to broaden a topic (see the example of parallelogram) and to help with the compilation of synonyms dictionaries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Future perspectives</head><p>A first immediate improvement of our method would be to work on a larger subgraph than the neighborhood subgraph. The neighborhood graph we have introduced may be rather small, and may therefore not include important near-synonyms. A good example is ox of which cow seems to be a good synonym. Unfortunately, ox does not appear in the definition of cow, neither does the latter appear in the definition of the former. Thus, the methods described above cannot find this word. The first idea would be to extend our neighborhood graph, either as Kleinberg does in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[8]</ref> for searching similar pages on the Web or as Dean and Henziger do in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[5]</ref> for the same purpose. However, such subgraphs are not any longer focused on the original word. That implies that our variation of    Kleinberg's algorithm forgets the original word and produces irrelevant results. Nevertheless, when we use the vicinity graph of Dean and Henziger, we obtain a few interesting results with specific words: for example, trapezoid appears as a near-synonym of parallelogram or cow as a near-synonym of ox. Yet there are also many degradations of performance for more general words. Perhaps a choice of the subgraph depending on the word itself would be appropriate. For instance, the extended vicinity graph may either be used for words whose neighborhood graph has less than a fixed number of vertices, or for words whose indegree is small, or for words who do not belong to the largest connected component of the dictionary graph.</p><p>One may wonder whether the results obtained are specific to the Webster's dictionary or whether the same methods could work on other dictionaries, in English or in other languages. Although the latter is most likely since our techniques were not designed for the particular graph we worked on, there will undoubtedly be differences with other languages. For example, in French, postpositions do not exist and thus verbs have not as many different meanings as in English. Besides, it is much rarer in French to have the same word for the noun and for the verb than in English. Furthermore, linguistics teach us that the way words are defined vary from one language to another. This seems to be an interesting research direction.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>we obtain the algorithm described above for syn- onym extraction.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Subgraph of the neighborhood graph of likely</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="true"><head>Table 2 : Proposed synonyms for parallelogram</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Distance 
Our method 
ArcRank 
Wordnet 
Microsoft Word 
1 
juice 
cane 
granulation 
sweetening 
darling 
2 
starch 
starch 
shrub 
sweetener 
baby 
2 
cane 
sucrose 
sucrose 
carbohydrate 
honey 
4 
milk 
milk 
preserve 
saccharide 
dear 
5 
molasses 
sweet 
honeyed 
organic compound 
love 
6 
sucrose 
dextrose 
property 
saccarify 
dearest 
7 
wax 
molasses 
sorghum 
sweeten 
beloved 
8 
root 
juice 
grocer 
dulcify 
precious 
9 
crystalline 
glucose 
acetate 
edulcorate 
pet 
10 
confection 
lactose 
saccharine 
dulcorate 
babe 
Average mark 
3.9 
6.3 
4.3 
6.2 
4.7 
Standard deviation 
2.0 
2.4 
2.3 
2.9 
2.7 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><head>Table 3 : Proposed synonyms for sugar</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Distance 

Our method 
ArcRank 
Wordnet 
Microsoft Word 
1 
art 
art 
formulate 
knowledge domain 
discipline 
2 
branch 
branch 
arithmetic 
knowledge base 
knowledge 
3 
nature 
law 
systematize 
discipline 
skill 
4 
law 
study 
scientific 
subject 
art 
5 
knowledge 
practice 
knowledge 
subject area 
6 
principle 
natural 
geometry 
subject field 
7 
life 
knowledge philosophical 
field 
8 
natural 
learning 
learning 
field of study 
9 
electricity 
theory 
expertness 
ability 
10 
biology 
principle 
mathematics 
power 
Average mark 
3.6 
4.4 
3.2 
7.1 
6.5 
Standard deviation 
2.0 
2.5 
2.9 
2.6 
2.4 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="false"><head>Table 4 : Proposed synonyms for science</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Feature extraction in large graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Vincent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Maureen</forename><surname>Blondel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Heymans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Van Dooren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>in preparation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The anatomy of a large-scale hypertextual Web search engine, Computer Networks and ISDN Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sergey</forename><surname>Brin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lawrence</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="117" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename><surname>Dean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Monika</forename><forename type="middle">Rauch</forename><surname>Henzinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Finding Related Pages in the World Wide Web, WWW8 / Computer Networks</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1467" to="1479" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Extraction d&apos;information dans les graphes, et application aux moteurs de recherche sur Internet. Mémoire de fin d&apos;´ etudes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Maureen</forename><surname>Heymans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<pubPlace>Louvain-la-Neuve, Belgium</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Université catholique de Louvain</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Thesaurus Entry Extraction from an On-line Dictionary, Proceedings of Fusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Jannink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gio</forename><surname>Wiederhold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<pubPlace>Sunnyvale CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Authoritative sources in a hyperlinked environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jon</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kleinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="604" to="632" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Extraction of information in large graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pierre</forename><surname>Senellart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<pubPlace>Louvain-laNeuve, Belgium</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Masters Internship Report</note>
	<note>Université catholique de Louvain</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
