<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T17:07+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Two-Level Processor-Sharing Scheduling Disciplines: Mean Delay Analysis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Samuli</forename><surname>Aalto</surname></persName>
							<email>samuli.aalto@hut.fi</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Urtzi</forename><surname>Ayesta</surname></persName>
							<email>urtzi.ayesta@francetelecom.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Eeva</forename><surname>Nyberg-Oksanen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Helsinki University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>France Telecom R&amp;D</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Helsinki University of Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Two-Level Processor-Sharing Scheduling Disciplines: Mean Delay Analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Permission to make digital or hard copies of all or part of this work for personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGMETRICS/Performance&apos;04, June 12-16, 2004, New York, NY, USA. Copyright 2004 ACM 1-58113-664-1/04/0006 ...$5.00.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>C4 [Performance of Systems]: Performance Attributes</term>
					<term>F22 [Nonnumerical Algorithms and Problems]: Se- quencing and Scheduling</term>
					<term>G3 [Probability and Statis- tics]: Queueing Theory General Terms Performance, Algorithms * Urtzi Ayesta is also with INRIA Sophia Antipolis, Keywords Scheduling, MLPS, PS, FB, LAS, M/G/1, mean delay, un- finished truncated work</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Inspired by several recent papers that focus on scheduling disciplines for network flows, we present a mean delay analysis of Multilevel Processor Sharing (MLPS) scheduling disciplines in the context of M/G/1 queues. Such disciplines have been proposed to model the effect of the differentiation between short and long TCP flows in the Internet. Under MLPS, jobs are classified into classes depending on their attained service. We consider scheduling disciplines where jobs within the same class are served either with Processor Sharing (PS) or Foreground Background (FB) policy, and the class that contains jobs with the smallest attained service is served first. It is known that the FB policy minimizes (maximizes) the mean delay when the hazard rate of the job size distribution is decreasing (increasing). Our analysis, based on pathwise and meanwise arguments of the unfinished truncated work, shows that Two-Level Processor Sharing (TLPS) disciplines, e.g., FB+PS and PS+PS, are better than PS scheduling when the hazard rate of the job size distribution is decreasing. If the hazard rate is increasing and bounded, we show that PS outperforms PS+PS and FB+PS. We further extend our analysis to study local op-timality within a level of an MLPS scheduling discipline.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Seminal work on one server scheduling disciplines was made in the 1960's and 1970's. Schrage <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> proved that the Shortest Remaining Processing Time (SRPT) discipline minimizes the mean delay, i.e., the expected time in the system. The SRPT discipline, however, requires the knowledge of the remaining service times of all jobs, but these remaining service times are not always known, e.g., the remaining length of an Internet session is not known by the scheduler. Kleinrock <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> gives a thorough overview of scheduling in such systems where only the attained service times are known together with the service time distribution. Yashkov <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> mentions that he has proven (in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>) that the Foreground Background (FB) 1 discipline is optimal among this set of scheduling disciplines if the hazard rate of the service time distribution is decreasing (DHR). Righter and Shantikumar <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> showed the optimality of FB in the stochastic sense, i.e., the tail of the queue-length distribution, P [N F B &gt; k], is minimal for all k ≥ 0. Righter et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> show that FB minimizes the mean delay when the job size distribution is of type New Worse than Used in Expectation (NWUE), which is a weaker condition than DHR. In a recent paper, Feng and Misra <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> prove the optimality of FB when the hazard rate is decreasing. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> The performance of FB under job size distributions with high variability and simulations of FB on the packet level has been studied by <ref type="bibr">Rai et al. [10]</ref>.</p><p>These job size aware scheduling disciplines have lately received new attention <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12]</ref> mainly due to the measurement findings that Internet traffic is heavy tailed <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">14]</ref>. This means that data transfers are composed of many very short flows, but the majority of traffic is due to few very long flows. In such a case, it seems reasonable to favor the short flows by a suitable scheduling algorithm. For example, if a router is able to determine, for each flow, the number of bytes or packets already transmitted, the flows could be divided into different priority classes with the highest priority given to the flows with the least number of transmitted bytes or packets. Such implementations are discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12]</ref>. Another method, based on the packet arrival rates within each flow, is described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref>.</p><p>On the flow level, these packet level scheduling algorithms can be modelled using Multilevel Processor Sharing (MLPS) scheduling disciplines. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> An MLPS discipline is defined by a finite set of thresholds 0 = a0 &lt; a1 &lt; · · · &lt; aN &lt; aN+1 = ∞, which define N + 1 levels. Jobs are classified into levels based on their attained service. Between these levels, a strict priority discipline is applied with the lowest level having the highest priority. Thus, those jobs that have attained service less than a 1 time units are served first. In this paper, the MLPS disciplines with two levels are called Two-Level Processor Sharing (TLPS) disciplines.</p><p>With respect to the performance analysis of these MLPS disciplines, the ordinary Processor Sharing (PS) discipline is a natural point of comparison, since it has been proposed as an ideal model for the bandwidth sharing among TCP flows in a bottleneck router <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">18]</ref>. Using a similar reasoning, the packet level priority discipline for TCP flows described above could be modelled as an MLPS discipline with PS used as the internal discipline within each level. Another natural point of comparison is FB due to its optimality property in the case of job size distributions with decreasing hazard rate, examples of which are the Pareto and hyper-exponential distributions that have been used to model flow sizes in the Internet.</p><p>In addition to the FB discipline, Feng and Misra <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> consider a TLPS discipline (called FLIPS) where those jobs with attained service time less than threshold a are served according to the FB discipline. If such jobs do not exist, the ordinary PS discipline is used. However, they do not compare the FLIPS discipline to the other disciplines in the mean delay sense. Guo and Matta <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> study, by simulations, another TLPS discipline (called ML-PRIO) where those jobs with attained service time less than threshold a are given priority and served according to the PS discipline. If such jobs do not exist, the ordinary PS discipline is used. The same discipline is considered, by analytical and numerical techniques, in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref>. Their numerical experimentations suggest that ML-PRIO is better than PS when the hazard rate is decreasing.</p><p>In this paper we compare the mean delays of TLPS disciplines for which the scheduling discipline within one level is either FB or PS, more specifically FB+PS (FLIPS) and PS+PS (ML-PRIO), in the context of M/G/1 queues. We show that (i) if the hazard rate is decreasing, then</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">E[T FB ] ≤ E[T FB+PS ] ≤ E[T PS+PS ] ≤ E[T PS ],</formula><p>but (ii) if the hazard rate is increasing and bounded, then</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">E[T FB ] ≥ E[T FB+PS ] ≥ E[T PS+PS ] ≥ E[T PS ].</formula><p>For more general MLPS disciplines, we show that, within a level, FB is always better than PS if the hazard rate is decreasing and vice versa for a job size distribution with increasing and bounded hazard rate. The results follow from a thorough analysis of the unfinished truncated work (defined in Section 2.1) including both meanwise and pathwise arguments. In particular, we provide a framework to prove that the mean unfinished truncated work is smaller under a given scheduling discipline compared to some other scheduling discipline.</p><p>The paper is organized as follows. Section 2 derives how, for different scheduling disciplines, differences in the mean delay can be deduced from differences in the mean unfinished truncated work, given a job size distribution and its hazard rate. In particular, we show that if the mean unfinished truncated work in one scheduling discipline is smaller than in another, the scheduling discipline has a smaller mean delay when the hazard rate of the job size distribution is decreasing. In Section 2 we also provide a framework that gives a sufficient condition for the comparison of the mean unfinished truncated work for different scheduling disciplines. Section 3 relaxes the Poisson arrival assumption and scheduling disciplines are compared using pathwise arguments on the unfinished truncated work for TLPS and MLPS scheduling disciplines. Section 4 summarizes the results in form of theorems, which order several TLPS disciplines according to the mean delay and within a level of an MLPS scheduling discipline, given assumptions on the hazard rate and the job size distribution. Section 5 concludes the paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">MEAN DELAY</head><p>Consider any work-conserving scheduling discipline of an M/G/1 queue. Let λ denote the arrival rate and S the service time of a job. We assume that E[S] &lt; ∞ and the system be stable, i.e., ρ = λE[S] &lt; 1. Furthermore, we assume that the service time distribution is continuous with the corresponding density function denoted by f (x). Let</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">F (x) = Z x 0 f (y) dy</formula><p>and F (x) = 1 − F (x). The corresponding hazard rate function is denoted by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">h(x) = f (x) F (x) .</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Mean delay in terms of mean unfinished truncated work</head><p>Let N denote the number of jobs in the system at an arbitrary time, and denote the service times of these jobs by S i and their attained services by X i , i ∈ {1, . . . , N }. The random variable Ux refers to the unfinished truncated work with truncation threshold x, i.e., the sum of remaining truncated service times of those jobs with attained service less than x time units,</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Ux = N X i=1 ((Si ∧ x) − (Xi ∧ x)),</formula><p>where we have used notation a ∧ b = min{a, b}. Note that U 0 = 0.</p><p>Let T (y) denote the delay of a job whose service time is y time units, and N (y) the number of such jobs who has attained service at most y time units. According to [2, equation (4.11)],</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">N (y) = λF (y)T (y),<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where we have used notation N (y </p><formula xml:id="formula_7">points y i such that N (y + i ) − N (y − i ) &gt; 0.</formula><p>For example, for the FIFO discipline, point 0 is such, and for the MLPS disciplines, the thresholds an &gt; 0 are such. By Little's result, we conclude that, for all such points yi,</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">N (y + i ) − N (y − i ) = λF (yi)(T (y + i ) − T (y − i )).<label>(2)</label></formula><p>Formulas <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(1)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(2)</ref> can be combined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">dN (y) = λF (y)dT (y),<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Let Rx(y) denote the remaining truncated service time of a job that has attained service y time units,</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">R x (y) = (S(y) ∧ x) − y, y &lt; x,</formula><p>where S(y) refers to the service time of a job whose attained service is y time units. For the mean value R x (y) = E[Rx(y)] we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">Rx(y) = E[(S ∧ x) − y|S &gt; y] = 1 F (y) Z x y F (t) dt.<label>(4)</label></formula><p>In particular, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">R x (0) = E[(S ∧ x)] = Z x 0 F (t) dt.<label>(5)</label></formula><p>From here on we restrict ourselves to such scheduling disciplines that do not use any information about the remaining service times of the jobs, but only information on the attained services. The family of such disciplines is denoted by Π. For such disciplines, N (y) and R x (y) (as well as</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">N (y + i ) − N (y − i )</formula><p>and R x (y i )) are independent and we have the following formula for the mean unfinished truncated work U x = E <ref type="bibr">[Ux]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">U x = Z x − 0 − R x (y)dN (y).</formula><p>By applying (3) and (4), we get</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">U x = λ Z x − 0 − Z x y F (t) dt dT (y) = λ Z x 0 Z t − 0 − dT (y) F (t) dt = λ Z x 0 T (t − ) F (t) dt.</formula><p>Since almost everywhere in the interval <ref type="bibr">[0, x]</ref>, we have T (t − ) = T (t), the integral remains unchanged if we replace T (t − ) by T (t). Thus, we have the following result (cf. [2, equation (4.60)]):</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">U x = λ Z x 0 F (t)T (t) dt.<label>(6)</label></formula><p>We note that the limiting value U ∞ with x → ∞ refers to the mean unfinished work that is known to be the same for all work-conserving disciplines. Furthermore, in the limit x → ∞ formula (6) is valid even for more general ergodic arrival processes than Poisson process <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref>.</p><p>Differentiating (6) yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">(U x ) = λF (x)T (x),<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where we have used notation (</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">U x) = d dx U x. Thus, T (x) = (U x) λF (x) .<label>(8)</label></formula><p>By averaging over x, we get the following result for the mean delay E <ref type="bibr">[T ]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">E[T ] = Z ∞ 0 T (x)f (x) dx = 1 λ Z ∞ 0 (U x) h(x) dx. (9)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Difference of mean delays</head><p>Formula <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(9)</ref> is our main tool in the mean delay comparisons, as the following two propositions reveal.</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">Proposition 1. Let π 1 , π 2 ∈ Π. If U π 1 x ≤ U π 2</formula><p>x for all x ≥ 0 and the hazard rate h(x) is decreasing, then</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">E[T π 1 ] ≤ E[T π 2 ].</formula><p>Proof. If the hazard rate is bounded so that h(0) and h(∞) exist, then the result can be derived easily as follows. By (9), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">E[T π 1 ] − E[T π 2 ] = 1 λ Z ∞ 0 [(U π 1 x ) − (U π 2 x ) ]h(x)dx.</formula><p>After integrating by parts <ref type="bibr">[20, pp. 118-119]</ref>, we get</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">E[T π 1 ] − E[T π 2 ] = 1 λ (U π 1 ∞ − U π 2 ∞ )h(∞) − 1 λ (U π 1 0 − U π 2 0 )h(0) − 1 λ Z ∞ 0 (U π 1 x − U π 2 x ) dh(x),</formula><p>where the integral is defined as a Stieltjes integral with respect to the decreasing function h(x). By observing that U</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">π 1 0 = U π 2 0 = 0 and U π 1 ∞ = U π 2 ∞ , we obtain E[T π 1 ] − E[T π 2 ] = − 1 λ Z ∞ 0 (U π 1 x − U π 2 x ) dh(x),</formula><p>from which the result straightly follows. But if the hazard rate is unbounded near 0, we have to apply <ref type="bibr">Lemma 1 (in Appendix</ref></p><formula xml:id="formula_25">) to φ(x) = U π 1 x −U π 2 x implying that, for all x ≥ 0, Z x 0 (( ¯ U π 1 y ) − ( ¯ U π 2 y ) )h(y) dy ≤ 0.</formula><p>Thus, in the limit x → ∞,</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">Z ∞ 0 (( ¯ U π 1 y ) − ( ¯ U π 2 y ) )h(y) dy ≤ 0.</formula><p>The claim follows now from (9).</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">Proposition 2. Let π1, π2 ∈ Π. If U π 1 x ≤ U π 2</formula><p>x for all x ≥ 0 and the hazard rate h(x) is increasing and bounded, then</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">E[T π 1 ] ≥ E[T π 2 ].</formula><p>Proof. Since the hazard rate is assumed to be bounded, we deduce, as in the first part of the proof of Proposition 1, that</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">E[T π 1 ] − E[T π 2 ] = − 1 λ Z ∞ 0 (U π 1 x − U π 2 x ) dh(x),</formula><p>where the integral is defined as a Stieltjes integral with respect to the increasing function h(x). The result follows straightly from this.</p><p>To compare two scheduling disciplines π1 and π2 in the mean delay sense, it is, thus, sufficient to prove that U</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">π 1 x ≤ U π 2</formula><p>x for all x ≥ 0.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Framework for comparisons between scheduling disciplines</head><p>In this subsection, we develop a mathematical framework that gives a sufficient condition that U</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">π 1 x ≤ U π 2 x for all x ≥ 0. Proposition 3. Let π1, π2 ∈ Π. If there exists some x * ≥ 0 such that T π 1 (x) ≤ T π 2 (x) for all x &lt; x * and T π 1 (x) ≥ T π 2 (x) for all x &gt; x * , then U π 1 x ≤ U π 2</formula><p>x for all x ≥ 0.</p><p>Proof. It follows from (6) that, for all x &lt; x * ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">U π 1 x ≤ U π 2 x .<label>(10)</label></formula><p>On the other hand, for all x &gt; x * ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">(U π 1 x ) = λF (x)T π 1 (x) ≥ λF (x)T π 2 (x) = (U π 2</formula><p>x ) . Since both π 1 and π 2 are work-conserving disciplines, for which the mean unfinished work is equal, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">U π 1 ∞ = U π 2 ∞ .</formula><p>The formulas above together with the fact that U x is a continuous function of x guarantee that, for all x ≥ 0,</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">U π 1 x ≤ U π 2</formula><p>x , which completes the proof.</p><p>Note that the condition of Proposition 3 seems natural in the context of MLPS disciplines. For instance, let π1 ∈ Π be a scheduling discipline that gives priority to short jobs. If one compares the conditional mean delay of π 1 with respect to PS, one expects there will exist some x * such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">T π 1 (x) ≤ T PS (x) for all x &lt; x * and that T π 1 (x) ≥ T PS (x)</formula><p>for all x &gt; x * . In Section 2.4 we show that this is indeed the case for π1 = PS + PS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Comparison between PS+PS and PS disciplines</head><p>In this subsection we show that the PS+PS(a) discipline is better than PS in reducing the value of U x .</p><p>It is well known that the mean delay of a job with service time x &gt; 0 in a PS system reads as</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">T PS (x) = x 1 − ρ .</formula><p>According to <ref type="bibr">[2, equations (4.27)</ref>, (4.36), (4.39)], the corresponding mean delay in a PS+PS(a) system can be expressed as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">T PS+PS(a) (x) = 8 &gt; &lt; &gt; : x 1 − ρa if x ≤ a, T FB (a) + α(x − a) 1 − ρ a if x &gt; a.<label>(11)</label></formula><p>Here ρ a = λE[S ∧ a] refers to the truncated load, and α(x) is such that α (x) = d dx α(x) satisfies the following integral equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">α (x) = λ 1 − ρ a Z x 0 α (y)F (a + x − y) dy + λ 1 − ρ a Z ∞ 0 α (y)F (a + x + y) dy + c(x) + 1 with c(x) ≥ 0. Note that T PS+PS(a) (x) is differentiable, at least, for all x &gt; a.</formula><p>A numerical example of T π (x) is depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref> for a bounded Pareto service time distribution BP(k, p, α). A random variable X has a bounded Pareto distribution if its distribution is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">F (x) = (1 − (k/x) α )/(1 − (k/p) α ) for all k ≤ x ≤ p.</formula><p>The hazard rate of a bounded Pareto distribution is decreasing for all k ≤ x ≤ p. Denote now</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">α * = inf x&gt;0 α (x).</formula><p>The following inequality follows straightforwardly from the integral equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">α * ≥ inf x&gt;0 λ 1 − ρ a Z x 0 α (y)F (a + x − y) dy + λ 1 − ρa Z ∞ 0 α (y)F (a + x + y) dy + 1 ≥ inf x&gt;0 λ 1 − ρa Z x 0 α * F (a + x − y) dy + λ 1 − ρ a Z ∞ 0 α * F (a + x + y) dy + 1 = λα * 1 − ρa Z ∞ 0 F (a + z) dz + 1. Now, taking into account that Z ∞ 0 F (a + z) dz = E[S] − E[S ∧ a],</formula><p>we deduce that</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">α * ≥ α * ρ − ρa 1 − ρa + 1.</formula><p>Thus,</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">α * ≥ 1 − ρ a 1 − ρ .<label>(12)</label></formula><p>By combining (11) and (12), we get</p><formula xml:id="formula_45">8 &gt; &lt; &gt; : (T PS+PS(a) ) (x) = 1 1 − ρa ≤ 1 1 − ρ if x &lt; a, (T PS+PS(a) ) (x) ≥ α * 1 − ρa ≥ 1 1 − ρ if x &gt; a.<label>(13)</label></formula><p>Note further that</p><formula xml:id="formula_46">(T PS ) (x) = 1 1 − ρ .<label>(14)</label></formula><p>Proposition 4. For all a ≥ 0 and x ≥ 0,</p><formula xml:id="formula_47">U PS+PS(a) x ≤ U PS x .</formula><p>Proof. We verify that T PS+PS(a) (x) and T PS (x) satisfy the assumptions stated in Proposition 3. Let a ≥ 0. Since T PS (0) = T PS+PS(a) (0) = 0, it follows from <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(13)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(14)</ref> that, for all x &lt; a,</p><formula xml:id="formula_48">T PS+PS(a) (x) ≤ T PS (x).</formula><p>Since PS+PS is a work-conserving discipline, there exists a value</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">x * = inf{x ≥ a | T PS+PS(a) (x) ≥ T PS (x)}.</formula><p>Thus, for all x &lt; x * .</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">T PS+PS(a) (x) ≤ T PS (x).</formula><p>On the other hand by equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(13)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(14)</ref> we have,</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">for all x &gt; x * T PS+PS(a) (x) ≥ T PS (x),</formula><p>which completes the proof.</p><p>A numerical example of U π x is depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref> for a bounded Pareto service time distribution BP(13, 3500, 1.1). Combining Propositions 1 and 4, we deduce that PS+PS is better than PS in the mean delay sense under condition DHR. This result gives a clue that the two-level packet scheduling algorithm referred to in Section 1 is a reasonable method to favor short flows in the Internet.</p><p>It is even possible to consider the pathwise difference U π 1 x (t)− U π 2 x (t), from which relationships for the difference U</p><formula xml:id="formula_52">π 1 x −U π 2 x</formula><p>follow. The pathwise arguments in the following section are based on the rate σ π x (t) at which the unfinished truncated work is reduced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">PATHWISE COMPARISON OF UNFIN-ISHED TRUNCATED WORK</head><p>In this section we relax the assumption of Poisson arrivals and concentrate on the pathwise comparison of the unfinished truncated work with a fixed truncation threshold x &gt; 0. Therefore, we add the time dimension into our considerations.</p><p>Consider any work-conserving discipline π. Let A(t) denote the number jobs who have arrived up to time t, N π (t) the number of jobs at time t, and N π (t) the set of jobs in the system at time t, where |N π (t)| = N π (t). Furthermore, let N π x (t) denote the number of such jobs with attained service less than x and U π x (t) the unfinished truncated work at time t. Note that N π x (t) = 0 ⇔ U π x (t) = 0. Finally, let Ai denote the arrival time of job i, Si its service time, and X π i (t) its attained service at time t. Then we have the following relationship:</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">i ∈ N π (t) ⇔ A i ≤ t and X π i (t) &lt; S i . Furthermore, U π x (t) = A(t) X i=1 ((Si ∧ x) − (X π i (t) ∧ x)),</formula><p>or, equivalently,</p><formula xml:id="formula_54">U π x (t) = X i∈N π (t) ((Si ∧ x) − (X π i (t) ∧ x)) = X i∈N π x (t) ((S i ∧ x) − X π i (t)).</formula><p>On the other hand, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">U π x (t) = A(t) X i=1 (S i ∧ x) − Z t 0 σ π x (u) du,<label>(15)</label></formula><p>where σ π x (t) refers to the rate at which such jobs that have attained service less than x units are served at time t. Certainly, we have, for any t,</p><formula xml:id="formula_56">σ π x (t) = 0, if N π x (t) = 0, σ π x (t) ≤ 1, if N π x (t) &gt; 0.<label>(16)</label></formula><p>For example, for the PS discipline this rate is as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_57">σ PS x (t) = 8 &lt; : 0, if N PS x (t) = 0, N PS x (t) N PS (t) ≤ 1, if N PS x (t) &gt; 0.<label>(17)</label></formula><p>Note further that the first term in (15) is independent of the scheduling discipline.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Optimal discipline to minimize unfinished truncated work</head><p>Let Π * x denote the family of work-conserving scheduling disciplines that give full priority to jobs that have attained service less than x units. Note that</p><formula xml:id="formula_58">FB, FB+PS(x), PS+PS(x) ∈ Π * x . Furthermore, FB+PS(a) ∈ Π * x for all a ≥ x. For any π * ∈ Π * x , we have σ π * x (t) = 0, if N π * x (t) = 0, 1, if N π * x (t) &gt; 0.<label>(18)</label></formula><p>It follows that U π * x (t) is the same for all π * ∈ Π * x . It is also easy to show that any π * ∈ Π * x is optimal in this sense.</p><p>Proposition 5. For any π * ∈ Π * x and t ≥ 0,</p><formula xml:id="formula_59">U π * x (t) = min π∈Π U π x (t).</formula><p>Proof. This follows immediately from equations <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(15)</ref>, <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(16)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(18)</ref> combined with the observation that if σ π x (t) &gt; σ π * x (t), then necessarily N π * x (t) = 0, which implies that</p><formula xml:id="formula_60">U π * x (t) = 0 ≤ U π x (t).</formula><p>Instead of U π x (t), both Righter et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and Feng and Misra <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> consider the corresponding untruncated random variable</p><formula xml:id="formula_61">V π x (t) = X i∈N π x (t) (S i − X π i (t)). Under the condition that V π1 x ≤ V π2 x for all x ≥ 0, Righter et al. [6] prove that E[T π 1 ] ≤ E[T π 2 ]</formula><p>when the service time distribution is of type NWUE; under the same condition, Feng and Misra <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> obtain the same result when the hazard rate is decreasing.</p><p>In order to prove the optimality of FB, both Righter et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and Feng and Misra <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, use a similar pathwise argument as above to demonstrate that FB minimizes V π x (t) in the pathwise sense.</p><p>However, if the remaining service times are not truncated, there is a vertical downward jump in V π x (t) amounting to S i − x time units at time t when job i jumps out of N π x (t). This fact is not taken into account in the proofs of FB's optimality in [6, Lemma (3.5)] and [9, <ref type="bibr">Lemma 2.4]</ref>   <ref type="figure">Figures 3 and 4</ref>, respectively. The former one demonstrates the non-optimality of FB regarding the unfinished untruncated work, while the latter one illustrates the optimality regarding the unfinished truncated work. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Comparison between TLPS disciplines</head><p>Consider now the TLPS disciplines FB+PS(a) and PS+PS(a). We show that the former one is better than the latter one in minimizing U x .</p><p>First we consider the TLPS disciplines FB+PS(a) and PS+PS(a) for which a ≥ x.</p><p>Proposition 6. For any a ≥ x and t ≥ 0,</p><formula xml:id="formula_62">U FB x (t) = U FB+PS(a) x (t) ≤ U PS+PS(a) x (t).</formula><p>Proof. The result is due to Proposition 5 and the fact that FB and FB+PS(a) belong to π * x in this case.</p><p>Next we consider the TLPS disciplines FB+PS(a) and PS+PS(a) for which a ≤ x. For the former one, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_63">σ FB+PS(a) x (t) = 8 &lt; : N FB+PS(a) x (t) N FB+PS(a) (t) , if N FB+PS(a) a (t) = 0, 1, if N FB+PS(a) a (t) &gt; 0,<label>(19)</label></formula><p>and for the latter one</p><formula xml:id="formula_64">σ PS+PS(a) x (t) = 8 &lt; : N PS+PS(a) x (t) N PS+PS(a) (t) , if N PS+PS(a) a (t) = 0, 1, if N PS+PS(a) a (t) &gt; 0.<label>(20)</label></formula><p>It follows that in this case we have, for any t ≥ 0,</p><formula xml:id="formula_65">σ FB+PS(a) x (t) = σ PS+PS(a) x (t).<label>(21)</label></formula><p>Proposition 7. For any a ≤ x and t ≥ 0,</p><formula xml:id="formula_66">U FB x (t) ≤ U FB+PS(a) x (t) = U PS+PS(a) x (t).</formula><p>Proof. The first inequality follows from Proposition 5 and the fact that FB ∈ Π * x . The second equality is due to equations (15) and (21).</p><p>We note that in the particular case x = a, there is no difference between the three disciplines,</p><formula xml:id="formula_67">U FB a (t) = U FB+PS(a) a (t) = U PS+PS(a) a (t).</formula><p>We further note that, while PS+PS is better than PS regarding the mean value of the unfinished truncated work (see Proposition 4), the pathwise version of this result is not true, which we verified by a counter-example.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Comparison inside MLPS disciplines</head><p>In this subsection, we consider the multilevel PS disciplines MLPS(a1, . . . , aN ), where 0 = a0 &lt; a1 &lt; . . . &lt; aN &lt; aN+1 = ∞.</p><p>For any π ∈ MLPS(a1, . . . , aN ), let πn ∈ {FB, PS} denote the scheduling discipline used at level n, where n ∈ {1, . . . , N + 1}.</p><p>First we observe that π ∈ MLPS(a1, . . . , aN ) is (locally) optimal, i.e., π ∈ Π * x , if there is n ∈ {1, . . . , N + 1} such that (i) a n = x, or (ii) a n−1 &lt; x &lt; a n and π n = FB.</p><p>The reason is that, for all these disciplines π and for all t ≥ 0, we have σ π x (t) = σ FB x (t). Next we compare two MLPS disciplines. For that, define the following order relation among the disciplines {FB, PS}: FB FB, FB PS, PS FB, PS PS.</p><formula xml:id="formula_68">Proposition 8. Assume that π ∈ MLPS(a 1 , . . . , a N ), π ∈ MLPS(a 1 , . . . , a N ), n ∈ {1, .</formula><p>. . , N +1} and n ∈ {1, . . . , N + 1} such that a n−1 = a n −1 ≤ x ≤ a n = a n .</p><formula xml:id="formula_69">(i) If π n = π n , then U π x (t) = U π x (t) for all t ≥ 0. (ii) If π n π n , then U π x (t) ≤ U π x (t) for all t ≥ 0. Proof. (i) Assume that π n = π n .</formula><p>It is easy to see that σ π x (t) = σ π x (t) for all t ≥ 0 in this case. Thus, by (15), we have U π x (t) = U π x (t) for all t ≥ 0. (ii) Due to (i), it is sufficient to consider the case πn = FB and π n = PS. In this case,</p><formula xml:id="formula_70">σ π x (t) = 0, if N π x (t) = 0, 1, if N π x (t) &gt; 0, while ( σ π x (t) = 0, if N π x (t) = 0, σ π x (t) ≤ 1, if N π x (t) &gt; 0.</formula><p>for all t ≥ 0. Thus, by <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">(15)</ref>, we have U π x (t) ≤ U π x (t) for all t ≥ 0.</p><p>Note that the results related to the comparison of the TLPS disciplines FB+PS(a) and PS+PS(a) presented in Propositions 6 and 7 follow from this one.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">MEAN DELAY COMPARISONS OF MLPS DISCIPLINES</head><p>As mentioned in section 2, in cases where the hazard rate is monotonous, the order of the scheduling disciplines is determined by the meanwise difference</p><formula xml:id="formula_71">E[U π 1 x − U π 2 x ].</formula><p>The following theorems related to the mean delay comparisons between scheduling disciplines follow from the propositions in the previous sections.</p><formula xml:id="formula_72">Theorem 1. Assume that the hazard rate h(x) is decreas- ing. (i) E[T FB ] = min π∈Π E[T π ].</formula><p>(ii) For all a ≥ 0,</p><formula xml:id="formula_73">E[T FB ] ≤ E[T FB+PS(a) ] ≤ E[T PS+PS(a) ] ≤ E[T PS ].</formula><p>(iii) For any π, π ∈ MLPS(a1, . . . , aN ) such that πn π n for all n ∈ {1, . . . , N + 1},</p><formula xml:id="formula_74">E[T π ] ≤ E[T π ].</formula><p>Proof. (i) The claim follows immediately from Propositions 1 and 5. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> (ii) The claim follows immediately from Propositions 1, 4, 6 and 7.</p><p>(iii) The claim follows immediately from Propositions 1 and 8.</p><p>This theorem strengthens the intuition that the multilevel packet scheduling algorithm referred to in Section 1 is a reasonable method to favor short flows in the Internet.</p><p>Theorem 2. Assume that the hazard rate h(x) is increasing and bounded.</p><formula xml:id="formula_75">(i) E[T FB ] = max π∈Π E[T π ]. (ii) For all a ≥ 0, E[T FB ] ≥ E[T FB+PS(a) ] ≥ E[T PS+PS(a) ] ≥ E[T PS ]. (iii) For any π, π ∈ MLPS(a 1 , . . . , a N ) such that π n π n for all n ∈ {1, . . . , N + 1}, E[T π ] ≥ E[T π ].</formula><p>Proof. (i) The claim follows immediately from Propositions 2 and 5.</p><p>(ii) The claim follows immediately from Propositions 2, 4, 6 and 7.</p><p>(iii) The claim follows immediately from Propositions 2 and 8.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Numerical comparison</head><p>In this subsection we present some numerical examples that illustrate the benefits of PS+PS(a) and FB+PS(a) in reducing the mean delay with respect to PS.</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref>, we depict the mean delay of the disciplines PS+PS(a) and FB+PS(a) as a function of the threshold a. In addition the mean delay values for the PS and FB disciplines are also depicted. The service time distribution is bounded Pareto BP(13, 3500, 1.1).</p><p>We first note that since the hazard rate of a bounded Pareto distribution is decreasing, the inequalities stated in Theorem 1 are indeed satisfied. As expected, we observe that</p><formula xml:id="formula_76">E[T FB+PS(0) ] = E[T PS+PS(0) ] = E[T PS ]</formula><p>and that</p><formula xml:id="formula_77">lim a→∞ E[T FB+PS(a) ] = E[T FB ] whereas lim a→∞ E[T PS+PS(a) ] = E[T PS ].</formula><p>5 Optimality of FB is not a new result <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. We present it here for the paper to be self-contained. Interestingly, we observe that choosing appropriately the value of the threshold a, PS + PS(a) can significantly reduce the mean delay value with respect to PS (up to 40% of reduction). Similarly, with the same optimal choice of the threshold a, PS + PS(a) can compete with FB in respect to the mean delay.</p><p>Another positive performance characteristic of PS + PS(a) stems from the apparent insensitivity properties with respect to the value of the threshold. For instance, the mean delay of PS + PS(a) does not vary significantly in the range 100 ≤ a ≤ 300 (F (100) = 0.9 and F (300) = 0.97). This effect is even more pronounced when more heavy-tailed distributions are considered (for example unbounded Pareto).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We have shown, in the mean delay sense, the order between PS, FB and TLPS scheduling disciplines, FB+PS and PS+PS, under given job size distributions. The analysis considered general distributions, based on the characteristics of their hazard rate. The given proofs are based on pathwise and meanwise arguments. Using similar techniques, we showed the order between disciplines within any level of an MLPS discipline.</p><p>Our results imply that, under the current Internet traffic mix, the better the scheduling policy takes into account the attained service of the job, the smaller the mean delay of the system is. Regarding implementations one must consider how this is done on the packet level. As proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref>, this can be done by assuming that the attained service can be inferred from the packet count or byte count (sequence number) of the flow. However, implementing a packet level mechanism based on FB, would require a strict ordering of each byte or packet of each flow at the core router's, e.g., infinite number of priority classes or full flow level information at all routers. On the other hand for twolevel scheduling, such as PS+PS, only division of packets or bytes into two priority classes at the edge of the network is required.</p><p>Topics of further research include studying more general MLPS disciplines including the quantitative gain between changing a discipline within a level of an MLPS discipline. Since the optimality of FB and SRPT holds under general job arrival processes, one would expect that PS+PS would be better than PS even when the Poisson assumption is removed. Other further research includes studying the order of these MLPS scheduling disciplines in terms of other metrics than mean delay, e.g., slowdown or throughput, and generalizing the results to distributions with weaker conditions than DHR, such as NWUE. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX</head><p>Furthermore, since φ(0) = 0 and φ(x) ≤ 0 for all x ≥ 0, there exists x0 such that φ (x) ≤ 0 for all x &lt; x0. Define now A b 1 = 0, and then recursively, for all k = 1, 2, . . ., </p><formula xml:id="formula_79">A e k = B b k = inf{x &gt; A b k | φ (x) &gt; 0} B e k = A b k+1 = inf{x &gt; B b k | φ (x) ≤ 0}.</formula><formula xml:id="formula_80">x ∈ (A b k , A e k ), φ (x) ≤ 0,<label>(23)</label></formula><p>and, for all x ∈ (B b k , B e k ), φ (x) &gt; 0.</p><p>Furthermore, denote, for all k, The last inequality is due to <ref type="bibr">(22)</ref>. Thus, the claim is true in these first intervals A 1 and B 1 . In particular, we have I1 ≤ h(B b 1 )∆1 ≤ 0. 2 • Let then k &gt; 1 and assume that</p><formula xml:id="formula_82">∆ k = Z B e k 0 φ (y)dy,<label>(25)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_83">I k−1 ≤ h(B b k−1 )∆ k−1 ≤ 0.<label>(27)</label></formula><p>By <ref type="bibr">(27)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">(23)</ref> Thus, the claim is true in these intervals A k and B k . In particular, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_84">I k ≤ h(B b k )∆ k ≤ 0</formula><p>, which completes the proof.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>= d dy E[N (y)] and T (y) = d dy E[T (y)]. In addition to the continuous part, for which N (y + i ) − N (y − i ) = 0, there may be a countable number of</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Mean delay T π (x) of a job with service time x, for π = {PS, PS + PS(1000)}, under service time distribution BP(13, 3500, 1.1) and load ρ = 0.9</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Mean unfinished truncated work U π x of those jobs with attained service less than x, for π = {PS, PS + PS(1000)}, under service time distribution BP(13, 3500, 1.1) and load ρ = 0.9</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 :Figure 4 :</head><label>34</label><figDesc>Figure 3: Mean unfinished untruncated work V π x for π = {PS, FB, PS + PS(1000)} under service time distribution BP(13, 3500, 1.1) and load ρ = 0.9</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5: Mean delay E[T π ], for π = {PS, PS + PS(a), FB + PS(a), FB}, as a function of a under service time distribution BP(13, 3500, 1.1) and load ρ = 0.9</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Lemma 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Let φ be a real-valued function on [0, ∞) and h a non-negative function on (0, ∞). Assume that φ is dif- ferentiable, φ(0) = 0, and φ(x) ≤ 0 for all x ≥ 0. Assume further that h is decreasing. Then, for any x ≥ 0, Z x 0 φ (y)h(y)dy ≤ 0. Proof. Note first that, for all x ≥ 0, Z x 0 φ (y)dy = φ(x) ≤ 0.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>I</head><label></label><figDesc>k = Z B e k 0 φ (y)h(y)dy. (26) 1 • Consider first the intervals A 1 and B 1 . By (23), we have, for all x ∈ [A b 1 , A e 1 ], Z x 0 φ (y)h(y)dy ≤ 0. Let then x ∈ [B b 1 , B e 1 ]. Now, since h is decreasing and A</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Let then x ∈ [B b k , B e k ]. Similarly as in 1 • , since h is decreas- ing and A e k = B b k , we have Z x A b kThus, by (27), (22) and the fact that h(B b k−1 ) ≥ h(B b k ), we have Z x 0 φ (y)h(y)dy = I k−1 + Z x A b k φ (y)h(y)dy ≤ h(B b k−1 )∆ k−1 + h(B b k ) Z x A b k φ (y)dy ≤ h(B b k ) Z x 0 φ (y)dy ≤ 0.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>4 .and U π x for a bounded Pareto service time distribution BP (13, 3500, 1.1) are depicted in</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Therefore, 
while FB minimizes U π 
x (t) (as seen above in Proposition 5), 
FB does not minimize V π 
x (t) nor V 

π 

x . 
Numerical examples of V 

π 

x </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>The x -axis is thus divided into intervals A 1 , B 1 , A 2 , B 2 , . . ., where A k = [A b k , A e k ) and B k = [B b k , B e k ).</head><label>x</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Note further that, 
for all </table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> Introduced by L. Kleinrock in the early 1970&apos;s, see [2].</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A proof of the optimality of the shortest remaining processing time discipline</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Schrage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Operations Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="687" to="690" />
			<date type="published" when="1968" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kleinrock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Queueing Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1976" />
			<publisher>John Wiley and Sons</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Processor-sharing queues: Some progress in analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Yashkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Queueing Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On feedback sharing a processor among jobs with minimal serviced length</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Yashkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technika Sredstv Svyazi. Ser. ASU</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Russian</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scheduling multiclass single server queueing systems to stochastically maximize the number of successful departures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Righter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Shanthikumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Probability in the Engineering and Informational Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="323" to="333" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On external service disciplines in single-stage queueing systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Righter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Shanthikumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Yamazaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Probability</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="416" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differentiated control of web traffic: A numerical analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Matta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SPIE ITCOM&apos;2002: Scalability and Traffic Control in IP Networks</title>
		<meeting>SPIE ITCOM&apos;2002: Scalability and Traffic Control in IP Networks<address><addrLine>Boston, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A note on comparing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wierman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bansal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Harchol-Balter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">; /Ps</forename><surname>Queues</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Operations Research Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mixed scheduling disciplines for network flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Misra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM SIGMETRICS Perform</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eval. Rev. Special issue on MAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of LAS scheduling for job size distributions with high variance</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Rai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Urvoy-Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Biersack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGMETRICS</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGMETRICS<address><addrLine>San Diego, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="218" to="228" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classifying scheduling policies with respect to unfairness in an M/GI/1</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wierman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Harchol-Balter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGMETRICS</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGMETRICS<address><addrLine>San Diego, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="238" to="249" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differentiation between short and long TCP flows: predictability of the response time</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Avrachenkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Ayesta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nyberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Infocom</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Infocom<address><addrLine>Hong Kong</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wide-area Internet traffic patterns and characteristics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wilder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Network</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Packet-level traffic measurement from the Sprint IP backbone</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fraleigh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Moon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lyles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cotton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Moll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rockell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Seely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Diot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Network</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving the performance of interactive TCP applications using service differentiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Noureddine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tobagi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Networks Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fair marking of web flows using partial state information</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alzati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bottigliengo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Casetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mellia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of International Teletraffic Congress (ITC-18)</title>
		<meeting>International Teletraffic Congress (ITC-18)<address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="851" to="860" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new method for analysing feedback-based protocols with applications to engineering Web traffic over the Internet</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Heyman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Lakshman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Neidhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGMETRICS</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGMETRICS<address><addrLine>Seattle, WA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="38" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical bandwidth sharing: A study of congestion at flow level</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ben Fredj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bonald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Proutiere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Regnie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="122" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distribution of attained service and residual service in general queueing systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>O&amp;apos;donovan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Operations Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="570" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Riesz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Szökefalvi-Nagy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Functional Analysis, Ungar</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1955" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
