<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/atharsefid/Desktop/grobid-0.5.3/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.3" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-26T16:28+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Link Lifetimes and Randomized Neighbor Selection in DHTs</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Zhongmei</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Texas A&amp;M University College Station</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>77843</postCode>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dmitri</forename><surname>Loguinov</surname></persName>
							<email>dmitri@cs.tamu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Texas A&amp;M University College Station</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>77843</postCode>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Link Lifetimes and Randomized Neighbor Selection in DHTs</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Several models of user churn, resilience, and link lifetime have recently appeared in the literature [12], [13], [34], [35]; however, these results do not directly apply to classical Distributed Hash Tables (DHTs) in which neighbor replacement occurs not only when current users die, but also when new user arrive into the system, and where replacement choices are often restricted to the successor of the failed zone in the DHT space. To understand neighbor churn in such networks, this paper proposes a simple, yet accurate, model for capturing link dynamics in structured P2P systems and obtains the distribution of link lifetimes for fairly generic DHTs. Similar to [8], our results show that deterministic networks (e.g., Chord [28], CAN [24]) unfortunately do not extract much benefit from heavy-tailed user lifetimes since link durations are dominated by small remaining lifetimes of newly arriving users that replace the more reliable existing neighbors. We also examine link lifetimes in randomized DHTs equipped with multiple choices for each link and show that users in such systems should prefer neighbors with smaller zones rather than larger age as suggested in prior work [13], [30]. We finish the paper by demonstrating the effectiveness of the proposed min-zone neighbor selection for heavy-tailed user lifetime distributions with the shape parameter α obtained from recent measurements [4], [31].</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Resilience of distributed peer-to-peer (P2P) networks under user churn has recently attracted significant attention and has become an important research area <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34]</ref>. Traditional metrics of performance in this analysis have been the ability of the graph to stay connected during user departure <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, behavior of immediate neighbors during churn <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, data delivery ratio <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30]</ref>, evolution of out-degree <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> and in-degree <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34]</ref>, and churn rate in the set of participating nodes <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. All metrics above depend on one fundamental parameter of churn -link lifetime, which is defined as the delay between formation of a link and its disconnection due to a sudden departure of the adjacent neighbor.</p><p>In many P2P networks, each user v creates k links to other peers when joining the system, where k may be a constant or a function of system size <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, and detects/repairs failed links in order to remain connected and perform P2P tasks (e.g., routing and key lookups) <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>. Under fairly general conditions on user lifetimes <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34]</ref>, link behavior is often modeled as an ON/OFF process in which each link is either ON at time t, which means that the corresponding user * Supported by NSF grants CCR-0306246, ANI-0312461, CNS-0434940, CNS-0519442, and CNS-0720571.</p><p>is currently alive, or OFF, which means that the user adjacent to the link has departed from the system and its failure is in the process of being detected and repaired. ON durations of links are commonly called link lifetimes and their OFF durations are called repair delays. With this setup, it is not hard to see that link lifetimes play a key role in the study of resilience, performance, and reliability of P2P networks. For instance, longer average link lifetime means that users must repair failed links less frequently, which leads to smaller churn rates in the terminology of <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, and queries are less likely to encounter dead neighbors during routing <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, which yields larger data delivery ratios <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30]</ref> and higher lookup success rates.</p><p>If links do not switch to other users during each ON duration (i.e., keep connecting to the same neighbors until they fail), then link durations are simply residual lifetimes of original neighbors. We call this model non-switching and note that it applies to certain unstructured P2P networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> and some DHTs <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. Link lifetimes for non-switching systems have been studied in fair detail under both age-independent <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34]</ref> and age-biased <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35]</ref> selection. However, many DHTs actively switch links to new neighbors before the current neighbor dies in order to balance the load and ensure DHT consistency. We call such systems switching and note that their link lifetimes require entirely different modeling techniques, which we present below. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Analysis of Existing DHTs</head><p>We start by introducing a stochastic process that keeps track of the changes in the identity of neighbors adjacent to the i-th link of a given user v as the system experiences churn. We show that this process is a regular semi-Markov chain whose first hitting time to the absorbing state corresponding to the failure of the last user holding the link is link lifetime R. Using this model, we find that the distribution of R is determined not only by lifetimes of attached users, but also by the zone size of the original neighbor holding the link.</p><p>We next obtain the Laplace transform of the distribution of R and derive its expected value E[R] for general user lifetimes L, including heavy-tailed cases. We then use this result to show that in systems with exponential peer lifetimes, link lifetime R follows the same exponential distribution, which indicates that for such cases link lifetimes are very similar to those in networks without switching <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. However, for heavytailed peer lifetimes (e.g., Pareto) observed in many real P2P networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[27]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref>, our model of link lifetime R shows that R is stochastically smaller than the residual lifetime Z of the initial neighbor holding the link and, as first observed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, the mean link lifetime E <ref type="bibr">[R]</ref> is very close to E <ref type="bibr">[L]</ref>. This is in stark contrast to the results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> where E[R] is several times larger than E[L] depending on Pareto shape α of the lifetime distribution (e.g., E[R] ≈ 11.1E <ref type="bibr">[L]</ref> for α = 1.09 observed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref> and E[R] ≈ 16.6E <ref type="bibr">[L]</ref> for α = 1.06 observed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>). This phenomenon occurs because older (i.e., more reliable) neighbors in DHTs are replaced with new arrivals that exhibit much shorter remaining lifetimes. As a result, classical DHTs unfortunately do not extract any benefits from heavytailed user lifetimes and suffer much higher link churn rates than the corresponding unstructured systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. A similar conclusion was obtained in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> for query failure rates in Chord.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Improvements</head><p>One method of overcoming the problem identified above is to utilize randomized DHTs (e.g., randomized Chord <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, randomized hypercube <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, and Symphony <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>) in which the i-th finger pointer of a given user v is randomly selected from some set S i of possible locations in the DHT space. By trying multiple options in S i and linking to the user with the best characteristics (which we determine below), the hope is to improve link lifetime and reduce the impact of churn on system performance. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> The first randomized technique, which we call max-age, selects m points in S i uniformly randomly and connects v to the user with the largest age (this method was suggested in <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30]</ref> for DHTs and <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35]</ref> for unstructured P2P systems). While quite effective in non-switching scenarios, this strategy has minimal impact in DHTs since link lifetime is determined by the remaining session length of not the first, but the last neighbor holding the link.</p><p>To overcome this limitation, we propose a novel randomized strategy that stems from our model of link lifetime R. Our theoretical results show that neighbors with larger zones (e.g., in Chord <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>, this means larger distance to the predecessor) are less reliable as they are more likely to be hit by a new arrival whose remaining lifetime will be small. To extract benefits from randomized selection, we show that users must prefer neighbors in S i with the smallest zone size rather than maximum age or any other characteristic. We call this strategy min-zone and show that it is vastly more effective than max-age selection given lifetime distributions observed in real systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref>. In addition to reduced link churn, min-zone selection benefits DHTs by balancing the load such that users with smaller zone sizes are responsible for fewer keys while forwarding more queries.</p><p>Note that min-zone selection allows one to achieve a spectrum of neighbor-selection strategies, where m = 1 corre-sponds to regular switching behavior of DHTs and m → ∞ (assuming |S i | → ∞) corresponds to a non-switching system (in fact, different links of the same peer may use different m depending on the size of each S i ). However, unlike purely nonswitching networks that create inconsistences in finger tables and sometimes require routing along successor/predecessor links, min-zone selection always keeps the network consistent.</p><p>We finish the paper by showing that under min-zone selection and shape parameter 1 &lt; α ≤ 2, the mean link lifetime E[R] tends to infinity as the number of samples m becomes large. We also suggest simple formulas for E[R] using examples of Pareto shape α obtained from recent measurements <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref> and show simple results demonstrating the growth rate of E <ref type="bibr">[R]</ref> as a function of m.</p><p>The rest of the paper is organized as follows. Section II overviews related work. Section III introduces our model of user churn, DHT space, and zone splitting. In Section IV, we propose a general model of analyzing link lifetimes based on the semi-Markov chain associated with neighbor zone occupancy. We then apply this model to examine link lifetimes in deterministic DHTs in Section V and randomized DHTs in Section VI. Section VII concludes the paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. RELATED WORK</head><p>Among the recent studies of link lifetimes, one direction focuses on non-switching P2P systems. <ref type="bibr">Leonard et al. [12]</ref> show that heavy-tailed lifetimes allow link lifetime E[R] to be significantly larger than user lifetime E <ref type="bibr">[L]</ref>. Additional results of this model and its application to unstructured networks are available in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35]</ref>. Another recent study <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30]</ref> examines DHTs without switching with a focus on the delivery ratio, which is the fraction of time that all forwarding nodes between each source and destination are alive. Their results show that the delivery ratio is a function of link lifetime R for all examined neighbor-selection techniques.</p><p>The other direction covers switching networks exemplified by traditional DHTs. Godfrey et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> study the impact of node-selection techniques on the churn rate and observe that switching DHTs exhibit dramatically smaller link lifetimes than non-switching networks. <ref type="bibr">Krishnamurthy et al. [11]</ref> compute the probability that neighbors in Chord are in one of three states (alive, failed, or incorrect) and use this model to predict lookup consistency and latency.</p><p>Additional work <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref> focuses on measurement and simulation of structured P2P systems under churn.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. GENERAL DHT MODEL</head><p>We start by formulating assumptions on the DHT space, churn model, and link switching in DHTs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Assumptions</head><p>Without loss of generality, we assume that the network maps keys and users into the same identifier (ID) space, which is a continuous ring in the interval [0, 1) <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Each user is responsible for a fraction of the DHT space from itself to its successor, which we call the user's zone. To facilitate routing, each joining peer v selects and then monitors using some stabilization technique k links in the DHT space as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1(a)</ref>. For the churn model, we adopt the recently introduced <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34]</ref> framework of n alternating renewal processes representing periodic online/offline behavior of users observed in real traces <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref>. In this model, each user i is viewed as alternating between online and offline states, where the duration of each state is random and has some user-specific distribution. While the total number of users n is fixed, the number of currently alive peers N t at time t is a random process that fluctuates over time. Once stationarity is reached, we usually replace N t with its limiting version N = lim t→∞ N t . We finally assume that when a particular user rejoins the system, it generates a new random ID (e.g., based on its IP-port pair) instead of using the same fixed hash. Note that the use of new IDs helps balance the load in the DHT <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref>. As a consequence of this churn model <ref type="bibr">[34, Theorem 5]</ref>, user arrivals into the system follow a Poisson process with a constant rate</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">λ = E[N ]/E[L], where E[N ]</formula><p>is the average number of users in the steady state and E <ref type="bibr">[L]</ref> is the mean user lifetime.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Neighbor Dynamics</head><p>Note that the main focus of the paper is on the behavior of one particular link i in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>(a) and neighbors adjacent to it during v's online session. As user v continues to stay in the system, the identity of its neighbors (i.e., successors of its neighbor pointers) may change over time as users join and leave the system. There are two types of changes in neighbor tables -graceful handoffs of an existing zone to another user and abrupt departures without explicit notification of v. The former type, which we call a switch, occurs when a new arrival takes ownership of a link by becoming the new successor of the corresponding neighbor pointer. This is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>(b) where a new arrival w splits the zone of an existing neighbor u and becomes the new neighbor of v. The latter type of neighbor change, which we call a recovery, happens when an existing neighbor dies (which is considered to be abrupt) and the successor of the failed neighbor takes over that zone to become the new neighbor of v.</p><p>We next define several additional metrics to facilitate explanation in later parts of the paper. Notice that one cycle in the life of a particular neighbor pointer is composed of several (a) one recovery cycle switches and one recovery as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref>(a). In the figure, thick horizonal lines represent online presence of peers that own v's neighbor pointer in the DHT space. The topmost line is the original neighbor with residual lifetime Z 1 acquired by v during join. As peers split the zone of the current neighbor, the link switches to two additional users. Once the last user dies at time R 1 , the link is considered dead and a replacement process is initiated. 3 Recovery is complete after S time units when another node takes over the zone of the dead peer and is selected as v's new neighbor.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">R 1 R 3 R 2 S S R 1 (b) ON/OFF link behavior</formula><p>In all other aspects, the second recovery cycle behaves identical to the first one and leads to link failure after R 2 time units. This ON/OFF nature of a link process is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref>(b) where we assume that all repair delays S are i.i.d. random variables, but the distribution of link lifetimes R 1 , R 2 , . . . may depend on the cycle number (in fact they do in certain cases studied below).</p><p>The final note is that it is important to distinguish the residual lifetime of the first neighbor from that of a link. While in non-switching systems the former metric (e.g., variables Z 1 , Z 2 , . . .) determine how long a link stays alive, this is no longer the case in switching networks. Instead, the latter metric formalized as R 1 , R 2 , . . . determines query performance and a user's ability to tolerate churn. Our next step is to understand the behavior of these random variables under general lifetime distributions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. LINK LIFETIME MODEL</head><p>In this section, we construct a semi-Markov model for the distribution of lifetimes R 1 , R 2 , . . . of a given link in a user's routing table.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Preliminaries</head><p>Recall that arriving users split zones of existing nodes based on a uniformly random hashing function. Denote by U the random zone size of existing users in a stationary system as shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3(a)</ref>. Further assume that during join or the current recovery step that starts cycle j, successor u takes over pointer i as shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3(b)</ref>. Then, define Y j to be the remaining zone size between this pointer and the index of u.</p><p>Intuitively, if the remaining zone Y j is large, then it is likely that a new arrival will soon split the zone and the ownership of the link will be transferred to another peer. Therefore, link lifetimes are determined not by the distribution of U , but rather by that of Y j . We derive both metrics later in the paper and next show how they can be used to obtain R 1 , R 2 , . . . For simplicity of notation, define conditional link lifetime R(y) as the duration of the link conditioned on the fact that the remaining zone size Y j is y &gt; 0. Then, observe that the CDF of link lifetimes R j can be written as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">P (R j &lt; x) = ∞ 0 P (R(y) &lt; x)f Yj (y)dy,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where f Yj (y) is the probability density function (PDF) of remaining zone size Y j (note that the distribution of Y j depends on cycle number j). Similarly, we can obtain the expectation of R j as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">E[R j ] = ∞ 0 E[R(y)]f Y j (y)dy.<label>(2)</label></formula><p>Thus, the task of deriving link lifetime R j is reduced to analyzing the properties of conditional link lifetime R(y) and the distribution of remaining zone size Y j . In the rest of this section, we construct a semi-Markov process for each R(y) and leave the derivation of the distribution of Y j for deterministic DHTs to Section V and that for randomized DHTs to Section VI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Conditional Link Lifetimes</head><p>For each zone size y, let variable A y δ count the number of switches (i.e., replacements by new users) that have occurred along the link in the time interval <ref type="bibr">[0, δ]</ref>, where time 0 denotes the instance when user v finds the first neighbor at the beginning of the current cycle. Denote by A y δ = F a special absorbing state into which A y δ arrives if the current neighbor attached to the link is in the failed state at time δ.</p><p>Then, it is easy to see that {A y δ ; δ ≥ 0} is a continuous-time stochastic process with state space {F, 0, 1, 2, . . .} whose state transitions are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref>. As depicted in this figure, for each state i ≥ 0, the process can jump into either state i + 1, which means that a given zone is further split by a new arrival (i.e., the number of switches increases by 1), or state F , which represents link failure. The initial state of the process at time 0 is always 0. Using notation {A y δ }, variable R(y) can be described as the first-hitting time of process {A y δ } onto state F given that</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">A y 0 = 0: R(y) = inf{δ &gt; 0 : A y δ = F |A y 0 = 0, Y j = y}.<label>(3)</label></formula><p>The next theorem shows that {A y δ ; δ ≥ 0} is a semi-Markov chain that describes the process of new users entering a given zone of initial length y and repeatedly splitting it.</p><p>Theorem 1: Process {A y δ , δ ≥ 0} for a given remaining zone size Y j = y is a regular semi-Markov chain. The sojourn time τ i in state i follows the following general distribution:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">P (τ i &gt; x) = P (W 0 &gt; x)P (Z j &gt; x) i = 0 P (W i &gt; x)P (L &gt; x) i ≥ 1 ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where Z j is the residual lifetime of the first neighbor that starts the j-th cycle, L is user lifetime with CDF F (x), W i is an exponential random variable with rate λ i :</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">λ i = E[N ]y E[L]2 i , i ≥ 0,<label>(5)</label></formula><p>and E[N ] is the mean system size. Furthermore, transition probability p i,i+1 from state i to i + 1 is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">p i,i+1 = P (W 0 &lt; Z j ) i = 0 P (W i &lt; L) i ≥ 1 ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>and the probability p i,F to absorb from state i is equal to 1 − p i,i+1 . Note from (5) that as the number of switches within a zone (i.e., variable i) increases, arrival rate λ i into state i decreases exponentially fast and the mean waiting time W i until the next arrival increases at the same rate. As state i → ∞, W i → ∞ and thus process {A y δ } jumps into failed state F with probability p i,F that converges to 1.</p><p>Next, we study the distribution and expectation of conditional link lifetime R(y). Denote the CDF of the sojourn time τ i in state i by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">G i (t) = P (τ i &lt; t).<label>(7)</label></formula><p>Noting from (4) that τ i of chain {A y δ } is independent of the next state, the matrix of the semi-Markov kernel Q(t) = [q ik (t)] is given by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">q ik (t) = p ik G i (t), i, k ∈ {F, 0, 1, . . .},<label>(8)</label></formula><p>where p ik is the transition probability from state i to state k given in (6). Taking the Laplace (Stieltjes) transform of q ik (t) leads to:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">ˆ q ik (s) = ∞ 0 e −st dq ik (t) = p ik ∞ 0 e −st dG i (t).<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Define the following Laplace transform of the first hitting time R(y) from state 0 to F as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">ˆ R(s, y) = E[e −sR(y) ].<label>(10)</label></formula><p>Though it is known that the Laplace transform of the firsthitting time of a semi-Markov chain can be computed using spectral properties of kernel Q(t) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, this approach hides the effect of system parameters on the resulting distribution. Due to the simplicity of state transitions of chain {A y δ }, we next derivê R(s, y) without involving matrix operations on Q(t). Theorem 2: The Laplace transformˆRtransformˆ transformˆR(s, y) of conditional link lifetime R(y) is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">ˆ R(s, y) = ˆ q 0F (s) + ∞ k=1 k−1 i=0ˆq i=0ˆ i=0ˆq i,i+1 (s) ˆ q kF (s),<label>(11)</label></formula><p>wherê q ik (s) are shown in (9). WithˆRWithˆ WithˆR(s, y) in hand, we can apply the inverse Laplace transform to retrieve the distribution of R(y) and take the derivatives ofˆRofˆ ofˆR(s, y) to get its moments. Next, we use a simpler approach to obtain the mean E[R(y)].</p><p>Theorem 3: The expected conditional link lifetime is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">E[R(y)] = E[τ 0 ] + ∞ k=1 k−1 i=0 p i,i+1 E[τ k ],<label>(12)</label></formula><p>where E[τ k ] is the expected sojourn time in state k shown in (4) and p i,i+1 are state transition probabilities in (6).</p><p>Theorems 1-2 demonstrate that variable R(y) is fully determined by user lifetimes L and residual neighbor lifetimes Z j . Our remaining steps are to analyze the properties of Z j and derive the distribution of remaining zone sizes Y j for both deterministic and randomized DHTs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. DETERMINISTIC DHTS</head><p>In deterministic DHTs, each neighbor pointer of user v is generated based on a fixed distance between the pointer and the user. We start this section by deriving a model for R(y) under two types of user lifetimes and then analyze the distribution of residual zone size Y j .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Residual Lifetimes of Neighbors</head><p>Using the user churn model summarized in Section III-A, it has been shown in <ref type="bibr">[34, Theorem 3]</ref> that the equilibrium CDF P (Z 1 &lt; x) of residual neighbor lifetimes under random selection during join is a simple function of the user lifetime distribution F (x):</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">P (Z 1 &lt; x) = 1 E[L] x 0 (1 − F (u))du,<label>(13)</label></formula><p>where E[L] is the mean user lifetime. The next lemma shows that (13) also holds for all j ≥ 2. Lemma 1: For all j ≥ 1, the CDF of residual lifetime Z j of the initial neighbor that starts the j-th cycle converges to (13) as system age approaches infinity.</p><p>It is important to emphasize that Lemma 1 holds when switching occurs in DHTs in response to Poisson user arrivals into the system and may not hold otherwise. When a neighbor pointer switches to a new user, it loses track of which peer on the ring will be the neighbor that will start the next cycle in the link's ON/OFF process. Hence, neighbor selection during link recovery is essentially uniformly random among the existing neighbors (due to random hash indexes) and independent of the selected neighbor's age.</p><p>Before we show simulation results in the next subsection, we define rules for generating a DHT under churn. In simulations, user arrivals follow a Poisson process with a constant rate E[N ]/E <ref type="bibr">[L]</ref>, where the mean system size E[N ] and the average user lifetime E[L] are determined a-priori. Each user departs at the end of its lifetime L, which is drawn from a given distribution F (x). In addition, each joining user obtains a uniformly random hash index in [0, 1), follows the randomsplit algorithm during join, and performs recovery when its predecessors die. After the system has evolved for enough time, we compare simulation results to the derived models.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Conditional Link Lifetimes</head><p>We next use exponential and later Pareto lifetimes to study the behavior of R(y). Assume that user lifetimes L are exponential with rate µ = 1/E <ref type="bibr">[L]</ref>. Then, it is easy to obtain from Lemma 1 that residual lifetime Z j of the initial neighbor, for all cycles j ≥ 1, is exponential with the same rate µ. Using L ∼ exp(µ) and Z j ∼ exp(µ) and invoking Theorem 2 leads to the following result.</p><p>Theorem 4: For user lifetimes L with CDF 1 − e −µx , link lifetime R j is independent of remaining zone size Y j and has the same distribution as L:</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">P (R j &lt; x) = 1 − e −µx , for all j ≥ 1,<label>(14)</label></formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">µ = 1/E[L].</formula><p>Model <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(14)</ref> is very accurate as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 5</ref>. Notice from the left figure that E[R j ] is equal to mean user lifetime E <ref type="bibr">[L]</ref> and from the right figure that the distribution of R j is indeed exponential, which holds for any j ≥ 1 (only R 3 is shown in the <ref type="figure">figure)</ref>.</p><p>The rationale behind Theorem 4 can be explained as follows. Recall that Z j is the residual lifetime of the first neighbor u that owns the neighbor pointer in each cycle. Due to the memoryless property of exponential distributions, the remaining time of Z j obtained at a random instant is still exponential with rate µ, which matches the lifetime distribution of new arrivals entering the same zone. Therefore, it makes no difference whether a current neighbor u is replaced by a new arrival or not. Then, it is not hard to see that the link lifetime has the same distribution as Z j , which is exp(µ). A similar scenario is observed in M/M/1 queues <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[33]</ref> where customers can be interrupted during services and the distribution of the total service time required for a customer does not change.</p><p>Theorem 4 indicates that switching has no impact on link lifetimes in any DHT with exponential user lifetimes, which makes analysis of system performance in such systems very simple. However, we should note that this result does not hold for any non-exponential lifetime distribution. As recent measurements of P2P networks show that user lifetimes are often heavy-tailed <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref>, we next use the Pareto distribution P (L &lt; x) = 1 − (1 + x/β) −α with shape parameter α &gt; 1 and scale parameter β &gt; 0 to estimate the performance of real DHTs under churn.</p><p>For Pareto lifetimes, it is clear from Lemma 1 that the residual lifetime Z j of initial neighbors follows the CDF P (Z j &lt; x) = 1−(1+x/β) −(α−1) for all j ≥ 1, which shows that Z j are also Pareto distributed but more heavy-tailed. Next, we apply Theorem 2 to obtain the Laplace transformˆRtransformˆ transformˆR(y, s) and Theorem 3 to obtain the mean of R(y).</p><p>Theorem 5: For Pareto lifetimes L, the mean conditional link lifetime E[R(y)] is given by (12) with</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">E[τ i ] = βe λ i β E αi (λ i β), p i,i+1 = λ i E[τ i ]<label>(15)</label></formula><p>where arrival rate λ i is given in (5), E k (x) = ∞ 1 e −xu u −k du is the generalized exponential integral, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">α i = α − 1, i = 0 α i ≥ 1 .<label>(16)</label></formula><p>Furthermore, the Laplace transformˆRtransformˆ transformˆR(y, s) is given by (11) withˆq</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">withˆ withˆq i,i+1 (s) = λ i E[τ i ]A, ˆ q iF (s) = (1 − λ i E[τ i ])A,<label>(17)</label></formula><p>where <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(15)</ref> and α i in (16). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 6</ref> shows that simulation results of E[R(y)] for any fixed remaining zone size y are consistent with the model given in Theorem 5. Moreover, notice from this figure that as remaining zone size y reduces, E[R(y)] increases and converges to E[Z 1 ], where the distribution of neighbor residual lifetime Z 1 is given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">A = 1 + (1 − λ i − s)βe (λi+s)β E α i ((λ i + s)β), and E[τ i ] is shown in</formula><p>We next derive the distribution of zone sizes in deterministic DHTs in order to obtain a computable model for R j . </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Zone Sizes</head><p>In order to determine the distribution of zone sizes U and Y j in <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>, we must decide on the zone splitting method. The derivations below only cover the random-split <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref> mechanism (i.e., zones are split at hash indexes of arriving users) that is used in Chord <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref> and only considers one-dimensional DHTs. A similar derivation can be carried out for the center-split <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> strategy (i.e., zones are always split in the center) and multi-dimensional DHTs, but this analysis is much more tedious and is not shown here.</p><p>Since all arriving users are placed in the interval [0, 1), the average zone size is approximately 1/E <ref type="bibr">[N ]</ref>, where N is the random system size in the steady-state. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> The next result states that in equilibrium DHTs, zone sizes no larger than 1/ E[N ] are distributed approximately exponentially. Since most zone sizes do not deviate from the mean very far, this result directly applies to random variable U defined earlier.</p><p>Lemma 2: As the mean system size tends to infinity, the distribution of small zones in the DHT becomes approximately exponential:</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">lim E[N ]→∞ P (U &gt; x) e −E[N ]x = 1<label>(18)</label></formula><p>for all x such that x 2 E[N ] → 0. Our next task is to obtain the distribution of remaining zone size Y j in each cycle j ≥ 1.</p><p>Lemma 3: For a given zone size y, assume that</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">y 2 E[N ] → 0 as E[N ] → ∞. Then, the PDF f Yj (y) of remaining zone size Y j is asymptotically:      lim E[N ]→∞ f Y 1 (y) E[N ]e −E[N ]y = 1 j = 1 lim E[N ]→∞ f Y j (y) E[N ] 2 ye −E[N ]y = 1 j ≥ 2 ,<label>(19)</label></formula><p>where E[N ] is the mean system size in equilibrium. Lemma 3 shows that the distribution of Y 1 is exponential and that of Y j for j ≥ 2 is Erlang-2. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 7,  model (19)</ref> is very accurate even for small average system size </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Putting the Pieces Together</head><p>The final step is to apply <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(1)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(2)</ref> to uncondition the distribution of link lifetime R j and its mean E[R j ] using the distribution of initial zone size Y j given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>. To this end, substituting E[R(y)] shown in Theorem 5 and the PDF of Y j in <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">(19)</ref> into <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">(2)</ref> leads to the final result on the mean link lifetime E[R j ]. Similarly, to get the distribution of R j , we first retrieve the distribution of R(y) fromˆRfromˆ fromˆR(s, y) in Theorem 5 by applying an existing inverse Laplace transform software package <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Then substituting the distribution of R(y) and (19) into (1) leads to the final model of the distribution of link lifetime R j . <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 8</ref> shows simulations results and the model of the mean link lifetime E[R j ] and the average residual lifetime E[Z j ] of the initial neighbor that starts the j-th cycle. The model of E[Z j ] is obtained using (13) and the general solution to E[R j ] is given in (2). As shown in the figure, both models match simulation results very well and as α becomes smaller, the difference between E[R j ] and E[Z j ] increases as expected. The above results also show that the process of switching to new users can significantly reduce the lifetime of a link and that deterministic DHT systems with Pareto L can exhibit</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">E[R j ] very close to E[L]</formula><p>. This is in contrast to unstructured P2P systems where E[R j ] can be 11 − 16 times higher than E[L] depending on shape parameter α <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref>.</p><p>Further observe from the model and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 8</ref>    The most intriguing result shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 8</ref> is that E[R j ] for all j ≥ 2 is very close to the mean user lifetime E <ref type="bibr">[L]</ref> under different values of α (e.g., E[R 4 ] = 0.986 hours for α = 3 and 1.096 for α = 2.2). However, from the model of the tail distribution of link lifetime R 4 shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig. 9</ref>, observe that the distribution of R j for j ≥ 2 is actually different from that of lifetime L and is less heavy-tailed than the original distribution. A similar result holds for other values of α and other distributions, which we do not show for brevity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. RANDOMIZED LINKS</head><p>Our analysis suggests that since the user arrival process into a DHT is unchangeable, peers may utilize knowledge of residual lifetime Z j of the initial owner of a given link and remaining zone size Y j to improve link lifetime R j . In the following, we make use of the freedom of selecting links in randomized DHTs to achieve the goal of increasing R j using two link-selection strategies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Max-Age Selection</head><p>The first strategy we apply for selecting neighbor pointers is called max-age <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35]</ref>. In this technique, which we explain using the example of Randomized Chord <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, user v with hash index id(v) ∈ [0, 1) uniformly randomly samples m points in the range [id(v) + 2 i /2 64 , id(v) + 2 i+1 /2 64 ) and selects the point whose successor has the maximum age as its i-th neighbor pointer. Note that switching occurs as described before (i.e., when new users split a given zone and replace existing neighbors) and link failure is repaired by replacing the dead neighbor (i.e., the last user holding the link) with the current successor.</p><p>It is clear that link lifetimes R j for all cycles j ≥ 1 have the same distribution since the neighbor pointer in each cycle is uniformly randomly generated within a certain range of users (as mentioned before, we assume the range is large enough to support non-trivial choices). Simulation results of max-age selection and the model of E[Z j ] from <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35]</ref> are shown in while E[R j ] rises from 1.17 hours to only 2.09 hours as m increases from 1 to 19. These two subfigures demonstrate that the improvement in terms of the mean link lifetime E[R j ] under max-age selection is generally very small since new arrivals sooner or later split initial neighbors to take ownership of the link and hence ages or residual lifetimes of original neighbors do not affect link churn rate very much.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Min-Zone Selection</head><p>To reduce the likelihood that new arrivals replace old neighbors when splitting a given zone, we propose a new strategy called min-zone. Similar to the max-age method, user v uniformly samples m points in [id(v)+2 i /2 64 , id(v)+2 i+1 /2 64 ), but then selects the point whose successor has the minimum zone size.</p><p>To obtain a model for E[R j ] under min-zone selection, first note that residual lifetime Z j of the initial neighbor starting the j-th cycle follows the distribution given in (13) since all m samples are uniformly random and zone sizes are independent of user ages or lifetimes. It is then clear that for a fixed remaining size Y j = y, the Laplace transform and the mean conditional link lifetime given in Theorem 5 are both still valid. Next, given that initial zone size Y j is minimum among m uniformly randomly selected samples, we readily obtain:</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">P (Y j &gt; y) = [P (U &gt; y)] m , for all j ≥ 1,<label>(20)</label></formula><p>where U is the zone size of a randomly selected user on the ring whose limiting distribution shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>. The final step is to combine <ref type="bibr">Theorem 5 and (20)</ref> to obtain the distribution of R j and its mean under min-zone selection. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 11</ref>, the model of E[R j ] matches simulation results very well. Most interestingly, the figure demonstrates that the mean link lifetime E[R j ] under min-zone selection is significantly larger than that under max-age selection for both choices of α and that the difference between the two metrics becomes more pronounced as the number of samples m increases or shape α decreases. Furthermore, this figure suggests that as m → ∞, E[R j ] for min-zone selection and α &lt; 2 goes to infinity, while E[R j ] for max-age selection converges to some fixed number regardless of α. The following theorem confirms this result.</p><p>Theorem 6: For Pareto user lifetimes with 1 &lt; α ≤ 2, the expected link lifetime under min-zone selection approaches infinity for sufficiently large system population and random sample size: lim E[N ]→∞ lim m→∞ E[R j ] = ∞. For max-age selection and any α, the mean link lifetime converges to a constant:</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">lim E[N ]→∞ lim m→∞ E[R j ] &lt; ∞.</formula><p>The above analysis indicates that min-zone selection is significantly better than max-age selection for very heavytailed user lifetimes. Since real systems have been observed to exhibit α ≈ 1.06 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and α = 1.09 in <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref>, this result paves a simple way for building better DHTs in practice. The amount of actual improvement in E[R j ] for these two values of α is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12</ref>, where the growth rate in both curves is approximately linear in m. The figures also show the corresponding linear fits to the model, which can be used to predict how m affects link lifetime E[R j ] in these two cases. For instance, with α = 1.09, users can obtain E[R j ] ≈ 76 hours by sampling m = 10 points for each suitable (i.e., with enough random choices) link in a randomized DHT. For α = 1.06, the corresponding average link lifetime is 127 hours. Comparing these numbers to E[R j ] ≈ E[L] = 1 hour in deterministic DHTs, the extent of improvement is undoubtedly dramatic.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. CONCLUSION</head><p>This paper formalized the notion of "link lifetimes" in certain types of DHTs where link pointers switch to new neighbors in response to arriving peers. We introduced a semiMarkov process to model random replacement of neighbors along a given link and showed that lifetimes of deterministic links are much worse than those in unstructured P2P networks with heavy-tailed user lifetimes. For randomized DHTs, our results show that the proposed min-zone selection method is substantially more effective than the commonly-used max-age selection strategy and the mean link lifetime E[R j ] under minzone selection can be increased approximately linearly in the number of points m each user v samples.</p><p>Future work involves development of more sophisticated algorithms for increased DHT resilience, analysis of nonPoisson arrivals, and analysis of asymptotically small networks where limiting results similar to Theorem 6 do not hold.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. User v's neighbors in the DHT.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. The i-th link failure and replacement of user v who joins at time 0 in a DHT, 1 ≤ i ≤ k.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Zone size U and remaining zone size Y j of user u.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. State diagram for the process {A j δ , δ ≥ 0} of neighbor changes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. Comparison of model (14) to simulations in a deterministic DHT with E[N ] = 2, 000 and exponential user lifetimes with E[L] = 1 hour.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. Comparison of model E[R(y)] in Theorem 5 to simulation results in a deterministic DHT with mean size E[N ] = 2, 000 and Pareto user lifetimes L with mean E[L] = 1 hour and β = E[L](α − 1).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Comparison of simulation results on the distribution of Y j to model (19) in a deterministic DHT with mean size E[N ] = 500 under churn introduced by Pareto L with α = 3 and E[L] = 1 hour.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. Comparison of E[R j ] to E[Z j ] in a deterministic DHT with mean size E[N ] = 2, 500 users, Pareto lifetimes with mean E[L] = 1 hour, and β = E[L](α − 1).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Link lifetimes R 4 are less heavy-tailed than Pareto user lifetimes L in a deterministic DHT with mean size E[N ] = 2, 500 peers, E[L] = 1 hour, and β = (α − 1)E[L].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10. Impact of shape α and number of samples m on mean link lifetime E[R j ] under max-age selection in a randomized DHT with mean size E[N ] = 2, 000 for Pareto lifetimes with E[L] = 1 hour and β = E[L](α − 1).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>First notice from part (a) that for a fixed number of samples m = 6, as shape α decreases, the mean link lifetime E[R j ] increases much slower than the mean residual lifetime E[Z j ] of the initial neighbor (in fact, E[Z j ] = ∞ for α ≤ 2). A similar phenomenon appears in part (b) where E[Z j ] increases at the rate of √ m for α = 3 (see [35, Lemma 5]),</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Fig. 11. Comparison of mean link lifetime E[R j ] under min-zone selection to that under max-age selection in a randomized DHT with mean size E[N ] = 2, 000 for Pareto user lifetimes with E[L] = 1 hour and β = E[L](α − 1).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Fig. 12. Approximation of E[R j ] as a linear function of number of samples m under min-zone selection for Pareto user lifetimes with E[L] = 1 hour and β = E[L](α − 1).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>that link lifetimes are completely characterized by two random variables R 1 and R 2 since R j for j ≥ 3 has the same distribution as R 2 . This arises from the fact that zone size Y 1 is different from Y 2 , while Y j for j ≥ 3 are all distributed as Y 2 . Since Y 1 is stochastically smaller than Y 2 (see Lemma 3), it follows that R 1 is stochastically larger than R 2 . Furthermore, from the analysis of the Markov chain in previous sections, it becomes clear that selecting neighbors with smaller initial zone sizes leads to larger link lifetimes since such neighbors are less likely to be replaced by newly arriving users and the link's E[R j ] will be closer to E[Z j ].</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> In the notation of [8], switching/non-switching are agnostic neighbor replacement strategies, where the former is called Active Preference List (APL) and the latter encompasses both Passive Preference List (PPL) and Random Replacement (RR).</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> Note that this method only works when set S i is sufficiently large. We assume that each node has at least one link that satisfies this condition.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> Specifics of detecting failure are not essential to our results as repair delay is not studied in this paper.</note>

			<note place="foot" n="4"> Approximation E[1/N ] ≈ 1/E[N ] is asymptotically accurate as system size tends to infinity.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-Precision Laplace Transform Inversion</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Abate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Valkó</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Numer. Meth. Engng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="979" to="993" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding Availability</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bhagwan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Savage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Voelker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IPTPS</title>
		<meeting>IPTPS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-02" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="256" to="267" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed Computation of Passage Time Quantiles and Transient State Distributions in Large Semi-Markov Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dingle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Knottenbelt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IPDPS</title>
		<meeting>IPDPS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Friendships that Last: Peer Lifespan and its Role in P2P Protocols</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bustamante</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Qiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Intl. Workshop on Web Content Caching and Distribution</title>
		<meeting>Intl. Workshop on Web Content Caching and Distribution</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance and Dependability of Structured Peer-to-Peer Overlays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rowstron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. DSN</title>
		<meeting>DSN</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to Stochastic Processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Gnutella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.gnutella.com/" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimizing Churn in Distributed Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Godfrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stoica</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Personal Communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Godfrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Impact of DHT Routing Geometry on Resilience and Proximity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gummadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gummadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gribble</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ratnasamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stoica</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="394" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Statistical Theory of Chord under Churn</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Krishnamurthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>El-Ansary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Aurell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haridi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IPTPS</title>
		<meeting>IPTPS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-02" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="103" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On Lifetime-Based Node Failure and Stochastic Resilience of Decentralized Peer-to-Peer Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Leonard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Rai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Loguinov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGMETRICS</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGMETRICS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-06" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="37" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On Static and Dynamic Partitioning Behavior of Large-Scale Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Leonard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Loguinov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE ICNP</title>
		<meeting>IEEE ICNP</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-11" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="345" to="357" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparing the Performance of Distributed Hash Tables under Churn</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stribling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kaashoek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IPTPS</title>
		<meeting>IPTPS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-02" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="99" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bandwidth-Efficient Management of DHT Routing Tables</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stribling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kaashoek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. USENIX NSDI</title>
		<meeting>USENIX NSDI</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-05" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Performance vs. Cost Framework for Evaluating DHT Design Tradeoffs under Churn</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stribling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kaashoek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-03" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="236" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of the Evolution of the Peer-to-Peer Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liben-Nowell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Balakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Karger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM PODC</title>
		<meeting>ACM PODC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-07" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="242" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graph-Theoretic Analysis of Structured Peer-to-Peer Systems: Routing Distances and Fault Resilience</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Loguinov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Rai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ganesh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="406" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Symphony: Distributed Hashing in a Small World</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Manku</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Raghavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. USITS</title>
		<meeting>USITS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-03" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="140" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Know thy Neighbor&apos;s Neighbor: the Power of Lookahead in Randomized P2P Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Manku</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Naor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Weider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM STOC</title>
		<meeting>ACM STOC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-06" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="63" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kademlia: A Peer-to-Peer Information System Based on the XOR Metric</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Maymounkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mazieres</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IPTPS</title>
		<meeting>IPTPS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-03" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="65" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel Architectures for P2P Applications: the Continuous-Discrete Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Naor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Wieder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SPAA</title>
		<meeting>ACM SPAA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-06" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="59" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building Low-Diameter Peer-to-Peer Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pandurangan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Raghavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Upfal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE J. Sel. Areas Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="995" to="1002" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Scalable Content-Addressable Network</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ratnasamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Handley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Karp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shenker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="172" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Handling Churn in a DHT</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rhea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Geels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Roscoe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kubiatowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. USENIX Ann. Tech. Conf</title>
		<meeting>USENIX Ann. Tech. Conf</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-06" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="140" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pastry: Scalable, Decentralized Object Location and Routing for Large-Scale Peer-to-Peer Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rowstron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Druschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc</title>
		<meeting>null</meeting>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
				<title level="m">IFIP/ACM International Conference on Distributed Systems Platforms (Middleware)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-11" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="329" to="350" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Measurement Study of Peer-to-Peer File Sharing Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Saroiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gummadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gribble</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE/ACM Multimedia Computing and Networking</title>
		<meeting>SPIE/ACM Multimedia Computing and Networking</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-01" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">4673</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="170" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chord: A Scalable Peer-to-Peer Lookup Service for Internet Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Stoica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Karger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kaashoek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Balakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGCOMM</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCOMM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="160" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding Churn in Peer-to-Peer Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stutzbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rejaie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM IMC</title>
		<meeting>ACM IMC</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="202" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stochastic Analysis and Improvement of the Reliability of DHT-based Multicast</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jarvis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007-05" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2198" to="2206" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Residual-Based Measurement of Peer and Link Lifetimes in Gnutella Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Loguinov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007-05" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="391" to="399" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On Zone-Balancing of Peer-to-Peer Networks: Analysis of Random Node Join</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Loguinov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM SIGMETRICS</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGMETRICS</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-06" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="222" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Stochastic Modeling and the Theory of Queues</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wolff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling Heterogeneous User Churn and Local Resilience of Unstructured P2P Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Leonard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Loguinov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE ICNP</title>
		<meeting>IEEE ICNP</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006-11" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="41" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On Node Isolation under Churn in Unstructured P2P Networks with Heavy-Tailed Lifetimes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Leonard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Loguinov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE INFOCOM</title>
		<meeting>IEEE INFOCOM</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007-05" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2126" to="2134" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
