<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reputation in Privacy Enhancing Technologies</p>
    <p>Paul Syverson Naval Research Laboratory</p>
    <p>E-mail: syverson@itd.nrl.navy.mil URL: www.syverson.org</p>
    <p>joint work with</p>
    <p>Roger Dingledine, Nick Mathewson The Free Haven Project</p>
    <p>URL: www.freehaven.net</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PETs does more than you think for privacy Privacy Enhancing Technologies Workshop (www.pet2002.org) Basic research on defining anonymity (information theory)</p>
    <p>Allows us to measure the privacy provided by a system Surprising system designs</p>
    <p>Private Information Retrieval (PIR):  Server cannot tell what was downloaded</p>
    <p>Location protected communication: Cell phones, Smart Tag Available systems</p>
    <p>Bugnosis: tells users when they get a web bug  LPWA/Proxymate: stateless, cryptographically robust, single</p>
    <p>signon  Safe Cookies: Sanitizing proxies  Cookie cooker: exchange cookies of participants</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PETs does more than you think for security Law Enforcement</p>
    <p>Anonymous communication makes people more comfortable when contacting authorities</p>
    <p>PETs protects activities of law enforcement Business</p>
    <p>Liability reduced if business 1. properly manages private data 2. understands and is consistent with its privacy policy</p>
    <p>Liability is really reduced if business can show it could not have (or access) private data</p>
    <p>Everyone  Pseudonymous certificates and authorization reduce identity</p>
    <p>theft and fraud</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reputation in Privacy Enhancing Technologies Reputation can enable privacy by reducing demand for information</p>
    <p>Remailer Networks How do you know if your message got through? Pinging only works for small, static networks</p>
    <p>Censorship-resistant Publishing Distributed (peer) servers store shares of documents for each other. Reputation keeps servers honest about storage. If a server reliably stores shares, it gains reputation Server (client) can &quot;spend&quot; reputation to store its own shares.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions: New Directions Reputation is not pixie dust.</p>
    <p>Reputation is already being used: eBay, Amazon, Slashdot, Google Reputation is itself a source of vulnerabilities Can we treat reputation as currency?</p>
    <p>To handle our pseudonymous future, we need good reputation systems</p>
    <p>PETs can solve a surprising variety of privacy problems</p>
    <p>Security and Privacy are not at odds, they are mutually dependent.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
