<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Secure and Efficient Network Access</p>
    <p>DIMACS Workshop, November 3rd, 2004, Piscataway, NJ, USA</p>
    <p>Jari Arkko Ericsson Research NomadicLab</p>
    <p>Pasi Eronen Nokia Research Center</p>
    <p>Pekka Nikander</p>
    <p>Vesa Torvinen Ericsson Research NomadicLab</p>
    <p>This presentation has been produced partially in the context of the Ambient Networks Project. The Ambient Networks Project is part of the European Community's Sixth Framework Program for research and is as such funded by the</p>
    <p>European Commission. All information in this document is provided ``as is'' and no guarantee or warranty is given that the information is fit for any particular purpose. The user thereof uses the information at its sole risk and liability. For the avoidance of all doubts, the European Commission has no liability in respect of this document,</p>
    <p>which is merely representing the authors view</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation Outline</p>
    <p>The Problem</p>
    <p>Ongoing work</p>
    <p>Some new ideas</p>
    <p>An example protocol run</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problem</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some Problems in Current Network Access Approaches (1/3) - Efficiency  Attachment involves a large number of messages</p>
    <p>Scanning &amp; 802.11 attachment  802.1X and EAP messaging  802.11i four-way handshake  DNA &amp; IP router and neighbor discovery  Address autoconfiguration, DAD  Mobile IP home registration  Mobile IPv6 correspondent node registration</p>
    <p>Over 50% of this is due to security</p>
    <p>Request/Response style, even across the Internet  Amount of data is growing with certificates, configuration, and discovery</p>
    <p>Multiple mandatory waiting periods  Even a second, such as for DAD</p>
    <p>Iteration over available accesses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some Problems in Current Network Access Approaches (2/3) - Security</p>
    <p>Im one of the trusted network nodes approach  Sufficient for large cell size, well protected base stations  Not very good for devices on the coffee shop wall</p>
    <p>Focus on authentication, not authorization  Does everyone know/agree with the service parameters ?</p>
    <p>Denial-of-Service problems  Use of cryptographic keys very late in the process  Attacks that create/leave state to network side elements  Insecure lower-layer detach messages  802.11 countermeasures functionality</p>
    <p>Privacy protection is non-existent or incomplete</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some Problems in Current Network Access Approaches (3/3) - Functionality</p>
    <p>Security models do not fit all types of deployment  Credit card payments</p>
    <p>Home deployments (e.g. leap of faith or physical connection instead of a certificate exercise)</p>
    <p>Configuration, discovery, and movement support  What are the IP parameters that I can get from this access point?</p>
    <p>Is my home operator available via this access point?</p>
    <p>How much would accessing this network cost?</p>
    <p>Could the network tell me when to move, and to what channel and parameters to use?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ongoing Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ongoing Work to Address the Problems...</p>
    <p>IP mobility  Better implementations that employ parallism</p>
    <p>allowed by the RFCs</p>
    <p>Faster route optimization schemes, such as moving tasks out of the critical path</p>
    <p>Address autoconfiguration  Turning DAD off</p>
    <p>Optimistic DAD</p>
    <p>DHCP and SEND security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ongoing Work, Continued</p>
    <p>DNA, Router and Neighbor Discovery  Faster algorithms for detecting whether or not</p>
    <p>movement has occurred</p>
    <p>More frequent and precise router advertisements</p>
    <p>Elimination first message delays from RFC 2461</p>
    <p>SEND security</p>
    <p>EAP authentication  Methods work (new credentials, deployment, )</p>
    <p>Channel binding and parameter authentication</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ongoing Work, Continued</p>
    <p>Link layer  Pre-authentication and proactive key distribution</p>
    <p>Better protection of payload packets (AES etc)  Better information channels from the network to the</p>
    <p>clients (e.g., 802.21)</p>
    <p>Discovery (WIEN SG)</p>
    <p>Faster scanning techniques, parameter tuning  Bigger subnets (less IP layer work after attachment)</p>
    <p>...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observations</p>
    <p>People care about this!  A lot of results!  Most work focused on a particular slice of the</p>
    <p>problem  No good understanding of what the impact of</p>
    <p>individual improvement is for effiency  E.g., I cant afford 1 RTT in Mobile IP</p>
    <p>Not enough system-level understanding of the security issues</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some New Ideas</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Approach</p>
    <p>Focus on the problem as a whole!  There are multiple parties involved -- not just two  Who needs to communicate with who?  How are the parties identified?  What is the optimal order of messages?  What system security properties are needed?  Are there bulk information transfer needs? How can</p>
    <p>they best be addressed?  Can we learn something from solutions in other</p>
    <p>contexts?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Caveat</p>
    <p>This may not be compatible with current protocols</p>
    <p>Layer-purists might object to our views</p>
    <p>We do not have all the details, just pointers to ideas</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Potential Solution Ingredients (1/5)</p>
    <p>Addressing:  All nodes (not just the client) need an address</p>
    <p>Addresses are hashes of public keys</p>
    <p>Benefits:  All parties -- such as the access network can be addressed in</p>
    <p>communications</p>
    <p>Avoid address stealing and functionality to bind addresses to credentials</p>
    <p>Nodes can generate their addresses and keys on their own, without infrastructure</p>
    <p>Privacy can be achieved via ephemeral keys</p>
    <p>Identifier vs. routing semantics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Potential Solution Ingredients (2/5)</p>
    <p>Message order:  Find out what information the whole problem involves,</p>
    <p>and how many messages need to carry it  And re-think message order  Example: If the clients IP address was known earlier,</p>
    <p>the authentication process with the home network could handle mobility-related registrations as well</p>
    <p>Benefits:  Number of messages can be reduced</p>
    <p>Ping-pong delays can be avoided</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Potential Solution Ingredients (3/5)</p>
    <p>Information transfer:  Do not fetch everything from the original source</p>
    <p>Cache information about, say, roaming consortium in the AP</p>
    <p>Learn from TCP no req-resp across the Internet  Either run TCP-like protocols directly between the client and the, say, home</p>
    <p>network  Or have the access point do this over the Internet, and use a request-response</p>
    <p>over the final radio hop</p>
    <p>Information transfer capabilities should not be restricted to the initial authentication exchange</p>
    <p>Benefits  More and faster information transfer, at any time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Potential Solution Ingredients (4/5)</p>
    <p>Miscallenous  Delegation</p>
    <p>Does the client have to be involved in tasks?</p>
    <p>Can some tasks be delegated to the access point/router?</p>
    <p>For instance, router based address assignment and DAD</p>
    <p>Even a mobility related registration could be delegated</p>
    <p>Denial-of-Service protection  No separation to attachment and secure attachment  Stateless design on the network side</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Potential Solution Ingredients (5/5)</p>
    <p>Miscallenous, continued  Privacy protection</p>
    <p>Build the protocols for non-static identifiers and addresses</p>
    <p>Protect communications from the start, not at the end</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Example Protocol Run</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Example</p>
    <p>Flows:  Current message flow</p>
    <p>Suggested basic message flow</p>
    <p>Variant with better mobility support</p>
    <p>Handoff</p>
    <p>Assumptions:  Authentication needed; roaming case</p>
    <p>IPv6</p>
    <p>Mobility with RO &amp; one peer</p>
    <p>Client - home authentication in 2 RTT (identifier / challenge / response / success)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Current Flow</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>client access</p>
    <p>network home other node</p>
    <p>Beacon</p>
    <p>IPv6 Router Discovery</p>
    <p>IPv6 DAD</p>
    <p>MIPv6 Home Reg</p>
    <p>MIPv6 RO Reg</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Improved Basic Flow</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>client access</p>
    <p>network home other node</p>
    <p>Beacon</p>
    <p>Beacon includes:</p>
    <p>- Access node identifier</p>
    <p>- Access network identifier</p>
    <p>- Possible other advertised information, such as capabilities, roaming partner identifiers, and so on</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>client access</p>
    <p>network home other node</p>
    <p>Beacon</p>
    <p>Secure Attachment</p>
    <p>The functions of the secure attachment protocol:</p>
    <p>- Authenticate the claimed identities (opportunistically)</p>
    <p>- Turn ciphering on, as in 802.11i 4-way handshake</p>
    <p>It also piggybacks the following:</p>
    <p>- Deliver IPv6 router advertisements</p>
    <p>- Authentication and authorization to the home (partially)</p>
    <p>- May perform address allocation on behalf of the client</p>
    <p>- May perform mobility registration on behalf of the client</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>client access</p>
    <p>network home other node</p>
    <p>Beacon</p>
    <p>Secure Attachment</p>
    <p>I1: trigger exchange --------------------------&gt; select pre-computed R1 R1: puzzle, D-H, key, sig &lt;------------------------check sig remain stateless solve puzzle I2: solution, D-H, {key}, sig --------------------------&gt; compute D-H check cookie check puzzle check sig R2: sig &lt;-------------------------check sig compute D-H</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>client access</p>
    <p>network home other node</p>
    <p>Beacon</p>
    <p>Secure Attachment Home auth &amp; authz</p>
    <p>- The home authentication process follows the identity/challenge/response/success model (for instance)</p>
    <p>- A mobility protocol home registration is carried in the same messages -- executed after the final response message is sent</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>client access</p>
    <p>network home other node</p>
    <p>Beacon</p>
    <p>Secure Attachment Home auth &amp; authz</p>
    <p>RO registration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Variation with Better Mobility Support</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>client access</p>
    <p>network home other node</p>
    <p>Beacon</p>
    <p>Secure Attachment Home auth &amp; authz</p>
    <p>RO registration</p>
    <p>Variation:</p>
    <p>A common authority can be avoided by a care-of address test.</p>
    <p>Care-of Address Test</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Handoffs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>client access node 1</p>
    <p>access node 2</p>
    <p>access network</p>
    <p>Beacon</p>
    <p>Secure Attachment</p>
    <p>- Access node 1 has a signed statement from the access network that it is a part of the network. This is given to the client.</p>
    <p>- After authentication and authorization at the home network, a set of explicit authorization criteria are known. A signed statement is given to the client, saying that the client is allowed to move to another access node within the same network, as long as the criteria are fulfilled.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>client access node 1</p>
    <p>access node 2</p>
    <p>access network</p>
    <p>Beacon</p>
    <p>Secure Attachment</p>
    <p>- Access node 2 has a similar statement from the access network as well.</p>
    <p>- Client presents its statements and the usual home authentication/authorization process can be skipped. Client gets access.</p>
    <p>- However, access node 2 needs to verify authorization criteria. In many case this implies contacting a central node in the access network (e.g. concurrent usage limit).</p>
    <p>Secure Attachment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Need to look at the whole problem  Measurements</p>
    <p>System-level security story</p>
    <p>Solutions</p>
    <p>Some early solution ideas presented  Clearly more work is needed for the details,</p>
    <p>security analysis &amp; actual benefits</p>
    <p>Feedback appreciated!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
