<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lock-Free Consistency Control for Web 2.0 Applications</p>
    <p>Jiang-Ming Yang, Hai-Xun Wang, Ning Gu, Yi-Ming Liu, ChunSong Wang, Qi-Wei Zhang</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation &amp; Challenges  Problem Setting  Our Solutions  Experiments  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation &amp; Challenges  Problem Setting  Our Solutions  Experiments  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Single Site</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Multiple Mirror Site</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>How to merge the conflicts in Multiple Mirror Site for Web 2.0 Application?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation &amp; Challenges  Problem Setting  Our Solutions  Experiments  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Setting</p>
    <p>Data shared in mirrored sites can be in varied forms. Here, we assume the shared data on mirrored sites are XML documents.</p>
    <p>Consequently, operations on the data are expressed by XML queries and updates.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Setting &lt;Root&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;book @title=&quot;Introduction to Algorithm&quot;&gt; &lt;category&gt;CS&lt;/category&gt; &lt;tag&gt;Hot&lt;/tag&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/book&gt; &lt;book @title=&quot;Advanced Statistical Learning&quot;&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;category&gt;UnKnow&lt;/category&gt; &lt;/book&gt; &lt;book @title=&quot;Linear Algebra&quot;&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;category&gt;Math&lt;/category&gt; &lt;/book&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/Root&gt;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Setting</p>
    <p>CAUSAL RELATIONSHIPS</p>
    <p>TRANSACTIONS</p>
    <p>CONCURRENT OPERATIONS (Lock Free)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Setting</p>
    <p>CAUSAL RELATIONSHIPS U1 Change the title Advanced Statistical Learning to Statistical Learning.</p>
    <p>U2 Set the category of the Statistical Learning book to Math.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Setting</p>
    <p>TRANSACTIONS</p>
    <p>Using transaction model to execute some critical operations</p>
    <p>Should be executed serialized with others</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Setting</p>
    <p>CONCURRENT OPERATIONS U3 Add a Discount tag to books in Math category.</p>
    <p>U4 Set the category of the Linear Algebra book to CS.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation &amp; Challenges  Problem Setting  Our Solutions</p>
    <p>Causality Preservation  Transaction  Consistency Control</p>
    <p>Experiments  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Causality Preservation  Definition. (Causal Ordering Relation ). Given two operations Oa and Ob from</p>
    <p>local replica sites i and j respectively, we have Oa  Ob, if and only if (1) i = j, and Oa is generated before Ob is generated; (2) i  j, and Oa is executed on site j before Ob is generated; (3) there exists an operation Ox, such that Oa  Ox and Ox  Ob.</p>
    <p>Definition.(Concurrent Relation  ). Given two operations Oa and Ob, we say Oa and Ob are concurrent or Oa Ob iff neither Oa  Ob, nor Ob  Oa.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Causality Preservation</p>
    <p>Vector based Timestamp  SV = &lt;SV1, SV2, . . . , SVn&gt;  Both for Site &amp; operation</p>
    <p>Definition. (Execution Condition). Operation O (from site i) is causally ready for execution at site j (i  j) if the following conditions are satisfied: (in reference [6, 14])  SVO [i] = SVj[i] + 1  SVO [k]  SVj [k], for all 1  k  N and k  i.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transaction</p>
    <p>The transaction model is introduced to achieve concurrent transparency</p>
    <p>Definition. (Serialized Transaction). Let T be a transaction, and O be an operation (O may or may not be a transaction). Transaction T is a serialized transaction only if either O is executed before T in all sites, or O is executed after T in all sites.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transaction</p>
    <p>O1  NOOP1  O3 and O2  NOOP2  O4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transaction  Definition. (TOrder: total order for transactions). Its a logical order among</p>
    <p>transactions : T1 T 2 T 3  T  n.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consistency Control  Basic Idea</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consistency Control - Operation</p>
    <p>XPath : /root/book</p>
    <p>XQuery &amp; XUpdate FOR $title in /root//title</p>
    <p>$category = $book/category WHERE $title = &quot;Advanced Statistical Learning&quot; ..</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consistency Control  Storage Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consistency Control  Storage Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consistency Control  Storage Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consistency Control - Query Process</p>
    <p>It is clear that there is no overlap in their timestamps, and at any time only one of them is valid.</p>
    <p>In general, only nodes whose timestamp (tcreate, tdelete) satisfies t (t create, tdelete) are valid at t.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consistency Control - Query Process</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consistency Control  Size of OHL</p>
    <p>In our approach, we store operations in an Operation History List (OHL).</p>
    <p>Each time a replica receives a new remote operation, it will update OHL.</p>
    <p>When an operation is executed on all replicas, it will be removed from OHL and its related state information will be removed from the inverted list.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation &amp; Challenges  Problem Setting  Our Solutions  Experiments  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation &amp; Challenges  Problem Setting  Our Solutions  Experiments  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>We proposed a lock-free approach for consistency maintance in Web 2.0 environment.  We do not use the locking mechanism, so concurrent</p>
    <p>operations are executed as soon as possible upon their arrival with ensuring the convergence.</p>
    <p>We also support the transaction semantics for critical operations without using the locking mechanism relying on the causality preservation approach.</p>
    <p>Better load balance, high-speed access and shorter respond time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You !</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
