<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Risk Models for Designing Privacy-Sensitive Ubiquitous Computing Systems</p>
    <p>Jason Hong Carnegie Mellon Jennifer Ng Carnegie Mellon</p>
    <p>Scott Lederer University of California, Berkeley</p>
    <p>James Landay University of Washington</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation Ubiquitous Computing is Coming</p>
    <p>Advances in wireless networking, sensors, devices  Greater awareness of and interaction with physical</p>
    <p>world</p>
    <p>E911Find Friends</p>
    <p>But what about my privacy?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation But Hard to Design Privacy-Sensitive Ubicomp Apps</p>
    <p>Discussions on privacy generate lots of heat but not light  Big brother, overprotective parents, telemarketers,</p>
    <p>genetics  Many conflicting values  Often end up talking over each other  Hard to have reasoned debates and create designs that</p>
    <p>address the issues</p>
    <p>Need a design method that helps design teams:  Identify  Prioritize  Manage privacy risks for specific applications</p>
    <p>Propose Privacy Risk Models for doing this</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Risk Model Analogy Security Threat Model</p>
    <p>[T]he first rule of security analysis is this: understand your threat model. Experience teaches that if you dont have a clear threat model  a clear idea of what you are trying to prevent and what technical capabilities your adversaries have  then you wont be able to think analytically about how to proceed. The threat model is the starting point of any security analysis.</p>
    <p>- Ed Felten</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Risk Model Two Parts: Risk Analysis and Risk Management</p>
    <p>Privacy Risk Analysis  Common questions to help design teams identify potential</p>
    <p>risks  Like a task analysis</p>
    <p>Privacy Risk Management  Helps teams prioritize and manage risks  Like severity rankings in heuristic evaluation</p>
    <p>Will present a specific privacy risk model for ubicomp  Draws on previous work, plus surveys and interviews  Provide reasonable level of protection for foreseeable risks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Privacy Risk Analysis</p>
    <p>Privacy Risk Management</p>
    <p>Case Study: Location-enhanced Instant Messenger</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Risk Analysis Common Questions to Help Design Teams Identify Risks</p>
    <p>Social and Organizational Context  Who are the users?  What kinds of personal info are shared?  Relationships between sharers and observers?  Value proposition for sharing?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Social and Organizational Context Who are the users? Who shares info? Who sees it?</p>
    <p>Different communities have different needs and norms  An app appropriate for families might not be for work</p>
    <p>settings</p>
    <p>Affects conditions and types of info willing to be shared  Location information with spouse vs co-workers  Real-time monitoring of ones health</p>
    <p>Start with most likely users  Ex. Find Friends  Likely sharers are people using mobile phone  Likely observers are friends, family, co-workersFind Friends</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Social and Organizational Context What kinds of personal info are shared?</p>
    <p>Different kinds of info have different risks and norms  Current location vs home phone# vs hobbies</p>
    <p>Some information already known between people  Ex. Dont need to protect identity with your friends and</p>
    <p>family</p>
    <p>Different ways of protecting different kinds of info  Ex. Can revoke access to location, cannot for birthday or</p>
    <p>name</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Social and Organizational Context Relationships between sharers and observers?</p>
    <p>Kinds of risks and concerns  Ex. Risks w/ friends are unwanted intrusions, embarrassment  Ex. Risks w/ paid services are spam, 2nd use, hackers</p>
    <p>Incentives for protecting personal information  Ex. Most friends dont have reason to intentionally cause</p>
    <p>harm  Ex. Neither do paid services, but want to make more money</p>
    <p>Mechanisms for recourse  Ex. Kindly ask friends and family to stop being nosy  Ex. Recourse for paid services include formally complaining,</p>
    <p>switching services, suing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Social and Organizational Context Value proposition for sharing personal information?</p>
    <p>What incentive do users have for sharing?</p>
    <p>Quotes from nurses using locator badges  I think this is disrespectful, demeaning and degrading  At first, we hated it for various reasons, but mostly we</p>
    <p>felt we couldnt take a bathroom break without someone knowing where we were[but now] requests for medications go right to the nurse and bedpans etc go to the techs first... I just love [the locator system].</p>
    <p>When those who share personal info do not benefit in proportion to perceived risks, then the tech is likely to fail</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Risk Analysis Common Questions to Help Design Teams Identify Risks</p>
    <p>Social and Organizational Context  Who are the users?  What kinds of personal info are shared?  Relationships between sharers and observers?  Value proposition for sharing?</p>
    <p>Technology  How is personal info collected?  Push or pull?  One-time or continuous?  Granularity of info?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technology How is personal info collected?</p>
    <p>Different technologies have different tradeoffs for privacy</p>
    <p>Network-based approach  Info captured and processed by external computers that</p>
    <p>users have no practical control over  Ex. Locator badges, Video cameras</p>
    <p>Client-based approach  Info captured and processed on end-users device  Ex. GPS, beacons  Stronger privacy guarantees, all info starts with you first</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technology Push or pull?</p>
    <p>Push is when user sends info first  Ex. you send your location info on E911 call  Few people seem to have problems with push</p>
    <p>Pull is when another person requests info first  Ex. a friend requests your current location  Design space much harder here</p>
    <p>need to make people aware of requests want to provide understandable level of control dont want to overwhelm</p>
    <p>E911</p>
    <p>Find Friends</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technology One-time or continuous disclosures?</p>
    <p>One-time disclosure  Ex. observer gets snapshot</p>
    <p>Fewer privacy concerns</p>
    <p>Find Friends Active Campus</p>
    <p>Continuous disclosure  Ex. observer repeatedly gets</p>
    <p>info</p>
    <p>Greater privacy concerns  Its stalking, man.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technology Granularity of info shared?</p>
    <p>Different granularities have different utility and risks</p>
    <p>Spatial granularity  Ex. City? Neighborhood? Street? Room?</p>
    <p>Temporal granularity  Ex. at Boston last month vs at Boston August 2 2004</p>
    <p>Identification granularity  Ex. a person vs a woman vs alice@blah.com</p>
    <p>Keep and use coarsest granularity needed  Least specific data, fewer inferences, fewer risks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Privacy Risk Analysis</p>
    <p>Privacy Risk Management</p>
    <p>Case Study: Location-enhanced Instant Messenger</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Risk Management Helps teams prioritize and manage risks</p>
    <p>First step is to prioritize risks by estimating:  Likelihood that unwanted disclosure occurs  Damage that will happen on such a disclosure  Cost of adequate privacy protection</p>
    <p>Focus on high likelihood, high damage, low cost risks first  Like heuristic eval, fix high severity and/or low cost  Difficult to get exact numbers, more important is the</p>
    <p>process</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Risk Management Helps teams prioritize and manage risks</p>
    <p>Next step is to help manage those risks</p>
    <p>How does the disclosure happen?  Accident? Bad user interface? Poor conceptual model?  Malicious? Inside job? Scammers?</p>
    <p>What kinds of choice, control, and awareness are there?  Opt-in? Opt-out?  What mechanisms? Ex. Buddy list, Invisible mode  What are the default settings?</p>
    <p>Better to prevent or to detect abuses?  Bob has asked for your location five times in the past</p>
    <p>hour</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study Location-enhanced Instant Messenger</p>
    <p>New features  Request a friends current</p>
    <p>location  Automatically show your location  Invisible mode, reject requests  Default location is unknown</p>
    <p>Who are the users?  Typical IM users</p>
    <p>Relationships?  Friends, family, classmates,</p>
    <p>One-time or continuous?  One-time w/ notifications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study Location-enhanced Instant Messenger</p>
    <p>Identifying potential privacy risks  Over-monitoring by friends and family  Over-monitoring at work place  Being found by malicious person (ex. stalker, mugger)</p>
    <p>Assessing the first risk, over-monitoring by family  Likelihood depends on family, conservatively assign</p>
    <p>high  Damage might be embarrassing but not life-threatening,</p>
    <p>assign medium</p>
    <p>Managing the first risk  Buddy list, Notifications for awareness, invisible mode,</p>
    <p>unknown if location not disclosed  All easy to implement, cost is low</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>Privacy risk models are only a starting point  Like task analysis, should try to verify assumptions and</p>
    <p>answers  Can be combined with field studies, interviews, low-fi</p>
    <p>prototypes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Privacy risk models for helping design teams identify, prioritize, and manage risks</p>
    <p>Privacy risk analysis for identifying risks  Series of common questions, like a task analysis</p>
    <p>Privacy risk management for prioritizing &amp; managing risks  Like severity ratings in heuristic evaluation</p>
    <p>Described our first iteration of privacy risk model  Help us evolve and advance it!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
