<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Framework for Monitoring AgentBased Normative Systems *</p>
    <p>Sanjay Modgil, Noura Faci, Felipe Meneguzzi, Nir Oren, Simon Miles, Michael Luck</p>
    <p>Agents and Intelligent Systems Group Dept Computer Science</p>
    <p>Kings College London</p>
    <p>* Research Funded by European Commission 6th framework CONTRACT project (www.ist-contract.org)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline of Talk</p>
    <p>Requirements for monitoring</p>
    <p>Overview of monitoring framework</p>
    <p>Representation and processing of norms for monitoring</p>
    <p>Conclusions and future work</p>
    <p>Implementation and use case</p>
    <p>Agreements on what observations count as norm statuses and trusted observers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Requirements for monitoring normative systems</p>
    <p>Autonomous agents may violate norms  enforcement mechanisms (sanctions) required to motivate compliance  monitoring of agent behaviours to determine compliance / violation</p>
    <p>Example obligation on purchaser P of goods G from a supplier S: If P is notified by S that goods G are in stock, then unless S is declared bankrupt, either P must  cancel the order within 7 days of receipt of notification, or;  accept the order and pay within 7 days of receipt of notification.</p>
    <p>Norms (obligations, prohibitions, permissions) used to regulate and coordinate agent behaviours</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Requirements for monitoring normative systems</p>
    <p>Autonomous agents may violate norms  enforcement mechanisms (sanctions) required to motivate compliance  monitoring of agent behaviours to determine</p>
    <p>compliance / violation</p>
    <p>Norms (obligations, prohibitions, permissions) used to regulate and coordinate agent behaviours</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General Framework for Monitoring Normative Systems</p>
    <p>Norms = N1, N2,</p>
    <p>Normative System</p>
    <p>Monitoring Framework</p>
    <p>system neutral representation of individual</p>
    <p>norms for monitoring Monitor</p>
    <p>inform agents and impose sanctions</p>
    <p>observations</p>
    <p>Manager</p>
    <p>norm status reports</p>
    <p>with explanations</p>
    <p>abstract model of norms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An abstract model of norms for monitoring</p>
    <p>If P is notified by S that goods G are in stock, then unless S is declared bankrupt, either P must :</p>
    <p>cancel the order within 7 days of receipt of notification, or;  accept the order and pay within 7 days of receipt of notification.</p>
    <p>Norms describe complex behaviours and world states brought about by (groups of) agents, e.g., consider following obligation:</p>
    <p>(Type, Target, Activation, Condition, Expiration)</p>
    <p>Type  {obligation, permission, prohibition}, Target = agents whose behaviour is governed by the norm (P)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An abstract model of norms for monitoring</p>
    <p>If P is notified by S that goods G are in stock, then unless S is declared bankrupt, either P must :</p>
    <p>cancel the order within 7 days of receipt of notification, or;  accept the order and pay within 7 days of receipt of notification.</p>
    <p>Norms describe complex behaviours and world states brought about by (groups of) agents</p>
    <p>Activation = conditions under which norm applies to Target</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An abstract model of norms for monitoring</p>
    <p>If P is notified by S that goods G are in stock, then unless S is declared bankrupt, either P must :</p>
    <p>cancel the order within 7 days of receipt of notification, or;  accept the order and pay within 7 days of receipt of notification.</p>
    <p>Norms describe complex behaviours and world states brought about by (groups of) agents</p>
    <p>Activation = conditions under which norm applies to Target Condition = state that must be (obligation) may be (permission )</p>
    <p>or must not be (prohibition) realised by Target</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An abstract model of norms for monitoring</p>
    <p>If P is notified by S that goods G are in stock, then unless S is declared bankrupt, either P must :</p>
    <p>cancel the order within 7 days of receipt of notification, or;  accept the order and pay within 7 days of receipt of notification.</p>
    <p>Norms describe complex behaviours and world states brought about by (groups of) agents</p>
    <p>Activation = conditions under which norm applies to Target Condition = state that must be (obligation) may be (permission )</p>
    <p>or must not be (prohibition) realised by Target</p>
    <p>Expiration = conditions under which norm no longer applies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Representing norms for Monitoring  Norms in many normative systems conform to abstract model</p>
    <p>=&gt; norms can be mapped to Augmented Transition Networks (ATNs) that reference elements of model and are used for monitoring status of norms</p>
    <p>Norms = N1, N2,</p>
    <p>(Type, Target, Activation, Condition, Expiration)</p>
    <p>ATN-1 ATN-2</p>
    <p>Monitor Manager</p>
    <p>status reports</p>
    <p>on norms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Processing ATN representations of norms</p>
    <p>DNF representations of Activation = (1    n)  (1   m)   and Condition = (1    n)  (1   m)   map to labels of ATN</p>
    <p>ATNs are directed labelled graphs that transition from node to node based on satisfaction of connecting arcs labels</p>
    <p>S1 S2 S3</p>
    <p>i=1  n i</p>
    <p>i=1  m i</p>
    <p>i=1  n i</p>
    <p>i=1  m i</p>
    <p>If Expiration does not hold, and: - ATN in S1 (norm not active) and at least one arc label satisfied then</p>
    <p>transition arc to activation state S2</p>
    <p>- ATN in S2 and at least one arc label satisfied then transition arc to fulfillment state S3 (if obligation/permission) or violation state S3 (if prohibition)</p>
    <p>- Obligation ATN in S2 and time window elapses then obligation violated</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Processing ATN representations of norms</p>
    <p>S1 S2 S3</p>
    <p>i=1  n i</p>
    <p>i=1  m i</p>
    <p>i=1  n i</p>
    <p>i=1  m i</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Processing ATN representations of norms</p>
    <p>S1 S2 S3</p>
    <p>If NormExpiration does not hold, and:</p>
    <p>- P notified by S that G in stock at time T then transition to S2 and norm activated (in force w.r.t. P )</p>
    <p>- If P cancels at T1 (T1  T +7) or P accepts at T2 (T2  T +7) and pays at T3 (T3  T +7) then transition corresponding arc to fulfillment node S3</p>
    <p>- If current time T greater than time window T + 7 and ATN in S2 then obligation violated</p>
    <p>P notified by S that G in stock</p>
    <p>P cancels within 7</p>
    <p>P accepts and pays within 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Processing ATN representations of maintenance norms</p>
    <p>3 node ATNs for achievement norms</p>
    <p>4 node ATNs for maintenance norms that may toggle between violated and not violated (e.g. obligation to drive on left)</p>
    <p>S1 S2</p>
    <p>S3</p>
    <p>Agent starts driving</p>
    <p>S4</p>
    <p>driving on left</p>
    <p>driving on right</p>
    <p>driving on right</p>
    <p>driving on left</p>
    <p>violated</p>
    <p>not violated</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Matching observations with ATN labels</p>
    <p>Norms = N1, N2,</p>
    <p>Normative System</p>
    <p>Monitoring Framework ATN-1 ATN-2</p>
    <p>Monitor Manager</p>
    <p>Monitors match observations of world states and agent behaviours with ATN labels =&gt; transition ATNs across corresponding arcs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Counts as agreements and trusted observers  Choice of observations (brute facts) that count as Activation, Condition,</p>
    <p>Expiration and choice of observers responsible for observations =&gt; important for motivating agent participation in normative systems since these choices impact on agents confidence that sanctions applied</p>
    <p>appropriately</p>
    <p>S1 S2 S3</p>
    <p>P notified by S that G in stock</p>
    <p>P cancels within 7</p>
    <p>P accepts and pays within 7</p>
    <p>What observed brute facts should count as P paying S and who should make and report these observations ?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Counts as agreements and trusted observers  Observed message sent from P to S notifying S of payment</p>
    <p>sent message counts as P pays S</p>
    <p>=&gt; P may send message without actually paying and so avoid sanction =&gt; S not motivated to participate</p>
    <p>S sends notification message to monitor (i.e., S acts as observer) that money deposited in bank money in bank counts as P pays S</p>
    <p>=&gt; money may be in bank but S does not notify and so sanction inappropriately imposed on P (resulting in some gain for S) =&gt; P not motivated to participate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Counts as agreements and trusted observers</p>
    <p>Norms = N1, N2,</p>
    <p>ATN-1 ATN-2</p>
    <p>Monitor Manager</p>
    <p>Agents agree on what brute facts count as Activation, Condition, and Expiration and agree on observers responsible for observing and relaying facts to monitor</p>
    <p>X counts as Y agreed by agents =&gt; X labels ATN arcs e.g. S and P agree that money in bank counts as S pays P</p>
    <p>agents entrust observer to observe for and report X to monitor</p>
    <p>e.g., S and P agree to trust bank</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation and Use Case *</p>
    <p>Jason implementation of interacting aerospace agents governed by electronic contract</p>
    <p>Examples of contract normative clauses: - Service site obliged to repair engine for airline operator within 7 days - Service site prohibited from sourcing parts from part manufacturer</p>
    <p>JAVA implemented monitor processes observed messages exchanged between aerospace agents, together with ATN representations of norms</p>
    <p>Norm status reports visualised in GUI proxy for manager</p>
    <p>* F. R. Meneguzzi, S. Modgil, N. Oren, S.Miles, M. Luck, N. Faci, C. Holt, M. Smith. Monitoring and Explanation of Contract</p>
    <p>Execution: A Case Study in the Aerospace Domain. To appear in: AAMAS 09,Industry and Applications Track, Hungary, 2009.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions and Future Work  General framework for monitoring individual norms in underlying normative</p>
    <p>systems</p>
    <p>- Monitors process ATN representations of norms labelled by observed facts agreed by system agents as counting as statuses of norms - Facts relayed to monitors by observers explicitly entrusted by agents</p>
    <p>- Monitors create status reports on norms</p>
    <p>Implementation of monitor validated on electronic contract</p>
    <p>Future Work: - predictive monitoring whereby recognition of danger states (encoded</p>
    <p>as additional nodes in ATNs) signals danger of normative violations</p>
    <p>- enhanced explanations of normative violations</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
