<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>mPuff: Automated Detection of Cigarette Smoking Puffs</p>
    <p>from Respiration Measurements</p>
    <p>Amin Ahsan Ali, Syed Monowar Hossain, Karen Hovsepian, Md. Mahbubur Rahman, Kurt Plarre, and</p>
    <p>Santosh Kumar</p>
    <p>University of Memphis</p>
    <p>Puff detection</p>
    <p>IPSN 2012, Beijing, China</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AcknowledgementsAcknowledgements</p>
    <p>Saul Shiffman Psychology</p>
    <p>University of Pittsburgh</p>
    <p>Mustafa alAbsi Behavioral Science</p>
    <p>University of Minnesota</p>
    <p>Emre Ertin Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering</p>
    <p>The Ohio State University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Causes cancer in different organs throughout the body  leads to cardiovascular and respiratory diseases  harms reproduction</p>
    <p>Smoking KillsSmoking Kills</p>
    <p>Tobacco Poor Diet &amp; Phy. Inactivity</p>
    <p>Alcohol Microbial Agents</p>
    <p>Toxic Agents Motor Vehicles</p>
    <p>Firearms Sexual Behavior</p>
    <p>Illicit Drug use</p>
    <p>Actual Causes of Deaths in USA in 2000</p>
    <p>Percentage of all Deaths</p>
    <p>In US alone</p>
    <p>Tobacco is the cause for one of every five deaths</p>
    <p>Smokers die 13-14 years younger</p>
    <p>Public health burden of $193 billion annually</p>
    <p>Ref: Mukdad A. H., et al., Actual Causes of Death in the United States, 2000, JAMA 2004</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The 6 month quit rate was 3-5% in 5 of the 6 studies</p>
    <p>Ref: Hughes J.R.,et. al., Shape of the relapse curve and long-term abstinence among untreated smokers, Hughes,, Addiction, 99(1),pp. 2938, 04.</p>
    <p>Self-Quitting is NOT an OptionSelf-Quitting is NOT an Option</p>
    <p>survival curve relapse curve self-quitters control groups in cessation</p>
    <p>programs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Eight (out of 27) divisions at NIH award research grants for smoking cessation programs</p>
    <p>NIH alone awards $350+ million annually in smoking research1</p>
    <p>Still, smoking continues to be prevalent  Each day about 3,000 people become new daily smokers  Success rate of most smoking cessation programs is less than 10%</p>
    <p>The reason seems to be  Most research are self report based that introduces bias  NO reliable method to detect smoking and intervene at the right</p>
    <p>moment</p>
    <p>Research in SmokingResearch in Smoking</p>
    <p>[1] Estimates of Funding for Various Research, Condition, and Disease Categories (RCDC), NIH (http://report.nih.gov/categorical_spending.aspx)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current State of the ArtCurrent State of the Art</p>
    <p>Devices are available that measure and display/store CO levels in a single breath exhaled through a mouthpiece attached to them</p>
    <p>piCO+/Micro+ are designed for use as motivational aid  CReSS is used to observe smoking patterns and the degree of tobacco intake  Requires compliance from the users  May cause embarrassment using in</p>
    <p>front of others</p>
    <p>piCO+ and Micro+</p>
    <p>CReSS Pocket</p>
    <p>DOES NOT DETECT SMOKING &amp; CANNOT PROVIDE REAL TIME INTERVENTIONS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AutoSense System for Data Capture in FieldAutoSense System for Data Capture in Field</p>
    <p>Using AutoSense System , Plarre et. al., showed that stress can be detected reliably from respiration measurements. (IPSN112)</p>
    <p>Chestband sensors: ECG, Respiration, GSR, Ambient &amp; Skin Temp. , Accelerometer</p>
    <p>Armband sensors: Alcohol (WrisTAS) , Temp., GSR, Accelerometer</p>
    <p>Wir eles</p>
    <p>s Android</p>
    <p>G1 Smart Phone</p>
    <p>Ten wireless sensors in two wearable unitsTen wireless sensors in two wearable units Long lifetime (10+ days)Long lifetime (10+ days)</p>
    <p>Continuous Assessment of Physiology, Stress, and Addictive Behaviors in Field</p>
    <p>Details about AutoSense is available in an ACM Sensys111 Paper</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Memphis Study  40 daily smokers and social drinkers  One week of AutoSense wearing in the field</p>
    <p>Stress, drinking, smoking, and craving for cigarettes are reported</p>
    <p>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA) Study  20 drug users undergoing treatment  Two lab sessions and 4 weeks of wearing AutoSense in the field</p>
    <p>Smoking, craving, and stress events are marked in the lab  Craving, stress, and drug usage are reported in the field</p>
    <p>Johns Hopkins Study  10 drug users in residential treatment  Drug self-administration sessions are marked in the lab</p>
    <p>Ongoing Field Studies with AutoSenseOngoing Field Studies with AutoSense</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Item Memphis Study NIDA Study</p>
    <p># of participants completed 20 3</p>
    <p># of person days worth of data 140 days 34 days</p>
    <p>Amount of good quality sensor data 76,312 min 22,125 min</p>
    <p># hours worth of data 1,272 hours 369 hours</p>
    <p>Avg data collection per day 9 hours/day 10.8 hours/day</p>
    <p># of EMA received 2145 (or 16/day) 253 (7.5/day)</p>
    <p>% of EMA answered 94% 91.3%</p>
    <p># of smoking self-report 953 (or 6.8/day) 116 (or 3.4/day)</p>
    <p># of drinking self-report 101 (5.6/week) --</p>
    <p># of craving self-report --- 10</p>
    <p># of drug used self-report --- 6</p>
    <p>Data Collection StatisticsData Collection Statistics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inference of Conversation and Stress from respiration is shown to be possible1,2  Most smokers smoke during conversations and with other</p>
    <p>smokers  Stress has been found to be a predictor of smoking</p>
    <p>Inferences from RespirationInferences from Respiration</p>
    <p>Real time detection of smoking opens up the opportunity for  Analysis of contexts of smoking  Finding true predictors of smoking</p>
    <p>[1] Md. Mahbubur Rahman, Amin Ahsan Ali,et. al., &quot;mConverse: Inferring Conversation Episodes from Respiratory Measurements Collected in the Field,&quot; In Proceedings of ACM Wireless Health, San Diego, CA. 2011.</p>
    <p>[2] K. Plarre, A. Raij, et. al., &quot;Continuous Inference of Psychological Stress from Sensory Measurements Collected in the Natural Environment,&quot; In Proceedings of the 10th ACM/IEEE International Conference on Information Processing in Sensor Networks ( IPSN), Chicago, IL, 2011.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Respiration Chest Band</p>
    <p>Concept of mPuffConcept of mPuff</p>
    <p>Smoking puff detection</p>
    <p>Cell Phone Captures Signal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Show puff detection is possible from respiration Show puff detection is possible from respiration</p>
    <p>Open up research on automated smoking detection</p>
    <p>Open up research on automated smoking detection</p>
    <p>Identify several new respiration featuresIdentify several new respiration features</p>
    <p>Key ContributionsKey Contributions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System OverviewSystem Overview</p>
    <p>Features  Computed from each cycle</p>
    <p>SVM Classifier  Trained using carefully labeled data</p>
    <p>Semi-Supervised Classifier  Utilizing the data collected in natural environment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inhalation Duration</p>
    <p>Exhalation Duration</p>
    <p>Stretch</p>
    <p>FeaturesFeatures</p>
    <p>IERatio = Inhalation Duration / Exhalation Duration</p>
    <p>Respiration Duration = Inhalation + Exhalation Duration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Respiration during SmokingRespiration during Smoking</p>
    <p>PUFFS</p>
    <p>Compared to Non-puff cycles PUFFs have:</p>
    <p>HIGH Stretch  Similar upper &amp; lower parts  Relative to neighboring cycles significant change in stretch and other features</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Feature Statistics</p>
    <p>New Features(1)New Features(1)</p>
    <p>St re</p>
    <p>ss Sp</p>
    <p>ea ki</p>
    <p>ng Sm</p>
    <p>ok in</p>
    <p>g</p>
    <p>Unlike Conversation or Stress, SMOKING PUFF</p>
    <p>Cycles have</p>
    <p>LONGER Stretch</p>
    <p>Symmetric across the midaxis</p>
    <p>Significant relative change in stretch and other features</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>New Features (2)New Features (2)</p>
    <p>Sm ok</p>
    <p>in g</p>
    <p>Ru nn</p>
    <p>in g</p>
    <p>Unlike Running SMOKING PUFFS Cycles</p>
    <p>Significant relative change in stretch and Exhalation Duration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>1st Difference of Inhalation, Exhalation durations, IE ratio, Stretch</p>
    <p>New FeaturesNew Features</p>
    <p>TOTAL OF 12 New FeaturesTOTAL OF 12 New Features</p>
    <p>Ratio of Stretch (Exhalation Duration) of a cycle, C to the avg. across neighboring cycles  We considered a window of 5 cycles centered around C</p>
    <p>Upper (Lower) Stretch value  taking the difference of peak(valley) amplitude from the running mean of valley amplitudes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Classification</p>
    <p>Support Vector Machines are used as classifier  Classify respiration cycles to Puffs and Non-puffs  Puff data obtained from 10 participants</p>
    <p>13 sessions</p>
    <p>Non-puffs come from  smoking sessions  Stress data  Conversation data  Physical Activity data</p>
    <p>Area Under ROC Curve (AUC) metric to assess the performance</p>
    <p>because we have highly imbalanced class sizes.</p>
    <p>ClassificationClassification</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TrainingTraining</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Unlabeled data collected from 4 participants  They provide self-reports of smoking episodes  May not report at the beginning of smoking</p>
    <p>episodes  Distance to self report is added as a feature  An S3VM is employed</p>
    <p>Increases accuracy to 87%</p>
    <p>Semi-Supervised ClassifierSemi-Supervised Classifier</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations &amp; Future Work</p>
    <p>Duration of smoking session: 6.62  1.66 minutes  Puff duration: 1.09  0.53 seconds  Inter-puff interval: 28.38  14.57 seconds  Number of puffs/smoking session: 12.38  0.92</p>
    <p>Consistent with previous lab and field based topology studies</p>
    <p>Smoking TopologySmoking Topology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance of classifier in different confounding events</p>
    <p>LimitationsLimitations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  Novelty</p>
    <p>First system to show smoking puff detection is possible from respiration which can enable scientific studies on  How stress level can predict smoking behavior  How conversation is related to smoking behavior  New predictors of smoking</p>
    <p>Identifies several new discriminatory features from respiration which may help in detecting other states, e.g.,  Eating, and drinking from respiration</p>
    <p>Ongoing Work  Use correlated contexts and robust features to develop</p>
    <p>an automated smoking session detector  Address the system reliability and efficiency issues</p>
    <p>ConclusionsConclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AutoSense Papers</p>
    <p>Further ReadingFurther Reading</p>
    <p>[System] E. Ertin, N. Stohs, S. Kumar, A. Raij, M. al'Absi, T.Kwon, S. Mitra, Siddharth Shah, and J. W. Jeong, AutoSense: Unobtrusively Wearable Sensor Suite for Inferencing of Onset, Causality, and Consequences of Stress in the Field, ACM SenSys, 2011.</p>
    <p>[Conversation] M. Rahman, A. Ahsan Ali, K. Plarre, M. al'Absi, E. Ertin, and S. Kumar, mConverse: Inferring Conversation Episodes from Respiratory Measurements Collected in the Field, ACM Wireless Health, 2011.</p>
    <p>[Incentive] M. Mustang, A. Raij, D. Ganesan, S. Kumar and S. Shiffman, Exploring Micro-Incentive Strategies for Participant Compensation in High Burden Studies, to appear in ACM UbiComp, 2011.</p>
    <p>[Stress] K. Plarre, A. Raij, M. Hossain, A. Ali, M. Nakajima, M. al'Absi, E. Ertin, T. Kamarck, S. Kumar, M. Scott, D. Siewiorek, A. Smailagic, and L. Wittmers, Continuous Inference of Psychological Stress from Sensory Measurements Collected in the Natural Environment, ACM IPSN, 2011.</p>
    <p>[Privacy] A. Raij, A. Ghosh, S. Kumar and M. Srivastava, Privacy Risks Emerging from the Adoption of Inoccuous Wearable Sensors in the Mobile Environment, In ACM CHI, 2011.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
