<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FLUID MODEL OF AN INTERNET ROUTER UNDER THE MIMD CONTROL SCHEME</p>
    <p>Urtzi Ayesta (LAAS-CNRS) Alexei Piunovskiy (University of Liverpool) Y. Zhang (University of Liverpool)</p>
    <p>INFORMS TELECOM 28 march, 2008</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>n TCP connections sharing a bottleneck</p>
    <p>TCP:  Distributed Congestion Control algorithm</p>
    <p>The TCP sender detects congestion on the network through the feedback received from the TCP receiver</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The packet sending rate (congestion window) is adapted dynamically  Increase in absence of packet losses  Decrease upon reception of congestion notification</p>
    <p>Current TCP Implementations:  AIMD paradigm : The increase is linear in time  Problem in fully utilizing the link capacity in the presence of High-Speed</p>
    <p>links  The MIMD TCP is one of the possible alternatives</p>
    <p>MIMD: Exponential Increase in time  After a loss, the elapsed time until the congestion window reaches the</p>
    <p>size before the loss is constant.  Scalable TCP is a particular case</p>
    <p>RTT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Buffer size: BDP rule [VS94]</p>
    <p>One TCP AIMD connection. The minimum buffer size in order to get 100% utilization is B0=RTT x .</p>
    <p>Interes in recent years: [AKMcK04] [BHLO03] [DJD05] [W06] [VS07]</p>
    <p>RTT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance criterion</p>
    <p>Maximize throughput:</p>
    <p>Minimize queueing delay:</p>
    <p>Contradictory goals: Example of multicriteria optimization. We construct the Pareto Set of the unconstrained optimization</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We deal with the optimal impulse control problem of a deterministic system with long-run average optimality criterion.</p>
    <p>Also, our model can be viewed as a hybrid system.</p>
    <p>In principle, the control policy in our model can depend on and</p>
    <p>In practice, however, all currently implemented buffer management schemes send congestion signals based only on the state of the buffer. Thus, we also limit ourselves to this case.</p>
    <p>Furthermore, we assume that one can only control B, the size of the buffer.</p>
    <p>Objective: Determine the buffer size that solves the optimization problem</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A fluid model  Let denote the sending rate of connection i at time t</p>
    <p>Assuming the same RTT for all connections</p>
    <p>Let denote the queue length at time t. Then</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Fluid model (cont.)</p>
    <p>When a packet is dropped, and the sending rate of a connection is reduced instantaneously</p>
    <p>Assuming that the sending rates are uniformly distributed in a congestion epoch:</p>
    <p>Hybrid model : Dynamical systems that combine both discrete and continuous behavior.</p>
    <p>Example: Scalable TCP, and [Kelly03]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theorem: Let</p>
    <p>Then unclipped (clipped) cycle exists if and only if</p>
    <p>The duration of the cycle equals</p>
    <p>Lemma: In the desynchronized case,  meaning that decreases to zero as.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theorem: Let be the value of immediately after the k-th jump. Then, starting from any initial value the limit exists.</p>
    <p>In addition there exist only simple limiting cycles, i.e. instant series of more than one jump are never realized, and all the values of immediately after a jump coincide with for the trajectory starting from , The limiting cycle is stable.</p>
    <p>Theorem: If then</p>
    <p>if then</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>For every , we can determine the value of the Buffer that maximizes</p>
    <p>Pareto Set or Trade-off curve  Corollary:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>MIMD : The cycle duration independent of the link capacity (for AIMD it does depend)</p>
    <p>As the number of connections increases, decreases with</p>
    <p>For Scalable TCP and one connection B0=0,22 x RTT x .</p>
    <p>For MIMD, depends linearly on For AIMD depends on MIMD not only scales well with capacity, but it also requires smaller buffer sizes in high-speed networks.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions (cont.)</p>
    <p>When then Then if and n=1, That is, even with no buffer, the utilization of Scalable TCP would be very high.</p>
    <p>Incorporate to the model : delays, heterogeneous RTT, dynamically arriving and departing connections etc.</p>
    <p>The Pareto Set of the multicriteria optimization problem may be useful in dimensioning routers</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
