<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FlexGroup Volumes A Distributed WAFL File System</p>
    <p>2019 NetApp, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
    <p>Ram Kesavan, Jason Hennessy, Richard Jernigan, Peter Macko, Keith A. Smith, Daniel Tennant, Bharadwaj V. R. USENIX ATC 19</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Where we were</p>
    <p>Individual WAFL volumes managed by a single controller</p>
    <p>Individual WAFL volumes</p>
    <p>ONTAP</p>
    <p>Clients mount individual volumes  If a client connects to a different node,</p>
    <p>requests will be forwarded over the cluster interconnect</p>
    <p>Can join multiple volumes into a junction tree</p>
    <p>home traces</p>
    <p>ram keith jason ontap eseries</p>
    <p>papers</p>
    <p>NFS/SMB</p>
    <p>Cluster</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FlexGroup Volumes</p>
    <p>FlexGroup = a distributed file system internally composed of WAFL volumes</p>
    <p>A distributed file system</p>
    <p>FlexGroup presents the member volumes as a single volume to clients</p>
    <p>ONTAP automatically manages file placement to spread the load</p>
    <p>ONTAP Cluster</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FlexGroup Volumes A very high-level view</p>
    <p>home</p>
    <p>/</p>
    <p>traces</p>
    <p>ram keith jason ontap eseries</p>
    <p>home traces</p>
    <p>jason</p>
    <p>logs</p>
    <p>ontappapers</p>
    <p>papers</p>
    <p>src</p>
    <p>storagegrid</p>
    <p>solidfire storagegrid</p>
    <p>patents</p>
    <p>data</p>
    <p>logs data</p>
    <p>Member Volume</p>
    <p>Remote Link</p>
    <p>Legend:</p>
    <p>No central metadata server</p>
    <p>Files and directories are stored in their entirety on the member volumes</p>
    <p>Remote links are automatically created to connect subtrees on the individual volumes into a single namespace</p>
    <p>Directoryname name</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FlexGroup Volumes Two key ingredients</p>
    <p>Remote Access Layer Atomically create, update, and delete remote links across volumes.</p>
    <p>Data Placement Heuristics Determine data placement, balancing data locality and spreading load and space utilization across the cluster.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Have we been successful?</p>
    <p>Scalable file system performance</p>
    <p>Thousands of FlexGroup volumes deployed storing hundreds of petabytes</p>
    <p>Customer data show effectiveness of the data placement heuristics</p>
    <p>Evaluation sneak peak</p>
    <p>SFS EDA SFS SWBUILD SFS VDA</p>
    <p>N or</p>
    <p>m al</p>
    <p>iz ed</p>
    <p>o ps</p>
    <p>/s ec</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Would you like to know more?</p>
    <p>2019 NetApp, Inc. All rights reserved.</p>
    <p>Come to the talk: Wednesday, July 10th, 2:20pm ATC 19, Track I (Filesystems)</p>
    <p>Read the paper: https://www.usenix.org/conference/atc19/ presentation/kesavan</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
