<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Supporting Security-Sensitive Tenants in a Bare-Metal Cloud*#</p>
    <p>NOTE: We define security-sensitive tenants as entities, like three letter government agencies or hospitals, who are both willing to pay a significant price for security and that have the expertise, desire, or requirement to trust their own security arrangements.</p>
    <p>Amin Mosayyebzadeh1, Apoorve Mohan4, Sahil Tikale1, Mania Abdi4, Nabil Schear2, Charles Munson2, Trammell Hudson3, Larry Rudolph3, Gene Cooperman4, Peter Desnoyers4, Orran Krieger1</p>
    <p>Boston University1 MIT Lincoln Laboratory2 Two Sigma3 Northeastern University4</p>
    <p>(Massachusetts Open Cloud) *Mosayyebzadeh, Mohan, and Tikale contributed equally.</p>
    <p>#DISTRIBUTION STATEMENT A. Approved for public release. Distribution is unlimited. This material is based upon work supported by the Under Secretary of Defense for Research and Engineering Under Air Force Contract No. FA8702-15-D-0001. Any opinions, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the Under Secretary of Defense for Research and Engineering.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security-Sensitive Organizations Detest Public Cloud Offerings</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problems with Existing Cloud Offerings</p>
    <p>A. A Virtualization-based offering is prone to side-chanel, covert-channel, hyperjacking, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problems with Existing Cloud Offerings</p>
    <p>B. Cloud orchestration softwares have huge trusted computing base (TCB) and hence a massive attack surface</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problems with Existing Cloud Offerings</p>
    <p>C. Limited visibility and control over implementation and operation - tenants needs to trust non-maliciousness and competence of the provider</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problems with Existing Cloud Offerings</p>
    <p>D. Adheres to one-size-fits-all security solutions for operational efficiency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bare-Metal clouds overcome the problems faced virtualized offerings BUT are prone to firmware-based attacks and data theft and still possess other public cloud problems (B, C, and D)</p>
    <p>Problems with Existing Cloud Offerings</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Is is Possible to Architect a Cloud that...</p>
    <p>Is appropriate for even the most security-sensitive tenants?</p>
    <p>Doesnt require the tenants to fully trust the provider?</p>
    <p>Doesnt impact tenants with less stringent security requirements or who are willing to trust the provider for their security?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Is appropriate for even the most security-sensitive tenants?</p>
    <p>Doesnt require the tenants to fully trust the provider?</p>
    <p>Doesnt impact tenants with less stringent security requirements or who are willing to trust the provider for their security?</p>
    <p>Bolted: An Architecture for Secure Bare-Metal Cloud Service</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bolted: An Architecture for Secure Bare-Metal Cloud Service</p>
    <p>Microservice-based Architecture  Tailor-Made Security Solution</p>
    <p>for Each Tenant  Minimal Trusted Computing</p>
    <p>Base (TCB)  Improved Visibility and</p>
    <p>Control</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bolted: An Architecture for Secure Bare-Metal Cloud Service</p>
    <p>Operational Efficiency vs Trust - Security-sensitive tenants can</p>
    <p>deploy most of the microservices.</p>
    <p>- Tenants who trust the provider can simply reply of provider for all the microservices.</p>
    <p>Microservice-based Architecture  Tailor-Made Security Solution</p>
    <p>for Each Tenant  Minimal Trusted Computing</p>
    <p>Base (TCB)  Improved Visibility and</p>
    <p>Control</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bolted: An Architecture for Secure Bare-Metal Cloud Service</p>
    <p>Most of the microservices can be implemented by the tenant.</p>
    <p>Security-sensitive tenants only need to trust the network isolation service.</p>
    <p>Microservice-based Architecture  Tailor-Made Security Solution</p>
    <p>for Each Tenant  Minimal Trusted Computing</p>
    <p>Base (TCB)  Improved Visibility and</p>
    <p>Control</p>
    <p>~3K LOC for Bolted Prototype</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bolted: An Architecture for Secure Bare-Metal Cloud Service</p>
    <p>Tenant Implemented and Verifiable Components</p>
    <p>Example  Firmware  Attestation Service  Key Management</p>
    <p>Microservice-based Architecture  Tailor-Made Security Solution</p>
    <p>for Each Tenant  Minimal Trusted Computing</p>
    <p>Base (TCB)  Improved Visibility and</p>
    <p>Control</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prototype Evaluation</p>
    <p>Speed, Performance, and Scalability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Supporting Security-Sensitive Tenants in a Bare-Metal Cloud</p>
    <p>Track II (Security #2: Isolation) Date: Thursday, July 11, 2019</p>
    <p>Time: 2:00 pm3:20 pm</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
