<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Designing an Ontology-based Intelligent Tutoring Agent</p>
    <p>with Instant Messaging</p>
    <p>Min-Yuh Day1,2, Chun-Hung Lu1,3, Jin-Tan David Yang4, Guey-Fa Chiou 3,Chorng-Shyong Ong2,Wen-Lian Hsu1</p>
    <p>ICALT 2005</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Introduction  System Architecture of the Proposed</p>
    <p>Intelligent Tutoring Agent (ITA)  User Case Scenario and Discussion  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction  Instant Messaging (IM)</p>
    <p>offers new opportunities as well as challenges to both educators and students.</p>
    <p>MSN Messenger  The most popular IM system  Communication protocol</p>
    <p>Intelligent Tutoring Agent (ITA)  uses the ontology, INFOMAP, and question answering</p>
    <p>techniques through the Instant Messaging platform for the operating system course.</p>
    <p>tutoring agent  help a teacher track, record, and understand a students</p>
    <p>status.  interpret natural language to facilitate communication</p>
    <p>between the student and the tutor.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ontology-based ITA  INFOMAP</p>
    <p>The ontology we used is an ontological knowledge representation framework called INFOMAP.</p>
    <p>INFOMAP consists of domain concepts and their related subconcepts, such as categories, attributes and actions.</p>
    <p>The relationships of a concept to its associated sub-concepts form a tree-like taxonomy.</p>
    <p>INFOMAP not only classifies the concepts, but also classifies related concepts.</p>
    <p>Feature of INFOMAP  represent and match complicated template structures</p>
    <p>hierarchical matching,  semantic matching,  frame (non-linear relations) matching,  graph matching.</p>
    <p>Extract important concepts from a natural language text.  ITA uses INFOMAP and question answering techniques</p>
    <p>during the teaching process.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Architecture of the Proposed Intelligent Tutoring Agent (ITA)  Expert model  Curriculum model  Student model  User interface</p>
    <p>Student TeacherITA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Intelligent Tutoring Agent</p>
    <p>VSM</p>
    <p>Porter Stemmer</p>
    <p>Porter Stemmer</p>
    <p>Student Teacher</p>
    <p>Textbook QA</p>
    <p>Textbook Chapter</p>
    <p>Textbook</p>
    <p>Lucene Full Text Indexer</p>
    <p>HighLighter</p>
    <p>Textbook Syllabus</p>
    <p>Syllabus Student</p>
    <p>Model</p>
    <p>Log Student Model</p>
    <p>Student Model Analyzer</p>
    <p>Question Chapter</p>
    <p>Similarity Recommendation</p>
    <p>Curriculum Model Student ModelExpert Model</p>
    <p>User Interface</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Expert Model  Textbook, Textbook QA, Matching</p>
    <p>module (VSM).  Jakarta Lucene full text indexer to</p>
    <p>index the full text of the textbook.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Curriculum Model  The curriculum model used in our ITA is</p>
    <p>similar to the pedagogical module in some ITSs.  The curriculum model in ITA includes the</p>
    <p>syllabus and the chapter module from the textbook.</p>
    <p>The teacher uses the curriculum manager to arrange learning modules (i.e., the syllabus or lesson plan), where each module may include one or more learning objects to help students learn.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Student Model  A Cognitive Student Model - An Ontological</p>
    <p>Approach  We have previously proposed a student model</p>
    <p>called Identification, Simulation, Interaction, and Mapping (ISIM).</p>
    <p>We adopt the ISIM strategy for the student model in ITA.</p>
    <p>The ITA logs a students learning behavior in the student model.  The teacher then uses the student model</p>
    <p>analyzer to detect the students beliefs and misconceptions from their answers to diagnostic tests and by tracing the students actions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Interface  Unlike traditional web-based</p>
    <p>approaches, we use MSN Messenger as the user interface of the proposed ITA (IASLITA).</p>
    <p>The benefit of adopting the Instant Messaging (IM) system in the ITA is that it is widely used by students.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IASL ITA  To use IASLITA, the student has to add the</p>
    <p>IASLITA contact ID: iaslita@hotmail.com to the MSN Messenger contacts list.</p>
    <p>Student IASL ITA</p>
    <p>What is the purpose of an operating system?</p>
    <p>To provide an environment for a computer user to execute programs on computer hardware in a convenient and efficient manner.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>iaslita@hotmail.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Case Scenario  After the teacher has finished a section of the</p>
    <p>Operating System, the teacher may give some assignment to the students, keep a record of learning objects, or answer students questions.</p>
    <p>We use the textbook Operating System Concept as the foundational knowledge of the ITA.</p>
    <p>When a teacher answers a students question, the ITA records the question and the answer in a knowledge base (QA pair).</p>
    <p>When another student has a question, the system searches the database for the question and the relevant answer.</p>
    <p>If the students question matches a previous question, the ITA provides the answer; otherwise, the ITA invites the teacher to answer the question and records the answer.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion  ITA assist the teacher to communicate</p>
    <p>with students, record their questions, and analyze their status.</p>
    <p>ITA plays a facilitator role in a collaborative learning environment.</p>
    <p>Instant Messaging (IM) used in ITA provides real-time communication and interaction, which enhances students learning motivation much more than a static website, or a Web-based ITS.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions  We propose an Intelligent Tutoring Agent (ITA) that</p>
    <p>integrates INFOMAP and question-answering techniques through the Instant Messaging platform of MSN Messenger for the operating system.</p>
    <p>During the teaching process, the ITA interface interprets natural language to facilitate communication between the student and the tutor.</p>
    <p>We have presented an overview of the architectural design, the AI techniques used, and the user interface.</p>
    <p>Advantages  Students: Receive help immediately upon encountering a</p>
    <p>problem  Teacher: Facilitate classroom instruction in a collaborative</p>
    <p>learning environment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future work  INFOMAP and AIML Integration  Systematic Evaluation</p>
    <p>Empirical Study  Technology Acceptance Model (TAM)</p>
    <p>(Davis, 1989)  Theory of Planned Behavior (TPB)</p>
    <p>(Ajzen, 1985)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Q &amp; A Designing an Ontology-based</p>
    <p>Intelligent Tutoring Agent with Instant Messaging</p>
    <p>Min-Yuh Day1,2, Chun-Hung Lu1,3, Jin-Tan David Yang4, Guey-Fa Chiou 3,Chorng-Shyong Ong2,Wen-Lian Hsu1</p>
    <p>E-mail: {myday, enrico, hsu}@iis.sinica.edu.tw yangdav@nknucc.nknu.edu.tw, gueyfa@ice.ntnu.edu.tw, ongcs@im.ntu.edu.tw</p>
    <p>ICALT 2005</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
