<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dayu: Fast and Low-interference Data Recovery in Very-large Storage Systems</p>
    <p>Zhufan Wang*, Guangyan Zhang*, Yang Wang, Qinglin Yang*, and Jiaji Zhu</p>
    <p>*Tsinghua University The Ohio State University Alibaba Cloud</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of Data Recovery Protocol  Basic idea: replicate data chunks and re-replicate lost chunks</p>
    <p>Responsibility of the recovery protocol:  Schedule the source, the destination, and the bandwidth for re-replicating</p>
    <p>each lost chunk</p>
    <p>Goals of scheduling: high quality and high speed  High quality: Achieve fast and low-interference recovery  High speed: The scheduling algorithm should not become the bottleneck</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observations from a Production System  Target system:</p>
    <p>AliClouds distributed storage system: Pangu  Deployed on a datacenter with approximately 3500 nodes</p>
    <p>Observations:  Very-large scale  Tight time constraint  Imbalanced resources  Dynamic foreground traffic</p>
    <p>Challenge: the scheduling algorithm needs to compute a large and complex problem within seconds</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Existing Approaches  Simple and decentralized scheduler</p>
    <p>E.g. GFS, HDFS, Azure, RAMCloud, Sparrow, etc  High speed but low quality</p>
    <p>Sophisticated and centralized scheduler  E.g. CAR, PPR, Mirador, DH-HDFS, Firmament, etc  High quality but low speed</p>
    <p>Computation speed</p>
    <p>S ch</p>
    <p>ed ul</p>
    <p>in g</p>
    <p>qu al</p>
    <p>ity Ideal</p>
    <p>Simple</p>
    <p>Sophisticated</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dayu: High-quality and high-speed Recovery</p>
    <p>Evaluation result:  2.96x recovery speed with only 3.7% increase in tail latency  Can scale to the cluster of 25K nodes</p>
    <p>Computation speed</p>
    <p>S ch</p>
    <p>ed ul</p>
    <p>in g</p>
    <p>qu al</p>
    <p>ity</p>
    <p>Simple</p>
    <p>Sophisticated Dayu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dayu: Fast and Low-interference Data Recovery in Very-large Storage Systems</p>
    <p>Coming soon.</p>
    <p>ATC 2019 Friday, July 12, 12:30 am</p>
    <p>Track: Storage Failure &amp; Recovery</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
