<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MArk: Exploiting Cloud Services for Cost-Effective, SLO-Aware</p>
    <p>Machine Learning Inference Serving Chengliang Zhang, Minchen Yu, Wei Wang, Feng Yan</p>
    <p>Hong Kong University of Science and Technology University of Nevada, Reno</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Machine Learning Model Serving</p>
    <p>Deploy a trained model for user requests  Highly dynamic demand  Stringent Service Level Objectives on latency</p>
    <p>Design objectives  Serve ML models on public cloud  Scale to dynamic queries  Cost-effective  SLO-aware: e.g. 98% of the requests must be served under 500ms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges &amp; Opportunities</p>
    <p>Cloud services  Multiple options: IaaS, CaaS, FaaS, MLaaS  Large configuration space: CPU, memory  Cost-performance tradeoffs: preemptable, burstable instances</p>
    <p>Unique properties of ML serving  Compute intensive  Hardware accelerators: GPU, TPU  Stateless computation</p>
    <p>How to reduce over-provisioning?</p>
    <p>What option to choose?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud Services for Model Serving</p>
    <p>Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS)</p>
    <p>Container as a Service (CaaS)</p>
    <p>Function as a Service (FaaS, serverless comp.)</p>
    <p>Cost</p>
    <p>Overhead to scale</p>
    <p>IaaS</p>
    <p>CaaS</p>
    <p>FaaS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud Services for Model Serving</p>
    <p>CPU GPU TPU</p>
    <p>Ondemand Preemptable Burstable</p>
    <p>Spot instances in AWS Preemptable VM in Google cloud</p>
    <p>t2, t3 instances in AWS f1-micro, g1-small in Google cloud</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We designed MArk</p>
    <p>Compared with AWSs SageMaker, MArk achieves  Up to 7.8x cost reduction  Better latency performance</p>
    <p>A scale-to-demand, cost-effective, SLO-aware model serving system on cloud</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Welcome to our talk!</p>
    <p>Our insights of IaaS, CaaS, FaaS and their configurations  Our insights of ML serving on GPUs and TPUs  How MArk translates our insights into system design  MArks provisioning algorithm  The evaluation of MArks performance</p>
    <p>Day 3, Track II, Machine Learning Applications &amp; System Aspects</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
