<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>On the Notion of Pseudo-Free Groups</p>
    <p>Ronald L. Rivest MIT Computer Science and Artificial</p>
    <p>Intelligence Laboratory TCC 2/21/2004</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Assumptions: complexity-theoretic, group-theoretic</p>
    <p>Groups: Math, Computational, BB, Free  Weak pseudo-free groups  Equations over groups and free groups  Pseudo-free groups  Implications of pseudo-freeness  Open problems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cryptographic assumptions</p>
    <p>Computational cryptography depends on complexity-theoretic assumptions.</p>
    <p>two types:  Generic: OWF, TDP, P!=NP, ...  Algebraic: Factoring, RSA, DLP, DH,</p>
    <p>Strong RSA, ECDLP, GAP, WPFG, PFG,</p>
    <p>Were interested in algebraic assumptions ( about groups )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Groups  Familiar algebraic structure in crypto.  Mathematical group G = (S,*): binary</p>
    <p>operation * defined on (finite) set S: associative, identity, inverses, perhaps abelian. Example: Zn* (running example).</p>
    <p>Computational group [G] implements a mathematical group G. Each element x in G has one or more representations [x] in [G]. E.g. [Zn*] via least positive residues.</p>
    <p>Black-box group: pretend [G] = G.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Free Groups  Generators: a1, a2, , at  Symbols: generators and their inverses.  Elements of free group F(a1, a2, , at) are</p>
    <p>reduced finite sequences of symbols---no symbol is next to its inverse. ab-1a-1bc is in F(a,b,c) ; abb-1 is not.</p>
    <p>Group operation: concatenation &amp; reduction.</p>
    <p>Identity: empty sequence  (or 1).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Free Group Properties  Free group is infinite.  In a free group, every element other than</p>
    <p>the identity has infinite order.  Free group has no nontrivial relationships.  Reasoning in a free group is relatively</p>
    <p>straightforward and simple;  Dolev-Yao for groups</p>
    <p>Every group is homomorphic image of a free group.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Abelian Free Groups  There is also abelian free group</p>
    <p>FA(a1, a2, , at), which is isomorphic to Z x Z x  x Z (t times).</p>
    <p>Elements of FA(a1, a2, , at) have simple canonical form: a1e1a2e2atet</p>
    <p>We will often omit specifying abelian; most of our definitions have abelian and non-abelian versions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pseudo-Free Groups (Informal)</p>
    <p>A finite group is pseudo-free if it can not be efficiently distinguished from a free group.</p>
    <p>Notion first expressed, in simple form, in Susan Hohenbergers M.S. thesis.</p>
    <p>We give two formalizations, and show that assumption of pseudofreeness implies many other wellknown assumptions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>a</p>
    <p>a</p>
    <p>a</p>
    <p>a a a</p>
    <p>b</p>
    <p>b b</p>
    <p>b b b b</p>
    <p>a a</p>
    <p>b b</p>
    <p>b b</p>
    <p>aa</p>
    <p>a</p>
    <p>bb</p>
    <p>Cayley graph of finite group</p>
    <p>Cayley graph of free group</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two ways of distinguishing</p>
    <p>In a weak pseudo-free group (WPFG), adversary cant find any nontrivial identity involving supplied random elements:</p>
    <p>a2 b5 c-1 = 1 (!)  In a (strong) pseudo-free group</p>
    <p>(PFG), adversary cant solve nontrivial equations:</p>
    <p>x2 = a3 b</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Weak Pseudo-freeness  A family of computational groups { Gk } is</p>
    <p>weakly pseudo-free if for any polynomial t(k) a PPT adversary has negl(k) chance of:  Accepting t(k) random elements of Gk,</p>
    <p>a1,  ,at(k)  Producing any word w over the symbols</p>
    <p>a1,  ,at(k) a1-1,  ,at(k)-1 when interpreted as a product in Gk using the obtained random values, yields the identity 1 , while w does not yield 1 in the free group.</p>
    <p>Adversary may use compact notion (exponents, straight-line programs) when describing w.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Order problem</p>
    <p>Theorem: In a WPFG, finding the order of a randomly chosen element is hard.</p>
    <p>Proof: The equation ae = 1 does not hold for any e in FA(a). No element other than 1 in a free group has finite order.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discrete logarithm problem</p>
    <p>Theorem: In a WPFG, DLP is hard.  Proof: The equation</p>
    <p>ae = b does not hold for any e in FA(a,b); a and b are distinct independent generators, one can not be power of other.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Subgroups of PFGs  Subgroup Theorem for WPFGs:</p>
    <p>If G is a WPFG, and g is chosen at random from G, then &lt;g&gt; is a WPFG. [not in paper]</p>
    <p>Proof sketch: Ability to find nontrivial identities in &lt;g&gt; can be shown to imply that g has finite order.</p>
    <p>==&gt; DLP is hard in WPFG even if we enforce promise that b is a (random) power of a .</p>
    <p>Similar proof implies that QRn is WPFG when n = (2p+1)(2q+1).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Equations in Groups  Let x, y,  denote variables in group.  Consider the equation</p>
    <p>x2 = a (*) This equation may be satisfiable in Zn* (when a is in QRn), but this equation is never satisfiable in a free group, since reduced form of x2 always has even length.</p>
    <p>Exhibiting a solution to (*) in a group G is another way to demonstrate that G is not a free group.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Equations in Free Groups  Can always be put into form:</p>
    <p>w = 1 where w is sequence over symbols of group and variables.</p>
    <p>It is decidable (Makanin 82) in PSPACE (Gutierrez 00) whether an equation is satisfiable in free group.</p>
    <p>Multiple equations equivalent to single one.</p>
    <p>For abelian free group it is in P. Also: if equation is unsatisfiable in FA() it is unsatisfiable in F().</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pseudo-freeness  A family of computational groups { Gk } is</p>
    <p>pseudo-free if for any polys t(k), m(k) a PPT adversary has negl(k) chance of:  Accepting t(k) random elements of Gk,  Producing any equation</p>
    <p>E(a1,,at(k),x1,,xm(k)): w = 1 with t(k) generator symbols and m(k) variables that is unsatisfiable over F(a1,,at(k))</p>
    <p>Producing a solution to E over Gk, with given random elements substituted for generators.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main conjecture</p>
    <p>Conjecture: { Zn* } is a (strong) (abelian) pseudo-free group</p>
    <p>aka Super-strong RSA conjecture</p>
    <p>What are implications of PFG assumption?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RSA and Strong RSA</p>
    <p>Theorem: In a PFG, RSA assumption and Strong RSA assumptions hold.</p>
    <p>Proof: For e&gt;1 the equation xe = a is not satisfiable in FA(a) (and also thus not in F(a)).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Taking square roots</p>
    <p>Theorem: In a PFG, taking square roots of randomly chosen elements is hard.</p>
    <p>Proof: As noted earlier, the equation x2 = a (*)</p>
    <p>has no solution in FA(a) or F(a).  Note the importance of forcing</p>
    <p>adversary to solve (*) for a random a; it wouldnt do to allow him to take square root of, say, 4 .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Computational Diffie-Hellman</p>
    <p>CDH: Given g , a = ge, and b = gf, computing x = gef is hard.</p>
    <p>Conjecture: CDH holds in a PFG.  Remark: This seems natural, since</p>
    <p>in a free group there is no element (other than 1) that is simultaneously a power of more than one generator. Yet the adversary merely needs to output x; there is no equation involving x that he must output.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Open problems</p>
    <p>Show factoring implies Zn* is PFG.  Show CDH holds in PFGs.  Show utility of PFG theory by</p>
    <p>simplifying known security proofs.  Determine is satisfiability of equation</p>
    <p>over free group is decidable when variables include exponents.</p>
    <p>Extend theory to groups of known size (e.g. mod p), and adaptive attacks (adversary can get solution to some equations of his choice for free).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>( THE END )</p>
    <p>Safe travels!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
