<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perspectives on Financial Cryptography</p>
    <p>Ronald L. Rivest</p>
    <p>MIT Lab for Computer Science</p>
    <p>(RSA / Security Dynamics)</p>
    <p>FC97 -- 2/27/97</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>I present for your consideration some debatable propositions</p>
    <p>about financial systems and financial cryptography.</p>
    <p>Warning: the propositions expressed may or may not be believed by the author, and may be phrased in a deliberately provocative manner. They may contradict each other.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Internet money == Interstellar money (?)</p>
    <p>P1: There is little difference between Internet payment schemes and interstellar payment schemes.</p>
    <p>In 2097, you will buy info off the GGG (Grand Galactic Grid) with starbucks.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Most schemes dont work well.</p>
    <p>P2: Historically, most payment schemes havent worked very well.</p>
    <p>Ref: Weatherford, History of Money.  Commodities (metal, tobacco, wampum, cocoa</p>
    <p>beans)  weighing, purity, quality, deterioration, transportation,</p>
    <p>storage, theft.</p>
    <p>Coins [Lydia, 630 B.C.]  Shaving, debasing, theft, government abuse.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Most schemes dont work well...</p>
    <p>Paper money (China, Italy, U.S. colonies)  counterfeiting (scanner/printer), government abuse (inflation),</p>
    <p>or lack of money</p>
    <p>Checks (England, 1770)  Forgery, insolvency, check-washing, ...</p>
    <p>Credit cards (U.S., 1950 Diners Club)  theft, counterfeiting, non-payment,</p>
    <p>Electronic money  ?? hyperinflation, system collapse, criminal activities protected</p>
    <p>by anonymity,  ??</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Everyone will make money</p>
    <p>P3: Electronic cash systems will enable anyone with a PC to be a mint for his own brand of currency.</p>
    <p>World is becoming more decentralized, more distributed, more democratic. (Compare with printing press.)</p>
    <p>Multiple (thousands) of currencies will exist and be traded. Appropriate discount rates will be used for poorly-rated issuers.</p>
    <p>Central banks have a smaller role to play.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The dollar stays around.</p>
    <p>P4: National currencies wont go away, to be replaced by cyberspace dollars.</p>
    <p>Ref: The Sovereign Individual (James Davidson and Lord William Rees-Mogg), for contrary view: governments will implode as debts spiral and tax base disappears into cyberspace tax havens.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy is already lost</p>
    <p>P5: Individual privacy is already lost, and must be regained.</p>
    <p>All information about individual is now electronic form, and is bought and sold.</p>
    <p>There is strong economic incentive for user profiling by merchants, card issuers, etc...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Profiling Not So Bad?</p>
    <p>P6: User profiling has a definite up side for the user:  reduction of unwanted marketing mail; user</p>
    <p>and advertiser both agree that mail sent should be interesting to user.</p>
    <p>spending profiles aid fraud detection.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>No anonymity for large payments</p>
    <p>P7: Governments will not allow payment systems to support true (payer or payee) anonymity for large payments.</p>
    <p>This is for law-enforcement reasons:  payer anonymity: bribery, kickbacks, political</p>
    <p>contributions  payee anonymity: extortion, blackmail, kipnapping,</p>
    <p>etc.</p>
    <p>Anonymity will only work for small payments.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>No anonymity for small payments</p>
    <p>P8: Achieving payer anonymity for small payments by cryptographic means is too expensive (in terms of complexity and cpu time).</p>
    <p>Isnt it just easier to pass very strong privacy-protection laws about the gathering and use of personal spending data?</p>
    <p>But costs decrease over time, too...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity to be bought and sold</p>
    <p>P9: Anonymity will be a value-added feature that a user may purchase. Conversely, a user may break his own anonymity in a transaction, for a fee.</p>
    <p>Most users may feel that anonymity is a good that he should control, and perhaps sell, but not normally a necessity.</p>
    <p>User may reveal his true identity, or else a pseudoidentity (to allow profiling).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>No multi-app smart cards</p>
    <p>P10: Multi-application smart cards will never make it big.</p>
    <p>Coordinating issuers is about as easy as making peace in the Middle East.</p>
    <p>Security issues on a multi-app card are difficult.</p>
    <p>User are comfortable and familiar with having one card per issuer.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity by smart-card choice</p>
    <p>P11: Anonymity for small-value payments will be arise (only) from anonymity of card-holder/card relationship.</p>
    <p>Smart cards can be obtained anonymously, as frequently as desired.</p>
    <p>Smart card ID is a pseudonym for user. (Nyms are already understood by AOL users)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cost of breaking SCs to rise</p>
    <p>P12: Smart cards will be broken into on a regular basis, but the cost of doing so will rise dramatically over the next decade.</p>
    <p>Smaller feature sizes make requisite lab equipment more expensive.</p>
    <p>Vast number of installed smart cards will stimulate further investment into security measures and lower production costs.</p>
    <p>Compare: bank safes.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>No large-value digital coins</p>
    <p>P13: Digital coins will not be used for largevalue transactions.</p>
    <p>In a coin-based system (as opposed to an account-based system), possession of bits means possession of value. Replication!</p>
    <p>Identification of double-spenders is unlikely to be a sufficient deterrent to prevent major fraud. (Compare with credit-card theft .)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>No transferable coins!</p>
    <p>P14: Payment schemes with off-line coin transfers between users wont make it.</p>
    <p>Need will decrease dramatically as every device and individual can be on-line whenever it wants to.</p>
    <p>No good business model: what does issuer gain by allowing transferability? (Extra float doesnt compensate for extra risk. Compare with early US bank notes...)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Micropayments will thrive</p>
    <p>P15: Micropayment schemes will be the system of choice for purchasing most information over the Web.</p>
    <p>Most information is low-value (&lt;10 cents).  Significant price umbrella underneath</p>
    <p>credit-card transactions (29 cents + 2%).  Latency of response is important. (Not</p>
    <p>enough time for serious crypto.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General PKIs not necessary</p>
    <p>P16: General-purpose public-key infrastructures (PKIs) are not necessary for financial cryptography---they can (and will) be special-cased.</p>
    <p>Name/key binding may be less important than attribute binding (e.g. account is in good standing; merchant has few problems).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Money and voting are close.</p>
    <p>P17: Voting systems and payment systems will be seen as being very close.</p>
    <p>Voting for candidate is like giving $1 coin to candidate so she can bid for and buy election. (Special registrar currency.)</p>
    <p>Anonymity of voting is necessary. (This is a great example against key escrow or key recovery.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>You can get anything you want...</p>
    <p>P18: Alices crypto restaurant can serve up any feasible combination of system requirements at a workable cost (not necessarily cheap).</p>
    <p>Be careful what you ask for  Some problems are not technical, but socio</p>
    <p>political (whom do you trust?---key recovery, etc.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Financial cryptography is an essential component of electronic payment schemes.</p>
    <p>Such schemes will augment and largely replace many existing payment schemes, and will offer new features (selective anonymity, interstellar payments)</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
