<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PayWordPayWord and and MicroMintMicroMint:: Two Simple MicroPayment Two Simple MicroPayment</p>
    <p>SchemesSchemes</p>
    <p>PayWordPayWord and and MicroMintMicroMint:: Two Simple MicroPayment Two Simple MicroPayment</p>
    <p>SchemesSchemes</p>
    <p>Ronald L. Rivest (MIT)Ronald L. Rivest (MIT)</p>
    <p>Adi Shamir (Weizmann)Adi Shamir (Weizmann)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OutlineOutlineOutlineOutline</p>
    <p>Micropayments: Framework and Micropayments: Framework and MotivationMotivation</p>
    <p>PayWordPayWord: a credit-based scheme using : a credit-based scheme using chains of hash values (or chains of hash values (or paywordspaywords):): ww0 0 ww1 1 w w22 w w3 3 ... ...</p>
    <p>MicroMintMicroMint: digital coins as : digital coins as kk-way hash -way hash function collisions: function collisions: xx1 1 x x22 x x33 x x44 yy</p>
    <p>ConclusionsConclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MicropaymentsMicropaymentsMicropaymentsMicropayments</p>
    <p>Payment scheme for Payment scheme for low-valuelow-value transactions, such as transactions, such as 1 per web page 1 per web page accessaccess</p>
    <p>Too small for credit-card Too small for credit-card macropayments (which may incur macropayments (which may incur fee of 29  + 2%)fee of 29  + 2%)</p>
    <p>Public-key crypto relatively expensive:Public-key crypto relatively expensive: RSA sign (private key)RSA sign (private key) 2 / sec2 / sec RSA verify (public key)RSA verify (public key) 200 / sec200 / sec Hash functionHash function 20000 / sec20000 / sec</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MicropaymentsMicropaymentsMicropaymentsMicropayments</p>
    <p>Some advanced features, such as Some advanced features, such as anonymityanonymity, are probably just too , are probably just too expensive to implement in a expensive to implement in a micropayment scheme.micropayment scheme.</p>
    <p>With light-weight schemes, one must be With light-weight schemes, one must be pragmatic about fraud and abuse: the pragmatic about fraud and abuse: the goal should be effective goal should be effective risk risk managementmanagement, rather than total , rather than total prevention. Bad apples can be prevention. Bad apples can be detected and eliminated from the detected and eliminated from the system.system.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MicropaymentsMicropaymentsMicropaymentsMicropayments</p>
    <p>Introduce Introduce BrokerBroker to intermediate to intermediate and aggregate:and aggregate:</p>
    <p>Broker</p>
    <p>VendorUser</p>
    <p>Banks and Credit-card companies</p>
    <p>(Inner loop)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Efficiency GoalsEfficiency GoalsEfficiency GoalsEfficiency Goals</p>
    <p>Try to minimize use of public-key Try to minimize use of public-key operations.operations.</p>
    <p>Try to keep Broker off-line as Try to keep Broker off-line as much as possible.much as possible.</p>
    <p>Make inner loop Make inner loop (purchase/payment) efficient, (purchase/payment) efficient, especially for repeated small especially for repeated small purchases.purchases.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PayWordPayWordPayWordPayWord</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PayWord ChainsPayWord ChainsPayWord ChainsPayWord Chains</p>
    <p>ww0 0 ww1 1 w w22 w w3 3 ... w ... wnn</p>
    <p>Easy for User to create a chain of length, Easy for User to create a chain of length, say, say, n = n = 1000 for a vendor using1000 for a vendor using h h = MD5, = MD5, by starting with by starting with wwnn..</p>
    <p>User commits (signs with RSA) root User commits (signs with RSA) root ww0 0 over to Vendor.over to Vendor.</p>
    <p>User makes successive 1 payments by User makes successive 1 payments by revealing paywords revealing paywords ww11, w, w22, ... , ... in turn.in turn.</p>
    <p>Vendor redeems commitment, and last Vendor redeems commitment, and last payword received, with Broker.payword received, with Broker.</p>
    <p>h h h h h</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PayWord CertificatePayWord CertificatePayWord CertificatePayWord Certificate</p>
    <p>Broker gives User a signed certificate Broker gives User a signed certificate CCU U good for one month authorizing User good for one month authorizing User to make PayWord chains. Broker is to make PayWord chains. Broker is extending credit to User.extending credit to User.</p>
    <p>CCUU = = {Broker, User, Users IP Address,{Broker, User, Users IP Address, PK PKU U , expiration-date, limits, etc.}, expiration-date, limits, etc.}SKBSKB</p>
    <p>wherewhere PK PKUU = Users Public RSA Key. = Users Public RSA Key.</p>
    <p>Certificate authorizes delivery of goods Certificate authorizes delivery of goods only to specified Internet address.only to specified Internet address.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PayWord CommitmentPayWord CommitmentPayWord CommitmentPayWord Commitment</p>
    <p>User commits root User commits root ww00 to Vendor by to Vendor by signing a commitment message signing a commitment message MMUVUV::</p>
    <p>MMUVUV = = {User, Vendor, {User, Vendor, ww00 , , CCUU , , expiration-date } expiration-date }SKUSKU</p>
    <p>Commitment contains Users certificate Commitment contains Users certificate CCUU ..</p>
    <p>User commits to PayWord chain for, say, User commits to PayWord chain for, say, one day. one day.</p>
    <p>Note that Broker is Note that Broker is not not directly involved.directly involved.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PayWordPayWordPayWordPayWord</p>
    <p>Basic PayWord information flow. Basic PayWord information flow. Note that Broker is Note that Broker is off-line off-line except except for issuing monthly certificate and for issuing monthly certificate and final redemption.final redemption.Broker</p>
    <p>VendorUser</p>
    <p>(1) Certificate CU</p>
    <p>(2) Goods</p>
    <p>(2) Commitment MUV , w1 (first payment) w2 (second payment) ... w20 (20th payment)</p>
    <p>(3) MUV , w20</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PayWord CostsPayWord CostsPayWord CostsPayWord Costs</p>
    <p>One signature by Broker / user / month One signature by Broker / user / month ((CCUU))</p>
    <p>One signature by User / vendor / day (One signature by User / vendor / day (MMUVUV))</p>
    <p>Two verifications by Vendor / user / day Two verifications by Vendor / user / day ((CCUU and and MMUVUV))</p>
    <p>One verification by Broker / user / One verification by Broker / user / vendor /day (for vendor /day (for MMUVUV))</p>
    <p>One hash function computation by each of One hash function computation by each of User, Vendor, and Broker for each 1 User, Vendor, and Broker for each 1 payment.payment.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PayWord ExtensionsPayWord ExtensionsPayWord ExtensionsPayWord Extensions</p>
    <p>Can pay for a 5 item by revealing Can pay for a 5 item by revealing ww1010 after after ww55 (like revealing five (like revealing five paywords at once).paywords at once).</p>
    <p>Can have several payword chains Can have several payword chains per commitment, with different per commitment, with different values per payword in each chain: values per payword in each chain: e.g. a chain of 1 paywords, a chain e.g. a chain of 1 paywords, a chain of 25 paywords, and a chain of 1$ of 25 paywords, and a chain of 1$ paywords.paywords.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MicroMintMicroMintMicroMintMicroMint</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MicroMintMicroMintMicroMintMicroMint</p>
    <p>A A digital coindigital coin should be: should be:  Hard to produce [except by Broker]Hard to produce [except by Broker]</p>
    <p>Easy to verify [by anyone]Easy to verify [by anyone]</p>
    <p>Digital signatures work, but are Digital signatures work, but are relatively expensive.relatively expensive.</p>
    <p>MicroMint uses hash functions MicroMint uses hash functions only only ((nono public-key crypto).public-key crypto).</p>
    <p>Broker utilizes Broker utilizes economy of scale economy of scale to to produce MicroMint coins cheaply (as with produce MicroMint coins cheaply (as with a regular mint).a regular mint).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Suppose hash function Suppose hash function hh : {0,1}: {0,1}4848 {0,1}{0,1}3636 maps maps m = 48-m = 48-bit strings to bit strings to n = 36-n = 36-bit strings.bit strings.</p>
    <p>A A k-way collision k-way collision is a is a kk-tuple -tuple (x(x11,x,x22,...,x,...,xkk) ) of of values such that values such that h(h(xx11)) = = h(h(xx22)) = ... = = ... = h(h(xxkk))::</p>
    <p>A MicroMint coin is a A MicroMint coin is a k-k-way collision way collision ((k=4). k=4). Verifying a coin is easy.Verifying a coin is easy.</p>
    <p>MicroMint CoinsMicroMint CoinsMicroMint CoinsMicroMint Coins</p>
    <p>x1 x2 x3 x4</p>
    <p>y</p>
    <p>h h h h</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Minting CoinsMinting CoinsMinting CoinsMinting Coins</p>
    <p>Producing coins is like tossing balls into Producing coins is like tossing balls into 22nn bins; bins; k k balls in a bin makes one coin.balls in a bin makes one coin.</p>
    <p>Producing Producing first first 2-way collision requires 2-way collision requires time 2time 2n/2n/2 ; this is the birthday paradox.; this is the birthday paradox.</p>
    <p>Producing Producing firstfirst k-k-way collision requires way collision requires time time NNkk = 2 = 2n(k-1)/kn(k-1)/k . . (e.g. (e.g. 222727 for for k=4, n = 36.)k=4, n = 36.) (Its hard to forge even one coin.)(Its hard to forge even one coin.)</p>
    <p>Time Time cNcNkk yields yields cck k coins; once threshold coins; once threshold of of NNk k is passed, coins are produced is passed, coins are produced rapidly. (Mint has rapidly. (Mint has economy of scaleeconomy of scale).).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow of MicroMint CoinsFlow of MicroMint CoinsFlow of MicroMint CoinsFlow of MicroMint Coins</p>
    <p>Broker mints coins and sells them Broker mints coins and sells them to User.to User.</p>
    <p>User spends coins with Vendor.User spends coins with Vendor.</p>
    <p>Vendor deposits coins back to Vendor deposits coins back to Broker.Broker. Broker</p>
    <p>User Vendor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security ConcernsSecurity ConcernsSecurity ConcernsSecurity Concerns</p>
    <p>ForgeryForgery: Can an adversary forge : Can an adversary forge MicroMint coins? (Economically?)MicroMint coins? (Economically?)</p>
    <p>Double-spendingDouble-spending: What if a user : What if a user double-spends his MicroMint coins?double-spends his MicroMint coins?</p>
    <p>Vendor fraudVendor fraud: What if a vendor gives : What if a vendor gives copies of coins received to an copies of coins received to an accomplice?accomplice?</p>
    <p>FramingFraming: Can vendor frame user for : Can vendor frame user for double-spending, or user frame double-spending, or user frame vendor for fraud?vendor for fraud?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protections against Protections against forgeryforgeryProtections against Protections against forgeryforgery</p>
    <p>Computational difficulty of minting coins.Computational difficulty of minting coins.</p>
    <p>Small-scale forgery not really a concern; Small-scale forgery not really a concern; large-scale forgers will get caught.large-scale forgers will get caught.</p>
    <p>Coins expire monthly. New hash Coins expire monthly. New hash function revealed each month, and old function revealed each month, and old coins exchanged for newly minted ones. coins exchanged for newly minted ones. (Broker works during May to make coins (Broker works during May to make coins good for June; forger only learns good for June; forger only learns hhJuneJune at at beginning of June, and so starts out way beginning of June, and so starts out way behind.)behind.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protection against Protection against double-doublespendingspending</p>
    <p>Protection against Protection against double-doublespendingspending</p>
    <p>There is no anonymity in MicroMint: There is no anonymity in MicroMint: the Broker keeps track of whom each the Broker keeps track of whom each coin was sold to, and notes when it is coin was sold to, and notes when it is returned by vendor.returned by vendor.</p>
    <p>Small-scale double-spending not a Small-scale double-spending not a concern.concern.</p>
    <p>A user whose coins are consistently A user whose coins are consistently double-spent (with many vendors) will double-spent (with many vendors) will be caught and black-listed; he will not be caught and black-listed; he will not be sold any more MicroMint coins.be sold any more MicroMint coins.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protection against Protection against vendor vendor fraudfraud</p>
    <p>Protection against Protection against vendor vendor fraudfraud</p>
    <p>Vendors who consistently redeem Vendors who consistently redeem coins that are also redeemed by coins that are also redeemed by other vendors will be black-listed other vendors will be black-listed and refused further redemption and refused further redemption service by the Broker.service by the Broker.</p>
    <p>Users can cooperate with Broker to Users can cooperate with Broker to identify bad vendors by identifying identify bad vendors by identifying where coin was first spent.where coin was first spent.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protection against Protection against framingframingProtection against Protection against framingframing</p>
    <p>It may be difficult for Broker to It may be difficult for Broker to distinguish user double-spending distinguish user double-spending from vendor fraud.from vendor fraud.</p>
    <p>Small-scale double-spending or Small-scale double-spending or fraud not a concern. Large-scale fraud not a concern. Large-scale cheaters should be distinguishable cheaters should be distinguishable by weight of evidence against by weight of evidence against them.them.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Additional protection Additional protection against against forgeryforgery</p>
    <p>Additional protection Additional protection against against forgeryforgery</p>
    <p>Coins may satisfy hidden predicates Coins may satisfy hidden predicates which are only announced if forgery is which are only announced if forgery is detected by Broker.detected by Broker.</p>
    <p>For example, legitimate coins may all satisfy For example, legitimate coins may all satisfy condition that low-order bit of condition that low-order bit of xxi i is equal to is equal to some complicated function of other bits.some complicated function of other bits.</p>
    <p>Forgers coins will typically not pass this Forgers coins will typically not pass this additional verification condition.additional verification condition.</p>
    <p>Broker can announce several such Broker can announce several such conditions (or even one each day of month).conditions (or even one each day of month).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Micropayment Related Micropayment SchemesSchemes</p>
    <p>Related Micropayment Related Micropayment SchemesSchemes</p>
    <p>Millicent (Manasse et al. / DEC)Millicent (Manasse et al. / DEC)   Scrip for each vendor, broker on-line.Scrip for each vendor, broker on-line.</p>
    <p>NetBill (Tygar / CMU)NetBill (Tygar / CMU)  Heavy use of public-key crypto.Heavy use of public-key crypto.</p>
    <p>NetCard (Anderson / Cambridge)NetCard (Anderson / Cambridge)  Similar to PayWord, but bank signs commitments.Similar to PayWord, but bank signs commitments.</p>
    <p>CAFE (Pederson and IBM Zurich)CAFE (Pederson and IBM Zurich)  Similar to PayWord, but not credit-based.Similar to PayWord, but not credit-based.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ConclusionsConclusionsConclusionsConclusions  We have presented two new We have presented two new</p>
    <p>micropayment schemes, micropayment schemes, PayWordPayWord and and MicroMintMicroMint, that minimize or , that minimize or eliminate public-key operations.eliminate public-key operations.</p>
    <p>PayWord/ MicroMint paper PayWord/ MicroMint paper available from:available from: http://theory.lcs.mit.edu/~rivesthttp://theory.lcs.mit.edu/~rivest</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
