<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PracExtractor: Extracting Configuration Good Practices from Manuals to Detect Server</p>
    <p>Misconfigurations Chengcheng Xiang1, Haochen Huang1, Andrew Yoo1, Yuanyuan Zhou1,</p>
    <p>Shankar Pasupathy2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our lives are largely served by online services today</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What serve us are these powerful and complex data center systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In particular: data center configuration has become highly complex</p>
    <p>Too many config parameters</p>
    <p>Parameters are correlated</p>
    <p>No. of parameters</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Software release large manuals to assist sysadmins with configurations</p>
    <p>Sysadmin</p>
    <p>Too long to read</p>
    <p>Not easy to navigate Unreliable sources</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Is there any useful information that can be automatically extract from manuals?  Yes! Good Practices  Describe how to set parameters in a good way from usage experiences  Examples</p>
    <p>Software parameter Good practices Violation outcomes</p>
    <p>Httpd ExtendedStatus For highest performance, set ExtendedStatus off.</p>
    <p>Performance downgrade</p>
    <p>HBase hbase.regionserv er.thrift.framed</p>
    <p>Setting this to false will select the default transport, vulnerable to DoS.</p>
    <p>Vulnerable to DoS attack</p>
    <p>Cassandra enable_transient _replication</p>
    <p>Transient replication is experimental and is not recommended for production use.</p>
    <p>Unreliable service</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How useful are the good practices in manuals?</p>
    <p>Q1: Are good practices specific or general? General good practices like set to a large value are not helpful.</p>
    <p>Q2: Are good practices already checked in source code? If they are, it is non-necessary to extract them from manuals.</p>
    <p>Q3: Are good practices always equivalent to default settings? If they are, then sysadmins can just leave configurations as default.</p>
    <p>We collected 261 good practices from six software manuals to answer these questions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How useful are the good practices in manuals?</p>
    <p>Q1: Are good practices specific or general? General advice like set to a large value is not helpful.</p>
    <p>Answer: 60% of studied good practices are specific.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How useful are the good practices in manuals?</p>
    <p>Answer: only 3% of specific good practices are checked in source code.</p>
    <p>Q2: Are good practices already checked in source code? If they are, it is non-necessary to extract them from manuals.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How useful are the good practices in manuals?</p>
    <p>Answer: 61% of specific good practices are not equivalent to default settings</p>
    <p>Q3: Are good practices always equivalent to default settings? If they are, then sysadmins can just leave configurations as default.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Based on the study we designed PracExtractor to</p>
    <p>Good practices descriptions</p>
    <p>p1: The crc32 option is recommended.&quot;</p>
    <p>p2: A value between 8 to 16 is suggested.</p>
    <p>p3: We suggest to set it less than ThreadsPerChild.</p>
    <p>Manual Specifications</p>
    <p>p1 == crc32</p>
    <p>p2  [8, 16] p3 &lt; ThreadsPerChild</p>
    <p>Config files</p>
    <p>p2 = 6</p>
    <p>Extract Convert Check</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two challenges with PracExtractor</p>
    <p>How to effective filter noises and extracts only good practice descriptions?  99.6%  97.3% of sentences in manuals are NOT related to good</p>
    <p>practices.</p>
    <p>How to convert good practice descriptions in free-text into checkable specifications?  Sentences like the crc32 option is recommended is not directly</p>
    <p>checkable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenge 1: Extract good practice descriptions</p>
    <p>Keyword filtering  Syntactic-pattern filtering</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenge 1: Extract good practice descriptions</p>
    <p>Good practices candidates</p>
    <p>The crc32 option is recommended.&quot;</p>
    <p>This is not guaranteed even with the recommended settings</p>
    <p>Sentences in manuals The crc32 option is recommended.&quot;</p>
    <p>This is not guaranteed even with the recommended settings</p>
    <p>Specifies how to generate and verify the checksum stored in the disk blocks</p>
    <p>Keyword filtering</p>
    <p>Keyword filtering  Syntactic-pattern filtering</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenge 1: Extract good practice descriptions</p>
    <p>Keyword filtering  Syntactic-pattern filtering</p>
    <p>Good practices candidates The crc32 option is recommended.&quot;</p>
    <p>This is not guaranteed even with the recommended settings</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenge 1: Extract good practice descriptions</p>
    <p>Good practices descriptions The crc32 option is recommended.&quot;</p>
    <p>Syntacticpattern filtering</p>
    <p>Keyword filtering  Syntactic-pattern filtering Good practices candidates</p>
    <p>This is not guaranteed even with the recommended settings. amod</p>
    <p>nsubj</p>
    <p>The crc32 option is recommended . csubj acomp</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenge 2: Convert descriptions into specifications</p>
    <p>Setting entity identification  Semantic pattern matching</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenge 2: Convert descriptions into specifications</p>
    <p>Setting entity identification  Semantic pattern matching Good practices descriptions</p>
    <p>p1: The crc32 option is recommended.</p>
    <p>p2: A value between 8 to 16 is suggested.</p>
    <p>p3: We suggest to set it less than ThreadsPerChild.</p>
    <p>Good practices descriptions</p>
    <p>p1: The crc32 option is recommended.</p>
    <p>p2: A value between 8 to 16 is suggested.</p>
    <p>p3: We suggest to set it less than ThreadsPerChild .</p>
    <p>enum</p>
    <p>int int</p>
    <p>parameter</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenge 2: Convert descriptions into specifications</p>
    <p>Setting entity identification  Semantic pattern matching</p>
    <p>Good practices descriptions</p>
    <p>p1: The crc32 option is recommended.</p>
    <p>p2: A value between 8 to 16 is suggested.</p>
    <p>p3: We suggest to set it less than ThreadsPerChild .</p>
    <p>enum</p>
    <p>int int</p>
    <p>parameter</p>
    <p>Specifications</p>
    <p>p1 == crc32</p>
    <p>p2  [8, 16] p3 &lt; ThreadsPerChild</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PracExtractor  Extract good practices from software manuals  Detect real-world configuration errors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PracExtractor  Accuracy of good practice extraction  Training sets: 6 studied manuals included in our characteristic study  Testing sets: 6 new manuals not included in our study</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PracExtractor  Accuracy of good practice extraction  Precision: what percentage of good practices extracted are true  Recall: what percentage of true good practices are extracted</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PracExtractor  Accuracy of good practice extraction  Good practice descriptions extraction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PracExtractor  Accuracy of good practice extraction  Good practice specifications extraction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PracExtractor  Detect real-world configuration errors  Downloaded 2200 docker images from docker hub.  Detected 1423 practice violations from 853 unique images.  Got 47 confirmed as real configuration errors (325 reported in total).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PracExtractor  Outcome of the confirmed configuration errors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PracExtractor  Analysis of the detected violations  Wrong change: a parameter is changed to a value violating good practices  Wrong default: a parameters default violate good practices but is not changed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PracExtractor  Analysis of the detected violations  Wrong change: a parameter is changed to a value violating good practices  Wrong default: a parameters default violate good practices but is not changed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PracExtractor  Analysis of the detected violations  Wrong change: a parameter is changed to a value violating good practices  Wrong default: a parameters default violate good practices but is not changed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary of PracExtractor  Identified good practices as useful information from manuals for configuration validation.  Studied 261 good practices from six software manuals to prove usefulness.</p>
    <p>Built PracExtractor to automatically extract good practices from manuals.  PracExtractor achieved reasonably high precision and recall.  PracExtractor detected 47 real-world configuration errors.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>c4xiang@cs.ucsd.edu</p>
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
