<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Modular Voting Architecture (Frogs)</p>
    <p>Shuki Bruck (CalTech) David Jefferson (Compaq) Ronald L. Rivest (MIT)</p>
    <p>(WOTE, August 28, 2001)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Moving from paper  electronic  Voting with frogs  Advantages of frogs  Security  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Whats next in voting?</p>
    <p>We propose a practical voting system for the near term (2004?) that  moves from paper to electronic  emphasizes and standardizes a clean</p>
    <p>separation between vote generation and vote casting components (for many good reasons).</p>
    <p>uses digital signatures to witness votes cast</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ballots are printed beforehand.  On election day, voter:</p>
    <p>Identifies himself  Receives ballot  Fills out ballot (vote generation)  Casts ballot (vote casting)</p>
    <p>Ballots scanned; results tabulated.  Problems: UI, printing and storage</p>
    <p>costs, scanning accuracy, security.</p>
    <p>Where are we now? Opscan</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Move from paper to electronic?</p>
    <p>Preserve voting experience  Paper ballot  electronic frog</p>
    <p>(term intended to be neutral as to technology)</p>
    <p>Frog might be dumb flash memory card (4K bytes) with freeze (lock) capability. (No software on frog to validate/certify!)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voting with Frogs: (1) Signin</p>
    <p>Voter identifies himself to pollworker.</p>
    <p>Pollworker takes blank frog, and initializes it. (Election specification, ballot style written on frog.)</p>
    <p>Pollworker gives frog to voter.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(2) Vote Generation</p>
    <p>Voter inserts frog into vote generation equipment.</p>
    <p>Vote generation equipment reads ballot style, provides superb UI for voter to indicate his selections.</p>
    <p>Voters selections are written onto frog in a standard format.</p>
    <p>Voter removes frog.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(3) Vote-casting  Voter inserts his frog into vote</p>
    <p>casting equipment.  Voter sees frog contents displayed.  If voter pushes Cast button:</p>
    <p>Frog is digitally signed; same signing key(s) used for all votes.</p>
    <p>Frog is frozen and deposited in frog bin.  Electronic copy(s) of vote  storage.</p>
    <p>Else frog is returned and voter goes back to (2) vote generation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(4) Web posting/Tabulation</p>
    <p>Once election is over, election officials for each precinct post on Web, as separate, unmatched lists in random order:  Names of all voters who voted.  All cast ballots (with digital</p>
    <p>signatures)</p>
    <p>Everyone can verify signatures on ballots, and compute total.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Advantages of frogs  Electronic: no scanning errors  Frogs can be kept as physical audit</p>
    <p>trail after election.  No printing costs: frogs can be</p>
    <p>purchased blank in bulk (20 cents?)  Frogs can be stored compactly (size</p>
    <p>of business card?)  Frog can be frozen when cast</p>
    <p>making it read-only (unmodifiable).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Advantages of frogs</p>
    <p>Frogs are digital: so they are compatible with cryptography (e.g. digital signatures).</p>
    <p>Frog is just a carrier for a digital representation of ballot; technology can evolve while keeping underlying data formats constant (our proposal is technolgy-neutral).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Standardized Frog Format  This may be the most important</p>
    <p>part of our proposal: Standardize the format of electronic ballots !!!</p>
    <p>Standard data file format: header + one line/race, standard character set (UTF-8).</p>
    <p>This should be vigorously pursued, independent of whether the rest of our proposal is adopted.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Massachusetts, Middlesex County, Precinct 11 Election Closes November 7, 2004 at 8pm EST Ballot: MA/Middlesex/1; English; No rotation Ballot Initialized by Election Official 10</p>
    <p>You have chosen: U.S. President: Mary Morris U.S. Vice President: Alice Applebee Middlesex Dog Catcher: Sam Smith (write-in) Proposition 1 (Casino): FOR Proposition 2 (Taxes): AGAINST Proposition 3 (Swimming Pool): FOR Proposition 4 (Road Work): NO VOTE</p>
    <p>Standardized Frog Format</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Standardized Frog Format</p>
    <p>Is both human and machine-readable.  Provides a clean interface between</p>
    <p>vote-generation (frog-writing) and vote-casting (frog confirmation/ freezing / depositing).</p>
    <p>Allows different manufacturers to build different vote-generation equipment (varying UIs) compatible with same vote-casting equipment.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security</p>
    <p>In near term, the only trustworthy equipment available to voter will be that provided by election officials. (PCs/handhelds/phones all vulnerable. Thus, no individual digital signatures, and no voting from home.)</p>
    <p>In effect, vote-casting equipment is proxy for voter in electronic voting scheme.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security</p>
    <p>A secure system needs to be simple. Very simple. Very very simple.</p>
    <p>A good user interface is complex. Quite complex. Really very complex.</p>
    <p>It follows that the sophisticated user interface should be separated from the security-critical components.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is most securitycritical?</p>
    <p>Vote-casting, wherein voter  Confirms that his selection are</p>
    <p>recorded accurately,  Officially casts his recorded selections.</p>
    <p>This operation needs to be exceptionally trustworthy.</p>
    <p>With electronics, records are indirect; voter is much like a blind man voting with someones assistance.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vote-Casting: the critical instant</p>
    <p>From Bobs vote</p>
    <p>To anonymous vote</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vote-casting equipment should:</p>
    <p>Display exactly and completely whatever is in frog.</p>
    <p>Be stateless (no test/real modes!)  For cast vote, digitally sign whatever</p>
    <p>is in frog, using one key (election official) or more (political parties too).</p>
    <p>Send copies of cast votes  storage units.</p>
    <p>Be open source.  Be long-term purchase.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vote-generation equipment:</p>
    <p>Is less security-critical.  May have proprietary design/code.  Has less stringent certification</p>
    <p>requirements, and so can evolve more quickly with technology.</p>
    <p>May be leased rather than purchased.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Notes:</p>
    <p>Anonymity up to precinct level; should be OK.</p>
    <p>Write-ins might be handled by splitting into write-in/non-writein components to preserve privacy.</p>
    <p>Provisional ballots can be handled as usual. (Put aside in envelope.)</p>
    <p>Voter may prepare ballot at home and bring it to poll-site for final editing/casting.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>We have presented a practical proposal for a modular architecture for near-term pollsite voting that can achieve a high degree of security while simultaneously enabling innovation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(The End)</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
