<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Virtual Power System Testbed (VPST) and Inter</p>
    <p>Testbed Integration</p>
    <p>A u</p>
    <p>g u</p>
    <p>st 1</p>
    <p>David Bergman Dong Jin</p>
    <p>Prof. David Nicol Tim Yardley (Presenter)</p>
    <p>www.iti.illinois.eduUniversity of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Information Trust Institute</p>
    <p>Institute Themes:  Critical Applications, Infrastructures,</p>
    <p>and Homeland Defense  Embedded and Enterprise Computing  Multimedia and Distributed Systems</p>
    <p>Example: distributed air traffic management</p>
    <p>Providing WorldWide Excellence in Information Trust and Security Institute Vision: Trust in Society Institute Personnel: Core faculty from CS and ECE 95+ faculty and senior researchers from 21 Depts.</p>
    <p>Institute Centers  Boeing Trusted Software</p>
    <p>Center  CAESAR: the Center for</p>
    <p>Autonomous Engineering Systems and Robotics</p>
    <p>Center for Information Forensics</p>
    <p>NCASSR: the National Center for Advanced Secure Systems</p>
    <p>NSA Center for Information Assurance Education</p>
    <p>TCIP: Trustworthy Cyber Infrastructure for the Power Grid</p>
    <p>Trusted ILLIAC CenterInstitute Highlights  Established, rapidly growing effort  Large, diverse community of</p>
    <p>researchers  Societal and industrial problems  Major corporate partnerships  Led by the College of Engineering at</p>
    <p>UIUC 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TCIP secures the devices, communications, and data systems that make up the power grid, to ensure trustworthy operation during normal conditions, cyber attacks and/or power emergencies.</p>
    <p>TCIP Industry Advisory Board</p>
    <p>Comprises over 30 industry organizations, representing the entire spectrum of the power industry.</p>
    <p>Focus Research Areas</p>
    <p>Developing a secure and reliable computing base and providing foundations for systemwide security and reliability.</p>
    <p>Designing, implementing and integrating communications and control protocols that provide secure, timely and reliable data collection and control.</p>
    <p>Providing evaluative methodologies and tools for modeling, simulation, emulation and experimentation for security technologies for the power grid.</p>
    <p>Providing education, outreach and training at the K12, undergraduate, and graduate levels and to prepare the next generation workforce.</p>
    <p>TCIP Center: Trustworthy Cyber Infrastructure for Power</p>
    <p>William H. Sanders, Director</p>
    <p>Organization  19 Faculty and Senior Staff; 30 Graduate Research Assistants from Univ. of Illinois, Dartmouth, Cornell, and Washington State University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VPST - Introduction</p>
    <p>VPST - Designed to support exploration of security technologies being developed for large scale power grid infrastructure</p>
    <p>Integrates the following  Real Power Equipment  Electrical Simulations (PowerWorld)  Computation/Communication Simulation</p>
    <p>(RINSE)  Secure remote connectivity to other resources</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VPST  High Level Overview</p>
    <p>External Testbed</p>
    <p>Utility Power Co</p>
    <p>Secure Link</p>
    <p>Secure Link</p>
    <p>VPST</p>
    <p>PowerWorld RINSE</p>
    <p>EMSPI Power Equip</p>
    <p>Custom Apps</p>
    <p>ReadOnly Grid Research Systems Data Feeds</p>
    <p>Experimental Systems Interactive Attacks</p>
    <p>Research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RINSE objectives</p>
    <p>Modeling methodologies for high performance / high capability network analysis  Model composition to support nearly</p>
    <p>transparent parallel processing  Multi-resolution modeling of traffic</p>
    <p>mixed/fluid models of transport protocols, routers, links</p>
    <p>immersive faster-than-real-time simulation for exercises</p>
    <p>very fast net-wide background bandwidth use computation</p>
    <p>x1000s speedup over optimized full-resolution model</p>
    <p>Multi-resolution modeling of network topology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Parallel / Realtime Simulation Kernel</p>
    <p>Network Simulator</p>
    <p>Interaction Support</p>
    <p>Emulation Support</p>
    <p>Attack Models</p>
    <p>Traffic Models</p>
    <p>Network Routing</p>
    <p>Web Interface / Database Management</p>
    <p>RINSE Host Architecture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VPST Motivation (SCADA context)</p>
    <p>Supervisory Control And Data Acquisition (SCADA)</p>
    <p>Simplified, a hybrid of physical devices and the software controlling and monitoring them</p>
    <p>SCADA systems have a rising need for security  Scale and operational context makes using actual</p>
    <p>equipment infeasible in the long run</p>
    <p>SCADA resources have a relatively high barrier to entry</p>
    <p>Emulation alleviates part of this concern, but accurate models are needed</p>
    <p>Other testbeds have valuable resources as well, and wed like to leverage that</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VPST Architecture</p>
    <p>VPST-E  Electrical powergrid simulation  PowerWorld (can simulate over 100,000 buses)</p>
    <p>VPST-C  RINSE-based network simulator  Trusted ILLIAC (can simulate over 1 million</p>
    <p>devices)  VPST-R-local</p>
    <p>Real SCADA devices in TCIP lab  VPST-R-Remote</p>
    <p>Other SCADA/security testbeds  DETER, NSTB, VCSE  Super node</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interconnection Requirements</p>
    <p>Secure Connectivity  May face threats from external cyber-attack</p>
    <p>and internal malicious code  Several layers of protection similar to OPSAID</p>
    <p>Transmission security (IPSec and SSL)  Authentication and access control at all</p>
    <p>accessing points (IPSec)  Traffic isolation (private network)  Intrusion detection if necessary (Snort)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Requirements</p>
    <p>Performance  Overcome latency across multiple testbeds</p>
    <p>Inter-Testbed Connector (ITC), single point of contact and then distributes the workload</p>
    <p>Two connections between each testbed  Control channel  Aggregated data channel</p>
    <p>Use lookahead algorithms to keep the simulation at least as fast as real time (emulated devices)</p>
    <p>Must use highly scalable simulation environment  VPST-C (RINSE network simulator)  VPST-E (PowerWorld simulator)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Resource Requirements</p>
    <p>Resource Allocation  Flexible configuration  Accurate resource mapping that can balance</p>
    <p>customizability and speed  Design of ITC takes decentralized approach and</p>
    <p>is decomposed into modules  VPST must intelligently partition simulation</p>
    <p>models and expand that to heterogeneous testbeds</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reproducibility Requirements</p>
    <p>Reproducibility  Dynamics of SCADA networks (size of network,</p>
    <p>type of physical medium, time-varying traffic patterns) requires precise experiment reproduction</p>
    <p>VPST-C enhances local reproducibility with fully configurable and controllable parameter space</p>
    <p>Human-in-the-loop interaction necessitates that parameters can be changed online and recorded for later reproduction (VPST uses tcpdump/libpcap files for network traffic capture)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fidelity Requirements</p>
    <p>Fidelity  VPST must be as transparent as possible to real</p>
    <p>devices  Realistic data patterns and interactions  Latency  Accurate simulated hosts</p>
    <p>Counterpoint to performance, must be addressed carefully</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VPST Architecture</p>
    <p>VPST-E  Electrical powergrid simulation  PowerWorld (can simulate over 100,000 buses)</p>
    <p>VPST-C  RINSE-based network simulator  Trusted ILLIAC (can simulate over 1 million</p>
    <p>devices)  VPST-R-local</p>
    <p>Real SCADA devices in TCIP lab  VPST-R-Remote</p>
    <p>Other SCADA/security testbeds  DETER, NSTB, VCSE  Super Node</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inter-Testbed Connector (ITC) Architecture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inter-Testbed Connector (ITC) Architecture</p>
    <p>Simulation Control Plane  ITC Controller</p>
    <p>Exchanges control commands with a remote ITC  Collects/distributes commands on local control</p>
    <p>plane  Resource Allocator</p>
    <p>Load balancing and allocation  Verify correctness of topology mapping  Guarantee IP uniqueness/mapping</p>
    <p>Resource configurator  Uses DML to configure hosts, links, traffic, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inter-Testbed Connector (ITC) Architecture</p>
    <p>Simulation Control Plane (continued)  Run-time controller</p>
    <p>Control experiment online  E.g. launch DoS attacks, altering data</p>
    <p>polling behavior  Error Detector</p>
    <p>Detect host failures, asynchronization, out-ofbound parameters, etc.</p>
    <p>Respond by allocating extra resources, generating alerts, writing to logs or terminating/restarting experiment</p>
    <p>Data Plane Configurator  Issue controls to the data plane at</p>
    <p>initialization, run-time, and cleanup stages</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inter-Testbed Connector (ITC) Architecture</p>
    <p>Model Data Plane  Traffic Distributor</p>
    <p>Bridges traffic across interconnected testbeds</p>
    <p>Minimizes the number of physical links by using a super node</p>
    <p>Measurement Reporter  Collects metrics  Leverages both local and remote collection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Use Case 1</p>
    <p>Training and Human-in-the-loop Event Analysis  Mid-western blackout of 2003</p>
    <p>Operators need to be trained with full situational awareness</p>
    <p>Requirements  Secure Connectivity for sensitive information  Reproducibility for event replay and analysis</p>
    <p>of the impact of human decisions  Scalability for large-scale power systems  Fidelity to ensure realistic scenarios</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Use Case 2</p>
    <p>Analysis of Incremental Deployment  Old and new technologies must co-exist</p>
    <p>DNP3SA, for instance, must be tested on a large-scale heterogeneous environment before being deployed</p>
    <p>Requirements  Reproducibility for ensuring new technology</p>
    <p>is the root cause of change  High performance for accurate scale models  Fidelity to ensure new technology behaves</p>
    <p>the same as in the wild</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Use Case 3</p>
    <p>Attack Robustness Analysis</p>
    <p>Simulation &amp; Emulation can combine to test a proposed defense against an attack</p>
    <p>Goals</p>
    <p>Leverage something like DETER for cyber-attack capabilities</p>
    <p>Use National Labs for various SCADA equipment</p>
    <p>VPST-C is the master coordinating and providing the modeling and analysis for the experiment</p>
    <p>Requirements</p>
    <p>Secure connectivity to provide containment</p>
    <p>Reproducibility to allow attack replay against various defenses</p>
    <p>Fidelity to ensure defense results are real</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Difficult Problems</p>
    <p>Coordinated resource allocation and aggregation</p>
    <p>Time contraction and dilation</p>
    <p>Representative traffic generation and modeling  Production SCADA networks are generally very</p>
    <p>closed  Responses can be highly contextual leading to</p>
    <p>complex models</p>
    <p>Interconnected testbed GOTCHAs  virtual attacks become real</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Shown the need to integrate multiple testbeds for SCADA networks and requirements/difficulties therein</p>
    <p>Some aspects currently implemented, more to come</p>
    <p>Future work  To develop a black-box implementation of the</p>
    <p>ITC  To develop a mechanism to ensure efficient</p>
    <p>WAN transmission via coordinated control and integration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgments</p>
    <p>We thank Prof Susan Hinrichs for constructive feedback early on in this project</p>
    <p>This work was supported in part by a grant from the National Science Foundation (CNS-0524695) as part of the TCIP Center</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References</p>
    <p>[1] Dnp3 specification, secure authentication, supplement to volume 2. http://www.dnp.org/Modules/Library/Document.aspx.</p>
    <p>[2] National scada test bed program. http://www.inl.gov/scada/publications/index.shtml.</p>
    <p>[3] Powerworld simulator. http://www.powerworld.com/.</p>
    <p>[4] T. Benzel, R. Braden, D. Kim, C. Neuman, A. Joseph, K. Sklower, R. Ostrenga, and S. Schwab. Experience with deter: a testbed for security research. pages 10 pp.388, 0-0 2006.</p>
    <p>[5] DNP.org. Dnp: Distributed network protocol. http://www.dnp.org.</p>
    <p>[6] W. Hwu, W. Sanders, R. Iyer, and K. Nahrstedt. Trusted illiac: A configurable, application-aware, high-performance platform for trustworthy computing. http://www.iti.illinois.edu/sites/default/files/docs/crisnowbird-06-talk-final.pdf.</p>
    <p>[7] M. Liljenstam, J. Liu, D. Nicol, Y. Yuan, G. Yan, and C. Grier. Rinse: The real-time immersive network simulation environment for network security exercises. In PADS 05: Proceedings of the 19th Workshop on Principles of Advanced and Distributed Simulation, pages 119128,Washington, DC, USA, 2005. IEEE Computer Society.</p>
    <p>[8] M. J. McDonald, G. N. Conrad, T. C. Service, and R. H. Cassidy. Cyber effects analysis using vcse. Tech. Rep. SAND2008-5954, Sandia National Laboratories, September 2008.</p>
    <p>[9] D. M. Nicol, C. M. Davis, and T. Overbye. A virtual power system testbed for cyber-security decision support. Proceedings of the 2009 INFORMS Simulation Society Workshop on Simulation: At the Interface of Modeling and Anaylsis.</p>
    <p>[10] OPSAID. Department of energy office of electric delivery and reliabilitys national scada testbed program. Initial Design and Testing Report.</p>
    <p>[11] PNNL. Looking back at the august 2003 blackout. http://eioc.pnl.gov/research/2003blackout.stm.</p>
    <p>[12] UIUC. Trustworthy cyber infrastructure for the power grid. http://tcip.iti.illinois.edu.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks!</p>
    <p>?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
