<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Spoofer Project Inferring the Extent of Source Address</p>
    <p>Filtering on the Internet</p>
    <p>Rob Beverly and Steve Bauer {rbeverly,bauer}@mit.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Spoofer Project Goal:  Quantify the extent and nature of source address filtering</p>
    <p>on the Internet</p>
    <p>Key results:  ~23% of observed netblocks corresponding to ~24% of observed</p>
    <p>ASes allow some from of spoofing  Filtering is frequently applied inconsistently allowing spoofing of</p>
    <p>parts of the address space  Filtering policies corresponds reasonably well to netblocks</p>
    <p>announced in BGP  No discernable geographic pattern in address filtering policies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation and background</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What are spoofed packets?</p>
    <p>Attackers/compromised-hosts forge or spoof source address of an IP packet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What type of addresses are spoofed?</p>
    <p>IPv4 Address Space</p>
    <p>Unallocated June 29, 2005</p>
    <p>http://www.completewhois.com/bogons/</p>
    <p>Multicast</p>
    <p>Private Intranet</p>
    <p>Loopback</p>
    <p>Valid 10.0.0.0/8 172.16.0.0/12 192.168.0.0/16</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How are bogons filtered?  Bogon list sources:</p>
    <p>http://www.cymru.com/Bogons/  http://www.completewhois.com/bogons/</p>
    <p>Ingress or egress filters on a router</p>
    <p>Need updating (ideally automatically) as assignments change</p>
    <p>Not always 100% accurate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Does spoofing matter in 2005?</p>
    <p>All ISP filter (right?)  RFC2827, uRPF</p>
    <p>Zombie farms  Spoofing provides little additional anonymity</p>
    <p>for actual attacker  Prevalence of NATs</p>
    <p>headers rewritten anyway so spoofing useless</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Indications that spoofing is employed in current attacks</p>
    <p>Backscatter [Moore01][Pang04] shows continued, strong spoofing activity</p>
    <p>In Jan 2005 during one DDoS attack 12% of the source addresses were bogons [Dietrich05]</p>
    <p>High-profile spoofing-based DDoS attacks in 2000-2004:  Yahoo, Ebay, E*trade  Shaft, TFN, trinoo, Stacheldraht, RingZero  Protx online payment site, Nov 2004</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VictimMaster Slave 2</p>
    <p>Slave 1</p>
    <p>Slave N</p>
    <p>Reflector 1</p>
    <p>Reflector n</p>
    <p>Reflector 2</p>
    <p>Attacker Victim Spoofed 1</p>
    <p>Spoofed n</p>
    <p>Spoofed 2</p>
    <p>VictimMaster Slave 2</p>
    <p>Slave 1</p>
    <p>Slave N</p>
    <p>Spoofed 1</p>
    <p>Spoofed n</p>
    <p>Spoofed 2</p>
    <p>DoS attack with spoofing</p>
    <p>Distributed DoS attack</p>
    <p>with spoofing</p>
    <p>Distributed DoS attack</p>
    <p>with reflectors</p>
    <p>Spoofed packets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prediction: spoofing increasingly a problem in the future</p>
    <p>Spoofed traffic complicates a defenders job  Adaptive programs that make use of all local host</p>
    <p>capabilities to amplify their attacks  Consider a 10,000 node zombie DDoS</p>
    <p>Today (worst case scenario): if non-spoofing zombies are widely distributed, a network operator must defend against attack packets from 5% of routeable netblocks.</p>
    <p>Future: if 25% of zombies capable of spoofing significant volume of the traffic could appear to come any part of the IPv4 address space</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spoofer Project: Collection and analysis</p>
    <p>methodology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Collection methodology</p>
    <p>Objective: collect reports of the spoofing capabilities from as many locations on the network as possible</p>
    <p>Spoofing packets requires administrator privileges  No way to induce spoofed packets on remote machines</p>
    <p>need willing participants, unavoidably introducing a potential bias  Clients run a spoofer test program generating a report</p>
    <p>from their network locations  Availability advertised on various mailing lists</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Five of each type with random inter-packet delay  UDP destination port 53 (normally DNS) to avoid secondary</p>
    <p>filtering effects  Payload includes unique 14 byte identifier</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>via TCP  TCP destination port 80 used to avoid secondary filtering</p>
    <p>effects</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spoofed packets</p>
    <p>Neighbor SpoofClient IP  (2N) for 0&lt;N&lt;24</p>
    <p>RFC1918 Private address</p>
    <p>Valid (In BGP table)</p>
    <p>DescriptionSpoofed Source</p>
    <p>Chosen to infer specific filtering policies</p>
    <p>IPv4 Address Space</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example client run [root@coco spoofer]# ./spoofer &gt;&gt; Spoofing Tester v0.2 &gt;&gt; Source 5 spoofed packets (IP: 1.2.3.4) (Seq: g8cb4gc6ojezw1)... &gt;&gt; Source 5 spoofed packets (IP: 172.16.1.100) (Seq: 09kamtjjugxwvy)... &gt;&gt; Source 5 spoofed packets (IP: 6.1.2.3) (Seq: 0dzpw2obc80ff3)... &gt;&gt; &gt;&gt; Checking spoofing result... &gt;&gt; Server response: HOWDY 5am11w18zzc86g &gt;&gt; Server response: COOL 3 &gt;&gt; Server response: FOUND g8cb4gc6ojezw1 &gt;&gt; Server response: FOUND 09kamtjjugxwvy &gt;&gt; Server response: FOUND 0dzpw2obc80ff3 &gt;&gt; Running Trace (please wait): /usr/sbin/traceroute -n 18.26.0.235 traceroute to 18.26.0.235 (18.26.0.235), 30 hops max, 38 byte packets &gt;&gt; Server response: SEND-TRACE LINUX &gt;&gt; Server response: BYE 5am11w18zzc86g</p>
    <p>Test Complete. Your test results: http://momo.lcs.mit.edu/spoofer/report.php?sessionkey=5am11w18zzc86g</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis and results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Client population  From March 2005 to present:</p>
    <p>688 client reports generated  544 unique client reports  No network abuse complaints reported from users or</p>
    <p>received by us</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spoofing failures for reasons not related to ISP policies</p>
    <p>Non-ISP related spoofing failures 326 client reports  Blocked by Windows XP SP2: 155  Hosts Behind NATs: 126  Otherwise blocked by operating system: 20</p>
    <p>We exclude these from our analysis  because they do not definitively provide any indication</p>
    <p>of the capability of other hosts in the same netblock to spoof</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spoofable: spoofing of private, or unallocated, or valid IP packets possible from these network locations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Filtering policies</p>
    <p>Client CountValidUnallocatedPrivate</p>
    <p>Filtered Spoofable policies found in operation on the Internet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Filtering Boundaries</p>
    <p>Filtering occurring on a /8 boundary enables a client within that network to spoof 16,777,215 other addresses.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Correspondence between filtering granularity and BGP prefix size</p>
    <p>Important to understand how filtering granularity relates to routing announcements  Are our extrapolations valid?  Provides clues to a providers network structure</p>
    <p>and operational practices.  BGP view from University of Oregon Routeviews</p>
    <p>tables  prefix size  AS numbers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Correspondence between filtering granularity and BGP prefix size</p>
    <p>Over 36% of the time filtering boundary is exactly the same as announced netblock size</p>
    <p>Over 95% of the time within 65,536 IP addresses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spoofed packets that make it past the ingress edges are likely to travel across the entire Internet  No geographic pattern to filtering policies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ongoing collection effort</p>
    <p>Hourly-updated web page  Summarizes current state of IP spoofing  Goal: continue collecting reports to improve</p>
    <p>accuracy, detect trends, etc.  We need help to expand coverage and gain more</p>
    <p>data!</p>
    <p>http://spoofer.csail.mit.edu/summary.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>http://spoofer.csail.mit.edu Summary of key results:  ~23% of observed netblocks corresponding to</p>
    <p>~24% of observed ASes allow some from of spoofing</p>
    <p>Filtering policies corresponds reasonably well to netblocks announced in BGP</p>
    <p>Filtering is frequently applied inconsistently allowing spoofing of parts of the address space</p>
    <p>No discernable geographic pattern in address filtering policies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
