<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adapting RAID Methods for Use in Object Storage Systems</p>
    <p>David Bigelow, Scott A. Brandt, Carlos Maltzahn, Sage Weil University of California, Santa Cruz</p>
    <p>{dbigelow, scott, carlosm, sage}@cs.ucsc.edu</p>
    <p>FAST 2007 Work-In-Progress February 27, 2008</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adapting RAID Methods for Use in Object Storage Systems 2</p>
    <p>Motivation: OSD Reliability</p>
    <p>Mirroring is Expensive  System may have petabytes of data in thousands of devices  For two-way mirroring alone, the system cost doubles  Linear scaling of system cost for each additional degree of protection</p>
    <p>RAID (and other error-correction codes)  Simple RAID codes can reduce overhead to (N + 1)/N  More advanced error-correction codes (like Reed-Solomon) are</p>
    <p>available  How to adapt these methods for use in object-based storage?</p>
    <p>High-Performance Storage  Typical systems will have very high performance requirements  Can RAID maintain the necessary performance level?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adapting RAID Methods for Use in Object Storage Systems 3</p>
    <p>Client-Based RAID</p>
    <p>Client</p>
    <p>Writes Reads</p>
    <p>P H I J K</p>
    <p>The client alone determines how its data will be stored  Storage system only responsible for storing and returning objects</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adapting RAID Methods for Use in Object Storage Systems 4</p>
    <p>RAID Across Objects</p>
    <p>Client</p>
    <p>Write Read</p>
    <p>P H I J KWrite</p>
    <p>Other Clients</p>
    <p>No overhead to client -- storage system maintains own records  Device failure can lead to large reconstruction times  Very jagged performance curve in degraded mode</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adapting RAID Methods for Use in Object Storage Systems 5</p>
    <p>RAID Within Objects</p>
    <p>Client</p>
    <p>Write</p>
    <p>Read</p>
    <p>Writes</p>
    <p>Reads</p>
    <p>P H I J K</p>
    <p>Always additional delay to the client for both reading and writing  Device failure has smaller reconstruction times  Smoother performance curve in degraded mode</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adapting RAID Methods for Use in Object Storage Systems 6</p>
    <p>Current Status  Simulation</p>
    <p>Measuring of relative performance</p>
    <p>Implementation  Applying techniques to Ceph Object Storage System  Initial approach of parity based RAID</p>
    <p>Continuing Work  More complex schemes to tolerate multiple failures  Hierarchical model to allow multiple reliability schemes</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
