<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C f f t d b h ll f C f f t d b h ll f C f f t d b h ll f C f f t d b h ll f Conferences confronted by challenges of Conferences confronted by challenges of maturitymaturity</p>
    <p>Conferences confronted by challenges of Conferences confronted by challenges of maturitymaturity</p>
    <p>Ken BirmanKen Birman</p>
    <p>Cornell University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>My views in a nutshellMy views in a nutshell</p>
    <p>The systems conferences are approaching aThe systems conferences are approaching a crisis point  Overwhelmed by numbers of submissions, hard to</p>
    <p>convince people to do the PC job properly  Many signs of this stress</p>
    <p>We need to fix these problems before they cause some form of collapsecause some form of collapse</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case in pointCase in point</p>
    <p>Why are the numbers of papers so high?Why are the numbers of papers so high?  Students feel huge pressure to have a lot of papers   but they also feel that conferences are a roll of the y</p>
    <p>dice, hence tend to gamble by submitting a lot</p>
    <p>Why are conferences rolling the dice?  Mostly due to issues in the first round</p>
    <p>Th PC d t ll t i l d til l t i th The PC doesnt really get involved until late in the second round, except the most dedicated members</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The First RoundThe First Round</p>
    <p>Ken assigns 30 papers to Mary SmithKen assigns 30 papers to Mary Smith  Mary shudders and goes into denial  Eventually farms out a lot of the work to her studentsy  Many of these have very little experience</p>
    <p>Back come reviews (with scores!)  And lots of good papers bite the dust</p>
    <p>The PC does a much better job on those that isurvive</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Could we fix this?Could we fix this?</p>
    <p>By any reasonable estimate the systemsBy any reasonable estimate the systems community numbers in the thousands  Just track past participants in SOSP, SICOMM, OSDI,</p>
    <p>NSDI, etc  Many have published, many attend lots of conferences.</p>
    <p>Why not have our own community do the first round reviewing using a social networkinground reviewing, using a social networking approach that HotCRP (or Google) could support?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More ideasMore ideas</p>
    <p>My paper lists other ideas .My paper lists other ideas.  Clear the backlog the way medical conferences do: by</p>
    <p>accepting a LOT more papers as communications Key: they need to be citable on your CV and included into the proceedings (in a communications section)</p>
    <p>Evokes a vision of short papers But in fact why not Evokes a vision of short papers. But in fact, why not eliminate length restrictions completely?</p>
    <p>Review based on 6-8 page extended abstracts but (all) ld b l h i l d dpapers could be as long as the material demands</p>
    <p>Institutionalize rebuttal opportunities  Track histories of reviews (and lives of papers ) Track histories of reviews (and lives of papers)</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
