<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>E-Voting and Forensics: Prying Open the Black Box</p>
    <p>Sean Peisert Matt Bishop Candice Hoke Mark Graff David Jefferson</p>
    <p>given at EVT/WOTE09</p>
    <p>Montreal, Canada August 10, 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Questions That We Address</p>
    <p>What questions can a forensic examination answer?</p>
    <p>When should election administrators consider an election forensic examination?</p>
    <p>How should they prepare for an examination?  Who should be included on the forensic team?  What sort of legal, contractual, and practical</p>
    <p>provisions may be needed?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Questions We Do Not Answer</p>
    <p>Study the merits of e-voting, or specific types of e-voting systems.</p>
    <p>Analyze or discuss proposed voting systems.</p>
    <p>Analyze specific auditing techniques.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some Causes of Problems in Voting</p>
    <p>Malicious attacks can occur.  Many problems are caused by accident and are</p>
    <p>not malicious.</p>
    <p>Someone trips over a power cord.  The polling place floods due to rainstorms.</p>
    <p>Basic Problem: what happens when something goes wrong with an election?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions Driving Election Forensics</p>
    <p>Why dont vote totals always reconcile?  Why does a system keep failing?  Are totals accurate and complete?  Can election officials certify the results?  Will the public accept the results?  Should candidates demand a recount?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Issues With Election Forensics</p>
    <p>No generally/broadly accepted logging/ auditing standards.</p>
    <p>No generally/broadly accepted machine standards.</p>
    <p>No concrete legal guidance from court precedents.</p>
    <p>In forensic auditing, accountability and traceability are key. But votes cannot be tied to individual voters.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy and Security Must Be Balanced (Peisert, Bishop, &amp; Yasinsac HICSS09)</p>
    <p>Election officials need to be able to count ballots  Forensic analysts need to be able to determine if</p>
    <p>and how a machine failed.</p>
    <p>Cannot allow a voter to indicate to an auditor who they are (vote selling)</p>
    <p>Cannot allow an auditor to determine who a voter is (voter coercion)</p>
    <p>This leads to a direct conflict.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What About VVPATs?  VVPATs are not audit trails (Yasinsac &amp; Bishop, HICSS08)</p>
    <p>If a VVPAT shows an undervote:  could be malfunction  could be voter choice</p>
    <p>If a VVPAT shows an over-vote:  probably malfunction, but where?</p>
    <p>If a VVPAT shows an equal balance:  implies that any problem did not involve dropping or</p>
    <p>adding votes (but could simply be mis-recording votes)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions a Forensic Examination Can Answer  How many votes did the problem affect?  How accurate are the canvass totals?  If the totals are wrong, can the investigation recover the</p>
    <p>data needed to correct the problem?</p>
    <p>Is the voting equipment functioning according to documentation?</p>
    <p>Were any procedural guidelines violated?  Which jurisdictions does the problem affect?  ...and others...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Requirements</p>
    <p>Accuracy  Availability  Secrecy  Anonymity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Laocon: A Model of Forensic Logging</p>
    <p>Our approach: what data do we need to record in order to be able to analyze certain events?</p>
    <p>Attack graphs of goals.  Goals can be attacker goals</p>
    <p>(i.e., targets) or defender goals (i.e., security policies)</p>
    <p>Predicates represented by preconditions &amp; post-conditions of events to accomplish goals.</p>
    <p>Method of translating those conditions into logging requirements.</p>
    <p>a b c d</p>
    <p>start of attack unknown</p>
    <p>intermediate steps end goals of intruder</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Laocon &amp; E-Voting</p>
    <p>Many violations of security policy on evoting are easy to define precisely (e.g., changing or discarding cast votes)</p>
    <p>Machines have (theoretically or ideally) limited modes of operation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Applying the Model to E-Voting: Start with E-Voting Requirements</p>
    <p>Laws and requirements become security policies</p>
    <p>Security policies define attack graphs</p>
    <p>Attack graphs start with ultimate goals</p>
    <p>Attack graphs are translated into detailed specifications and implementations to guide logging</p>
    <p>a b c d</p>
    <p>start of attack unknown</p>
    <p>intermediate steps end goals of intruder</p>
    <p>logging points</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Law to Policy</p>
    <p>California Constitution, Article 2 (Voting, initiative and referendum, and recall)</p>
    <p>Law: Sec. 7. Voting shall be secret.  Manual Voting Policy: the person who opens envelopes</p>
    <p>containing absentee ballots and removes the ballots is different than the person who tallies the ballots.</p>
    <p>E-Voting Policy: information must not leak outside the system through any method other than the prescribed ballot.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Policy to Goals</p>
    <p>Examine the ballots for signs of unique identifiers.  Examine the setup of the e-voting machines to see if</p>
    <p>network cables, wireless devices, or physical sight lines could cause votes to be observed.</p>
    <p>Interview poll workers to determine the locations of people during voting.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Laocon &amp; Over-Voting  Over-voting occurs when more candidates are selected</p>
    <p>than allowed in a given race.</p>
    <p>At some point, the value of a bit changes.  What are the paths to that event?</p>
    <p>Start with the entry to the system (e.g., touchscreen, supervisor screen, HW manipulation).</p>
    <p>End at the data.  This places bounds on the intermediate steps.  Monitor those paths.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Laocon &amp; Over-Voting</p>
    <p>Memory Card #1</p>
    <p>Memory Card #2</p>
    <p>Memory Card #3</p>
    <p>Touchscreen</p>
    <p>Supervisor Screen</p>
    <p>Hardware Access</p>
    <p>Intermediate Steps</p>
    <p>Open Box</p>
    <p>Magnetic Manipulation</p>
    <p>Swap Mem Cards</p>
    <p>&quot;write&quot; syscall</p>
    <p>Introduce HW via USB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Procedural Elements</p>
    <p>What about methods of bypassing the logging system?</p>
    <p>How tamperproof are logs?  What about denial-of-service?  What about human error?  What about DREs vs. optical scanners?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Concept</p>
    <p>Repeated crashes, freezes, or auto-reboots may indicate a failure of the system.</p>
    <p>This describes a goal state of the fault graph.  The model states that data to describe the</p>
    <p>system and failure should be recorded.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Data to Preserve</p>
    <p>Laocon prescribes the need to begin with the endpoint of the attack/fault graph and work backwards to understand prior indications. Thus:</p>
    <p>Rule P1: Record indications of any failure, what happened, when it happened, and any error indicators.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Laocon and Data Preservation</p>
    <p>System-level events  Commands capable of performing such actions</p>
    <p>Human events  Who was using the machine?  Who had access to the machine?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Laocon and Data Preservation</p>
    <p>Memory Card #1</p>
    <p>Memory Card #2</p>
    <p>Memory Card #3</p>
    <p>Touchscreen</p>
    <p>Supervisor Screen</p>
    <p>Hardware Access</p>
    <p>Intermediate Steps</p>
    <p>Open Box</p>
    <p>Magnetic Manipulation</p>
    <p>Swap Mem Cards</p>
    <p>&quot;write&quot; syscall</p>
    <p>Introduce HW via USB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Data to Preserve</p>
    <p>Laocon also prescribes the need to start at the beginning of the fault graph. So:</p>
    <p>Rule P2: Record information about entry points into the system, including the locations from which people accessed the system.</p>
    <p>Voter interface  Maintenance bays  Include non-voters, such as officials and vendors  Visual descriptions of the state of entry points  Locations of power cords, weather, etc...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Data to Preserve  Laocon prescribes the need to record possible paths</p>
    <p>from initial states to error states. So:  Rule P3: Collect external data relevant to the state of the</p>
    <p>voting system  VVPATs  Audit logs  Memory cards  Removable peripherals (e.g., USB sticks)  Cables indicating network/telephone connections  Videotapes  People!  Chain of custody details</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Data to Preserve</p>
    <p>Laocon prescribes the data necessary to analyze an event, and thus also the data not adhering to that standard. So:</p>
    <p>Rule P4: Record any signs that the data is incomplete or may not be trustworthy</p>
    <p>E.g., if a system is supposed to record all occurrences of X but does so only intermittently.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Assurance and How to Preserve Data  Laocon prescribes that data should be recoded at</p>
    <p>failure points (both temporally and physical proximity).</p>
    <p>Rule A1: Preserve all artifacts as soon as the problem is discovered, in the state in which the problem was discovered.</p>
    <p>Copies of data, clones, backups, memory  Precinct devices  Freezing evidence  Digital photographs  Network state</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Laocon and Data Preservation</p>
    <p>Memory Card #1</p>
    <p>Memory Card #2</p>
    <p>Memory Card #3</p>
    <p>Touchscreen</p>
    <p>Supervisor Screen</p>
    <p>Hardware Access</p>
    <p>Intermediate Steps</p>
    <p>Open Box</p>
    <p>Magnetic Manipulation</p>
    <p>Swap Mem Cards</p>
    <p>&quot;write&quot; syscall</p>
    <p>Introduce HW via USB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Assurance and How to Preserve Data  A human process is equally important as a Laocon</p>
    <p>attack graph, although sometimes more difficult to implement. Nevertheless:</p>
    <p>Rule A2: Election officials must have a process documenting how to handle potential evidence</p>
    <p>Chain of custody  Observations from humans  Forensic logs  Two-person rule  Tamper-evidence (crypto hashes, tape)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Assurance and How to Preserve Data</p>
    <p>Rule A3: Potential evidence should be frozen and secured.  Only forensic examiners should have access.  Maintain as close as possible to original state.  All access must be observable.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Assurance and How to Preserve Data  Rule A4: The process for preserving evidence must be public.  Rule A5: The methodology and results of the forensic</p>
    <p>examination must be public.</p>
    <p>Transparency is usually preferable.  Secrecy creates doubt and inhibits assurance.  Confidentiality of examiners discussions is important.  Vendors have proprietary information.  Voters privacy must also be protected.</p>
    <p>In the California TTBR, video of meetings was broadcast, but not audio.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary  Forensic analysis is difficult in general  Forensic analysis of e-voting machines is particularly</p>
    <p>challenging.</p>
    <p>Tradeoffs and contradictions  Varying laws, technology, and human behavior</p>
    <p>Voting is as mission critical as designing aircraft and satellites</p>
    <p>We need good design and forensic practices  We need high assurance in design and analysis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Going Forward</p>
    <p>Compare election requirements to design and implementation of voting machines</p>
    <p>Apply high assurance techniques to e-voting  Analyze inherent contradictions in security,</p>
    <p>anonymity, and secrecy within elections</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In the Paper</p>
    <p>Providing a facility for investigations  Investigation team organization and size  Technical qualifications of investigators  Non-technical qualifications of investigators  Role of the voting machine vendor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In the Paper</p>
    <p>Legal, Contractual and Practical Issues  Appendices  Example NDA  Partial List of Voting Systems Studies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
