<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Blocker Tag: Selective Blocking of RFID Tags for</p>
    <p>Consumer Privacy</p>
    <p>Ari Juels RSA Laboratories</p>
    <p>Ron Rivest MIT CSAIL</p>
    <p>Mike Szydlo RSA Laboratories</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is a Radio-Frequency Identification (RFID) tag?</p>
    <p>Chip (IC)</p>
    <p>Antenna</p>
    <p>In terms of appearance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>You may own a few RFID tags  Contactless physical-access cards  Automated toll payment</p>
    <p>At present, an RFID tag simply calls out its (unique) name or static data over a short distance</p>
    <p>What is an RFID tag?</p>
    <p>74AB8</p>
    <p>5F8KJ3</p>
    <p>Plastic #3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The capabilities of basic RFID tags</p>
    <p>No power  Receives power from reader  Range a few meters</p>
    <p>Little memory  Static 64-to-128-bit identifier in current ultra-cheap</p>
    <p>generation (five cents / unit)  Hundreds of bits soon</p>
    <p>Little computational power  A few thousand gates  No cryptographic functions available  Static keys for read/write permission</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The grand vision: RFID as next-generation barcode</p>
    <p>Barcode RFID tag</p>
    <p>Line-of-sight Radio contact</p>
    <p>Specifies object type Uniquely specifies object</p>
    <p>Fast, automated scanning</p>
    <p>Provides pointer to database entry for every object</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Commercial applications  Smoother inventory tracking</p>
    <p>Military supply logistics  Gulf War I: Placement of double orders to ensure arrival  Gulf War II: RFID renders supply chain much more reliable</p>
    <p>Product recalls  Anti-counterfeiting  Maintaining shelf stocks in retail environments</p>
    <p>Gillette Mach3 razor blades  Parenting logistics</p>
    <p>Water park uses RFID bracelets to track children</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>There is an impending explosion in RFID-tag use</p>
    <p>Wal-Mart requiring top 100 suppliers to deploy RFID at pallet level by 2005</p>
    <p>Gillette announced order of 500,000,000 RFID tags  Auto-ID Center at MIT</p>
    <p>Wal-Mart, Gillette, Procter &amp; Gamble, etc.  Spearheading EPC (electronic product code) data standard for tags  Developing cheap manufacturing techniques  Handing over standards to Uniform Code Council</p>
    <p>Estimated costs  2005: $0.05 per tag; $100 per reader  2008: $0.01 per tag; several dollars per reader (?)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Consumer-Privacy Problem</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Serial numbers: 597387,389473</p>
    <p>Wig model #4456</p>
    <p>(cheap polyester)</p>
    <p>Das Kapital and Communist-party</p>
    <p>handbook</p>
    <p>Replacement hip medical part #459382</p>
    <p>RFID tags will be everywhere</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simple approaches to consumer privacy</p>
    <p>Method 1: Place RFID-tags in protective mesh or foil</p>
    <p>Problem: makes locomotion difficult perhaps useful for wallets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method 2: Kill RFID tags</p>
    <p>Problem: RFID tags are much too useful</p>
    <p>Simple approaches to consumer privacy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some consumer applications today</p>
    <p>House pets</p>
    <p>Prada, Soho NYC  Personalization / accessorization</p>
    <p>Building access (HID)  ExxonMobil Speedpass</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consumer applications tomorrow  Smart appliances</p>
    <p>Refrigerators that automatically create shopping lists  Closets that tell you what clothes you have available, and search the</p>
    <p>Web for advice on current styles, etc.  Ovens that know how to cook pre-packaged food</p>
    <p>Smart products  Clothing, appliances, CDs, etc. tagged for store returns</p>
    <p>Smart paper  Airline tickets that indicate your location in the airport  Library books  Business cards</p>
    <p>Recycling  Plastics that sort themselves</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Early examples of consumer backlash</p>
    <p>42% of Google results on RFID include word privacy</p>
    <p>CASPIAN (Consumers Against Supermarket Privacy Invasion and Numbering)  Diatribes on RFID at:</p>
    <p>NoCards.org  BoycottGillette.com  BoycottBenetton.com</p>
    <p>National news coverage: NY Times, Time, etc.  Wal-Mart smart-shelf project cancelled  Benetton RFID plans withdrawn</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The two messages of this talk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Blocker Tag</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Blocker Tag Blocker simulates all (billions of) possible tag serial numbers!!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tree-walking anti-collision protocol for RFID tags</p>
    <p>?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In a nutshell  Tree-walking protocol for identifying tags</p>
    <p>recursively asks question:  What is your next bit?</p>
    <p>Blocker tag always says both 0 and 1!  Makes it seem like all possible tags are present  Reader cannot figure out which tags are actually</p>
    <p>present  Number of possible tags is huge (at least a billion</p>
    <p>billion), so reader stalls</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two bottles of Merlot #458790</p>
    <p>Blocker tag system should protect privacy but still avoid blocking unpurchased items</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consumer privacy + commercial security</p>
    <p>Blocker tag can be selective:  Privacy zones: Only block certain ranges of RFID-tag</p>
    <p>serial numbers  Zone mobility: Allow shops to move items into privacy</p>
    <p>zone upon purchase  Example:</p>
    <p>Blocker blocks all identifiers with leading 1 bit  Items in supermarket carry leading 0 bit  On checkout, leading bit is flipped from 0 to 1</p>
    <p>PIN required, as for kill operation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Blocking with privacy zones</p>
    <p>Transfer to privacy zone on purchase of item</p>
    <p>Privacy zone</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Polite blocking  We want reader to scan privacy zone when blocker</p>
    <p>is not present  Aim of blocker is to keep functionality active  when</p>
    <p>desired by owner</p>
    <p>But if reader attempts to scan when blocker is present, it will stall!</p>
    <p>Your humble servant requests that you not scan the privacy zone</p>
    <p>Polite blocking: Blocker informs reader of its presence</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More about blocker tags</p>
    <p>Blocker tag can be cheap  Essentially just a yes tag and no tag with a</p>
    <p>little extra logic  Can be embedded in shopping bags, etc.</p>
    <p>With multiple privacy zones, sophisticated, e.g., graduated policies are possible</p>
    <p>Standards integration would be quite helpful  AutoID Center (UCC) may support this</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Final remarks  Spectrum of RFID devices</p>
    <p>$0.05 vs. $1.00  Privacy is not just a consumer issue  its also a corporate issue  Privacy is just one of many RFID-related security issues!</p>
    <p>As Extended Internet, RFID represents extension of traditional security perimeter</p>
    <p>Legislation and technology most effective in concert</p>
    <p>Proponents [of RFID] envision a pervasive global network of millions of receivers along the entire supply chain -- in airports, seaports, highways, distribution centers, warehouses, retail stores, and in the home. This would allow for seamless, continuous identification and tracking of physical items as they move from one place to another, enabling companies to determine the whereabouts of all their products at all times.</p>
    <p>Contrast a physical reality of RFID tags:  Manufacturers struggling with reliability, e.g., UHF tags hard to read near</p>
    <p>human body!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More about RFID work  See ari-juels.com for blocker info  Also see:</p>
    <p>MIT RFID Privacy Workshop, 15 November 2003  www.rfidprivacy.org</p>
    <p>AutoID center: www.autoidcenter.org  Masters thesis of Steve Weis  Bill of Rights of Simson Garfinkel  Electronic Privacy Information Center Web site</p>
    <p>(URL: www.epic.org/privacy/rfid/)  CASPIAN (yellow journalism) (URL: www.nocards.org)</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
