<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>intertrust Persistent Security, Privacy, and Governance for Healthcare Information Knox Carey, Jarl Nilsson, and Steve Mitchell Intertrust Technologies Corporation</p>
    <p>USENIX HealthSec Workshop 9 August 2011</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(c) 2011intertrust</p>
    <p>The Fundamental Problem</p>
    <p>Medical information needs to be widely distributed  To the point of care, regardless of origin  To specialists consulting on a particular case  To researchers and public health authorities  To family caregivers  &amp;c.</p>
    <p>Technology can make this happen</p>
    <p>This is not happening</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(c) 2011intertrust</p>
    <p>Nature of the Problem</p>
    <p>Every interface between systems poses risk  Systems may not interoperate at all  Policies differ between systems</p>
    <p>Laws and regulations  Corporate policies  Patient preferences</p>
    <p>No assurance that policies will be respected</p>
    <p>Resulting behaviors  Data hoarding  Asking patients to sign away rights</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(c) 2011intertrust</p>
    <p>Elements of the Solution: Persistent Governance</p>
    <p>Protect healthcare information at its source</p>
    <p>Persistently associate rules that govern access  Access granted to certain principals or roles  Rules under the control of the patient, ideally  Access can be audited</p>
    <p>Ensure uniform enforcement of those rules</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(c) 2011intertrust</p>
    <p>Elements of the Solution: Consistent Trust Management</p>
    <p>Systems must be able to interoperate</p>
    <p>No prior interaction should be assumed</p>
    <p>Senders must be able to rely upon computations performed by a recipient</p>
    <p>Role for government?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(c) 2011intertrust</p>
    <p>Elements of the Solution: Derived Resources</p>
    <p>Meeting the conditions in a rule unlocks a resource</p>
    <p>Should the resource look the same to all?  You  Your doctor  The nurse  Your physical therapist  Your therapist therapist  Your children  An epidemiologist</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(c) 2011intertrust</p>
    <p>Derived Resources</p>
    <p>A derived resource combines:  A resource  A set of rules  A set of computations to be performed upon the resource</p>
    <p>Virtual Secure Package</p>
    <p>Secure Computing Environment</p>
    <p>Rules Evaluation</p>
    <p>Output Computation</p>
    <p>Secure Database</p>
    <p>ComputationsRules</p>
    <p>Original Resource</p>
    <p>Context Intent</p>
    <p>Keys</p>
    <p>Derived Resource</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(c) 2011intertrust</p>
    <p>In Conclusion</p>
    <p>Our goal is to get information moving</p>
    <p>Trusted distributed computing, policy management are essential ingredients</p>
    <p>New applications require new approaches</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
