<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ruhr-University Bochum Chair for System SecurityRuhr-University Bochum Chair for System Security</p>
    <p>Transparent Mobile Storage Protection</p>
    <p>in Trusted Virtual Domains</p>
    <p>Luigi Catuogno1, Hans Lhr1, Mark Manulis2, Ahmad</p>
    <p>Reza Sadeghi1, Marcel Winandy1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mobile Storage Devices (MSD)</p>
    <p>Memory devices used as portable hard disks.</p>
    <p>Pluggable into a wide variety of equipments (e.g., cameras)(e.g., cameras)</p>
    <p>Robust, reliable and flexible</p>
    <p>However  Raise several security issues</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Issues with MSD</p>
    <p>Can be intercepted by outsiders  Unauthorized read &amp; manipulation of</p>
    <p>sensitive data</p>
    <p>However However  Usage policy and restrictions not sufficient</p>
    <p>Impacts on flexibility  Policies are often error prone</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goals</p>
    <p>Flexible and transparent deployment of MSDs within the same organizational network  Guaranteeing data confidentiality and</p>
    <p>integrityintegrity  Prevention of unauthorized access by</p>
    <p>outsiders  Prevention of unintentional keys/data</p>
    <p>disclosure by insiders  Enforcing access policy also when the</p>
    <p>platform is off-line.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trusted Virtual Domains (TVD)</p>
    <p>The forthcoming framework to implement multi-domain/single</p>
    <p>infrastructure computer networks</p>
    <p>Externalized data centers Externalized data centers  Organizational intranets which require the</p>
    <p>separation of different data flows.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trusted Virtual Domains</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trusted Virtual Domains (TVD)</p>
    <p>Coalition of Virtual Machines that:  Trust each other  Enforce a common security policy (TVD</p>
    <p>Policy)Policy)</p>
    <p>Span over a physical infrastructure, shared with other TVDs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>physical</p>
    <p>platform 1</p>
    <p>physical</p>
    <p>platform 2</p>
    <p>Trusted Virtual Domain</p>
    <p>Red</p>
    <p>VM1</p>
    <p>Blue</p>
    <p>VM2</p>
    <p>Red</p>
    <p>VM3</p>
    <p>Blue</p>
    <p>VM4</p>
    <p>Red TVDRed TVD Blue TVDBlue TVD</p>
    <p>Virtual machines of different TVDs are separated even if running on the same platform</p>
    <p>Virtual machines of the same TVD are connected through a dedicated and isolated VLAN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TVD Architecture</p>
    <p>TVD Master  A special node that controls the access to</p>
    <p>the TVD is done by following the admission</p>
    <p>control rules specified in the TVD Policycontrol rules specified in the TVD Policy</p>
    <p>TVD Proxy  A compartment deployed on each platform</p>
    <p>to locally enforce the TVD Policy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trusted Virtual Domain Deployment &amp; Joining</p>
    <p>Red TVDMaster</p>
    <p>Policy</p>
    <p>Red TVDMaster</p>
    <p>Policy</p>
    <p>Physical platform 1</p>
    <p>Red</p>
    <p>TVDProxy</p>
    <p>Policy</p>
    <p>Red</p>
    <p>VM3</p>
    <p>Physical platform 1</p>
    <p>Red</p>
    <p>TVDProxy</p>
    <p>Policy</p>
    <p>TVD Deploy TVD Join</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Proposal:</p>
    <p>System operationSystem operation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Handling Mobile Storage Devices</p>
    <p>Red</p>
    <p>TVD Master</p>
    <p>Admin. Platform</p>
    <p>Blue</p>
    <p>TVD Master</p>
    <p>Physical network</p>
    <p>Platform P1</p>
    <p>Red</p>
    <p>VM1</p>
    <p>Platform P2</p>
    <p>Blue</p>
    <p>VM2</p>
    <p>Platform P3</p>
    <p>Red</p>
    <p>VM3</p>
    <p>Blue</p>
    <p>VM4</p>
    <p>Platform P4</p>
    <p>Red</p>
    <p>VM5</p>
    <p>Device D2Device D1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Requirements</p>
    <p>Different MSDs may unpredictably appear and disappear within the TVD</p>
    <p>Device identification. Whenever an MSD is plugged in, the platform should be able to distinguish the device and</p>
    <p>the domain this device belongs to.the domain this device belongs to.</p>
    <p>Dynamic device management. The architecture should be able to enforce the policy and deliver the</p>
    <p>correct encryption keys wherever the device is plugged-in</p>
    <p>Transparent and mandatory data encryption and signature.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Solution</p>
    <p>Device identification. A unique identification record (IR) is assigned to the device when it is initialized</p>
    <p>Key retrieval. Encryption (and signing) keys are indexed with the IR and stored in a two level database (Local/Domain Device Directory)(Local/Domain Device Directory)</p>
    <p>Access Policy Enforcement Is accomplished by the TVD infrastructure. Device access policy is incorporated into the TVD Policy.</p>
    <p>Device Access. Data encryption/integrity verification is transparently done by a specific component on the platform and is not in charge to the user VM.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Red VM1</p>
    <p>Red</p>
    <p>TVD Master</p>
    <p>Admin. Platform</p>
    <p>DDD</p>
    <p>Key</p>
    <p>The Platform Architecture</p>
    <p>HardwareTPM</p>
    <p>L4 microkernel</p>
    <p>Storage Manager</p>
    <p>LDD MSD</p>
    <p>Manager</p>
    <p>Compartment</p>
    <p>Manager</p>
    <p>Red TVDProxy</p>
    <p>Policy</p>
    <p>vMSD</p>
    <p>Identification record</p>
    <p>Keys</p>
    <p>Key</p>
    <p>retrieval</p>
    <p>Physical device</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Proposal:</p>
    <p>Data Encryption and StorageData Encryption and Storage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accessing data</p>
    <p>Each device is associated to a unique encryption key</p>
    <p>Each platform has an individual signing key for each device and a shared public key for each device and a shared public key</p>
    <p>Written data are encrypted and signed  Reads succeed only if data has a valid</p>
    <p>signature</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Encryption Scheme</p>
    <p>Lazy revocation:  Triggers re-encryption of only newly</p>
    <p>modified data</p>
    <p>Not all distributed data has to be re- Not all distributed data has to be reencrypted</p>
    <p>Whenever a user is revoked  A new key is delivered to remaining users  Encryption is done always with the most recent</p>
    <p>key</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Off-line access to MSDs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Off-line scenario: requirements</p>
    <p>Delegation. Off-line platforms should be able to enforce the access control policy</p>
    <p>Delayed re-encryption. Off-line platforms should be enabled to access data written up to the time they were on</p>
    <p>lineline</p>
    <p>Traceability and recovery. Domain member should be able to track ad revert unauthorized data changes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Off-line scenario: our solutions</p>
    <p>Ki Ki Ki</p>
    <p>Delegation: off-line platforms store keys into</p>
    <p>their LDD</p>
    <p>Delayed re-encryption: Lazy revocation of encryption</p>
    <p>Ki</p>
    <p>Ki+1 Ki+1</p>
    <p>revocation of encryption</p>
    <p>keys allows off-line platform</p>
    <p>to access (at less) old-data.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Off-line scenario: our solutions</p>
    <p>Traceability and recovery: Employing a versioning file system to keep track of all</p>
    <p>modifications.</p>
    <p>Off-line platforms are enabled to access the most  Off-line platforms are enabled to access the most recent version they can decrypt</p>
    <p>Whenever a revocation occurs it is possible to revert all changes done by revoked platforms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security considerations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attacks to the user machine</p>
    <p>The adversary could exploit any VM:  Enjoys its data access</p>
    <p>privileges</p>
    <p>cannot access or handle the keys</p>
    <p>Red TVDProxy</p>
    <p>Red VM1</p>
    <p>the keys</p>
    <p>Cannot override the TVD Policy</p>
    <p>Keys in the LDD cannot be accessed by corrupted compartments</p>
    <p>Cannot tamper the devices IR</p>
    <p>HardwareTPM</p>
    <p>L4 microkernel</p>
    <p>Storage Manager</p>
    <p>LDD MSD</p>
    <p>Manager</p>
    <p>Compartment</p>
    <p>Manager</p>
    <p>Red TVDProxy</p>
    <p>Policy</p>
    <p>vMSD</p>
    <p>Identification record</p>
    <p>Keys</p>
    <p>Physical device</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attacks to MSDs</p>
    <p>Denial of Service  file deletion/corruption  device re-initialization</p>
    <p>Roll-back</p>
    <p>VM1</p>
    <p>Roll-back  Bringing back the device at a</p>
    <p>certain time in the past by</p>
    <p>overwriting the current file</p>
    <p>system with an older</p>
    <p>(though legitimate) image</p>
    <p>VM2</p>
    <p>adv</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attacks to off-line platforms</p>
    <p>Revoked platform can exchange data with unaware off-line platforms.</p>
    <p>Provide corrupted data</p>
    <p>VM1adv</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Free and transparent deployment of MSDs within the same TVD  Coherently incorporated into the TVD</p>
    <p>infrastructure  Data confidentiality and integrity through  Data confidentiality and integrity through</p>
    <p>transparent and mandatory encryption and signature</p>
    <p>Decentralized Access Policy enforcement  Even while data is accessed by an off-line</p>
    <p>platform</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Direction</p>
    <p>File system improvement  Preventing the diffusion of malware</p>
    <p>through MSDs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Further Info</p>
    <p>System Security Lab at Ruhr Universitt Bochum (DE)</p>
    <p>http://www.trust.rub.de</p>
    <p>Turaya Security Kernel Turaya Security Kernel  http://www.emscb.org</p>
    <p>OpenTC: EU Project featuring an implementation of Trusted Virtual Domain</p>
    <p>http://www.opentc.net</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!Thank you!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
