<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Style Guide for Voting System Documentation: Why User-Centered Documentation Matters to Voting Security</p>
    <p>Sharon Laskowski, NIST sharon.laskowski@nist.gov</p>
    <p>Dana Chisnell, UsabilityWorks Svetlana Lowry, NIST Susan Becker, Codewords</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Whats wrong with this picture?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Nashville, TN Super Tuesday, 2008 A voting machine that would not function sits near a line of people waiting go vote.</p>
    <p>Deborah Hastings, AP National Writer</p>
    <p>Was it broken or were the poll workers confused?</p>
    <p>AP Photo/Mark Humphrey, File</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Washington, DC Super Tuesday, 2008 While folks in Washington were waiting hours to vote under record turnout Feb. 12, poll workers hid electronic voting machines because they didn't like the touchscreen devices.</p>
    <p>Deborah Hastings, AP National Writer</p>
    <p>Why didnt the poll workers like the touch-screen devices? Was it because they couldnt figure them out?</p>
    <p>Rick Laferriere</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Chicago Super Tuesday, 2008 Poll workers passed out pens meant for e-voting machines.</p>
    <p>When those instruments made no mark on paper ballots, election workers said they were full of invisible ink  an explanation that was upheld by onsite precinct judges.</p>
    <p>Deborah Hastings, AP National Writer</p>
    <p>Did anyone check the doc? Maybe it was full of invisible ink, too.</p>
    <p>Dana Chisnell</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cuyahoga County, OH November, 2006 In at least one case in the 2006 midterm election, a thermal paper roll had been installed backward, so nothing printed out onto it. In other locations, there were reports of paper jamming so that votes printed over one another.</p>
    <p>National Public Radio</p>
    <p>Unattributed - Polling Place Photo Project</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Washington, DC November, 2008 Data cartridges that store votes were unreadable at one precinct. The voting system manufacturer suggested two possible causes: static discharge or election workers mishandling the cartridges.</p>
    <p>Washington Post</p>
    <p>Unattributed voting system documentation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Missing:</p>
    <p>Clear information</p>
    <p>Design for typical poll workers</p>
    <p>Whats wrong with this picture?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NIST, The Help America Vote Act (HAVA), and Voting System Standards</p>
    <p>HAVA calls out the need for improved standards for voting systems</p>
    <p>NIST provides the technical support to develop these standards and test methods through the Election Assistance Commission and its Technical Guidelines Development Committee</p>
    <p>VVSG (Voluntary Voting System Guidelines) Section 3  Comprehensive usability and accessibility for voting systems</p>
    <p>Design and performance standards based on best practice and research</p>
    <p>Includes usability for poll workers</p>
    <p>See: http://vote.nist.gov and http://www.eac.gov</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reflecting poll workers need for clear documentation and easy procedures in the VVSG</p>
    <p>The procedures for system setup, polling, and shutdown, as documented by the manufacturer, shall be reasonably easy for the typical poll worker to learn, understand, and perform.</p>
    <p>The system shall include clear, complete, and detailed instructions and messages for setup, polling, and shutdown.</p>
    <p>EAC-accredited voting system test laboratories will certify that systems meet the requirements</p>
    <p>How do you test such requirements?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Developing a style guide for voting system documentation</p>
    <p>Literature on technical communication and information design is extensive</p>
    <p>We examined over 70 resources on technical communication, document design, information architecture, and plain language</p>
    <p>Current voting system poll worker guides  We reviewed over 750 pages in 9 documents; Included all major</p>
    <p>manufacturers</p>
    <p>Voting system documentation does not always follow best practice  We developed specific guidelines for voting system documentation</p>
    <p>Team has experience as technical communicators, usability researchers, information architects, teachers, and writers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Low points in the review of existing documentation</p>
    <p>Instructions describe the interface, not poll workers tasks</p>
    <p>Manuals dont have headers or footers</p>
    <p>Headings are cryptic or ambiguous</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More low points</p>
    <p>Warnings come after consequences</p>
    <p>Tasks are not illustrated</p>
    <p>Several steps are included in one instruction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voting system documentation guideline categories</p>
    <p>Write for specific users  Organize to meet your users needs  Use simple words your users understand  Write directly to your users  Keep instructions short and simple  Design for easy scanning and reading  Use graphics effectively  Test the documentation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Use familiar, common words</p>
    <p>Before</p>
    <p>It will take approximately two minutes for the scanner to load the election definition from the card into its operating system. The scanner will display S-Mode in the upper left corner of the LCD screen and the message Open polls now?</p>
    <p>After 1. Insert the scanner key and turn it to Open/Close Poll.</p>
    <p>Wait until this message appears (in about two minutes): Open polls now?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Understand your users tasks</p>
    <p>Before</p>
    <p>After</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test the documentation</p>
    <p>For documentation developers:</p>
    <p>Have people follow instructions  Observe without helping or hinting  Take notes on where they had problems  Revise and test again  Do a usability test with your users or participants like your users</p>
    <p>Our research  Develop a pass/fail usability test protocol for test labs to demonstrate</p>
    <p>usability for poll workers of the documentation (and, to some extent, the voting system itself)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Qualitative exploratory study of voting system documentation</p>
    <p>for poll workers Dana Chisnell</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research questions</p>
    <p>Tasks:  What are they?  How long do they take?</p>
    <p>Participants:  Pairs?  How many?</p>
    <p>Pass/fail criteria for the documentation?</p>
    <p>Dana Chisnell</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How we tested the test</p>
    <p>Dana Chisnell</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test plan</p>
    <p>Draft protocol and checklists</p>
    <p>Four pairs of poll worker participants</p>
    <p>Two voting systems - one DRE* and one optical scan</p>
    <p>Each pair worked on both systems</p>
    <p>*Direct Recording Electronic Touchscreen</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We iterated the test design</p>
    <p>At the end of each day, we adjusted</p>
    <p>wording in the test script and tasks</p>
    <p>instructions for the test administrator</p>
    <p>the organization and layout of the overall protocol</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results of the documentation study</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Matching the documentation to the machine was difficult</p>
    <p>Dana Chisnell</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participants had questions that the documentation didnt answer</p>
    <p>Dana Chisnell</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Information on troubleshooting was hard to use because it was not related to tasks</p>
    <p>Dana Chisnell</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Documentation covered too many systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Met many best practices but fails because the configuration is not the same as implementation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Met many best practices but fails because the configuration is not the same as implementation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Determining pass/fail criteria</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participants are able to use voting system documentation to:</p>
    <p>Complete tasks without asking questions</p>
    <p>Find the information they need</p>
    <p>Match messages between system and documentation</p>
    <p>Read, understand, and react</p>
    <p>Perform tasks without missing steps</p>
    <p>Perform steps to complete tasks</p>
    <p>Evidence</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Have participants asked for help?</p>
    <p>Have they completed the tasks in the time allotted?</p>
    <p>Pass / fail criteria</p>
    <p>Dana Chisnell</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What questions remain?</p>
    <p>Could someone else get the same results?</p>
    <p>How to compute overall pass/fail score?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Where to learn more</p>
    <p>http://vote.nist.gov</p>
    <p>NIST IR 7519, Style Guide for Voting System Documentation http://vote.nist.gov/NISTIR-7519.pdf</p>
    <p>UPA Usability in Civic Life Project http://www.usabilityprofessionals.org/civiclife/ voting/index.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
