<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scaling Internet Research Publication Processes to Internet Scale</p>
    <p>Jon Crowcroft University of Cambridge</p>
    <p>S. Keshav University of Waterloo</p>
    <p>Nick McKeown Stanford University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Problems with current process  Author and reviewer incentives  Two mechanisms</p>
    <p>Punch-line: While any system is imperfect and can be gamed</p>
    <p>it is time to experiment with more radical approaches.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problems  Rapid increase in number of papers</p>
    <p>More researchers in field (a good thing!)  Recirculation of minor variants  Publish-or-perish and merit schemes  Not commensurate increase in number of reviewers</p>
    <p>Skimpy reviews  Declining paper quality</p>
    <p>Just getting feedback from reviewers?</p>
    <p>Favoritism  Preference to the in-crowd, friends and famous researchers</p>
    <p>Overly negative reviews  A systems tradition</p>
    <p>The increase in number of papers seems to amplify the problem</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Game A cynical but pragmatic view of wants</p>
    <p>Authors wants:  Get published or get feedback.  Avoid reviewing.</p>
    <p>Reviewers/PC members wants:  Minimize work (scores, but no justification)  Reject competing papers  Accept papers from friends/famous people  Reject embarrassing papers  Prestige by association</p>
    <p>Conference organizers, PC Chairs, All of us  Highest slate of papers  Fresh ideas</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Incentives and Goals</p>
    <p>A1 Authors should not submit poor papers</p>
    <p>A2 Authors should become reviewers</p>
    <p>R1 Reviewers should file good reviews</p>
    <p>R2 Reviewers should not favor friends</p>
    <p>R3 Reviewers should not favor famous people</p>
    <p>R4 Reviewers should not trash competition</p>
    <p>C1 Conference should have high quality papers and fresh ideas.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mechanisms</p>
    <p>Any mechanism can be gamed, so these are necessarily vague at this point.</p>
    <p>Just trying to get discussion going.  Needs more study and discussion.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Author incentives</p>
    <p>A1: Authors should not submit poor papers</p>
    <p>Proposal: Conference publish authors acceptance rate for conference (even if zero)</p>
    <p>Conjecture: Peer pressure will help.</p>
    <p>More radical: Publish titles/authors of rejected papers.</p>
    <p>Conjecture: Will reduce recirculation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Author Incentives (2)</p>
    <p>A2: Authors should become reviewers.</p>
    <p>Proposal: Best reviewer award and public acknowledgment.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Author Incentives (3)</p>
    <p>More radical: Virtual economy. Tokens paid to reviewers; spent to submit papers.</p>
    <p>Basic idea:  One token per review, three tokens to</p>
    <p>submit (assuming 3 reviews per paper)  Accepted papers are credited 1-3 tokens</p>
    <p>no cost for good papers</p>
    <p>Conjecture: Solves A1 and A2</p>
    <p>Clearly many details needed to get implementation right.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reviewer Incentives</p>
    <p>R1: Reviewers should submit good reviews R2: Reviewers should not favor their friends R4: Reviewers should not trash competing papers</p>
    <p>Proposal: Authors rate (anonymous) reviews. Reviews circulated to PC.</p>
    <p>Conjecture: Peer pressure among PC. More radical: Use pseudonyms and publish all reviews Even more radical: Openly publish reviews with name of</p>
    <p>reviewer. Or a blend of real names and pseudonyms.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reviewer Incentives (2)</p>
    <p>R3: Reviewers should not favor famous researchers.</p>
    <p>We have no idea how to solve this! Public reviews can make this worse.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A more radical approach</p>
    <p>Too much of process is hidden  We dont exploit the web or reputation</p>
    <p>schemes  Can we make the entire process open and</p>
    <p>transparent?</p>
    <p>Basic Idea: All papers and reviews are public and signed (some could use pseudonyms).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consequences</p>
    <p>A1: Readers can draw their own conclusion and tell the world. Peer pressure.</p>
    <p>A2: Infrequent reviewers would be exposed.  R1- R4: Reviewer names would be alongside</p>
    <p>reviews.  Correlation of reviews help us decide what</p>
    <p>papers to read.  Some good papers in less well-known</p>
    <p>conferences are raised to the top by acclaim.  Continued discussion and feedback after paper</p>
    <p>has been published.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We believe</p>
    <p>Academic community is crying out for a better system.</p>
    <p>There are underlying incentives we need to acknowledge. Our list is probably incomplete.</p>
    <p>We dont exploit the web enough.  While any system is imperfect and can be</p>
    <p>gamed    it is time to experiment with more radical</p>
    <p>approaches.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
