<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance</p>
    <p>Learning from Early A0empts to</p>
    <p>Measure Informa7on Security Performance</p>
    <p>Jing Zhang1, Robin Berthier2, Will Rhee1, Michael Bailey1, Partha Pal3, Farnam Jahanian1, and William H. Sanders2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance 2</p>
    <p>Importance of Organiza3ons in the Security Ecosystem</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>Ac)onability</p>
    <p>Visibility</p>
    <p>User Organiza)on</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance 3</p>
    <p>Our Organiza3ons</p>
    <p>Security operation teams at our universities  Informa3on and Infrastructure Assurance (IIA) at University of Michigan</p>
    <p>Security teams at UIUC</p>
    <p>We oversee IT security at the universities  More than 40,000 students  More than 30,000 faculty and staff at UofM, and more than 10,000 at UIUC  Facilita3ng campus-wide incident response ac3vi3es  Provide services such as security assessment and consulta3on, network scans,</p>
    <p>educa3on and training  Managing IT security issues at the university level</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance 4</p>
    <p>Organiza3onal Background</p>
    <p>Context: Account compromise at UofM and UIUC</p>
    <p>613 incidents related to unauthorized use of university accounts during 2010 and first 6 months of 2011 at UofM</p>
    <p>Spam</p>
    <p>Phishing</p>
    <p>Others</p>
    <p>178 compromised accounts were reported in the first half of 2011 at UIUC</p>
    <p>Market place for the compromised university accounts</p>
    <p>$20 = UofM account with VPN and Library access</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance 5</p>
    <p>Organiza3onal Goals</p>
    <p>We want to answer:  How secure is the organiza3on?  Has the secure posture improved over the last years?  How to compare with peers with respect to security?  What is the marginal change in the security, given the use of a tool or</p>
    <p>prac3ce?  How to priori3ze resources to maximize security and minimize risks?</p>
    <p>Security Metrics  Micro-level of view  Quan3fied measurement  Hard to achieve</p>
    <p>Complexity of the environment  rapid evolu3on of technology and adversarial ac3on</p>
    <p>We cannot manage what we cannot measure!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance</p>
    <p>What we have</p>
    <p>Incidents Tickets  Authentication Logs  Victim Information  Password-cracking results  Security quiz results</p>
    <p>Factors Analyzed</p>
    <p>Victim Demographic  Temporal Factor  Geographical Factor  Topological Factor  Usage Behavior  Password Strength  Security Quiz</p>
    <p>Our Work Today</p>
    <p>State Ques3ons and Hypothesis</p>
    <p>Data Collec3on Sta3s3cal Inference</p>
    <p>Accept or Reject Hypothesis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance</p>
    <p>What we have</p>
    <p>Incidents Tickets  Authentication Logs  Victim Information  Password-cracking results  Security quiz results</p>
    <p>Factors Analyzed</p>
    <p>Victim Demographic  Temporal Factor  Geographical Factor  Topological Factor  Usage Behavior  Password Strength  Security Quiz</p>
    <p>Our Work Today</p>
    <p>State Ques3ons and Hypothesis</p>
    <p>Data Collec3on Sta3s3cal Inference</p>
    <p>Accept or Reject Hypothesis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance 8</p>
    <p>Example 1 - User Suscep3bility</p>
    <p>Question  What roles gender, age, educa+on-level, ci+zenship, and department</p>
    <p>play in the compromise of student accounts?</p>
    <p>Data  Student vic3ms: 242 at UofM from 2009 to 2011, 130 at UIUC in 2011  Aggregated Demographics for the total student popula3on</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance 9</p>
    <p>Example 1 - User Suscep3bility</p>
    <p>Methodology: Multivariate Linear Regression  Predict the effect of one factor, holding other factors constant.  Example: Age and Educa3on Level</p>
    <p>Simple distribu3on -&gt; 20-21, undergraduate  Undergraduate students has more people in age 20-21 than graduate students</p>
    <p>Which is the real significant factor? Or both?  Logis3c Regression Model:</p>
    <p>Null Hypothesis Ho: Bi = 0 (Variable Xi is not sta3s3cally significant in predic3ng user suscep3bility)</p>
    <p>Test Sta3s3cs: p-value &lt; 0.05</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance 10</p>
    <p>Example 1 - User Suscep3bility</p>
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Factor University Year p-value Coef.</p>
    <p>Undergraduate</p>
    <p>UofM</p>
    <p>UIUC 2011 0.958 -10.733</p>
    <p>Age (20-21)</p>
    <p>UofM</p>
    <p>UIUC 2011 0.410 -0.472</p>
    <p>Ci3zenship</p>
    <p>UofM</p>
    <p>UIUC 2011 0.007 0.5433</p>
    <p>Disagreement between the two universi3es</p>
    <p>Gender is not sta3s3cally significant!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance 11</p>
    <p>Example 2 - Temporal Factor</p>
    <p>Question  Whether the incidence of compromises varies at different 3me of the</p>
    <p>year?</p>
    <p>Data  Monthly number of 3ckets at UofM from 2009 to 2011</p>
    <p>N u m</p>
    <p>b e r</p>
    <p>o f T</p>
    <p>ic k e ts</p>
    <p>Month</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance 12</p>
    <p>Example 2 - Temporal Factor</p>
    <p>Methodology: Time series data analysis  Holt-Winters exponen3al smoothing procedure</p>
    <p>Long-term trend + Seasonality</p>
    <p>Result  No seasonality panern in the monthly number of 3ckets</p>
    <p>-20</p>
    <p>-15</p>
    <p>-10</p>
    <p>-5</p>
    <p>S e</p>
    <p>a s o</p>
    <p>n a</p>
    <p>lit y</p>
    <p>N u</p>
    <p>m b</p>
    <p>e r</p>
    <p>o f</p>
    <p>T ic</p>
    <p>k e</p>
    <p>ts</p>
    <p>Month</p>
    <p>Real data seasonality Predicted seasonality</p>
    <p>Crea3on 3me  Compromise 3me</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance 13</p>
    <p>Example 3 - Password Policy</p>
    <p>Question  Whether accounts with weak passwords are more likely to be</p>
    <p>compromised?</p>
    <p>Data  Password-cracking performed at UofM (2012)</p>
    <p># of total # of compromised Pr (compromise)</p>
    <p>Weak Password 2,284 12 0.525%</p>
    <p>Total Popula3on 550,000 380 0.069%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance 14</p>
    <p>Example 3 - Password Policy</p>
    <p>Methodology: Test of Homogeneity  Whether the response of iden3fiable sub-popula3ons differ from</p>
    <p>those of others  Null Hypothesis Ho: users who have weak passwords have the same</p>
    <p>probability to be compromised as other users  Test sta3s3cs: deviance; Confidence level: p-value &lt; 0.05</p>
    <p>Result  Test sta3s3cs of deviance of 28.09 and a p-value of 1.16-16  Reject Null Hypothesis, and conclude that the users, who use weak</p>
    <p>passwords, have a higher probability to be compromised</p>
    <p>But are the limited number of poten3ally impacted accounts worth our effort?</p>
    <p>Is weak password the reason of compromise?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jing Zhang CSET 12: Learning from Early Attempts to Measure Information Security Performance 15</p>
    <p>Discussions</p>
    <p>Are the questions meaningful?</p>
    <p>Is it the right data?</p>
    <p>Are we using right analysis techniques?</p>
    <p>How to reproduce the measurement?  Con3nuous measurement  Reproduce across mul3ple organiza3ons</p>
    <p>How to form actionable strategies based on those metrics?</p>
    <p>Ac3onable? Proac3ve or Reac3ve?</p>
    <p>Quality? Sensi3vity?</p>
    <p>Observa3on  Sta3s3cal Inference Correla3on  Causality</p>
    <p>Generalized measurement metrics and techniques Data collec3on and sharing plarorm</p>
    <p>Results  Strategy Strategy  Success</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
