<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Towards a Framework for Evaluating BGP Security</p>
    <p>Olaf Maennel, Iain Phillips, Debbie Perouli, Randy Bush, Rob Austein, Askar Jaboldinov</p>
    <p>CSET</p>
    <p>August 6, 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)</p>
    <p>Security was not a concern in the first days of the Internet.</p>
    <p>Things have changed...</p>
    <p>Detect and prevent mis-origination:</p>
    <p>a prefix is originated by an AS which does not own it.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Large Scale Testing Implementations of the RPKI exist. Some initial tests have been performed.</p>
    <p>The code is deployed by some RIRs and ISPs.</p>
    <p>Not enough evidence that deployment will scale to the Internet of 2020.</p>
    <p>Propagation times of the RPKI objects (like certificates) critical for the success of the system; could vary based on scale.</p>
    <p>How do times change with more tiers of ASes, more layers of caches per AS, more load per certification/publication point or cache, ...?</p>
    <p>TestBed experiments needed to answer the question:</p>
    <p>does the proposed framework for AS origin validation scale?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RPKI High Level View</p>
    <p>Certification Who is the legitimate owner of a prefix?</p>
    <p>Who is authorized to announce it in BGP?</p>
    <p>Publication Who publishes, and how, the Route Origin Authorizations (ROAs)?</p>
    <p>Verification How do the relying parties know which announcements to trust?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Challenges</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>StarBED: 1000 Physical Machines</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment Setup</p>
    <p>Machine resources:</p>
    <p>I StarBED VMs hosting caches and Certification Authorities (CAs)</p>
    <p>I Junosphere for routers (currently 50 virtual routers)</p>
    <p>Configuration:</p>
    <p>Extend AutoNetkit to generate automatic configurations not only for routers but also RPKI servers and caches</p>
    <p>Design the abstractions needed for RPKI.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reduce the Load to the Publication Points</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What does a Tier 1 AS look like?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is Propagation?</p>
    <p>The time from when a CA publishes an object (Cert or ROA) to when a Relying Party receives it.</p>
    <p>A Relying Party is a validated cache or a router via the rpki-rtr protocol.</p>
    <p>Measured by caches and routers logging every received object.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What do Current Topologies look like?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Early Results</p>
    <p>pubdtocaches</p>
    <p>time (min)</p>
    <p>cu m</p>
    <p>u la</p>
    <p>tiv e d</p>
    <p>e n si</p>
    <p>ty</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>BGP security is a concern. The RPKI is a solution.</p>
    <p>We have designed the abstractions needed for RPKI to be tested in large experiments.</p>
    <p>We have automated the configuration of the machines running RPKI code.</p>
    <p>We are performing large scale experiments.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
