<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A High Coverage Method for Automatic False Friends Detection for Spanish and Portuguese</p>
    <p>S. Castro, J. Bonanata y A. Ros</p>
    <p>Grupo de Procesamiento de Lenguaje Natural Universidad de la Repblica  Uruguay</p>
    <p>VarDial 2018, COLING</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Objective: classify between false friends or cognates for Spanish-Portuguese</p>
    <p>False friends: pair of words from different languages that are written or pronounced in a similar way, but have different meanings.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example False Friends</p>
    <p>obligado  obrigado no  no</p>
    <p>aceite  aceite borracha  borracha</p>
    <p>cadera  cadeira desenvolver  desenvolver</p>
    <p>propina  propina</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>False friends make harder to learn a language or to communicate, especially when its similar to the mother tongue.</p>
    <p>Between Spanish and Portuguese, the amount of cognates reaches the 85% of the total vocabulary (Ulsh, 1971).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Frunza, 2006: supervised machine learning using orthographic distances as features to classify between cognates, false friends or unrelated.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Mitkov et al., 2007: used a combination of distributional and taxonomy-based approaches. Worked with English-French, English-German and English-Spanish.</p>
    <p>They use WordNet taxonomy similarities to classify, and if a word is missing they fall back to a distributional method.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Mitkov et al., 2007</p>
    <p>For the distributional method they build vectors based on word windows, computing the co-occurrence probability. Then, they compared the N closest words of each word in the pair, translate one of them and count occurrences in the other one. They defined a threshold based on Dice coefficient.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Ljubei et al., 2013: based on (Mitkov et al., 2007), experiment with several ways to build the vector space (e.g. tf-idf) and measure vector distances (e.g. cosine distance). They also proposed to use PMI.</p>
    <p>They worked with closely related languages: Slovene and Croatian.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Seplveda and Alusio, 2011: false friends resolution for Spanish-Portuguese, highly based on (Frunza, 2006).</p>
    <p>They added an experiment with a new feature whose value is the likelihood of translation, from a probabilistic dictionary (generated taking a large sentence-aligned bilingual corpus).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Word Vector Representations</p>
    <p>Related work crafted their own word vector representations. We propose to use the skip-gram-based word2vec model (Mikolov et al, 2013a).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transform between Vector Spaces</p>
    <p>Mikolov et al, 2013b: propose a method to correspond two word2vec vector spaces via a linear transformation.</p>
    <p>Used to build dictionaries and phrase tables.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transform between Vector Spaces</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Method</p>
    <p>Build word2vec vector spaces, find a linear transformation and measure vector distances.</p>
    <p>Note that we dont cope with related/unrelated, we just focus on cognate/false friends</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Method</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Method</p>
    <p>We used the Wikipedias for the vector spaces.</p>
    <p>Open Multilingual WordNet (Bond and Paik, 2012) was used as a bilingual lexicon to fit the linear transformation: we iterate over synsets and took lexical units from each language. Then we employed Least Squares.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Method</p>
    <p>We take one of the word vectors, transform it to the other space and compute: 1. The cosine distance between T(source_vector) and</p>
    <p>target_vector. 2. The number of word vectors in the target vector space</p>
    <p>closer to target_vector than T(source_vector). 3. The sum of the distances between target_vector and</p>
    <p>T(source_vector_i) for the top 5 word vectors source_vector_i nearest to source_vector.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>We used (Seplveda and Alusio, 2011) dataset, which is composed by 710 pairs (338 cognates and 372 false friends).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Method Accuracy Coverage</p>
    <p>WN Baseline 68.18 55.38</p>
    <p>Seplveda 2 63.52 100.00</p>
    <p>Seplveda 3.2 76.37 59.44</p>
    <p>Apertium 77.75 66.01</p>
    <p>Our method 77.28 97.91</p>
    <p>+ frequencies 79.42 97.91</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments: different configurations Method configuration Accuracy</p>
    <p>es-400-100 77.28</p>
    <p>es-800-100 76.99</p>
    <p>es-100-100 76.98</p>
    <p>es-200-100 76.84</p>
    <p>es-200-200 76.55</p>
    <p>pt-200-200 76.13</p>
    <p>es-200-800 75.99</p>
    <p>pt-400-100 75.99</p>
    <p>pt-100-100 75.84</p>
    <p>es-100-200 75.83</p>
    <p>es-100-100-2 74.98</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments: bilingual lexicon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>We have provided a new approach to classify false friends with high accuracy and coverage.</p>
    <p>We studied it for Spanish-Portuguese and provided state-of-the-art results for the pair.</p>
    <p>The method doesnt require rich bilingual datasets.</p>
    <p>It could be easily applied to other language pairs.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Experiment with other word vector representations and state-of-the-art vector space linear transformation.</p>
    <p>Work on fine-grained classifications.</p>
    <p>E.g., partial false friends.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you! Questions?</p>
    <p>Code and slides available at: github.com/pln-fing-udelar/false-friends</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
