<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vermelding onderdeel organisatie</p>
    <p>USENIX/CSET 2013 1</p>
    <p>Internet Measurements and Public Policy: Mind the Gap</p>
    <p>Hadi Asghari * Michel JG van Eeten * Milton L Mueller +</p>
    <p>* Delft University of Technology, Faculty of Technology, Policy and Management + Syracuse University, School of Information Studies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In Summary</p>
    <p>Measurement projects (often) fail to have the desired (deserved) impact on cyber policy debates</p>
    <p>because of a gap between how computer scientists think of measurement data and how other researchers use it</p>
    <p>USENIX/CSET 2013 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why This Matters</p>
    <p>There is a real need for large scale empirical evidence in policy research (e.g., versus ideas based on hunches, anecdotes or untested models)</p>
    <p>Policy makers are very receptive towards empirically backed policy research</p>
    <p>So: measurement science and policy research should be a fruitful marriage; however, its often frustrating</p>
    <p>USENIX/CSET 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Understanding the Gap</p>
    <p>Measurement Experts</p>
    <p>Create a measurement tool</p>
    <p>Have it run for a while on some infrastructure</p>
    <p>USENIX/CSET 4</p>
    <p>Policy Researchers</p>
    <p>Obtain &amp; convert logs to dataset</p>
    <p>Experiment with models, add variables, extract patterns and insights for policy</p>
    <p>GAP</p>
    <p>Caused by different needs &amp; values with regards to data, e.g.: granular vs aggregated, real-time vs historical, etc</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Ideal Measurement Set (1/5)</p>
    <p>Measurement sets ought to keep archives and benefit from being up to date</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Ideal Measurement Set (2/5)</p>
    <p>Providing spatially and temporally aggregated versions of the data is helpful</p>
    <p>Due to different units of analysis</p>
    <p>Also less to download; solves some privacy issues</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Ideal Measurement Set (3/5)</p>
    <p>Measurements ought to have clear verdicts and interpretations</p>
    <p>In practice:</p>
    <p>i. documentation</p>
    <p>ii. complete audit trail (Paxson, 2004)</p>
    <p>iii. parsers</p>
    <p>iv. access to authors / community 25 August 2013 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Ideal Measurement Set (4/5)</p>
    <p>Consistency of the measurement instrument and logs over time is important.</p>
    <p>E.g., have parallel versions running; monitor test infrastructure, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Ideal Measurement Set (5/5)</p>
    <p>Data collection should be organized in a manner that promotes sample validity.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion (1)  N=1</p>
    <p>Time Period</p>
    <p>Aggregation &amp; format</p>
    <p>Logs to verdicts Consistency Sample size</p>
    <p>Glasnost 2009-now (-) Individual test logs</p>
    <p>(-) Parsing involves many steps</p>
    <p>(-) Multiple discontinuities</p>
    <p>(+/-) Mixed</p>
    <p>Spam-trap 2005-now (+/-) Logs, daily. IP based.</p>
    <p>(+) Relatively clear, excellent support</p>
    <p>(+) Yes (+)</p>
    <p>Good</p>
    <p>DShield 2006-now (+/-) Logs, daily. IP &amp; port.</p>
    <p>(+/-) False positives still unclear</p>
    <p>(+) Yes (+)</p>
    <p>Good</p>
    <p>SSLObservatory</p>
    <p>Only 2010 (+) SQL dump; Certificates</p>
    <p>(+) Good documentation and support</p>
    <p>N/A (+/-) Full, but once</p>
    <p>Conficker sinkhole</p>
    <p>(+) Relatively Clear (-) Log format change</p>
    <p>(+) Full</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion (2) - Costs</p>
    <p>Q: Great ideas! But who will pay for them?</p>
    <p>See it as cost of doing business, if impact important</p>
    <p>And not necessarily expensive, e.g. like hallway usability testing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion (3)  Alternative View</p>
    <p>Q: Maybe it makes more sense to improve the technical competencies of social scientists</p>
    <p>A: Weve tried. Definitely useful for those with some engineering background; but has limitations; e.g. using SQL is intuitive and productive, whereas text parsing is a no-no</p>
    <p>Rich context and other points still important</p>
    <p>25 August 2013 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgements</p>
    <p>We would like to thank the developers and maintainers of the measurement projects that have provided us great data for our research</p>
    <p>I would like to thank USENIX for graciously funding my trip to present this paper and have this discussion here</p>
    <p>Papers: http://homepage.tudelft.nl/r0d9v/research.html</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
