<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multi-Project Reticle Design &amp; Wafer Dicing</p>
    <p>under Uncertain Demand</p>
    <p>Andrew B Kahng, UC San Diego Ion Mandoiu, University of Connecticut Xu Xu, UC San Diego Alex Zelikovsky, Georgia State University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multi-Project Wafers  Mask set cost: &gt;$1M for 90 nm technology  Share cost of mask tooling between multiple designs!</p>
    <p>Prototyping  Low volume production</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Flow for MPW Die Sizes + Production</p>
    <p>Volumes</p>
    <p>Project Partitioning</p>
    <p>Project Cloning</p>
    <p>Reticle Floorplaning</p>
    <p>Shotmap Definition</p>
    <p>Dicing Plan Definition</p>
    <p>Reticle, Wafer Shotmap, Wafer Dicing Plans</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Flow for MPW Die Sizes + Production</p>
    <p>Volumes</p>
    <p>Project Partitioning</p>
    <p>Project Cloning</p>
    <p>Reticle Floorplaning</p>
    <p>Shotmap Definition</p>
    <p>Dicing Plan Definition</p>
    <p>Reticle, Wafer Shotmap, Wafer Dicing Plans</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Standard wafer dicing MPW dicing</p>
    <p>Why is Dicing a Problem?  Side-to-side dicing!  Correctly sliced out dies</p>
    <p>Cut lines along all four edges  No cut line partitioning the die</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Side-to-side Dicing Problem</p>
    <p>Given:  Production volume for each die  Reticle floorplan  Wafer shot-map</p>
    <p>Find:  Horizontal and vertical dicing</p>
    <p>plans for each wafer</p>
    <p>To Minimize:  #wafers required to meet</p>
    <p>production volumes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dicing Strategies  Wafer Dicing Plan (DP): all horizontal and vertical cut lines used</p>
    <p>to cut a wafer  Row/Column DP: cut lines through row/column of reticle images</p>
    <p>Single wafer dicing plan (SDP) [ISPD04] [KahngR04]  The same wafer DP used for all wafers  Different DPs used for different rows/cols in a wafer</p>
    <p>Multiple wafer dicing plans (MDP)  Restricted MDP: the same DP used for all rows/cols of a wafer  Graph coloring based heuristic in [Xu et al. 04]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Independent Dies</p>
    <p>Maximal Independent Sets: {1, 4} {2} {3}</p>
    <p>Under restricted MDP dicing, all reticle images on wafer yield the same set of dies</p>
    <p>Independent set: set of dies that that can be simultaneously diced from a reticle image  Only maximal independent sets are of interest!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ILP for Restricted MDP</p>
    <p>:Subject to</p>
    <p>:Minimize pw nn</p>
    <p>IyxN</p>
    <p>xn</p>
    <p>yn</p>
    <p>DDNyDIQ</p>
    <p>II</p>
    <p>I Ip</p>
    <p>I Iw</p>
    <p>CD I</p>
    <p>max</p>
    <p>)(),(</p>
    <p>otherwise 0 ,0 if 1</p>
    <p>set indep. dice toused wafers#</p>
    <p>II</p>
    <p>I</p>
    <p>yx</p>
    <p>Iy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CMP Floorplan</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SDP vs. MDP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Partition each wafer into 4 parts then dice each part separately using side-to-side cuts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Flow for MPW Die sizes + Production</p>
    <p>Volumes</p>
    <p>Project Partitioning</p>
    <p>Project Cloning</p>
    <p>Reticle Floorplaning</p>
    <p>Shotmap Definition</p>
    <p>Dicing Plan Definition</p>
    <p>Reticle, Wafer Shotmap, Wafer Dicing Plans</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Shotmap Definition Problem</p>
    <p>Reticle Floorplan</p>
    <p>Shotmap #1</p>
    <p>Shotmap #2</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>Simple grid-based shotmap definition algorithm yields an average reduction of 13.6% in #wafers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Flow for MPW Die sizes + Production</p>
    <p>Volumes</p>
    <p>Project Partitioning</p>
    <p>Project Cloning</p>
    <p>Reticle Floorplaning</p>
    <p>Shotmap Definition</p>
    <p>Dicing Plan Definition</p>
    <p>Reticle, Wafer Shotmap, Wafer Dicing Plans</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Given:  Die sizes &amp; production volumes  Maximum reticle size</p>
    <p>Find:  Placement of dies within the reticle</p>
    <p>To Minimize:  Production cost (reticle cost, #wafers, )</p>
    <p>Reticle Floorplaning Problem</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reticle Floorplaning Methods</p>
    <p>Key challenge: cost estimation</p>
    <p>Previous approaches  Simulated annealing [ISPD04]  Grid-packing [Andersson et al. 04, KahngR04]  Integer programming [WuL05]</p>
    <p>Our approach: Hierarchical Quadrisection (HQ)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hierarchical Quadrisection Floorplan</p>
    <p>At most one die assigned to each region at lowest level  Region widths/heights easily computed from die assignment  HQ mesh more flexible than grid</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HQ Algorithm</p>
    <p>Random initial assignment improved using simulated annealing  SA moves: region exchange, die rotation  Max reticle size enforced throughout the algorithm</p>
    <p>Hierarchical structure enables quick cost estimation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reticle Area = 2.30 (vs. 2.45)</p>
    <p>HQ Floorplan of CMP Testcase</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Flow for MPW Die sizes + Production</p>
    <p>Volumes</p>
    <p>Project Partitioning</p>
    <p>Project Cloning</p>
    <p>Reticle Floorplaning</p>
    <p>Shotmap Definition</p>
    <p>Dicing Plan Definition</p>
    <p>Reticle, Wafer Shotmap, Wafer Dicing Plans</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Project Cloning  Motivation</p>
    <p>Die-to-die inspection [Xu et al.]  Reduced wafer cost when there is large variation in production</p>
    <p>demands</p>
    <p>Post-processing approach [WuL05]  Insert clones in white space left on reticle</p>
    <p>Our approach  Before floorplaning: number of clones proportional to square root of</p>
    <p>production volume; clones arranged in clone arrays  During floorplaning: clone arrays assigned to single cell in HQ;</p>
    <p>new SA moves: add/delete clone array row/column  After floorplaning: insert additional clone array rows/columns</p>
    <p>without increasing cell size</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Flow for MPW Die sizes + Production</p>
    <p>Volumes</p>
    <p>Project Partitioning</p>
    <p>Project Cloning</p>
    <p>Reticle Floorplaning</p>
    <p>Shotmap Definition</p>
    <p>Dicing Plan Definition</p>
    <p>Reticle, Wafer Shotmap, Wafer Dicing Plans</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Schedule Aware Partition</p>
    <p>More decision knobs: fabrication schedule I will not pay you</p>
    <p>after June But, money will be saved if waiting for</p>
    <p>other orders?</p>
    <p>Project Partitioning Problem  Given: Reticle size, set of projects  Find: Partition of projects into reticles  To minimize: Sum of manufacturing cost and delay cost</p>
    <p>[BACUS05] Schedule-aware partitioning leads to an average cost reduction of 63.8% vs. schedule-blind partitioning</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demand Uncertainty</p>
    <p>Customer demands (over reticle life period) may not be fully known at design time</p>
    <p>Only rough customer demand distribution available (e.g., min/max demand)</p>
    <p>MPW become even more attractive in this context: sharing of demand misprediction risks</p>
    <p>Online wafer dicing combined with production of larger wafer lots can bring further economies of scale (see paper)</p>
    <p>Feasible when there are no IP protection issues</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Given:  Die sizes  Maximum reticle size  Distribution of customer orders</p>
    <p>Find:  Placement of dies within the reticle</p>
    <p>To Minimize:  Expected #wafers required to meet customer orders over a fixed time horizon</p>
    <p>Robust Reticle Floorplaning</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Compared Algorithms</p>
    <p>HQ with production volume set to the expected customer demand</p>
    <p>HQ+Cloning with production volume set to the expected customer demand</p>
    <p>Distribution-driven simulated annealing  Use expected production cost for evaluating SA moves  Monte-Carlo simulation used to estimate expected cost</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Robustness Results - Normal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Robustness Results  Uniform</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions &amp; Future Research</p>
    <p>Improved MPW design flow  Schedule-aware partitioning: 60% average cost reduction  Project cloning: 10% average wafer cost reduction  HQ reticle floorplan: 15% average wafer cost reduction  Wafer shot-map definition: 13% average wafer cost reduction  MDP wafer dicing: 60% average wafer cost reduction</p>
    <p>Future work  Multi-layer reticle design</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
