<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BugBox</p>
    <p>A corpus, a testbed, a framework, an aid to research</p>
    <p>Gary Nilson, Kent Wills, Jeff Stuckman, Jim Purtilo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vulnerability data facilitating empirical security research  Studying past vulnerabilities may provide insight toward detecting</p>
    <p>or preventing future ones</p>
    <p>Our current research requires well-structured vulnerability data</p>
    <p>Metrics characterizing aspects of code that are uniquely associated with vulnerabilities</p>
    <p>New types of vulnerability signatures  Examining relationship between features and vulnerability introduction</p>
    <p>Need: A collection of vulnerable applications with clearly identified vulnerabilities and metadata, running in a test environment facilitating reproducible exploits</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is BugBox?</p>
    <p>BugBox is a corpus of web application vulnerabilities and associated exploits within a testbed, allowing for repeatable experiments and automated data collection.  Application and Exploit Modules</p>
    <p>Sandbox for controlled experiments</p>
    <p>A scriptable framework for running security experiments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SANDBOX</p>
    <p>E x p e rim</p>
    <p>e n ta</p>
    <p>l In stru</p>
    <p>m e n</p>
    <p>tRun Exploit</p>
    <p>Application Modules</p>
    <p>Recorded data</p>
    <p>Exploit 1 Exploit 2</p>
    <p>BugBox</p>
    <p>Exploit 2</p>
    <p>Exploit 1</p>
    <p>Exploit 2</p>
    <p>Re-usable modules  Automated data</p>
    <p>collection  Easily developed</p>
    <p>exploits</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Corpus Structure</p>
    <p>How is BugBox a corpus?</p>
    <p>Benefits of a public corpus.</p>
    <p>What data does the corpus contain?</p>
    <p>Exploit module  PHP web application module  Instrumented Data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Essential qualities of our corpus</p>
    <p>Linguistics</p>
    <p>A large structured collection used to perform statistical analysis and software testing.</p>
    <p>Facilitates replications of experiments</p>
    <p>Representative examples of the most common exploit classes</p>
    <p>Quality controlled data</p>
    <p>Metadata</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A testbed for experiments</p>
    <p>Large-scale automated security experiments</p>
    <p>Query and run exploits by metadata</p>
    <p>A fresh application environment is created for each exploit</p>
    <p>The testing is contained in a sandbox for exploit - application interaction</p>
    <p>Exploit script</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A framework for quick module development  Selenium Browser automation framework</p>
    <p>Javascript support  Live display capability</p>
    <p>Engine  Automatic application installation and configuration  Old applications with dependencies</p>
    <p>Application Module  Reuse</p>
    <p>Exploit Module</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OSVDB_83152: Uploads a XSS payload to WordPress 3.2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BugBox applications</p>
    <p>Simulating malicious activities</p>
    <p>Test  Intrusion Detection System (IDS)</p>
    <p>Intrusion Prevention System (IPS)</p>
    <p>Gauging effectiveness of software hardening techniques</p>
    <p>Testing and training static analysis tools and vulnerability predictive models</p>
    <p>Education and Demonstration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons Learned</p>
    <p>Summer Undergraduate Research</p>
    <p>Developing exploit scripts accelerated the corpus development process</p>
    <p>Vulnerabilities became self documenting  Structured development tasks</p>
    <p>Quality control methods are helpful  Verification  Validation  Testing</p>
    <p>Live playback of exploits speeds up development</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>BugBox is a corpus of web application vulnerabilities and associated exploits within a testbed, allowing for repeatable experiments and automated data collection.</p>
    <p>71 Exploits available and development is continuing</p>
    <p>Download @ http://seam.cs.umd.edu/projects/BugBox</p>
    <p>Debian package  GitHub repository</p>
    <p>Contribution of BugBox modules are welcome!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions? Availability:</p>
    <p>http://seam.cs.umd.edu/projects/BugBox</p>
    <p>A corpus, a testbed, a framework, an aid to research.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
