<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dr. Melissa Danforth</p>
    <p>Dr. Charles Lam</p>
    <p>Four Week Summer Program in Cyber Security for High School Students</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>Hands-on, intensive program during summer  Mid-July to early August  Four days each week (Mon.  Thurs.)  Six hours each day, including breaks</p>
    <p>Focused on cyber security  Cryptography (Charles Lam)  Network/Computer Security (Melissa Danforth)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cryptography Schedule</p>
    <p>Week 1  SubsOtuOon ciphers, Euclidean algorithm, Modular arithmeOc</p>
    <p>Week 2  Fermats LiSle Theorem, Modular exponenOaOon algorithm, RSA encrypOon</p>
    <p>Weeks 3 &amp; 4  Work on hands-on project &amp; prepare poster</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cryptography Projects</p>
    <p>Students used knowledge gained in first two weeks to develop a project in cryptography</p>
    <p>Students developed three projects  Fact-or FicOon (factoring and its effects on RSA)  EllipOc Enigma (ellipOc curve cryptography)  Zero Knowledge, We Know Everything (zero knowledge protocols)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General Security Schedule</p>
    <p>Week 1  Ethics and legality (reinforced throughout), security principles, authenOcaOon, passwords, password cracking, how to use Linux/CLI</p>
    <p>Week 2  Passwords conOnued, secure authenOcaOon, network aSacks, social engineering</p>
    <p>Start projects: primarily in the aaernoon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Schedule ConOnued</p>
    <p>Week 3  Social engineering conOnued, malware, access control, protecOng informaOon, best pracOces</p>
    <p>ConOnue working on projects  Week 4  Watch videos on recent security topics  Prepare posters, print posters, pracOce for poster compeOOon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General Security Projects</p>
    <p>Students spent the aaernoon of Week 2 and most of Week 3 on projects</p>
    <p>Students developed two projects  Crack Me if You Can: Using GPU Machines to Crack Passwords  Highest placing MathemaOcs/Engineering/Computer Science poster in the poster compeOOon</p>
    <p>Defense Against Human Hacking (social engineering)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Lecture notes, presentaOons, worksheets, acOviOes, and posters are available at</p>
    <p>hSp://www.cs.csub.edu/~melissa/revs-up/</p>
    <p>Disclaimer: ParOal support for this work was provided by the NaOonal Science FoundaOons Federal Cyber Service: Scholarship for Service (SFS) program under Award No. 1241636. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendaOons expressed in this</p>
    <p>material are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the NaOonal Science FoundaOon.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
