<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Non-tree Routing for Reliability &amp; Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>Non-tree Routing for Reliability &amp; Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>A.B. Kahng  UCSDA.B. Kahng  UCSD B. Liu  IncentiaB. Liu  Incentia</p>
    <p>I.I. Mandoiu  UCSDI.I. Mandoiu  UCSD</p>
    <p>Work supported by Cadence, MARCO GSRC, and NSF</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OutlineOutline</p>
    <p>Motivation for non-tree routing</p>
    <p>Problem formulation</p>
    <p>Exact solution by integer programming</p>
    <p>Greedy heuristic</p>
    <p>Experimental results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation for Redundant InterconnectMotivation for Redundant Interconnect</p>
    <p>Manufacturing defects increasingly difficult to control in nanometer processes  Cannot expect continued decreases in defect density</p>
    <p>Defects occur at  Front end of the line (FEOL), i.e., devices  Back end of the line (BEOL), i.e. interconnect and vias</p>
    <p>In nanometer processes BEOL defects are increasingly dominant  Aluminum interconnects etched  defect modality =</p>
    <p>short faults  Copper interconnects deposited  defect modality =</p>
    <p>open faults</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Catastrophic Interconnect FaultsCatastrophic Interconnect Faults</p>
    <p>Open faults = missing material (or extra oxide where via should be formed)</p>
    <p>Short faults = Extra material (or missing oxide)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Opens vs. Shorts - Probability of FailureOpens vs. Shorts - Probability of Failure</p>
    <p>Open faults are significantly more likely to occur</p>
    <p>opens opens</p>
    <p>shorts</p>
    <p>shorts</p>
    <p>Defect size (Source: de Gyvez, SLIP01)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Opens vs. Shorts - Critical Area (CA)Opens vs. Shorts - Critical Area (CA) Shorts Opens</p>
    <p>(Source: de Gyvez, SLIP01)</p>
    <p>Open fault CA larger than short fault CA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reliability Improvement ApproachesReliability Improvement Approaches</p>
    <p>Reduction of short critical area  Conservative design rules  Decompaction  Effective in practice!</p>
    <p>Reduction of open critical area  Wider wires  Non-tree interconnect  How effective? What are the tradeoffs involved?</p>
    <p>Related work  [McCoy-Robins 1995, Xue-Kuh 1995] non-tree interconnect for</p>
    <p>delay and skew reduction  2-Edge-Connectivity Augmentation (E2AUG)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our ContributionsOur Contributions</p>
    <p>Post-processing approach to non-tree routing for reliability improvement  One net at a time  Easy to integrate in current flows  Most appropriate for large non-critical nets</p>
    <p>Compact integer program, practical up to 100 terminals</p>
    <p>Faster, near-optimal greedy heuristic</p>
    <p>Experimental study including comparison with best E2AUG heuristics and SPICE verification of delay and process variability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem FormulationProblem Formulation</p>
    <p>Manhattan Routed Tree Augmentation (MRTA) Problem</p>
    <p>Given: Tree T routed in the Manhattan plane Feasible routing region FRR Wirelength increase budget W</p>
    <p>Find: Augmenting paths A within FRR</p>
    <p>Such that: Total length of augmenting paths is less than W Total length of biconnected edges in TA is maximum</p>
    <p>Wirelength increase budget used to balance open CA decrease with short CA increase</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>Allowed Augmenting PathsAllowed Augmenting Paths</p>
    <p>(A) Paths parallel to tree edges</p>
    <p>(A)</p>
    <p>(B)</p>
    <p>(B) Paths connecting tree nodes (including corners)</p>
    <p>(C)</p>
    <p>(C) Paths connecting tree nodes or projections of tree nodes onto adjacent tree edges (D)</p>
    <p>(D) Arbitrary paths on the Hanan grid defined by tree nodes and FRR corners</p>
    <p>Given routed tree</p>
    <p>Augmenting paths</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>Hanan Grid TheoremHanan Grid Theorem</p>
    <p>Theorem: MRTA has an optimum solution on the Hanan grid defined by tree nodes and FRR corners.</p>
    <p>Sliding in at least one direction is not decreasing biconnectivity</p>
    <p>Re-embedding along Hanan grid does not decrease biconnectivity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>Hanan Grid TheoremHanan Grid Theorem</p>
    <p>Theorem: MRTA has an optimum solution on the Hanan grid defined by tree nodes and FRR corners.</p>
    <p>Sliding in at least one direction is not decreasing biconnectivity</p>
    <p>Re-embedding along Hanan grid does not decrease biconnectivity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>MRTA vs. 2-Edge-Connectivity AugmentationMRTA vs. 2-Edge-Connectivity Augmentation</p>
    <p>Given weighted graph G=(V,E) and spanning tree T, find minimum weight A  E s.t. TA is 2-edge-connected, i.e., cannot be disconnected by removal of a single edge</p>
    <p>E2AUG can be solved by performing binary search on WL increase budget of MRTA  MRTA is NP-hard</p>
    <p>Differences between MRTA and E2AUG WL increase budget Geometric context (Manhattan plane with obstacles) Partial parallel edges Steiner points (paths of type C and D)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>Integer Linear Program (type A-C paths)Integer Linear Program (type A-C paths)</p>
    <p>Total biconnected length</p>
    <p>Subject to:</p>
    <p>Wirelength budget</p>
    <p>e biconnected if p connecting Tu &amp; Tv</p>
    <p>{e|xe=1} gives augmenting paths</p>
    <p>{e|ye=1} gives biconnected tree edges Tey</p>
    <p>Ppx</p>
    <p>Teyx</p>
    <p>Wplx</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>p</p>
    <p>TTp ep</p>
    <p>Pp p</p>
    <p>vu</p>
    <p>}1,0{</p>
    <p>}1,0{</p>
    <p>)(</p>
    <p>to connects</p>
    <p>Te Pp pe plxWely )()( Maximize</p>
    <p>P = set of -- at most O(n2) -- augmenting paths</p>
    <p>WL budget is fully utilized by (implicit) parallel paths</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>Integer Linear Program (type D paths)Integer Linear Program (type D paths)</p>
    <p>Tey</p>
    <p>Hex</p>
    <p>vuXTvuyx</p>
    <p>Welx</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>Xe vue</p>
    <p>He e</p>
    <p>}1,0{</p>
    <p>}1,0{</p>
    <p>and separatingcut ,),(</p>
    <p>)(</p>
    <p>),(</p>
    <p>Te He ee elxWely )()( Maximize</p>
    <p>Subject to</p>
    <p>H = Hanan grid defined tree nodes and FRR corners</p>
    <p>Exponentially many cut constraints  Fractional relaxation can still be solved using the ellipsoid</p>
    <p>algorithm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>Input : Routed tree T, wirelength budget W, feasible routing region, set V of</p>
    <p>allowed augmenting path endpoints</p>
    <p>Output: Augmented routing T  A, with l(A)  W</p>
    <p>Greedy MRTA AlgorithmGreedy MRTA Algorithm</p>
    <p>Runtime = O(N*D + K*N2), reduced to O(K*N2) w/o obstacles</p>
    <p>where N = #allowed endpoints, K = #added paths, D = Dijkstra runtime</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>Experimental SetupExperimental Setup</p>
    <p>Compared algorithms  Greedy  Integer program solved with CPLEX 7.0  Best-drop E2AUG heuristic [Khuller-Raghavachari-Zhu 99]</p>
    <p>Uses min-weight branching to select best path to add and multiple restarts</p>
    <p>Modified to observe WL budget  Recent E2AUG genetic algorithm [Raidl-Ljubic 2002]</p>
    <p>Features compact edge-set representation + stochastic local improvement for solution space reduction</p>
    <p>Test cases  WL increase budget = 1%, 2%, 5%, 10%, 20%, no limit  Net size between 5 and 1000 terminals</p>
    <p>Random nets routed using BOI heuristic  Min-area and timing driven nets extracted from real designs</p>
    <p>No routing obstacles</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>Extra wirelength (%) and runtime (sec.) for Unlimited WL Increase Budget Extra wirelength (%) and runtime (sec.) for Unlimited WL Increase Budget</p>
    <p>#sinks CPLEX Genetic Best-Drop Greedy</p>
    <p>CPLEX finds optimum (least) wirelength increase with practical runtime for up to 100 sinks</p>
    <p>Greedy always within 3.5% of optimum; runtime practical for up to 1000 sinks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>Biconnectivity (%) and runtime (sec.) for 10% WL Increase Biconnectivity (%) and runtime (sec.) for 10% WL Increase</p>
    <p>#sin ks</p>
    <p>Greedy B Greedy C</p>
    <p>BestDrop B</p>
    <p>BestDrop C</p>
    <p>CPLEX B</p>
    <p>CPLEX C</p>
    <p>Biconnectivity grows with net size</p>
    <p>Greedy within 1-2% of optimum (max) biconnectivity computed by CPLEX</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>Biconnectivity-Wirelength Tradeoff for Type C Augmentation, 20-terminals Biconnectivity-Wirelength Tradeoff for Type C Augmentation, 20-terminals</p>
    <p>% B</p>
    <p>ic o</p>
    <p>n ne</p>
    <p>ct iv</p>
    <p>it y</p>
    <p>Greedy CPLEX Best-Drop WL Increase</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>SPICE Max-Delay (ns) ImprovementSPICE Max-Delay (ns) Improvement</p>
    <p>52-56 terminal nets, routed for min-area</p>
    <p>28.26% average and 62.15% maximum improvement in max-delay for 20% WL increase</p>
    <p>Smaller improvements for timing driven initial routings</p>
    <p>Testcase Initial Routing</p>
    <p>(WarpRoute)</p>
    <p>WL Increase</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>Process Variability RobustnessProcess Variability Robustness</p>
    <p>Width w=w0, w06.67%</p>
    <p>Delay variation computed as (maxw d(w)  minw d(w)) / d(w0)</p>
    <p>13.79% average and 28.86% maximum reduction in delay variation for 20% WL increase</p>
    <p>Testcase Initial Routing</p>
    <p>(WarpRoute)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICCAD02 -- Non-tree Routing for Reliability and Yield Improvement</p>
    <p>SummarySummary</p>
    <p>Post-processing tree augmentation approach to reliability and manufacturing yield improvement  Results show significant biconnectivity increase with</p>
    <p>small increase in wirelength, especially for large nets</p>
    <p>Future work includes Multiple net augmentation Simultaneous non-tree augmentation &amp; decompaction Consideration of defect-size distribution Reliability with timing constraints</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!Thank You!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
