<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Author Program</p>
    <p>Simulating Malicious Insiders in Real HostMonitored User Data San Diego, CA August 18, 2014 USENIX Workshop on Cyber Security Experimentation and Test (CSET14) Software Engineering Institute, Carnegie Mellon University Kurt Wallnau, PhD (presenter) Brian Lindauer, Michael Theis Skaion Corp. Robert Durst, Terrence Champion Eric Renouf, Christian Petersen</p>
    <p>This Presentation: Aim and Approach Problem: Providing red team threat data for anomaly-based insider threat detector research under a specified protocol Approach: Overlay synthetic threats 0btained from recorded simulated threat dramas onto real background Where Next: Limits of what we know and speculation on what could or may follow</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Author Program</p>
    <p>Threat Data for DARPA ADAMS (1 of 2) ADAMS: Anomaly Detection at Multiple Scales</p>
    <p>Detect early indicators of malicious insider threats  Aim: Enable response to threats before suffering damage</p>
    <p>Technology:</p>
    <p>Data mining, social analytics, machine learning  Anomaly detectors, not violation (or tripwire) detectors</p>
    <p>Unique resource:</p>
    <p>Real (de-identified) host monitored user data for ~5000 industry users  Rich collection policy (including file and communication content)  2.5B user events = 107 events per month x 25 months (29 planned)</p>
    <p>PROBLEM</p>
    <p>Threat Data for DARPA ADAMS (2 of 2) ADAMS Red Team: SEI/CERT Red team objective: Deliver threat data</p>
    <p>Select representative and valid sample of the threat domain  Sample expresses plausible and realistic social complexity  Minimize risk of confusing (real v. synthetic) for (benign v. malicious)</p>
    <p>ADAMS protocol imposes on red team ZERO VISIBILITY into</p>
    <p>detectors: data features observed, correlations, algorithms, what is/is not regarded as anomalous, or threat models used in classification</p>
    <p>outcomes from using threat data: detection results, user classification, user ranking, explanation of results,</p>
    <p>PROBLEM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Author Program</p>
    <p>Experiments, Simulations, Fiction (1 of 2)</p>
    <p>Nature, natural processes</p>
    <p>Simulation, simulated processes</p>
    <p>observation data</p>
    <p>simulation data</p>
    <p>sensor</p>
    <p>Uses:</p>
    <p>Uses:</p>
    <p>Science experiment</p>
    <p>insight</p>
    <p>others</p>
    <p>Science experiment</p>
    <p>insight</p>
    <p>others</p>
    <p>We use simulations all the time in physics, but theres no substitute for experiments. Personal communication, 2013, Prof. Michael Levine, CMU, Director PSC</p>
    <p>real</p>
    <p>synthetic</p>
    <p>APPROACH</p>
    <p>Experiments, Simulations, Fiction (2 of 2)</p>
    <p>(Normal) workplace activity</p>
    <p>Dramatic simulation: malicious insider threat</p>
    <p>observation data</p>
    <p>simulation data</p>
    <p>synthetic</p>
    <p>APPROACH</p>
    <p>real</p>
    <p>Narrative: causally linked events arising from interaction of intentional agents</p>
    <p>Fiction: abstraction, compression, simulation of social experience</p>
    <p>Drama: interpretation and performance of fiction in a medium</p>
    <p>background: deep fabula</p>
    <p>casting for effect</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Author Program</p>
    <p>Data from Drama (Logical)</p>
    <p>U real users</p>
    <p>threat window</p>
    <p>Collecting</p>
    <p>Recording</p>
    <p>(c1, s1)</p>
    <p>u3 u2 u1</p>
    <p>F !!PP (U)</p>
    <p>uc1=(u2, c1) uc2=(u3, c2)</p>
    <p>F character features</p>
    <p>C dramatic characters</p>
    <p>Layoff Logic Bomb</p>
    <p>u1</p>
    <p>ua1 ua2</p>
    <p>endogenous dramas</p>
    <p>exogenous dramas</p>
    <p>ua1 ua2</p>
    <p>S synth users</p>
    <p>B = U !! S !! A</p>
    <p>A augmented users</p>
    <p>character features</p>
    <p>cast</p>
    <p>synth activity</p>
    <p>compiled script</p>
    <p>(c2, s2)</p>
    <p>central casting</p>
    <p>APPROACH</p>
    <p>Sample Treat Dramas (1 of 2)</p>
    <p>Story Class Predicate Plot/Summary</p>
    <p>Subject</p>
    <p>Low+or+mid0level+ employee+who+hears+ rumors+that+the+project+ on+which+he/she+has+ worked+for+a+decade+is+ being+phased+out.</p>
    <p>Coworker1 Co0worker+and+friend+of+ Subject.</p>
    <p>Coworker2 Co0worker+and+friend+of+ Subject.</p>
    <p>Supervisor Superisor+of+Subject,+CCA,+ CCB</p>
    <p>Characters</p>
    <p>Passed/ Over</p>
    <p>IT/ Sabotage</p>
    <p>Subject+ installed+ malware+on+ multiple+ company+IT+ assets+before+ resigning.</p>
    <p>After+hearing+rumors+to+the+effect,+Subject+ learns+that+his/her+project+is+being+phased+ out+in+a+company+re0organization.+Since+ Subject+has+devoted+more+than+a+decade+to+ the+project+and+been+groomed+for+project+ leader,+he/she+becomes+extremely+ disgruntled,+makes+demands+and+threats+to+ his/her+leadership,+and+then+installs+ malware+on+several+machines+before+ submitting+a+resignation.</p>
    <p>APPROACH</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Author Program</p>
    <p>Results 2012-Now</p>
    <p>sabotage, theft, fraud  lone wolfs, conspirators,</p>
    <p>offstage conspirators</p>
    <p>since Aug 2012</p>
    <p>Indecent RFP 2 1 Insider Startup 6 Job Hunter 1 Layoff Logic Bomb 2 Manning Up 2 Manning Up Redux 1 Masquerading 3 Naughty by Proxy 3 Outsourcer's ApprenFce 3 Panic AGack 1 ParFng Shot 1 ParFng Shot Deadly Aim (1) Passed Over 3 Selling Login CredenFals 1 Snowed In 4 Stealing Login CredenFals 1 Strategic Tee Time (1) Survivor's Burden 3 What's the Big Deal? 1</p>
    <p>Title/Performances</p>
    <p>APPROACH</p>
    <p>Anomalous EncrypFon 5 Bollywood Breakdown 1 Bona Fides 3 Breaking the Stovepipe 3 Byte Me! 2 Byte Me! Middleman 1 CircumvenFng Sureview 2 Conspiracy Theory 1 Credit Czech 1 Czech Mate 1 Exfil with steganography 1 Exfil Before Layoff 2 Exfil with Screenshots 5 From Belarus With Love 1 GiW Card Bonanza 1 Hiding Undue Affluence 3 Indecent RFP 1 Indecent RFP II 1</p>
    <p>Title/Performances</p>
    <p>Data from Drama (Authoring)</p>
    <p>U real users</p>
    <p>threat window</p>
    <p>Collection</p>
    <p>Recording</p>
    <p>(c1, s1)</p>
    <p>u3 u2 u1</p>
    <p>F !!PP (U)</p>
    <p>uc1=(u2, c1) uc2=(u3, c2)</p>
    <p>F character features</p>
    <p>C dramatic characters</p>
    <p>Layoff Logic Bomb</p>
    <p>u1</p>
    <p>ua1 ua2</p>
    <p>endogenous dramas</p>
    <p>exogenous dramas</p>
    <p>ua1 ua2</p>
    <p>S synth users</p>
    <p>B = U !! S !! A</p>
    <p>A augmented users</p>
    <p>cast</p>
    <p>synth activity</p>
    <p>(c2, s2)</p>
    <p>central casting</p>
    <p>Narrative fiction is a good way to talk about socially-manifested threats  Insider Threat is a large construct, and</p>
    <p>threats simulate social realities within the construct  The Function of Fiction is the Abstraction</p>
    <p>and Simulation of Social Experience.* Stories are authored  Judgment sampling  Authored by counter-intelligence and insider</p>
    <p>threat subject matter experts  Recently  Contributed (not Red Team) treatments  Professional screenwriter for character</p>
    <p>development and dialog</p>
    <p>* Mar, Raymond and Oatley, Kieth. The Function of Fiction is the Abstraction and Simulation of Social Experience. Perspectives on Psychological Science, Vol., 3, No. 3, 2008, pp 173-192.</p>
    <p>APPROACH</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Author Program</p>
    <p>Data from Drama (Recording)</p>
    <p>U real users</p>
    <p>threat window</p>
    <p>Collection</p>
    <p>Recording</p>
    <p>(c1, s1)</p>
    <p>u3 u2 u1</p>
    <p>F !!PP (U)</p>
    <p>uc1=(u2, c1) uc2=(u3, c2)</p>
    <p>F character features</p>
    <p>C dramatic characters</p>
    <p>Layoff Logic Bomb</p>
    <p>u1</p>
    <p>ua1 ua2</p>
    <p>ua1 ua2</p>
    <p>S synth users</p>
    <p>B = U !! S !! A</p>
    <p>A augmented users</p>
    <p>cast</p>
    <p>synth activity</p>
    <p>(c2, s2)</p>
    <p>central casting</p>
    <p>compiled script</p>
    <p>Fictional actions are simulated in a recording environment  outside of Vegas, configured consistently with data provider sites  code generators for stories, not simulations of users per se</p>
    <p>A very good heuristic: place data generating processes as close to the user in the user-&gt;automation stack as possible  let the collector produce the data (including noise and other flaws)</p>
    <p>APPROACH</p>
    <p>Data from Drama (Casting)</p>
    <p>U real users</p>
    <p>threat window</p>
    <p>Collection</p>
    <p>Recording</p>
    <p>(c1, s1)</p>
    <p>u3 u2 u1</p>
    <p>F !!PP (U)</p>
    <p>uc1=(u2, c1) uc2=(u3, c2)</p>
    <p>F character features</p>
    <p>C dramatic characters</p>
    <p>Layoff Logic Bomb</p>
    <p>u1</p>
    <p>ua1 ua2</p>
    <p>ua1 ua2</p>
    <p>S synth users</p>
    <p>B = U !! S !! A</p>
    <p>A augmented users</p>
    <p>synth activity</p>
    <p>(c2, s2)</p>
    <p>central casting We model the data collection as a</p>
    <p>central casting service  users indexed by personal and social</p>
    <p>features found in background data  we model features for narrative</p>
    <p>coherence not threat constructs We cast users who are closest to dramatic characters in their job roles, social relationships activity patterns  eliminates a big source of anomaly</p>
    <p>APPROACH</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Author Program</p>
    <p>Data from Drama (Performing)</p>
    <p>U real users</p>
    <p>threat window</p>
    <p>Collection</p>
    <p>Recording</p>
    <p>(c1, s1)</p>
    <p>u3 u2 u1</p>
    <p>F !!PP (U)</p>
    <p>uc1=(u2, c1) uc2=(u3, c2)</p>
    <p>F character features</p>
    <p>C dramatic characters</p>
    <p>Layoff Logic Bomb</p>
    <p>u1</p>
    <p>ua1 ua2</p>
    <p>endogenous dramas</p>
    <p>exogenous dramas</p>
    <p>ua1 ua2</p>
    <p>S synth users</p>
    <p>B = U !! S !! A</p>
    <p>A augmented users</p>
    <p>cast</p>
    <p>synth activity</p>
    <p>(c2, s2)</p>
    <p>central casting</p>
    <p>Synthetic activity is inserted in temporal gaps in user activity  similar to editing film cuts  we verify no temporal anomalies</p>
    <p>Other blending  communication details (eg email</p>
    <p>salutations and signatures)  tool use preferences of cast users  source of rewrite! to re-record</p>
    <p>stories to match user preference</p>
    <p>APPROACH</p>
    <p>Limitations and Speculations APPROACH</p>
    <p>Enclave</p>
    <p>Anywhere</p>
    <p>Anywhere</p>
    <p>indexer applicance</p>
    <p>features and virtual actors</p>
    <p>stage appliance</p>
    <p>Anywhere</p>
    <p>fictional characters</p>
    <p>features cast of users</p>
    <p>simulation and casting metadata</p>
    <p>fictional threat drama</p>
    <p>ops tests</p>
    <p>A B</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>E</p>
    <p>Authoring</p>
    <p>Studio Casting</p>
    <p>DATA</p>
    <p>We have a practical (heuristic) demonstration of fiction to simulate, abstract, compress social threats  The idea works and has many promising</p>
    <p>(speculative) extensions We must learn the craft of telling threat stories and performing threat dramas  What makes a good story? How are</p>
    <p>psycho-socio indicators reflected in character actions?</p>
    <p>What makes a good production? How should dramas be presented (sequence, window, real-time)?</p>
    <p>Measurable production goals  Testing, training, research, assessment,</p>
    <p>sharing, improving, ..  Realism, plausibility, challenge level</p>
    <p>Fully abstract threats from collection policy &amp; detectors?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Author Program</p>
    <p>Contact Information Slide Format</p>
    <p>Kurt C Wallnau Principal Researcher Networked Survivable Systems Telephone: +1 412-268-3265 Email: kcw@sei.cmu.edu</p>
    <p>kcw@cert.org</p>
    <p>U.S. Mail Software Engineering Institute Customer Relations 4500 Fifth Avenue Pittsburgh, PA 15213-2612 USA</p>
    <p>Web www.sei.cmu.edu www.sei.cmu.edu/contact.cfm</p>
    <p>Customer Relations Email: info@sei.cmu.edu Telephone: +1 412-268-5800 SEI Phone: +1 412-268-5800 SEI Fax: +1 412-268-6257</p>
    <p>Copyright 2014 Carnegie Mellon University.</p>
    <p>This material is based upon work supported by the Department of Defense under Contract No. FA8721-05-C-0003 with Carnegie Mellon University for the operation of the Software Engineering Institute, a federally funded research and development center.</p>
    <p>Any opinions, findings and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the United States Department of Defense.</p>
    <p>NO WARRANTY</p>
    <p>THIS CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY AND SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INSTITUTE MATERIAL IS FURNISHED ON AN ASIS BASIS. CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY MAKES NO WARRANTIES OF ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED, AS TO ANY MATTER INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, WARRANTY OF FITNESS FOR PURPOSE OR MERCHANTABILITY, EXCLUSIVITY, OR RESULTS OBTAINED FROM USE OF THE MATERIAL. CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY DOES NOT MAKE ANY WARRANTY OF ANY KIND WITH RESPECT TO FREEDOM FROM PATENT, TRADEMARK, OR COPYRIGHT INFRINGEMENT.</p>
    <p>This material has been approved for public release and unlimited distribution except as restricted below.</p>
    <p>Internal use:* Permission to reproduce this material and to prepare derivative works from this material for internal use is granted, provided the copyright and No Warranty statements are included with all reproductions and derivative works.</p>
    <p>External use:* This material may be reproduced in its entirety, without modification, and freely distributed in written or electronic form without requesting formal permission. Permission is required for any other external and/or commercial use. Requests for permission should be directed to the Software Engineering Institute at permission@sei.cmu.edu.</p>
    <p>*These restrictions do not apply to U.S. government entities.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
