<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style</p>
    <p>Defeating Vanish with Low-Cost Sybil Attacks Against Large DHTs</p>
    <p>Scott Wolchok1 Owen S. Hofmann2 Nadia Heninger3 Edward W. Felten3 J. Alex Halderman1 Christopher J. Rossbach2 Brent Waters2 Emmett Witchel2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Road Map</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Why Self-Destructing Data?</p>
    <p>Transient messages tend to persist</p>
    <p>Stored copies enable retroactive attacks</p>
    <p>Attacker subpoenas data months or years later</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style</p>
    <p>DHTDHT</p>
    <p>Vanish</p>
    <p>Alice Bob</p>
    <p>Geambasu, Kohno, Levy, Levy  USENIX Security 09</p>
    <p>M M</p>
    <p>Mallory</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Vanish and Vuze</p>
    <p>Vanish uses the Vuze DHT (Distributed Hash Table) Over 1 million nodes, mostly BitTorrent Nodes delete values after 8 hours</p>
    <p>Vuze DHT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Vanish and Vuze</p>
    <p>Vuze DHT</p>
    <p>Shares placed at random locations in the DHT Replicated to 20 closest nodes</p>
    <p>M</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Is Vanish Secure?</p>
    <p>Vanish 0.1 prototype released at publication</p>
    <p>Included user-friendly Firefox plugin</p>
    <p>Focused wide attention on its practical security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Road Map</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style DHT Crawling Threat</p>
    <p>Threat: attacker might continuously archive all data in the DHT</p>
    <p>Later, query archive to decrypt messages</p>
    <p>Dont need specific targets when recording</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Crawling with a Sybil Attack</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Making the Attack Practical</p>
    <p>Insight: have 8 hours to observe fragments</p>
    <p>Vuze replicates to 20 nearest nodes 1. Every 30 minutes 2. On join!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Hopping Strategy</p>
    <p>Sybils hop to new IDs every 3 minutes</p>
    <p>Practical attack needs only ~2000 concurrent Sybils with hopping</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Making the Attack Practical</p>
    <p>Insight: Vuze client is a notorious resource hog</p>
    <p>Only 50 instances fit in 2 GB of RAM!</p>
    <p>Can we more efficiently support 2000 Sybils?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Optimized Sybil Client</p>
    <p>C, lightweight, event-based implementation</p>
    <p>Listen-only (no Vuze routing table!)</p>
    <p>Thousands of Sybils in one process</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Road Map</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Attack Costs?</p>
    <p>Vanish paper estimate (for 25% recovery at k=45, n=50):  87,000 Sybils  $860,000/year</p>
    <p>What does attacking Vanish really cost?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Experiments</p>
    <p>DHT coverage = % key shares recovered Key coverage = % messages decrypted Attack cost = EC2 charges (Sep. 2009)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Experimental Results Cost for &gt;99% Vanish key recovery?</p>
    <p>Attack Concurrent Sybils</p>
    <p>Key Shares Recovered</p>
    <p>Annual Attack Cost*</p>
    <p>Hopping 500 92% $23,500</p>
    <p>Hopping + Optimized</p>
    <p>Client</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style DHT Coverage vs. Attack Size</p>
    <p>Hopping plus Optimized Client</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Key Recovery vs. Attack Size</p>
    <p>Hopping plus Optimized Client</p>
    <p>Key-sharing parameters (k/n)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Annual Cost vs. Key Recovery</p>
    <p>Hopping plus Optimized Client</p>
    <p>Key-sharing parameters (k/n)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Storage</p>
    <p>$1400/yr for all observed data</p>
    <p>$80/yr for potential key shares</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Road Map</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Increase Key Recovery Threshold?</p>
    <p>Required coverage increases in n and k/n</p>
    <p>Why not raise them? (99/100?)</p>
    <p>Reliability: some shares lost due to churn Performance: pushing shares is slow!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Limit Replication?</p>
    <p>Attack exploits aggressive replication</p>
    <p>Less replication might make the attack harder, but how much?</p>
    <p>More in a few slides</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Sybil Defenses from the Literature?</p>
    <p>Client puzzles</p>
    <p>Limit ports/IP, IPs/subnet, etc.</p>
    <p>Social networking</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Detecting Attackers</p>
    <p>Find and target IPs with too many clients</p>
    <p>Use node enumerator, Peruze</p>
    <p>Can detect attack IPs hours after the attack</p>
    <p>Detected the Vanish demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Road Map</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Cost Estimation Issues</p>
    <p>Vanish paper extrapolated from 8000-node DHT</p>
    <p>Assumed Sybils must run continuously</p>
    <p>Assumed attacker uses inefficient Vuze client</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Cost Not Linear in Recovery</p>
    <p>P r e c o v e r s h a re</p>
    <p>P r</p>
    <p>e c</p>
    <p>o v</p>
    <p>e r</p>
    <p>V D</p>
    <p>O</p>
    <p>Ke y</p>
    <p>Re co</p>
    <p>ve ry</p>
    <p>F ra</p>
    <p>cti on</p>
    <p>Key-sharing parameters (k/n)</p>
    <p>Coverage Fraction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Response to Our Work</p>
    <p>Second report and prototype by Vanish team1</p>
    <p>New defenses  Use both Vuze DHT and OpenDHT  Disable replicate-on-join in Vuze  Use less aggressive threshold replication</p>
    <p>Will these defenses stop real attackers? 1 Geambasu, Falkner, Gardner, Kohno, Krishnamurthy, Levy. Experiences building security applications on DHTs. Technical report, UW-CSE-09-09-01.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Conclusion</p>
    <p>Showed attacks that defeat Vanish 0.1 in practice for $9000/year</p>
    <p>Vanish team has proposed new defenses Future work: are new defenses effective?</p>
    <p>Our take: building Vanish with DHTs seems risky.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style</p>
    <p>Defeating Vanish with Low-Cost Sybil Attacks Against Large DHTs</p>
    <p>Scott Wolchok1 Owen S. Hofmann2 Nadia Heninger3 Edward W. Felten3 J. Alex Halderman1 Christopher J. Rossbach2 Brent Waters2 Emmett Witchel2</p>
    <p>http://z.cs.utexas.edu/users/osa/unvanish/http://z.cs.utexas.edu/users/osa/unvanish/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title styleVanish Attack Model</p>
    <p>Need to recover k of n fragments p = Pr{recover key fragment} Pr{recover VDO} = Pr{recover k or more</p>
    <p>fragments} Binomial distribution Pr{recover VDO} = (1 )</p>
    <p>n i n i</p>
    <p>i k</p>
    <p>n p p</p>
    <p>k</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title styleCoverage Model</p>
    <p>m Sybils see c of N objects Balls-in-bins problem Expected fraction = 1  e-cm/N = 1  e-sm</p>
    <p>s = c/N is the (overlapping) fraction of the network observed by each Sybil</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title stylePrior Work</p>
    <p>Enumerating DHT nodes  Cruiser [Stutzbach 2006a,b]  Blizzard [Steiner 2007a]</p>
    <p>Measuring DHT traffic  Mistral [Steiner 2007b]  Montra [Memon 2009]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Click to edit Master title style Hopping plus Optimized Client Concurrent</p>
    <p>Sybils Hours # VDO</p>
    <p>Fragments Fragments</p>
    <p>Found</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
