<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FAA Cybersecurity Test Facility (CyTF) By: Enterprise Information Security Team ANG-B31 Patrick Hyle, William J Hughes Technical Center Date: 08 August, 2016</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FAA Provides Aviation Portion of Critical</p>
    <p>Infrastructure According to a 2005 DHS report:</p>
    <p>A successful cyber attack which shuts down aircraft operations, the potential losses to the economy would be in the range of $2.5 billion per day. Additional losses could occur due to decreased consumer confidence , and cascading disruptions.</p>
    <p>The primary goal of the CyTF is to provide cybersecurity research, test &amp; evaluation services which address the changing threat landscape to the FAA NextGen Air Transportation System.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FAA Cybersecurity Test Facility (CyTF)</p>
    <p>FAA Test and Evaluation Capability for Cybersecurity Interoperability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mission: Provide cybersecurity Evaluation and research services to strengthen FAA information security in a Research and Development (R&amp;D) environment.</p>
    <p>CyTF combines management support, expert engineers, well defined testing procedures, and appropriate technologies in the development and operation of a cost-effective, state-of-the-art cyber test facility</p>
    <p>Evaluates, verifies, and validates Information Security Continuous Monitoring (ISCM) capabilities for application to the NAS</p>
    <p>Provides an environment where cyber testing and training will not interfere with NAS and Mission Support continuous operations</p>
    <p>Offers a facility to assimilate multiple existing partner capabilities for testing and evaluation of vulnerabilities in the integrated aviation environment</p>
    <p>FAA Cybersecurity Test Facility (CyTF)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NAS Enterprise Test Environment</p>
    <p>IDN</p>
    <p>NPN</p>
    <p>R&amp;D Networks</p>
    <p>FAA Cybersecurity Test Facility  State-of-the-art cybersecurity facility</p>
    <p>providing virtualized and existing NAS laboratories to assess impact of new tools and capabilities on the NAS.</p>
    <p>Robust and resilient laboratory able to provide a virtual NAS environment under simulated cybersecurity attacks to train and evaluate cyber response and recovery procedures for cybersecurity events</p>
    <p>Utilizes existing developmental NAS capabilities and R&amp;D networks</p>
    <p>Labnet</p>
    <p>Others</p>
    <p>Virtual NAS</p>
    <p>systems</p>
    <p>CyTF</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CyTF Notional Layout</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CyTF Physical Layout</p>
    <p>White Cell</p>
    <p>Range</p>
    <p>FAA Cybersecurity Test Facility</p>
    <p>Range</p>
    <p>Blue Team</p>
    <p>Red Team</p>
    <p>White Team</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FAA Exercise High Level Network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulated Cyber Exercise</p>
    <p>Simulated FAA environment enabled hands-on experience vs. previous TTX iterations</p>
    <p>Inaugural exercise involved ~ 50 real time participants utilizing the CyTF VM network</p>
    <p>CyTF provided all network components  routers, switches &amp; over 125 end users ( both real and simulated)</p>
    <p>Team oriented exercise with Red, Blue, White, Orange, Green team members:  RED TEAM: represent Intruders WHITE TEAM: plans and conducts the exercise  BLUE TEAM: represents the defenders GREEN TEAM: provides Network ops support  ORANGE TEAM: provides Technical assessment of the exercise  in how it did/did not work;</p>
    <p>did it meet training needs; note possible improvements for future X ops</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GREEN TEAM</p>
    <p>Exercise Roles &amp; Responsibilities</p>
    <p>Ensures the overall virtual environment is available and functional.  Intercedes in the event of a virtual environment problem.</p>
    <p>WHITE TEAM  Before Exercise: Core Planning, Scenario development, Logistics.  During Exercise: Controls &amp; Manages pace of exercise.</p>
    <p>RED TEAM  Attacks the network environment and its machines.</p>
    <p>BLUE TEAM  Defends against the attack.  defends the network by executing blocks on firewalls, proxies,</p>
    <p>etc</p>
    <p>ORANGE TEAM  Before Exercise: Collects the training objectives / requirements.  During Exercise: Captures observations &amp; lessons learned, if training</p>
    <p>objectives were met and generates Blue team assessment reports.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Product Evaluations  CyTF enables test/evaluation of Security products &amp;</p>
    <p>procedures isolated from live Ops  CyTF has to date evaluated ~ 2 dozen various products;</p>
    <p>Range from very large (Enterprise level) to individual system components/processes</p>
    <p>Evaluation assesses operational impacts, induced latency, cyber security improvements, and overall product efficacy  at the system(s) and aggregated Enterprise levels</p>
    <p>Evaluations support DHS &amp; USCYBERCOM US Govt continuous detection and mitigation efforts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Training Services</p>
    <p>The simulated environment enables hands-on training and testing of training procedures  Assessing the efficiency/efficacy  Assessing aggregate impacts  Identifying areas for improvement</p>
    <p>Adaptive VM environment enables tailored training environment</p>
    <p>Tailorable, adaptive, responsive, contained</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons Learned  There is a growing need for Cyber Labs  CyTF addresses this need for the FAA</p>
    <p>This is the 1st step of many on a continuous path  Collaboration is the BIGGEST key to success</p>
    <p>Continued collaboration is essential to operations  Scalability, adaptive components, are essential from the</p>
    <p>outset  Leverage current &amp; Emerging Cyber initiatives</p>
    <p>Maintain Cyber acumen, utilize all available resources  Government, Business, Academia</p>
    <p>This is not STATIC and will evolve over time and per force of the changing Cyber Landscape</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In Summary.</p>
    <p>Proactively manage cybersecurity risks and threats using a mission-oriented enterprise-wide development and prototyping approach</p>
    <p>Establish cybersecurity test and evaluation capabilities that protect FAA essential systems and</p>
    <p>information</p>
    <p>Tailor continuous monitoring capabilities to efficiently and effectively detect cybersecurity</p>
    <p>events and attacks</p>
    <p>Establish a robust and resilient environment able to evaluate critical services while under a</p>
    <p>cybersecurity attack</p>
    <p>Provide robust training and simulation capabilities to respond to and recover from sophisticated</p>
    <p>cybersecurity events</p>
    <p>The CyTF addresses the</p>
    <p>need to improve current</p>
    <p>cybersecurity capabilities</p>
    <p>commensurate with growing and evolving cybersecurity</p>
    <p>risks and threats to the</p>
    <p>FAA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Collaboration is Key</p>
    <p>We need to continue to collaborate internally/externally to reduce FAA</p>
    <p>vulnerabilities and understand security risks accepted by our partner</p>
    <p>stakeholders</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contact Information</p>
    <p>FAA Cyber Test Facility : Via E-Mail:</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
