<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evalua&amp;ng Malware Mi&amp;ga&amp;on by Android Market Operators</p>
    <p>Yosuke KIKUCHI*, Hiroshi MORI*, Hiroki NAKANO*,</p>
    <p>Katsunari YOSHIOKA*, Tsutomu MATSUMOTO*, Michel VAN EETEN**</p>
    <p>*Yokohama Na&amp;onal University **DelI University of Technology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mo&amp;va&amp;on  The number of Android apps is con&amp;nuously increasing  There are many third party app markets(e.g. Amazon App Store)  At the same &amp;me, the number of Android malware are increasing[1]  In this situa&amp;on, we are interested in whether these market operators</p>
    <p>make effort for mi&amp;ga&amp;ng malware and if yes, how well they do</p>
    <p>APK APK APK APK APK APK</p>
    <p>APK APK</p>
    <p>APK APK APK APK APK APK APK App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK APK APK APK APK</p>
    <p>App Market</p>
    <p>Operator Operator</p>
    <p>I cannot afford to take malware mi&amp;ga&amp;on</p>
    <p>I remove malware to protect users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Agenda  Mo&amp;va&amp;on  Agenda  Method  Result of Evalua&amp;on  Conclusion  Limita&amp;ons</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK</p>
    <p>App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What markets we have selected?  We measured five markets  Why did we select these markets?</p>
    <p>We wanted to track survival period of apps, so we selected popular (at least once) and not too new markets</p>
    <p>Market Collected Apps Collection Period</p>
    <p>Google Play (GP_PO)</p>
    <p>Goolgle Play (GP_PD)</p>
    <p>Mumayi (MY)</p>
    <p>Liqucn (LQ)</p>
    <p>eoeMarket (EM)</p>
    <p>Freeware Lovers (FL)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Collec&amp;on - Google Play -</p>
    <p>We collected apps from Google Play in two ways</p>
    <p>examined by market operator</p>
    <p>We selected 15,000 free apps from the dataset at random  Since Play Drone was collected in 2014, we then checked whether these apps s&amp;ll exist in the</p>
    <p>Play store at the &amp;me of the study  We picked up 8,966 apps that are s&amp;ll in Google Play  Note: Collec&amp;on period of this dataset is older than our other app dataset</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Colec&amp;on - Other Markets -</p>
    <p>We could collect apps by crawling web pages of apps in other markets  Mumayi(EM): 19,794 apps  eoeMarket(EM): 10,203 apps  Liqucn(LQ): 6,884 apps  Freeware Lovers(FL): 3,652 apps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK</p>
    <p>App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK</p>
    <p>APK APK APK</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK</p>
    <p>Detec&amp;on Ra&amp;o: How many AV vendors flag the app as malicious?</p>
    <p>Label: What kinds of malware(Note: some&amp;mes adware is included)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK</p>
    <p>App Market</p>
    <p>APK APK APK</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method - Metrics for Evalua&amp;on -</p>
    <p>We calculate three security metrics for each market for evalua&amp;on:  the malware presence raBo (MPR)</p>
    <p>percentage of all collected apps that are detected as malware</p>
    <p>the malware download raBo (MDR)  percentage of all downloads of all collected apps that are detected as malware</p>
    <p>the survival period of malware  how long apps detected as malware remain in the app store</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Posi&amp;ve Detec&amp;on Ra&amp;o  We defined Posi&amp;ve Detec&amp;on Ra&amp;o (PDR)  Ra&amp;o of number of AV products that flag the app malicious (=Detec&amp;on Ra&amp;o)</p>
    <p>a : Android App av: An&amp; Virus Product S : Set of AV products with which VirusTotal used to scan the app</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Posi&amp;ve Detec&amp;on Ra&amp;o  We defined Posi&amp;ve Detec&amp;on Ra&amp;o(PDR)  Ra&amp;o of AV products say malicious for an app (=Detec&amp;on Ra&amp;o)</p>
    <p>a : Android App av: An&amp; Virus Product S : Set of av VirusTotal used to scan</p>
    <p>Detec&amp;on Ra&amp;o: How many AV vendors flag the app as malicious?</p>
    <p>Label: What kinds of malware (Note: some&amp;mes adware is included)</p>
    <p>PDR = 78[%]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Malware Presence Ra&amp;o  We define Malware Presence Ra&amp;o (MPR)</p>
    <p>This means percentage of all collected apps that are detected as malware</p>
    <p>How to judge malware or not?  We judge an app as malware if PDR of the app above m[%]</p>
    <p>a : Android App av: An&amp; Virus Product S : Set of AV products with which VirusTotal used to scan the app</p>
    <p>M: Set of Apps in a market m: Threshold</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Malware Presence Ra&amp;o</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Malware Presence Ra&amp;o - What is a reasonable value of m? -</p>
    <p>MPR depend on m (Posi&amp;ve Detec&amp;on Threshold), so this value is important. If we set m to too high value (e.g. m= 70[%]), almost all apps are counted as not malware. In this study, we decided m = 30[%] is reasonable value according to other studies[4][5]</p>
    <p>[4] F-SECURE. Threat report h2 2013. hjps://www.f-secure. com/documents/996508/1030743/Threat_Report_H2_ 2013.pdf. [5] ZHOU, Y., WANG, Z., ZHOU, W., AND JIANG, X. Hey, you, get off of my market: Detec&amp;ng malicious apps in official and alterna&amp;ve android markets. In NDSS (2012).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Google Play is Really Safe? - MPR for Google Play via Keyword Search -</p>
    <p>The MPR for GP_PO is low, but we have explored whether this risk was perhaps concentrated, and thus higher, in certain areas of the market.</p>
    <p>For this purpose, we collected another sample of apps, via keyword searches.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Google Play is Really Safe? - MPR for Google Play via Keyword Search -</p>
    <p>We used 155 popular keywords listed on the keyword ranking sites [6-8], and 11 keywords in the security report by Symantec [9]</p>
    <p>We then collected the 40 apps that are shown on the first page of search results</p>
    <p>Keywords like sms and adult lead users to apps with an MPR that is more than 50 &amp;mes higher than the rate for GP_PO.</p>
    <p>[6] The most popular app store keywords from chomp &amp; google play. hjp://searchengineland.com/the-most-popular- app-store-keywords-from-chomp-google-play-135744 [7] SIMILARWEBPRO. Google play top 20 popular keywords in apr 2015. hjp://www.similar- web.jp/blog/archives/1004 [8] App annie app store stats google play top app charts united states overall. hjps://www.appannie.com/apps/google- play/top/ [9] SYMANTEC. Malicious websites by search term. hjp://securityresponse.symantec.com/threatreport/topic.jsp? id=threat_ac&amp;vity_trends&amp;aid= malicious_websites_by_search_term.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MPR for Google Play via Keyword Search</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Google Play is Really Safe? - MPR for Google Play via Keyword Search -</p>
    <p>We used 155 popular keywords listed on the keyword ranking sites [6-8], and 11 keywords in the security report by Symantec [9]</p>
    <p>We then collected the 40 apps that are shown on the first page of search results</p>
    <p>Keywords like sms and adult lead users to apps with an MPR that is more than 50 &amp;mes higher than the rate for GP_PO.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Malware Download Ra&amp;o  We define Malware Download Ra&amp;o(MDR)  This means percentage of all downloads of the collected apps that are detected as malware</p>
    <p>m: Threshold S : Set of AV products VirusTotal used to scan M: Set of Apps in a market M: Set of Malware in M a : Android App</p>
    <p>Total download number of all apps</p>
    <p>Total download number of all malware</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Malware Download Ra&amp;o</p>
    <p>*</p>
    <p>*In FL, the number of downloads is unpublished. For reference, we calculated the index on the assump&amp;on that each app was downloaded same &amp;mes.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Malware Survival Period  We measure malware survival period</p>
    <p>The survival period of an app is the &amp;me that an app has been present in an</p>
    <p>app store.</p>
    <p>To calculate a survival period, we count the number of days between the date when we downloaded the app and the date when it was last updated</p>
    <p>We expected that if market operators make effort to mi&amp;gate malware, high posi&amp;ve detec&amp;on ra&amp;o (PDR) apps cannot live a long &amp;me</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Google Play Popular(GP_PO)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Google Play Popular(GP_PO)</p>
    <p>Detected with no Adware labels</p>
    <p>Detected with some Adware labels</p>
    <p>Detected with many Adware labels</p>
    <p>Color of Dots</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Google Play Play Drone(GP_PD)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mumayi(MY)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Liqucn(LQ)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>eoeMarket(EM)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Freeware Lovers(FL)</p>
    <p>No app submission was accepted in this period</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  At a PDR of 30%, around one in five apps are flagged as malicious in EM, MY and</p>
    <p>LQ</p>
    <p>MPR, MDR are rela&amp;vely low for GP and FL but when users of Google Play search with specific keywords, they may have a 50 &amp;mes higher probability of encountering malware that when selec&amp;ng from the popular app list</p>
    <p>EM, MY, LQ and FL do not seem to act against malware even when PDRs are very high</p>
    <p>Google Play is the only market that seems to conduct ac&amp;ve malware removal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limita&amp;ons  Our results depend on VirusTotal (An&amp; Virus products)</p>
    <p>We simply count numbers of detec&amp;on. We did not delve deeply into the labels</p>
    <p>There are some markets becoming popular in last few years that we didnt evaluate. (e.g. Baidu)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You for Your Ajen&amp;on!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
