<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Honey Sheets: What Happens to Leaked Google Spreadsheets?</p>
    <p>Mar8n Lazarov, Jeremiah Onaolapo, and Gianluca Stringhini University College London, UK 9th USENIX Workshop on Cyber Security Experimenta8on and Test Aus8n, TX August 8, 2016</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduc8on  Many useful services are cloud-based  Dropbox, OneDrive, etc.</p>
    <p>Valuable content in online accounts  Cybercriminals aWack online accounts and sell creden8als (Bursztein et al. 2014; Herley and Florencio 2010; Stone-Gross et al. 2011) 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ques8on  What happens to online accounts and documents a_er compromise?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Previous work  Malicious ac8vity in webmail accounts</p>
    <p>(Bursztein et al. 2014, Stringhini and Thonnard 2015)  Emphasize spearphishing as primary aWack vector</p>
    <p>No publicly available infrastructure to monitor compromised accounts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Aim  Study ac/ons and access pa1erns of cybercriminals on leaked online spreadsheets</p>
    <p>We developed an infrastructure to help researchers understand what happens to compromised cloud documents</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our infrastructure  Honeypot system comprising honey spreadsheets and monitoring infrastructure</p>
    <p>We developed proof-of-concept to test our ideas</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System components</p>
    <p>Honey spreadsheets containing fake informa8on, including honey links</p>
    <p>Web server to monitor clicks on honey links  No/fica/on store to receive messages about ac8vity in honey spreadsheets</p>
    <p>IMAP client to retrieve those messages 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System overview</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scenarios We tested 2 scenarios using our proof-ofconcept 1. Scenario 1 Hacker leaking financial informa8on 2. Scenario 2  Nave user sharing spreadsheet info</p>
    <p>with colleagues</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quick note  The system is flexible and can be adapted to many scenarios</p>
    <p>The scenarios to set up depend on the ques8ons that the researcher intends to find answers to</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proof-of-concept</p>
    <p>Created 5 spreadsheets with fake payroll info  Inserted goo.gl honey links in spreadsheets  3 honey links point to our website  6 honey links point to nonexistent bank pages</p>
    <p>To track loca8on, browser info, IP addresses etc. of visitors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spreadsheet example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Honey links example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Leaking the spreadsheets</p>
    <p>We leaked URLs poin8ng to the spreadsheets on pastebin.com</p>
    <p>Known mode of opera8on of cybercriminals leaking creden8als and documents</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ethical considera8ons  No real informa8on in the spreadsheets  We did not leak creden8als of the accounts hos8ng the spreadsheets</p>
    <p>We obtained IRB approval from our ins8tu8on</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary of results  Scenario 1 (Hacker): 46 days  112 accesses, 17 modifica8ons</p>
    <p>Scenario 2 (Nave user): 26 days  53 accesses, 11 modifica8ons</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary of results  Differences in accesses not sta8s8cally significant</p>
    <p>Dataset available online</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Examples of modifica8ons  Decoy bank account number deleted  C++ code snippet inserted  Insult in spreadsheet  Defacement of spreadsheet  Our infrastructure could poten8ally aWract trolls and cyberbullies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ac8vity on goo.gl links  39 unique IPs visited the 3 honey links poin8ng to our webserver</p>
    <p>44 visits to those 3 honey links  174 clicks total on all 9 honey links  Accesses from 35 countries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Loca8ons of accesses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limita8ons  Visitors likely not sophis8cated cybercriminals  AWackers could copy the honey sheets and interact with them offline</p>
    <p>Google Apps Script tracking limited for visitors that are not logged in</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future work  Make spreadsheets more believable  Scale up experiments  Devise taxonomy of aWackers targe8ng cloud documents</p>
    <p>Build comprehensive infrastructure for monitoring compromised webmail accounts and spreadsheets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Another piece of the puzzle  Jeremiah Onaolapo, Enrico Maricon8, Gianluca Stringhini.</p>
    <p>What Happens A_er You Are Pwnd: Understanding The Use Of Leaked Webmail Creden8als In The Wild.  To be presented at the ACM Internet Measurement Conference 2016</p>
    <p>(IMC 2016), Santa Monica, California.</p>
    <p>Honeypot infrastructure that monitors ac8ons and accesses to compromised webmail accounts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overarching idea  Publicly available comprehensive infrastructure</p>
    <p>To help the research community see further into the underground ecosystem of compromised accounts and documents</p>
    <p>Criminologists are already using the system 25</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks Ques8ons?</p>
    <p>j.onaolapo@cs.ucl.ac.uk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References Cormac Herley and Dinei Florencio. Nobody sells gold for the price of silver: Dishonesty, uncertainty and the underground economy. In: Economics of Informa9on Security and Privacy. 2010. BreW Stone-Gross et al. The underground economy of spam: A botmaster's perspec8ve of coordina8ng large-scale spam campaigns. In: USENIX Workshop on Large-Scale Exploits and Emergent Threats (LEET). 2011.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References Elie Bursztein et al. Handcra_ed Fraud and Extor8on: Manual Account Hijacking in the Wild. In: ACM SIGCOMM Conference on Internet Measurement. 2014. Stringhini, Gianluca, and Olivier Thonnard. That aint you: Blocking spearphishing through behavioral modelling. Interna9onal Conference on Detec9on of Intrusions and Malware, and Vulnerability Assessment. Springer Interna8onal Publishing, 2015.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
