<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Antoine Lemay (PM) Jos M. Fernandez (PM)</p>
    <p>WORLD-CLASS ENGINEERING</p>
    <p>Providing SCADA network data</p>
    <p>sets for intrusion detection</p>
    <p>research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction to SCADA networks</p>
    <p>(Mis?)use of SCADA data sets in the literature</p>
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Traffic generation infrastructure</p>
    <p>Data sets</p>
    <p>Conclusion and future work</p>
    <p>PLAN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction to SCADA networks</p>
    <p>(Mis?)use of SCADA data sets in the literature</p>
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Traffic generation infrastructure</p>
    <p>Data sets</p>
    <p>Conclusion and future work</p>
    <p>PLAN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Supervisory Control And Data Acquisition (SCADA) is a form of industrial automation</p>
    <p>Sensors collect data (DA)</p>
    <p>Actuators allow remote control (C)</p>
    <p>Centralized system</p>
    <p>Operators connect to the central data repository through Human Machine Interfaces (HMI)</p>
    <p>Dedicated workstation for the operators</p>
    <p>Operator actions in the HMI are translated into SCADA network protocol packets</p>
    <p>Changing the status of a valve in the HMI will trigger the sending of a Modbus write coil packet</p>
    <p>INTRODUCTION TO SCADA NETWORKS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TYPICAL SCADA ARCHITECTURE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction to SCADA networks</p>
    <p>(Mis?)use of SCADA data sets in the literature</p>
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Traffic generation infrastructure</p>
    <p>Data sets</p>
    <p>Conclusion and future work</p>
    <p>PLAN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hadiosmanovi et al. [4] research on anomaly detection in n-grams</p>
    <p>Use of DigitalBond dataset</p>
    <p>Emphasis on malformed packets</p>
    <p>Barbosa et al. [5, 6] research on intrusion detection using traffic from a water plant deployment</p>
    <p>Use of real data</p>
    <p>How do we establish the ground truth ?</p>
    <p>Valdes and Cheung [7] research on anomaly detection</p>
    <p>Effects of using the wrong model for data (use of T-Test on non-normal data)</p>
    <p>USE OF DATA SETS IN THE LITERATURE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction to SCADA networks</p>
    <p>(Mis?)use of SCADA data sets in the literature</p>
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Traffic generation infrastructure</p>
    <p>Data sets</p>
    <p>Conclusion and future work</p>
    <p>PLAN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Timing</p>
    <p>Scaling attack traffic to polling timing</p>
    <p>Injecting noise in the traffic</p>
    <p>Match information properties of the physical system</p>
    <p>Labeling</p>
    <p>Definition of malicious (intent-based?)</p>
    <p>Especially important for some of our attack types</p>
    <p>Use of a connection-based label (all the packets of a connection that contains malicious traffic are labeled malicious)</p>
    <p>CHALLENGES</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction to SCADA networks</p>
    <p>(Mis?)use of SCADA data sets in the literature</p>
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Traffic generation infrastructure</p>
    <p>Data sets</p>
    <p>Conclusion and future work</p>
    <p>PLAN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GENERATION OF THE TRAFFIC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GENERATION OF THE TRAFFIC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction to SCADA networks</p>
    <p>(Mis?)use of SCADA data sets in the literature</p>
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Traffic generation infrastructure</p>
    <p>Data sets</p>
    <p>Conclusion and future work</p>
    <p>PLAN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two data sets</p>
    <p>Modbus</p>
    <p>Covert channel</p>
    <p>The Modbus data set uses variations of the default network</p>
    <p>Attack traffic vs no attack traffic</p>
    <p>Number of controllers</p>
    <p>Polling interval</p>
    <p>Human interaction or no interaction</p>
    <p>Covert channel data set includes only attack traffic using a different network</p>
    <p>Based on Lemay, Fernandez and Knight [13]</p>
    <p>All data sets and associated labeling files available at :</p>
    <p>https://github.com/antoine-lemay/Modbus_dataset</p>
    <p>DATA SETS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Name Description Malicious activity?</p>
    <p>Number of</p>
    <p>entries</p>
    <p>Run8 1 hour of regular Modbus traffic including polling and manual operation - 2 MTU, 3 RTU and 10 seconds polling interval</p>
    <p>No 72 186</p>
    <p>Run11 1 hour of regular Modbus traffic including polling and manual operation - 2 MTU, 3 RTU and 10 seconds polling interval</p>
    <p>No 72 498</p>
    <p>Run1_6RTU 1 hour of regular Modbus traffic including polling and manual operation - 2 MTU, 6 RTU and 10 seconds polling interval</p>
    <p>No 134 690</p>
    <p>Run1_12RTU 1 hour of regular Modbus traffic including polling and manual operation - 2 MTU, 12 RTU and 10 seconds polling interval</p>
    <p>No 238 360</p>
    <p>Run1_3RTU_2s 1 hour of regular Modbus traffic including polling and manual operation - 2 MTU, 3 RTU and 2 seconds polling interval</p>
    <p>No 305 932</p>
    <p>Modbus_polling_only_ 6RTU</p>
    <p>No 58 325</p>
    <p>DATA SET - MODBUS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Name Description Malicious activity?</p>
    <p>Number of entries</p>
    <p>Moving_two_files_Mo dbus_6RTU</p>
    <p>Yes 3 319</p>
    <p>Send_a_fake_comman d_Modbus_ 6RTU_with_operate</p>
    <p>Yes 11 166</p>
    <p>Characterization_Modb us_6RTU_ with_operate</p>
    <p>Yes 12 296</p>
    <p>CnC_uploading_exe_m odbus_ 6RTU_with_operate</p>
    <p>Yes 1 426</p>
    <p>Yes 1 856</p>
    <p>DATA SET - MODBUS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Name Description Malicious activity?</p>
    <p>Number of entries</p>
    <p>Channel_2d_3s Modbus covert channel using the two least significant digits of three storage registers Yes 383 312</p>
    <p>Channel_3d_3s Modbus covert channel using the three least significant digits of three storage registers Yes 255 668</p>
    <p>Channel_4d_1s Modbus covert channel using the four least significant digits of one storage registers Yes 414 412</p>
    <p>Channel_4d_2s Modbus covert channel using the four least significant digits of tw0 storage registers Yes 266 387</p>
    <p>Channel_4d_5s Modbus covert channel using the four least significant digits of five storage registers Yes 107 577</p>
    <p>Channel_4d_9s Modbus covert channel using the four least significant digits of nine storage registers Yes 60 295</p>
    <p>Channel_4d_12s Modbus covert channel using the four least significant digits of twelve storage registers Yes 44 977</p>
    <p>Channel_5d_3s Modbus covert channel using the five least significant digits of three storage registers Yes 143 809</p>
    <p>DATA SET  COVERT CHANNEL</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction to SCADA networks</p>
    <p>(Mis?)use of SCADA data sets in the literature</p>
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Traffic generation infrastructure</p>
    <p>Data sets</p>
    <p>Conclusion and future work</p>
    <p>PLAN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Importance of the choice of data sets</p>
    <p>Examples of errors induced by poor use of data sets in the literature</p>
    <p>Challenges associated with creating SCADA data sets</p>
    <p>Matching polling intervals</p>
    <p>Matching natural information properties of the traffic</p>
    <p>Labelling malicious traffic</p>
    <p>Presented a data set to be used as a baseline for research</p>
    <p>Freely available https://github.com/antoinelemay/Modbus_dataset</p>
    <p>CONCLUSION</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Improving limitations</p>
    <p>Diversity of information properties</p>
    <p>Diversity of controller configuration</p>
    <p>Diversity of protocols</p>
    <p>Path forward</p>
    <p>Calibrating existing infrastructure with real network data</p>
    <p>Adding more attacks</p>
    <p>Obstacles</p>
    <p>Non-disclosure</p>
    <p>Generation of human traffic</p>
    <p>FUTURE WORK</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>[4] D. Hadiosmanovi, L. Simionato, D. Bolzoni, E. Zambon and S. Etalle, &quot;NGram Against the Machine: On the Feasibility of the N-Gram Network Analysis for Binary Protocols,&quot; 15th International Symposium on Research in Attacks, Intrusion and Defenses (RAID) . pp. 354373, Amsterdam, 2012.</p>
    <p>[5] R. R. R. Barbosa, A. Pras and R. Sadre, &quot;Flow whitelisting in SCADA networks,&quot; in 7th Annual IFIP Working Group 11.10 International Conference on Critical Infrastructure Protection, Washington, 2013.</p>
    <p>[6] R. R. R. Barbosa, R. Sadre and A. Pras, &quot;A First Look into SCADA Network Traffic,&quot; in Network Operations and Management Symposium (NOMS)Maui, 2012.</p>
    <p>[7] A. Valdes and S. Cheung, &quot;Communication Pattern Anomaly Detection in Process Control Systems,&quot; in IEEE Conference on Technologies for Homeland Security, Waltham, MA, 2009.</p>
    <p>[13] A. Lemay, J. M. Fernandez and S. Knight, &quot;A Modbus command and control channel,&quot; in IEEE Systems Conference (SYSCON), Orlando, 2016.</p>
    <p>WORKS CITED IN THIS PRESENTATION</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>QUESTIONS</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
