<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2016 Noblis, Inc.</p>
    <p>Chappie Swarm: PersonaDriven Web Corpus Generation</p>
    <p>Nicholas Kaufman</p>
    <p>August 8, 2016</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>I. Introduction of the Tool</p>
    <p>II. A Look Under the Hood</p>
    <p>III. Use Cases</p>
    <p>IV. Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2016 Noblis, Inc.</p>
    <p>Chappie Introduction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Chappie Swarm: Scope of Application</p>
    <p>Why build it?</p>
    <p>What is it?  Tool for generating accurate and current web corpora.  Formulated to be systematic, reproducible, and offer the ability to quickly</p>
    <p>disseminate created datasets.  Intended to replicate enterprise or business type browsing.  Simulates users not the internet.</p>
    <p>What is it not?  Intrusion Detection or Prevention System.  Repository of web surfing data.  Traffic Simulator.</p>
    <p>Designed only to interface with the web.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Chappie Swarm: Who Cares?</p>
    <p>Why should you use the application?  Rapidly generate web traffic data for use in Machine Learning systems.</p>
    <p>Why focus on human emulation?  Increased validity of data in Machine Learning systems.</p>
    <p>Why not just pay graduate students or interns to do this?  Combat observer effect  people will behave differently when they know theyre</p>
    <p>being watched.</p>
    <p>What about existing web corpora?  Addresses question of currency  designed to be a better reflection of the web as</p>
    <p>it exists today.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2016 Noblis, Inc.</p>
    <p>A Look Under the Hood</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Building Blocks</p>
    <p>Core technology behind Chappie Swarm is Docker, Pipework, Wireshark, and PhantomJS, Docker-NAT-Router.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Chappie in Particular</p>
    <p>Chappies browse the web in accordance with a Markov Model.  The state that a Chappie is in corresponds to its current interest.</p>
    <p>Each Chappie is seeded at run time with a major interest.  These might be things such as sports or movies.  While browsing, a Chappie may decide to change its interest with a certain</p>
    <p>probability, or to continue browsing according to its current interest.</p>
    <p>Chappies interact with websites in multiple ways:  Search for terms associated with an interest.  Select a website from a favorites list.  Click links on a webpage.  Utilize the browsers back button.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Chappie: A Visual Description</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Chappie: A Visual Description</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>State Transitions Explained</p>
    <p>Chappie always remembers its major topic.  Major topic is the topic selected during initial seeding.</p>
    <p>Before deciding on a new webpage, the Chappie asks itself: Am I still interested in this topic?  Random number chosen via uniform probability distribution. State change</p>
    <p>depends upon the value selected.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Browsing Features</p>
    <p>Treading the line between automated browsing and human experience, we attempt to control for a few features that will look more human.  Time between successive page calls.</p>
    <p>Default behavior is a randomly chosen number in a given time window. o Utilizes uniform distribution.</p>
    <p>Reported User-Agent String.  Selected from a pool of up-to-date and out-of-date web browsers.</p>
    <p>Status codes of visited pages.  Number of distinct webpages requested.  Types of web pages visited.</p>
    <p>Is there a cohesive story that can be put together given the web logs?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2016 Noblis, Inc.</p>
    <p>Use Cases</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Population Estimation</p>
    <p>From an outside perspective, enterprise-level web traffic will be obfuscated.  Firewalls, Proxies, NATting, etc.</p>
    <p>Hard to tell how many users exist behind a particular obfuscation layer  much less several of them.</p>
    <p>Dual vantage of capture allows a user to create both &quot;labelled&quot; and &quot;unlabeled&quot; data sets for a machine learning approach.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Geographical Profiling</p>
    <p>Geolocation affects the ecological validity of web surfing samples.  Geofencing  CDNs  Transit points</p>
    <p>The same website might behave differently for people who are in geographically disparate areas.</p>
    <p>Chappie swarm might be used in conjunction with a service, such as AWS, to study differences in traffic patterns to better understand regional discrepancies.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Threat Detection</p>
    <p>There are classes of attacks which use web pages as means of infecting individual computers, or corporate networks.  Watering Hole  Drive-By</p>
    <p>Chappie Swarm Application can be used to generate data which can be considered both normal/benign and malicious.</p>
    <p>This would allow researcher to be able to cheaply label network traces or proxy logs for use with a Multiple Instance Learning Algorithm.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2016 Noblis, Inc.</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Chappie Swarm: Future Development</p>
    <p>The basic model of how a Chappie behaves is simple. Better emulation of human behavior is a priority.</p>
    <p>Better automation of topic material.  More dynamic favorites list, home page, etc.  Consideration of ideas such as language barriers and belief systems in</p>
    <p>influencing websites that a Chappie might visit.</p>
    <p>Expand Application to utilize more of the Network Stack.  Chappies which send emails would be useful for experiments in detecting threats</p>
    <p>such as (spear) phishing in addition to web based exploits.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2016 Noblis, Inc.</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
