<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Improved Tag Set Design and Multiplexing Algorithms</p>
    <p>for Universal Arrays</p>
    <p>Ion Mandoiu</p>
    <p>Claudia Prajescu</p>
    <p>Dragos Trinca Computer Science &amp; Engineering Department</p>
    <p>University of Connecticut</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>Universal DNA Tag Arrays  Tag Set Design Problem  Tag Assignment Problem  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Watson-Crick Complementarity</p>
    <p>Four nucleotide types: A,C,T,G</p>
    <p>As paired with Ts (2 hydrogen bonds)</p>
    <p>Cs paired with Gs (3 hydrogen bonds)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Microarray Applications</p>
    <p>Gene expression (transcription analysis)</p>
    <p>Genomic-based microorganism identification</p>
    <p>Single Nucleotide Polymorphism (SNP) genotyping</p>
    <p>Molecular diagnosis/susceptibility to disease</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Microarray Technologies  Arrays of cDNAs</p>
    <p>Obtained by reverse transcription from Expressed Sequence Tags (ESTs)</p>
    <p>Oligonucleotide arrays  Short (20-60bp) synthetic DNA strands</p>
    <p>Limitations  cDNA arrays are inexpensive, but limited to</p>
    <p>measuring gene expression  Oligonucleotide arrays are flexible, but</p>
    <p>expensive unless produced in large quantities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Universal DNA Tag Arrays</p>
    <p>[Brenner 97, Morris et al. 98] Programmable oligonucleotide arrays  Array consisting of application independent</p>
    <p>oligonucleotides called tags</p>
    <p>Two-part reporter probes: aplication specific primers ligated to antitags</p>
    <p>Detection carried by a sequence of reactions separately involving the primer and the antitag part of reporter probes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Universal Tag Array Experiment</p>
    <p>+</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Universal Tag Array Advantages</p>
    <p>Cost effective  Same array used in many analyses  economies of scale</p>
    <p>Easy to customize  Only need to synthesize new set of reporter probes</p>
    <p>Reliable  Solution phase hybridization better understood than</p>
    <p>hybridization on solid support</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>Universal DNA Tag Arrays  Tag Set Design Problem  Tag Assignment Problem  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tag Set Requirements  Hybridization constraints</p>
    <p>(H1) Antitags hybridize strongly to complementary tags</p>
    <p>(H2) No antitag hybridezes to a non-complementary tag</p>
    <p>(H3) Antitags do not cross-hybridize to each other</p>
    <p>t1t1 t2t2 t1 t2t1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Complementary Oligo Hybridization</p>
    <p>Melting temperature Tm: temperature at which 50% of duplexes are in hybridized state</p>
    <p>2-4 rule</p>
    <p>Tm = 2 #(As and Ts) + 4 #(Cs and Gs)</p>
    <p>More accurate models exist, e.g., the nearneighbor model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Non-Complementary Oligo Hybridization Models</p>
    <p>Hamming distance  Assumes DNA is rigid strand</p>
    <p>Longest Common Subsequence/Edit Distance  Assumes DNA is infinitely elastic</p>
    <p>Near-neighbor with mismatches  Resulting thermodynamic alignment problem is</p>
    <p>NP-Hard</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C-token Hybridization Model</p>
    <p>Proposed by [Ben-Dor et al. 00]</p>
    <p>Based on nucleation complex theory  Duplex formation between non-complementary</p>
    <p>oligos starts with the formation of a nucleation complex between perfectly complementary substrings</p>
    <p>The nucleation complex must be sufficiently stable, i.e., must have weight  c, where weight(A)=weight(T)=1, weight(C)=weight(G)=2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>c-h Code Problem</p>
    <p>c-token: left-minimal DNA string of weight  c, i.e.,  w(x)  c</p>
    <p>w(x) &lt; c for every proper suffix x of x</p>
    <p>A set of tags is called c-h code if (C1) Every tag has weight  h</p>
    <p>(C2) Every c-token is used at most once</p>
    <p>c-h code problem: given c and h, find largest c-h code  [Ben-Dor et al.00] algorithm based on DeBruijn sequences</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extended c-h Codes</p>
    <p>Antitag-to-antitag hybridization  Formalization in c-token hybridization model:</p>
    <p>(C3) No two tags contain complementary substrings of weight  c</p>
    <p>Tag length constraints  Industry designs (e.g. Affymetrix GenFlex Arrays) require that</p>
    <p>tags have fixed length (20 nucleotides)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>c-Token Counting</p>
    <p>W=weight 1 nucleotide, S=weight 2 nucleotide</p>
    <p>Gn = #strings of weight n:G1 = 2; G2 = 6; Gn = 2Gn-2 + 2Gn-1</p>
    <p>[Ben-Dor et al.00] c-tokens in a tag have tail weight h-c+1</p>
    <p>At most (2Gc-1 +6Gc-2+8Gc-3)/(h-c+1) tags in a valid c-h code</p>
    <p>Token type Max #tokens Max Tail Weight</p>
    <p>&lt;c-2&gt;S 2 Gc-2 4 Gc-2</p>
    <p>S&lt;c-3&gt;S 4 Gc-3 8 Gc-3</p>
    <p>&lt;c-1&gt;W 2 Gc-1 2 Gc-1</p>
    <p>S&lt;c-2&gt;W 2 Gc-2 2 Gc-2</p>
    <p>Total 2Gc-1 +4Gc-2+4Gc-3 2Gc-1 +6Gc-2+8Gc-3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Upperbounds for Extended c-h Codes</p>
    <p>Theorem: The number of tags in a feasible extended c-h-l code is at most</p>
    <p>for odd c, and at most</p>
    <p>for even c</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithms</p>
    <p>Alphabetic tree search algorithm</p>
    <p>- Enumerate candidate tags in lexicographic order, save tags whose c-tokens are not used by previously selected tags</p>
    <p>- Easily modified to handle various combinations of constraints</p>
    <p>[MT 05] Optimum c-h codes can be computed in practical time for small values of c by using integer programming</p>
    <p>Maximum integer flow problem w/ set capacity constraints</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Periodic Tags</p>
    <p>c-token uniqueness constraint in c-h code formulation is too strong  c-tokens should not appear in different tags, but is OK</p>
    <p>to repeat a c-token in the same tag  Periodic tags make best use of available c-tokens</p>
    <p>[MT05] Tag set design can be cast as a maximum vertex-disjoint cycle packing problem</p>
    <p>Allowing periodic tags yields ~40% more tags</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>c-token factor graph, c=4 (incomplete)</p>
    <p>CC</p>
    <p>AAG AAC</p>
    <p>AAAA</p>
    <p>AAAT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>Background on DNA Microarrays  Universal DNA Tag Arrays  Tag Set Design Problem  Tag Assignment Problem  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More Possible Mis-Hybridizations</p>
    <p>What can be done:</p>
    <p>Leave some tags unassigned</p>
    <p>Distribute primers over multiple arrays</p>
    <p>Here we focus on avoiding case (a), primer-to-tag hybridization</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Constraints on tag assignment</p>
    <p>If primer p hybridizes with tag t, then either p or t must be left un-assigned, unless p is assigned to t</p>
    <p>p</p>
    <p>t</p>
    <p>t</p>
    <p>p</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Characterization of Assignable Sets</p>
    <p>[Ben-Dor 04] Set P is assignable to T iff X+Y  |P|, where, in the hybridization graph induced by P+T  X = number of primers incident to a degree 1 tag</p>
    <p>Y = number of degree 0 tags</p>
    <p>Y=2</p>
    <p>X=1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MAPS Problem</p>
    <p>Maximum Assignable Primer Set (MAPS) Problem: given primer set P and tag set T, find maximum size assignable subset of P</p>
    <p>[Ben-Dor 04] Greedy deletion heuristic: repeatedly delete primer of maximum weight from P until it becomes assignable, where  Potential of tag t is 2-|P(t)|</p>
    <p>Potential of primer p is sum of potentials of conflicting tags</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Universal Array Multiplexing Problem</p>
    <p>Multiplexing Problem: given primer set P and tag set T, find partition of P into minimum number of assignable sets</p>
    <p>[Ben-Dor 04] Repeatedly find approximate MAPS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Integration with Probe Selection</p>
    <p>In practice, several primer candidates with equivalent functionality  In SNP genotyping, can pick primer from either forward and</p>
    <p>reverse strand</p>
    <p>In gene expression/identification applications, many primers have desired length, Tm, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pooled Array Multiplexing Problem</p>
    <p>Given set of primer pools P and tag set T, find a primer from each pool and a partition of selected primers into minimum number of assignable sets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>X+Y Characterization no Longer Holds</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pooled Multiplexing Algorithms 1. Primer-Del = greedy deletion for pools similar to</p>
    <p>[Ben-Dor et al 04]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pooled Multiplexing Algorithms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: GenFlex Tags, c=8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Herpes B Gene Expression Assay</p>
    <p>Tm # pools Pool size</p>
    <p># arrays % Util. # arrays % Util. # arrays % Util.</p>
    <p>Tm # pools Pool size</p>
    <p># arrays % Util. # arrays % Util. # arrays % Util.</p>
    <p>GenFlex Tags</p>
    <p>Periodic Tags</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>Background on DNA Microarrays  Universal DNA Tag Arrays  Tag Set Design Problem  Tag Assignment Problem  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>New techniques for tag set design and tag assignment lead to significantly improved multiplexing rates and more reliable assays</p>
    <p>Other applications of universal tags:  Lab-on-chip, DNA-mediated assembly (e.g., carbon nano</p>
    <p>tubes), DNA computing [Brenneman&amp;Condon 02]</p>
    <p>Other applications of partition/assignment techniques:  Genotyping by mass-spectroscopy [Aumann et al 05]</p>
    <p>Genotyping using l-mer arrays</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgments</p>
    <p>UCONN Research Foundation</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
