<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pains, Gains and PLCs</p>
    <p>Ten Lessons from Building an Industrial Control Systems Testbed for Security Research</p>
    <p>Ben Green</p>
    <p>Anhtuan Le</p>
    <p>Rob Antrobus</p>
    <p>Utz Roedig</p>
    <p>David Hutchison</p>
    <p>Awais Rashid</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Testbeds</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Diversity</p>
    <p>Complexity Scalability</p>
    <p>?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Diversity</p>
    <p>Complexity Scalability</p>
    <p>?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lesson 1: Device and technology selec@ons should be market-driven</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lesson 2: Homogeneity and heterogeneity in field sites</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Siemens-only PLCs</p>
    <p>Siemens and Allen-Bradley PLCs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lesson 3: Process diversity is not always crucial</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Diversity</p>
    <p>Complexity Scalability</p>
    <p>?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lesson 4: Hardware-in-the-Loop (HIL) is not essen@al in the Manufacturing Zone</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lack of exact mathema&gt;cal models for represen@ng the behaviours of sensors and actuators factors impac@ng simula@on accuracy such as noise</p>
    <p>Process diversity not a primary concern hot-swap capability allows for a level of scalability with sensors and actuators, moving them between devices as and when required</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lesson 5: Simula@ons in the Manufacturing Zone are not favoured</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SoBware does not provide simula&gt;ons of many essen&gt;al types of devices from different vendors OR same vendor but dis@nc@ve versions</p>
    <p>Accuracy and reliability issues in mimicking reallife opera&gt;ons Despite cost, physical equipment helps experimental rigour</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lesson 6: Virtualisa@on and VLANs provide ease of integra@on and scaling</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Provide an easy and cost-effec&gt;ve way To integrate new systems OR Scale up exis@ng instances</p>
    <p>Reduces technical knowledge required during experimental set up</p>
    <p>Clean backups of known good systems should damage be caused during experimenta&gt;on</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Diversity</p>
    <p>Complexity Scalability</p>
    <p>?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lesson 7: Employ a Management Network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reduces the need for pre-requisite knowledge Relies on all relevant research tools being in place Currently being addressed</p>
    <p>Requires appropriate data capture points Capture traffic from all zones into a centralised loca@on Currently being addressed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lesson 8: Setup Mul@ple Manufacturing Zones</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lesson 9: Comprehensively document as you build</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Document Communica@on and control processes Known vulnerabili@es in devices and soUware Sample aVack scenarios</p>
    <p>Keeping documenta&gt;on up-to-date is significant effort!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lesson 10: Op@mise data logging for security purposes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contribu&gt;ng to open ICS datasets Collec@on and distribu@on of data is limited Involves a manual and @me consuming process One for the future!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimenta@on using the testbed</p>
    <p>q William Jardine, Sylvain Frey, Ben Green, and Awais Rashid. SENAMI: Selec@ve Non- Invasive Ac@ve Monitoring for ICS Intrusion Detec@on. In: Proceedings of the Second ACM Workshop on Cyber-Physical SystemsSecurity, Vienna, Austria. ACM, 2016, pp. 2334.</p>
    <p>q Rob Antrobus, Sylvain Frey, Benjamin Green, and Awais Rashid. Sima@cScan: towards a specialised vulnerability scanner for industrial control systems. In: Proceedings 4th InternaJonal Symposium for ICS and SCADA Cyber Security Research. BCS, June 2016, pp. 1118.</p>
    <p>q Benjamin Green, Marina Krotofil, and David Hutchison. Achieving ICS resilience and security through granular data flow management. In Proc. 2nd ACM Workshop on Cyber-Physical Systems Security &amp; Privacy, Vienna, Austria pages 93101. ACM, 2016.</p>
    <p>q Jeremy Simon Busby, Benjamin Green, and David Hutchison. Analysis of Affordance, Time, and Adapta@on in the Assessment of Industrial Control System Cybersecurity Risk. Risk Analysis, 2017.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
