<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measuring the Effectiveness of Embedded</p>
    <p>Phishing Exercises</p>
    <p>Hossein Siadati Sean Palka</p>
    <p>Damon McCoy Avi Siegel</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Embedded Phishing Exercises Overview</p>
    <p>Content Creation  A limited set of phishing emails are manually or automatically generated by</p>
    <p>subject matter experts for each embedded phishing exercise.</p>
    <p>Grouping</p>
    <p>Users are partitioned into cohorts or exercise groups, and exercise content</p>
    <p>is determined for each cohort.</p>
    <p>Execution</p>
    <p>Users are sent e-mails.</p>
    <p>Clicking links results in some action, typically static or interactive training</p>
    <p>Multiple rounds of testing are typical</p>
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>Effectiveness measures are evaluated to determine improvement metrics</p>
    <p>This is the perhaps most important phase, with the least established</p>
    <p>approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Develop methodologies for correcting possible sources of bias in exercise analysis,</p>
    <p>which would enables more sound evaluation of the effectiveness of embedded phishing</p>
    <p>exercises.</p>
    <p>THE PROBLEM</p>
    <p>THE GOAL</p>
    <p>Untrained users are a</p>
    <p>significant exploitable</p>
    <p>weakness of many modern IT</p>
    <p>systems.</p>
    <p>Determining whether the anti</p>
    <p>phishing measures are effective</p>
    <p>presents significant difficulties.</p>
    <p>Anti-phishing measures such as</p>
    <p>user awareness training try to</p>
    <p>prevent phishing attacks from</p>
    <p>succeeding.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Campaign Design</p>
    <p>This study is based on data acquired from a large-scale phishing training campaign conducted in a medium-size company.</p>
    <p>19,180 participants</p>
    <p>32 unique exercise groups/cohorts</p>
    <p>28 unique test e-mails varying in persuasiveness</p>
    <p>6 rounds of testing over 8 months</p>
    <p>115,080 test phishing emails distributed</p>
    <p>Exercise design highlighted difficulties and lack of best practices for structuring large-scale phishing exercises.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Campaign Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Campaign Results</p>
    <p>Emails sorted based on the</p>
    <p>maximum click-through</p>
    <p>rates.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Questions</p>
    <p>Did the organization become more resilient to</p>
    <p>phishing attacks?</p>
    <p>Did the individuals involved become more resilient</p>
    <p>to phishing attacks?</p>
    <p>How much improvement was measured?</p>
    <p>What were the major influences on click-through</p>
    <p>rate increases or decreases?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Persuasiveness and Normalization</p>
    <p>Looking at the data, there appeared to be some interesting features.</p>
    <p>E-mail persuasiveness appears to be a key factor in measuring effectiveness.  Example: Group 20 started out with 35.9% of participants being phished in</p>
    <p>exercise A. The rate then dropped to 1.9% and 2.4%, respectively, in exercise B and C, before increasing to 19.4% in exercise D.</p>
    <p>Same individuals, but dramatically different click-through rates per e-mail</p>
    <p>This observation suggests that the click-through rate should be normalized based on the persuasiveness of the content of phishing email text to produce a sounder analysis.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We used linear regression analysis over click-through rates to compute email persuasiveness scores.</p>
    <p>The calculations of these scores took into account bias for the exercise round of the e-mail.</p>
    <p>Multiple normalization approaches were then evaluated</p>
    <p>We determined that a Pratio normalization scheme was most appropriate for normalization.</p>
    <p>Persuasiveness and Normalization</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Normalized Results</p>
    <p>According to the P-ratio normalized values, the click-through rates decreased from 80% to 40% as a result of phishing exercises.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recidivism Analysis</p>
    <p>The mere fact that the overall performance of the participants has improved as a result of phishing exercises does not fully validate the effectiveness of the training on individuals.</p>
    <p>If the training is effective, it should be much less likely that trained participants will fall for a phishing e-mail.</p>
    <p>Comparing the percentage of recidivism for users who were not trained vs. users who were trained shows that 25.94% of not trained participants fall for phishing compared to only 15.57% of trained participants. (p-value &lt; 0.01)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Persuasiveness and Training</p>
    <p>Previous works did not look at whether training is</p>
    <p>equally useful for phishing emails of different levels of</p>
    <p>persuasiveness.</p>
    <p>We analyzed 3 classes of e-mails from our study:</p>
    <p>(P1) includes emails with persuasiveness score below 5%</p>
    <p>(P2) includes emails with score between 5% and 20%</p>
    <p>(P3) includes emails with score above 20%</p>
    <p>We computed the probability of participants falling for</p>
    <p>such email after being trained in the previous round and</p>
    <p>also computed the probability for participants who were</p>
    <p>not trained or notified after the previous round.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Persuasiveness and Training</p>
    <p>The results show that training makes a more significant difference for email types that are initially more persuasive (i.e., P3).</p>
    <p>The improvement on click-through rate of lesspersuasive phishing emails is not significant (i.e., P1).</p>
    <p>Highly susceptible users fall for even unpersuasive phishing emails, which suggests it might be more difficult to educate this type of user at all.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Embedded phishing exercises can be useful, but require solid exercise design protocols rather than ad hoc testing.</p>
    <p>Post-analysis is critical for evaluation and requires normalization.</p>
    <p>The improvement from training seems to be limited to more persuasive phishing emails and that there is no improvement for unpersuasive phishing emails.</p>
    <p>Unfortunately, some users will fall for obvious phishing e-mails, and it is unlikely that they will benefit from such exercises or training.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
