<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Percentages, Probabilities and Professions of Performance</p>
    <p>Jim Alves-Foss</p>
    <p>University of Idaho</p>
    <p>jimaf@uidaho.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How we Report Experimental Cybersecurity Results  Several papers in cybersecurity compare the results of some tool or</p>
    <p>algorithm to:  Other tools/algorithms</p>
    <p>Across different datasets</p>
    <p>These papers are written to show successful results, but often with limited information and poor statistics.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Show some percentages</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What does mean mean?</p>
    <p>You use the same dataset for all tools.</p>
    <p>Your numbers are bigger than their numbers.</p>
    <p>Are you always better?  If not, where and why?</p>
    <p>Are their a few instances where you are a lot better and these skew the means?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is the nature of your results?</p>
    <p>A mean (an average) is just a single value.</p>
    <p>You can do better than that.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Histogram of F1 values for combined datasets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scatterplot of F1 values for combined datasets (sorted by test name) Interesting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scatterplot for Unix utilities dataset, (grouped by optimization levels and sorted by name)</p>
    <p>O0 O1 O2 O3</p>
    <p>Still Interesting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scatterplot for Unix utilities dataset, (grouped by optimization levels and sorted by filesize)</p>
    <p>O0 O1 O2 O3</p>
    <p>More Interesting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Statistical Recommendations</p>
    <p>Distribution Assumptions  Make sure you use an appropriate statistical test, many results are not</p>
    <p>normal. A sign test may work best for comparing results of different tools.</p>
    <p>Power  Make sure you have enough tests to have valid statistical power</p>
    <p>Say you want to say Tool A is 3% better than Tool B (what is the confidence interval?):</p>
    <p>3% +/- 1% with 95% confidence looks good to me</p>
    <p>Requires over 9,000 test cases out of a population of 1 Million</p>
    <p>Randomness  The above power results assume your samples are randomly selected across</p>
    <p>the whole population. Not often the case.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How Accurate is Accuracy?</p>
    <p>Condition Positive</p>
    <p>Condition Negative</p>
    <p>Predicted Positive</p>
    <p>True Positive False Positive (Type 1 error)</p>
    <p>Predicted Negative</p>
    <p>False Negative (Type 2 error)</p>
    <p>True Negative</p>
    <p>Confusion Matrix</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some definition from confusion matrix</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consider the Following Ground Truth (rare instance of condition we are looking for)</p>
    <p>Condition Positive</p>
    <p>Condition Negative</p>
    <p>Predicted Positive</p>
    <p>Predicted Negative</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Condition Positive</p>
    <p>Condition Negative</p>
    <p>Predicted Positive</p>
    <p>Predicted Negative</p>
    <p>You found nothing, and are 99% accurate, but not very useful</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Precision, Recall and F1 value</p>
    <p>Condition Positive</p>
    <p>Condition Negative</p>
    <p>Predicted Positive</p>
    <p>Predicted Negative</p>
    <p>Precision is 0%, Recall is 0%, F1 is 0%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Precision, Recall and F1 value (New example)</p>
    <p>Condition Positive</p>
    <p>Condition Negative</p>
    <p>Predicted Positive</p>
    <p>Predicted Negative</p>
    <p>Precision is 50%, Recall is 50%, F1 is 50% (But I am still 99% accurate!)</p>
    <p>These areas are relevant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>If data will have small prevalence (low percentage of true conditions versus false conditions), ignore the true negatives</p>
    <p>Look at the data, visualize it</p>
    <p>Use large random data sets</p>
    <p>Use appropriate statistics (such as paired statistical test, eg. sign-test)</p>
    <p>Review the statistics of your own publications</p>
    <p>Consult statistician</p>
    <p>Ask review committees to hold authors accountable on presenting results.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>If we shadows have offended, Think but this, and all is mended,</p>
    <p>That you have but slumbered here While these visions did appear. And this weak and idle theme, No more yielding but a dream,</p>
    <p>Gentles, do not reprehend: If you pardon, we will mend..</p>
    <p>-Puck in William Shakespeare,</p>
    <p>A Midsummer Night's Dream</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
