<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Multi-level Fidelity Microgrid Testbed Model for Cybersecurity Experimentation</p>
    <p>Aditya Ashok, Siddharth Sridhar, Tamara Becejac,</p>
    <p>Theora Rice, Scott Harpool, Matthias Engels,</p>
    <p>Mark Rice, Thomas Edgar</p>
    <p>Experimentation and Test (CSET '19)</p>
    <p>August 12, 2019</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Cyber attacks on industrial control systems have been increasing in number and sophistication over the last decade.</p>
    <p>Testbeds are extremely essential in providing realistic environments for testing and validating new cybersecurity technologies.</p>
    <p>Self-contained test systems that have cross-domain critical infrastructure elements are ideal candidates for implementation and instantiation on a testbed.</p>
    <p>A campus microgrid provides cross-domain opportunities (electrical, buildings, cyber, water, etc.,) while also being self-contained with a single authority of control.</p>
    <p>This allows us to instantiate all the associated elements at a high-level of fidelity to allow realistic cybersecurity experimentation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proactive Adaptive Cybersecurity Framework for Control Systems (PACiFiC) Initiative</p>
    <p>Approach</p>
    <p>Problem</p>
    <p>Impact</p>
    <p>Define secure design and development principles that apply to</p>
    <p>all OT systems.</p>
    <p>Develop and test adaptive cyber defenses holistically.</p>
    <p>Include human, cyber, communications, and process physics.</p>
    <p>Measurably more secure, reliable, robust, and resilient control</p>
    <p>systems while retaining the same level of performance.</p>
    <p>Enhanced capability in measuring, testing, and demonstrating OT</p>
    <p>cyber security.</p>
    <p>Operational technology (OT) [control systems &amp; their environment]</p>
    <p>are in use in our high consequence infrastructures.</p>
    <p>Current OT is insecure, out of date, static, and targeted by our</p>
    <p>adversaries.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Select PACiFiC Initiative Projects</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Campus Microgrid Model for Cybersecurity Experimentation</p>
    <p>Microgrid Electrical Model</p>
    <p>Microgrid Building Models</p>
    <p>(Electrical)</p>
    <p>Microgrid Building Models</p>
    <p>(Thermal, Electrical)</p>
    <p>Real Building Controllers</p>
    <p>Protection Relays</p>
    <p>Virtual Building Controllers</p>
    <p>Building Operations</p>
    <p>Control Center</p>
    <p>Campus Corporate Network</p>
    <p>Building Operations</p>
    <p>Control Center</p>
    <p>Grid Operations</p>
    <p>Control Center</p>
    <p>Voltages Loads</p>
    <p>VoltagesLoads</p>
    <p>Corporate Network</p>
    <p>Control Network</p>
    <p>Wide-Area Network</p>
    <p>Substation Network</p>
    <p>Building Network</p>
    <p>Conceptual Cyber-Physical Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PACiFiC  Microgrid Testbed</p>
    <p>Objective: Enable research, testing, and validation of proactive, cyber attack prevention, detection, and mitigation strategies developed for grid and building critical infrastructure domains as a part of the PACiFiC initiative.</p>
    <p>Domains</p>
    <p>Grid  Buildings  Process</p>
    <p>control</p>
    <p>Simulators &amp; Tools</p>
    <p>OPAL-RT  Dymola  GridLAB-D  VOLTTRON  FNCS</p>
    <p>Hardware &amp; Software</p>
    <p>SEL 351A &amp; 451  Kepware OPC server  Allen Bradley Control Logix PLC  Johnson Controls Network</p>
    <p>Automation Engine  Wonderware Visualization</p>
    <p>Protocols</p>
    <p>DNP3  Modbus  BACNET</p>
    <p>Simulation Environment</p>
    <p>Micro-grid model in OPAL-RT</p>
    <p>High-fidelity Commercial Building in Dymola</p>
    <p>Low-fidelity residential Buildings in GridLAB-D</p>
    <p>VOLTTRON</p>
    <p>&amp;</p>
    <p>FNCS</p>
    <p>FNCS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PACiFiC Testbed  Architecture (Physical)</p>
    <p>Co-simulation data</p>
    <p>SCADA &amp; ICS data</p>
    <p>SEL-351ASEL-451</p>
    <p>OPC server</p>
    <p>Wonderware HMI</p>
    <p>VOLTTRON</p>
    <p>Johnson Controls NAE</p>
    <p>DNP3</p>
    <p>F N</p>
    <p>C S</p>
    <p>R T</p>
    <p>LA B</p>
    <p>D e</p>
    <p>v. H</p>
    <p>o st</p>
    <p>( P</p>
    <p>y th</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>A P</p>
    <p>I)</p>
    <p>BACNET</p>
    <p>Wonderware HMI</p>
    <p>Allen Bradley PLC</p>
    <p>GridLAB-DDymola</p>
    <p>Soft PLCs (Building level</p>
    <p>Controllers)</p>
    <p>BACNET BACNET</p>
    <p>Modbus</p>
    <p>Analog &amp; Digital I/O</p>
    <p>OPAL-RT</p>
    <p>DNP3</p>
    <p>BACNET</p>
    <p>BACNET</p>
    <p>DNP3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PACiFiC Testbed  Architecture (Cyber)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Microgrid Model (modified IEEE 37 node feeder)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demo Use Case  Cyber Attack Scenario</p>
    <p>Attacker Objective: To disrupt operations at critical facilities of the campus by causing a blackout in the microgrid; cause fear, uncertainty, and doubt.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demo Use Case  Results (Building Simulation)</p>
    <p>AHU fans turn on AHU fans turned off</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demo Use Case  Results (Microgrid Simulation)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Developing a scalable, high-fidelity, and realistic testbed is extremely valuable to test and evaluate cybersecurity research.</p>
    <p>A microgrid model serves as an ideal candidate use case that can be instantiated with a high-fidelity preserving cross-domain interactions (electrical, building, cyber) while being self-contained.</p>
    <p>We presented our testbeds capability to instantiate a campus microgrid model for supporting cybersecurity testing and experimentation.</p>
    <p>We also presented an exemplar multistage cyber attack case study to demonstrate and showcase the testbeds value and capability.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
