<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sandia National Laboratories is a multimission laboratory managed and operated by National Technology &amp; Engineering Solutions of Sandia, LLC, a wholly owned subsidiary of Honeywell International Inc., for the U.S. Department of</p>
    <p>Energys National Nuclear Security Administration under contract DE-NA0003525.</p>
    <p>Proteus: A DLT-Agnostic Emulation and Analysis Framework</p>
    <p>R u s s e l l Va n D a m T h i e n - N a m D i n h</p>
    <p>C h r i s t o p h e r C o r d i G r e g o r y J a c o b u s</p>
    <p>N i c h o l a s P a t t e n g a l e S t e v e n E l l i o t t</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Distributed Ledger Technologies (DLT) have seen exponential growth  2,400 listed cryptocurrencies  Varied trust models: permissionless, permissioned, federated  Varied data structures: blockchain, DAG, HashGraph</p>
    <p>Existing analysis tools  Simulation  simbit, VIBES  Emulation  SherlockFog  Hybrid  Shadow Bitcoin plugin  Physical Testbed  Bitcoin-NG, TrustChain, BLOCKBENCH, Grid5000</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions</p>
    <p>DLT-Agnostic emulation framework  Abstract away infrastructure common to all DLTs  Minimize user effort for implementing new DLTs  Provide standardized tools for analysis</p>
    <p>Extend capabilities of underlying FIREWHEEL orchestration platform</p>
    <p>Demonstrated use case: Ethereum 51% attack</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FIREWHEEL</p>
    <p>Experiment orchestration tool for managing emulated networks</p>
    <p>Focus on supporting well-structured experiments at a large scale</p>
    <p>Specific capabilities:  Programmatic definition of experiment topologies  VM deployment across compute clusters  Management and execution of in-experiment events  Centralized collection, analysis, and display of experimental data  Repeatability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FIREWHEEL Architecture</p>
    <p>Model components  Collection of files for modeling experiment components  Primary interface for building applications like Proteus</p>
    <p>Control  Translate model components into graph representation  Launch experiment using configurable emulation tools</p>
    <p>VM Resource Handler  Manage scheduled experiment events  Redirect output for logging and analysis</p>
    <p>Networking  Provide emulated switches and routers  Configure parameters such as bandwidth and latency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proteus Architecture</p>
    <p>Agent-based modeling paradigm  Compose simple behaviors to create</p>
    <p>complex topologies  Intuitive mapping to real-world agent types</p>
    <p>Extensible by design  Easy access to common model components  Well-defined process to add new DLTs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Your Emulation Can Do For You</p>
    <p>Balance &gt;</p>
    <p>x?</p>
    <p>Send Random Txns</p>
    <p>Mine Block</p>
    <p>No</p>
    <p>Yes</p>
    <p>Model components  Physical  physical, data-link, and networking layer topologies  Peering  peer-to-peer overlay topology  Policy  DLT-level actions (e.g. send tx or propose a new block)</p>
    <p>Messaging system  Coordinated launch and teardown  Information transfer between Agents  Global synchronization of Agents</p>
    <p>Analysis  Generic system metrics  DLT-level metrics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What You Can Do For Your Emulation</p>
    <p>Model components  Client  process for installing and configuring DLT</p>
    <p>software  Adapter  hooks for translating abstract Proteus</p>
    <p>instructions into DLT actions</p>
    <p>Blocky development tool  Terminal application to aid adapter development  Launch small-scale FIREWHEEL test environment  Incrementally develop and test adapter implementation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study: 51% Attack</p>
    <p>We emulated a 51% attack on a private Ethereum network</p>
    <p>We split the network into two partitions: a malicious partition with 60% of the network hash power, and an honest partition with the other 40%.</p>
    <p>This network topology facilitates a double spend and allows the 51% attack to occur.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment Setup</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>During the 51% attack, we collected metrics about network hash power and block times as seen by the honest partition.</p>
    <p>A large drop in hash power can be seen between the start of the attack (22:28) and the end (22:39). Block time is approximately the inverse.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>We also collected metrics about reorganization depth, as seen by the honest partition.</p>
    <p>There is a clear spike in reorganization depth when the 51% attack completes, indicating success.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Cross-DLT analytics to detect common attacks</p>
    <p>Developing adapters for non-cryptocurrency DLTs and assessing their compatibility.</p>
    <p>Incorporating real-world P2P topologies in Proteus and evaluating how that impacts the indicators of 51% attacks.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Proteus is an agent-based framework for conducting rapid, emulated analysis of DLTs.</p>
    <p>Proteus allows for quick development of DLT clients and adapters.</p>
    <p>The results of the 51% attack case study validate Proteus utility in assessing the security guarantees of DLTs.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
