<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ICS Testbed Tetris: Practical Building Blocks Towards a Cyber Security Resource</p>
    <p>Benjamin Green Richard Derbyshire William Knowles James Boorman Pierre Ciholas Daniel Prince David Hutchison</p>
    <p>CSET 20 - Long Preliminary Work Paper 13th USENIX Workshop on Cyber Security Experimentation and Test August 10, 2020</p>
    <p>https://www.lancaster.ac.uk/security-lancaster/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>What are Industrial Control Systems (ICS)  Our work to date/Related work  Design considerations  Experiment lifecycle  High-Level Model  Model breakdown  Practical implementation  Living resource  TIDE-H and future work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What are Industrial Control Systems (ICS)</p>
    <p>https://www.cisco.com/c/en/us/td/docs/solutions/Verticals/Industrial_Automation/IA_Horizontal/DG/Industrial-AutomationDG/Industrial-AutomationDG.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Our work  Over 6 years of ICS testbed development  Collaborative engagement  5 Existing publications in this space</p>
    <p>Related work  Surveys  Theoretical concepts  Practical implementation</p>
    <p>Green, B., Lee, A., Antrobus, R., Roedig, U., Hutchison, D. and Rashid, A., 2017. Pains, gains and PLCs: ten lessons from building an industrial control systems testbed for security research. In 10th {USENIX} Workshop on Cyber Security Experimentation and Test ({CSET} 17).</p>
    <p>Green, B., Frey, S.A.F., Rashid, A. and Hutchison, D., 2016. Testbed diversity as a fundamental principle for effective ICS security research. Serecin.</p>
    <p>Gardiner, J., Craggs, B., Green, B. and Rashid, A., 2019, November. Oops I did it again: further adventures in the land of ICS security testbeds. In Proceedings of the ACM Workshop on Cyber-Physical Systems Security &amp; Privacy (pp. 75-86)</p>
    <p>Ani, U.D., Watson, J.M., Green, B., Craggs, B. and Nurse, J., 2019. Design Considerations for Building Credible Security Testbeds: A Systematic Study of Industrial Control System Use Cases. arXiv preprint arXiv:1911.01471.</p>
    <p>Green, B., Paske, B., Hutchison, D. and Prince, D., 2014. Design and construction of an industrial control system testbed. In PG Net-The 15th Annual PostGraduate Symposium</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Considerations</p>
    <p>Ani, U.D., Watson, J.M., Green, B., Craggs, B. and Nurse, J., 2019. Design Considerations for Building Credible Security Testbeds: A Systematic Study of Industrial Control System Use Cases. arXiv preprint arXiv:1911.01471.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cyber Security Experiment Lifecycle</p>
    <p>Mirkovic, J., Benzel, T.V., Faber, T., Braden, R., Wroclawski, J.T. and Schwab, S., 2010, November. The DETER project: Advancing the science of cyber security experimentation and test. In 2010 IEEE International Conference on Technologies for Homeland Security (HST) (pp. 1-7). IEEE.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>High-Level Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model Breakdown</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Baseline Implementation Guide</p>
    <p>https://www.gunt.de/en/products/process-engineering/water-treatment/multistage-water-treatment/water-treatment-plant-1/083.58100/ce581/glct1:pa-148:ca-255:pr-57</p>
    <p>https://www.fischertechnik.de/en/products/teaching/training-models/554868-edu-training-factory-industry-4-0-24v-education</p>
    <p>https://factoryio.com/features</p>
    <p>http://snap7.sourceforge.net/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Living Resource</p>
    <p>Online resource  www.ics-testbed.co.uk  Transcends static nature of paper  Community contribution  tide-ssg@lancaster.ac.uk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Lancasters TIDE-H &amp; Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You for Watching!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
