<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>On Design and Enhancement of Smart Grid Honeypot System for Practical</p>
    <p>Collection of Threat Intelligence - Long preliminary work paper</p>
    <p>Daisuke Mashima, Derek Kok, Wei Lin Advanced Digital Sciences Center, Illinois at Singapore</p>
    <p>Muhammad Hazwan, Alvin Cheng Custodio Technologies Pte Ltd</p>
    <p>This material is based on research/work supported in part by the Singapore National Research Foundation and the Cybersecurity R&amp;D Consortium Grant Office under Seed Grant Award No. CRDCG2018-S01. This research is partly supported by the National Research Foundation, Singapore, Singapore University of Technology and Design under its National Satellite of Excellence in Design Science and Technology for Secure Critical Infrastructure Grant (NSoE_DeST-SCI2019-005).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background and Motivation</p>
    <p>Honeypot is an effective tool to collect intelligence about attackers in the real world.</p>
    <p>The collected intelligence helps us fine-tune cybersecurity measures (e.g., Firewall, IDS)</p>
    <p>Honeypot for smart grid systems is still in early stage  No honeypot emulating the whole architecture or its cyber-physical</p>
    <p>behaviours  No established methodology for evaluating goodness of honeypot</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Approach</p>
    <p>Develop prototype of honeypot (or honeynet) that emulates typical smart grid system</p>
    <p>Conduct penetration testing to evaluate the honeypot system from the attackers perspective</p>
    <p>Improve the honeypot implementation based on the findings</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Initial Honeypot Design and Implementation  Designed based on</p>
    <p>infrastructure compliant to IEC 60870 and IEC 61850</p>
    <p>Example of a setup that researchers would start with</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation from Attackers perspective</p>
    <p>Penetration testing by cybersecurity experts  Scenario developed based on ICS-CERT and ICS Cyber Kill Chain  Use widely-used tools, such as Nmap and Metasploit</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Insights obtained from the experiments</p>
    <p>Presence of virtual machines hinted by open ports</p>
    <p>Lack of user accounts on Windows machines, which does not look like active, lively used systems</p>
    <p>OS/device fingerprinting results that are different from typical smart grid devices (IEDs, substation gateways)</p>
    <p>Close related ports after virtual machines are started.</p>
    <p>Prepared user accounts with popular ID and weak password</p>
    <p>Discussed next</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Countering OS Fingerprinting against Smart Grid Devices  Passive device</p>
    <p>Only acts as a server (E.g. IEDs)</p>
    <p>Run the same network services (HTTP, IEC 61850 MMS)</p>
    <p>MAC address belonging to the same device vendor (e.g. Siemens)</p>
    <p>Honeyd to fake OS fingerprint</p>
    <p>Active device  Acts as a server and client (E.g., GW, PLC)</p>
    <p>Run the same network services (HTTP, IEC 60870-5-104, SSH)</p>
    <p>MAC address belonging to the same device vendor (e.g. Wago)</p>
    <p>Use VM running a Linux OS close to the real devices</p>
    <p>To counter passive fingerprinting tools (e.g., P0f), Honeyd is not effective.</p>
    <p>Devices of this category often run Linux</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Enhancement of Logging for Data Collection  Transparent proxy (TP) for secure logging of networking</p>
    <p>Implemented as bump-in-the-wire device for network traffic monitoring  Application-level logging at virtual IED, PLC, and substation gateway</p>
    <p>SoftGrid: an open-source software-based substation testbed URL: http://www.illinois.adsc.com.sg/softgrid/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OS Fingerprints of Passive Devices  Significant improvement</p>
    <p>compared to initial IED using Mininet</p>
    <p>Values of SP, ISR, and SS vary.  Only constant difference is IPL.</p>
    <p>Although the specific IED model we studied returns 240, smart grid devices return 164.</p>
    <p>Without the knowledge of the specific IED model, it is not feasible to tell if it is a fake device.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OS Fingerprints of Active Devices  Difference in P0f fingerprints is</p>
    <p>seen in mss*, which varies depending on the network link.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions &amp; Future Work  Designed and implemented a honeypot that emulate</p>
    <p>comprehensive smart grid infrastructure  Presented the evaluation and enhancement of honeypot</p>
    <p>through penetration testing by security experts  The outcome is publicly available.</p>
    <p>Conduct further evaluation with more participants, e.g., hacking/capture-the-flag competitions</p>
    <p>Deploy the improved honeypot for real-world data collection</p>
    <p>Explore use of honeypot for education/training purposes 11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you very much!</p>
    <p>Questions and Inquiries:  Email: daisuke.m@adsc-create.edu.sg</p>
    <p>Materials, Images, and Project Overview:  Web: https://www.illinois.adsc.com.sg/spotify/index.html</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
