<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>APTGen: An Approach towards Generating Practical Dataset Labelled with Targeted Attack Sequences</p>
    <p>NEC Corporation</p>
    <p>Yusuke Takahashi</p>
    <p>Shigeyoshi Shima</p>
    <p>Submission length: Long Paper Submission category: Research Paper</p>
    <p>Yokohama National University</p>
    <p>Rui Tanabe</p>
    <p>Katsunari Yoshioka</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>The constant threats of targeted cyber attacks are one of the major security challenges in nowadays.</p>
    <p>The computer security incident response team (CSIRT) responds to the incident.</p>
    <p>CSIRT tries to reveal the whole picture of the attack through an incident response cycle.  Attack methods that attacker executed in the corporate network</p>
    <p>Sequence of these attack methods (attack sequence)</p>
    <p>Attackers purpose. Detection</p>
    <p>&amp; Analysis</p>
    <p>Containment Eradication</p>
    <p>&amp; Recovery</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>The faster the whole picture of the attack gets revealed, the period between detection and containment or eradication becomes shorter.</p>
    <p>We focus on the process of investigating attack sequences and would like to develop methods to automate or support this process.</p>
    <p>Developing the methods needs various kinds of attack sequence data, network logs and endpoint logs that contain attack traces related to the sequence.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our goal</p>
    <p>To the best of our knowledge, these kinds of open dataset are limited.</p>
    <p>We have decided to build the dataset for R&amp;D for incident handling by ourselves.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Possible Approaches for building the dataset</p>
    <p>[1] Stevens Le Blond, Adina Uritesc, Cdric Gilbert, Zheng Leong Chua, Prateek Saxena, and Engin Kirda. A look at targeted attacks through the lense of an NGO.In23rd USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security14), pages 543558. USENIX Association, 2014. [2] Grant Ho, Aashish Sharma, Mobin Javed, Vern Paxson, and David Wagner. Detecting credential spearphishing in enterprise settings. In26th USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security 17), pages 469485. USENIX Association, 2017. [3] Brown Farinholt, Mohammad Rezaeirad, Paul Pearce, Hitesh Dharmdasani, Haikuo Yin, Stevens Le Blond, Damon McCoy, and Kirill Levchenko. To Catch a Ratter:Monitoring the Behavior of Amateur DarkComet RAT Operators in the Wild. InSecurity and Privacy (SP), 2017 IEEE Symposium On, pages 770787. IEEE, 2017.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Possible Approaches for building the dataset</p>
    <p>We propose APTGen, an approach for generating attack sequences and executing them for building a dataset.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Requirements</p>
    <p>Requirements for building a dataset for incident handling:</p>
    <p>Unify the names of attack methods and their scope in attack sequences. (Reproducibility)</p>
    <p>Clear how realistic generated attack sequences are. (Reality)</p>
    <p>Generate various attack sequences. (Diversity)</p>
    <p>At present, APTGen meets the requirements of reproducibility and diversity.</p>
    <p>To meet the requirement of reality is one of future works.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>APTGen</p>
    <p>APTGen consists of attack sequence generation and execution tools.</p>
    <p>APTGen:</p>
    <p>Generates artificial attack sequence from existing security reports based on the attack model defined in MITREs ATT&amp;CK.</p>
    <p>Executes generated sequence to obtain logs from execution environments.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>APTGen: Generation tool</p>
    <p>Inputs</p>
    <p>Technique list</p>
    <p>Targeted environment information</p>
    <p>Generation condition</p>
    <p>Output:</p>
    <p>Attack sequences</p>
    <p>Step Tactic Technique Software</p>
    <p>k Credential</p>
    <p>Access Credential Dumping</p>
    <p>Mimikatz</p>
    <p>n Tan Ten Sn</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>APTGen: Generation tool</p>
    <p>The tool selects Tactic/Technique/Software randomly under the following constraints.</p>
    <p>Selects Tactic/Technique/Software following the ATT&amp;CK design.</p>
    <p>Selects Tactic/Technique/Software so that an attack sequence is logically completed.</p>
    <p>e.g.: it is necessary to execute any Techniques in Discovery before executing any Techniques in Lateral Movement.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment</p>
    <p>The purpose of experiment is to evaluate the diversity of outputted attack sequences.</p>
    <p>We generated 800 different attack sequences based on eight actual security incidents.</p>
    <p>Incident (targeted organization, event, or attacker)</p>
    <p>APT29</p>
    <p>Bronze Butler</p>
    <p>Clinton campaign</p>
    <p>Japan Pension Service</p>
    <p>National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology</p>
    <p>SingHealth</p>
    <p>South Korean banks and broadcasting organizations</p>
    <p>Ukrainian electricity distribution companies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment: Technique list in Japan Pension Service Incident</p>
    <p>Tactic Technique Collection Email Collection</p>
    <p>Collection Data Staged</p>
    <p>Credential Access Account Manipulation</p>
    <p>Credential Access Credential Dumping</p>
    <p>Credential Access Credentials in Registry Defense Evasion File Deletion</p>
    <p>Discovery System Information Discovery</p>
    <p>Discovery System Network Configuration Discovery</p>
    <p>Discovery File and Directory Discovery</p>
    <p>Discovery Account Discovery</p>
    <p>Discovery Permission Groups Discovery</p>
    <p>Discovery Network Share Discovery</p>
    <p>Discovery Remote System Discovery</p>
    <p>Exfiltration Exfiltration Over Command and Control Channel</p>
    <p>Exfiltration Data Compressed</p>
    <p>Lateral Movement Remote File Copy</p>
    <p>Lateral Movement Pass the Hash</p>
    <p>Persistence Scheduled Task</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment: Generation conditions in Japan Pension Service Incident</p>
    <p>ID Generation Conditions</p>
    <p>Sequence length is 1 or more, last Technique in sequence is File Deletion, and sequence contains Lateral Movement and Exfiltration Over Command and Control Channel.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dataset</p>
    <p>We publish 800 generated attack sequences and corresponding logs as a dataset.</p>
    <p>We are preparing to provide our generation and execution tools for users who accept our terms of use.</p>
    <p>If you are interested, please see the following URL.</p>
    <p>https://ipsr.ynu.ac.jp/aptgen/index.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future work</p>
    <p>Contain benign activity logs in a dataset.</p>
    <p>Make attack sequences and logs more real.</p>
    <p>Algorithm of generating attack sequences.</p>
    <p>More exploit codes/tools.</p>
    <p>Test generated attack sequences against detection methods.</p>
    <p>Discuss with experts in CSIRT and have them evaluate the reality of the generated dataset.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>We presented APTGen, an approach for generating artificial attack sequences of targeted cyber attacks and executing corresponding attacks to generate dataset of targeted attacks.</p>
    <p>We analyzed the relationship between the generated attack sequences by visualization.</p>
    <p>We released a dataset consisting of generated attack sequences and corresponding logs that have been obtained by executing these sequences.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>Please let us know your questions and comments.</p>
    <p>ynugr-ylab-aptgen@ynu.ac.jp</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
