<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Towards accurate detection and genotyping of expressed variants</p>
    <p>from whole transcriptome sequencing data</p>
    <p>Jorge Duitama1, Pramod Srivastava2, and Ion Mandoiu1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>RNA-Seq is the method of choice for studying functional effects of genetic variability</p>
    <p>RNA-Seq poses new computational challenges compared to genome sequencing</p>
    <p>In this paper we present:  a strategy to map transcriptome reads using both the</p>
    <p>genome reference sequence and the CCDS database.  a novel Bayesian model for SNV discovery and genotyping</p>
    <p>based on quality scores</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Read Mapping</p>
    <p>Reference genome sequence</p>
    <p>&gt;ref|NT_082868.6|Mm19_82865_37:1-3688105 Mus musculus chromosome 19 genomic contig, strain C57BL/6J GATCATACTCCTCATGCTGGACATTCTGGTTCCTAG TATATCTGGAGAGTTAAGATGGGGAATTATGTCA ACTTTCCCTCTTCCTATGCCAGTTATGCATAATGCA CAAATATTTCCACGCTTTTTCACTACAGATAAAG AACTGGGACTTGCTTATTTACCTTTAGATGAACAGA TTCAGGCTCTGCAAGAAAATAGAATTTTCTTCAT ACAGGGAAGCCTGTGCTTTGTACTAATTTCTTCATT ACAAGATAAGAGTCAATGCATATCCTTGTATAAT</p>
    <p>@HWI-EAS299_2:2:1:1536:631 GGGATGTCAGGATTCACAATGACAGTGCTGGATGAG +HWI-EAS299_2:2:1:1536:631 ::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::222220 @HWI-EAS299_2:2:1:771:94 ATTACACCACCTTCAGCCCAGGTGGTTGGAGTACTC +HWI-EAS299_2:2:1:771:94 :::::::::::::::::::::::::::2::222220</p>
    <p>Read sequences &amp; quality scores</p>
    <p>SNP calling</p>
    <p>SNP Calling from Genomic DNA Reads</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mapping mRNA Reads</p>
    <p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:RNA-Seq-alignment.png</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C. Trapnell, L. Pachter, and S.L. Salzberg. TopHat: discovering splice junctions with RNA-Seq. Bioinformatics, 25(9):11051111, 2009.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mapping and Merging Strategy</p>
    <p>Tumor mRNA reads</p>
    <p>CCDS Mapping</p>
    <p>Genome Mapping</p>
    <p>Read Merging</p>
    <p>CCDS mapped reads</p>
    <p>Genome mapped reads</p>
    <p>Mapped reads</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Read Merging Genome CCDS Agree? Hard Merge Soft Merge</p>
    <p>Unique Unique Yes Keep Keep</p>
    <p>Unique Unique No Throw Throw</p>
    <p>Unique Multiple No Throw Keep</p>
    <p>Unique Not Mapped No Keep Keep</p>
    <p>Multiple Unique No Throw Keep</p>
    <p>Multiple Multiple No Throw Throw</p>
    <p>Multiple Not Mapped No Throw Throw</p>
    <p>Not mapped Unique No Keep Keep</p>
    <p>Not mapped Multiple No Throw Throw</p>
    <p>Not mapped Not Mapped Yes Throw Throw</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SNV Detection and Genotyping</p>
    <p>AACGCGGCCAGCCGGCTTCTGTCGGCCAGCAGCCAGGAATCTGGAAACAATGGCTACAGCGTGC AACGCGGCCAGCCGGCTTCTGTCGGCCAGCCGGCAG CGCGGCCAGCCGGCTTCTGTCGGCCAGCAGCCCGGA GCGGCCAGCCGGCTTCTGTCGGCCAGCCGGCAGGGA GCCAGCCGGCTTCTGTCGGCCAGCAGCCAGGAATCT GCCGGCTTCTGTCGGCCAGCAGCCAGGAATCTGGAA CTTCTGTCGGCCAGCCGGCAGGAATCTGGAAACAAT CGGCCAGCAGCCAGGAATCTGGAAACAATGGCTACA CCAGCAGCCAGGAATCTGGAAACAATGGCTACAGCG CAAGCAGCCAGGAATCTGGAAACAATGGCTACAGCG GCAGCCAGGAATCTGGAAACAATGGCTACAGCGTGC</p>
    <p>Reference</p>
    <p>Locus i</p>
    <p>Ri</p>
    <p>r(i) : Base call of read r at locus i r(i) : Probability of error reading base call r(i) Gi : Genotype at locus i</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SNV Detection and Genotyping</p>
    <p>Use Bayes rule to calculate posterior probabilities and pick the genotype with the largest one</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Models</p>
    <p>Maq:  Keep just the alleles with the two largest counts  Pr (Ri | Gi=HiHi) is the probability of observing k alleles r(i)</p>
    <p>different than Hi  Pr (Ri | Gi=HiHi) is approximated as a binomial with p=0.5</p>
    <p>SOAPsnp  Pr (ri | Gi=HiHi) is the average of Pr(ri|Hi) and Pr(ri|Gi=Hi)  A rank test on the quality scores of the allele calls is used</p>
    <p>to confirm heterozygocity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SNV Detection and Genotyping</p>
    <p>Calculate conditional probabilities by multiplying contributions of individual reads</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accuracy Assessment of Variants Detection</p>
    <p>113 million Illumina mRNA reads generated from blood cell tissue of Hapmap individual NA12878 (NCBI SRA database accession numbers SRX000565 and SRX000566)  We tested genotype calling using as gold standard 3.4</p>
    <p>million SNPs with known genotypes for NA12878 available in the database of the Hapmap project</p>
    <p>True positive: called variant for which Hapmap genotype coincides</p>
    <p>False positive: called variant for which Hapmap genotype does not coincide</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparison of Mapping Strategies</p>
    <p>Transcripts</p>
    <p>Genome</p>
    <p>SoftMerge</p>
    <p>HardMerge</p>
    <p>False Positives</p>
    <p>Tr ue</p>
    <p>P os</p>
    <p>iti ve</p>
    <p>s</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparison of Variant Calling Strategies</p>
    <p>SNVQ</p>
    <p>SOAPsnp</p>
    <p>Maq</p>
    <p>False Positives</p>
    <p>Tr ue</p>
    <p>P os</p>
    <p>iti ve</p>
    <p>s</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Filtering</p>
    <p>Transcripts</p>
    <p>Genome</p>
    <p>Hard Merge</p>
    <p>SoftMerge</p>
    <p>Read Position</p>
    <p>% o</p>
    <p>f m</p>
    <p>is m</p>
    <p>at ch</p>
    <p>es</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Filtering</p>
    <p>Allow just x reads per start locus to eliminate PCR amplification artifacts</p>
    <p>Chepelev et. al. algorithm:  For each locus groups starting reads with 0, 1 and</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparison of Data Filtering Strategies</p>
    <p>None</p>
    <p>Alignment Trimming</p>
    <p>Three Reads Per Start Locus</p>
    <p>One Read Per Start Locus</p>
    <p>False Positives</p>
    <p>Tr ue</p>
    <p>P os</p>
    <p>iti ve</p>
    <p>s</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accuracy per RPKM bins</p>
    <p>TPHomoVar TPHetero FP FNHomoVar FNHetero</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>We presented a new strategy to map mRNA reads using both the reference genome and the CCDS database and a new bayesian model for SNV detection and genotyping</p>
    <p>Experiments on publicly available datasets show that our methods outperform widely used SNV detection methods</p>
    <p>Future Work:  Improve genotype calling by adapting our model to</p>
    <p>differential allelic expression  Use our methods on RNA-Seq data from cancer tumor data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgments  Brent Graveley and Duan Fei (UCHC)  NSF awards IIS-0546457, IIS-0916948, and DBI-0543365  UCONN Research Foundation UCIG grant</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
