<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Detecting Spam in VoIP Networks Ram Dantu</p>
    <p>Prakash Kolan</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why use VOIP?  More Multimedia Features</p>
    <p>support for video-conferencing and video-phones  Easier integration of voice with applications and databases  Convergence of voice and data communications</p>
    <p>Cost  Long distance phone</p>
    <p>call costs virtually eliminated</p>
    <p>PC + headset + software = telephone</p>
    <p>Gartner: 90% of new corporate phones VOIP by 2008</p>
    <p>TeleGeography 2005 52% of online households said they were likely to subscribe to a flat-rate VoIP service package if it was priced at $30 per month</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of VoIP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SIP based SIP based VoIPVoIP ArchitectureArchitecture</p>
    <p>Legacy PBX</p>
    <p>SIP User Agents (UA)</p>
    <p>Application Services</p>
    <p>eMail LDAP Oracle XML</p>
    <p>SIPSIP</p>
    <p>RTP (Media)</p>
    <p>SIP</p>
    <p>CPLCPL 3pcc</p>
    <p>PSTN</p>
    <p>I N T E L L I G E N T</p>
    <p>S E R V I C E S</p>
    <p>SIP Proxy, Registrar &amp; Redirect Servers</p>
    <p>CAS or PRI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic SIP CallBasic SIP Call--FlowFlow SIP UA1 SIP UA2</p>
    <p>INVITE w/ SDP for Media Negotiation</p>
    <p>BYE</p>
    <p>MEDIA</p>
    <p>MEDIA</p>
    <p>ACK</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SIP Call Flow with Proxy Server Proxy Server</p>
    <p>Register</p>
    <p>OK (200) Register OK (200)</p>
    <p>Invite Invite Trying (100) Ringing</p>
    <p>(180) Ringing (180) OK (200) OK (200) ACK ACK</p>
    <p>RTP/RTCP media channels</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Issues  VoIP is going to be a critical infrastructure for the nation  Reliability and availability important for E911  VoIP is real-time traffic. So QoS must be maintained  VoIP inherits all properties of the IP protocol  including security weaknesses  Separate signaling and media require different protection mechanisms thus</p>
    <p>complicating solutions  FW and NAT traversal  New/Changing Standards  VoIP over WiFi/Cellular phones and mobility introduces new threats  VoIP protocols/infrastructure used for IM, Multimedia, and Video  Convergence of two global and structurally different networks (PSTN and VoIP)</p>
    <p>introduces new security weaknesses  Threats like DDOS and Spamming are more damaging to voice compared to data</p>
    <p>networks  Attack propagation; Threats and vulnerabilities will evolve and it is expected that they</p>
    <p>will impact (directly or indirectly) the existing PSTN.  Attacks affect subscribers, service providers and carriers who are considered part of</p>
    <p>the National Critical Infrastructure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VoIP Security Workshops</p>
    <p>1st VoIP Security workshop was held in Dallas, Texas as part of IEEE Globecom during December, 2004 (http://www.cs.unt.edu/~rdantu/VoIPSecurityWorkshop.htm)</p>
    <p>2nd VoIP Security workshop was held in Washington DC during June, 2005 (https://www.csialliance.org/news/events/voip/VoIP_Agenda.PDF)</p>
    <p>More than 260 people have participated in these workshops. The participants include representatives from Department of Homeland Security, Department of Defense, the FBI, NSA, NIST, FCC, industry consortiums such as the International Packet Communications Consortium (IPCC) and SIP.EDU in Internet2, VoPSF, VoIPSA, and several telecommunications service providers, vendors and universities.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voice Spam</p>
    <p>Voice Spam is different from E-mail Spam</p>
    <p>Voice Spam at 2am</p>
    <p>E-Mail Spam at 2am</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Email vs. Voice Mail</p>
    <p>Email Internet Remote SMTP</p>
    <p>Server Local SMTP</p>
    <p>Server</p>
    <p>Indirect (Un-intrusive)</p>
    <p>Voice Mail Network</p>
    <p>Voice Mail Server</p>
    <p>* Email server access is protected through series of mail servers and relays</p>
    <p>Direct (Intrusive) Would you allow</p>
    <p>un-trusted person to save directly</p>
    <p>on your system ?</p>
    <p>* Voice mail has less barrier than data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spamming</p>
    <p>Different from e-mail spam  At 2AM, Received a junk e-mail sitting in Inbox.</p>
    <p>But, a junk voice call is a real nuisance.  Most E-mail filters rely on content analysis. But in Voice calls, it</p>
    <p>is too late to analyze media for spamming</p>
    <p>Voice Spam Detection  difficult  Headers for voice spam detection : from , contact. Are these</p>
    <p>enough ?  Detection in real time before the media arrives</p>
    <p>Spam is basically an unwanted call !!!!!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Functional Elements  Elements in Spam Detection</p>
    <p>Black and White Lists  Database of wanted and unwanted callers- Black &amp;</p>
    <p>White Lists  Preference based on domains and contacts.</p>
    <p>Bayesian Learning  Learning based on past history  Past history specifies spam or valid behavior about</p>
    <p>the caller  Update the learning based on past history, new</p>
    <p>evidence like feedback from end users.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inference</p>
    <p>Trust  Trust is a a derived entity.</p>
    <p>Depends on</p>
    <p>Callers past behavior with callee</p>
    <p>Spam and valid calls from the caller</p>
    <p>The identifiers having extreme values of Trust can be added to Black and White lists.</p>
    <p>This is time bound as few spam calls after a good behavior might go unnoticed, or vice versa.</p>
    <p>Trust grows slowly with time for a valid behavior and drops fast for a spam behavior. Additive growth and multiplicative descent.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Functional Elements Contd..</p>
    <p>Inference  Inference from trusted neighbors  Reputation coefficient for each neighbor  Bayesian Inference of reputation for known proxy/neighbor</p>
    <p>topology  Update Trust and Reputation coefficients based on calling</p>
    <p>patterns</p>
    <p>Presence  Called party preferences and interests  Presence of situation  State of mind and mood of called party</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Functional Elements of VSD</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Setup Domain A</p>
    <p>Voice Spam Detector Proxy</p>
    <p>Proxy</p>
    <p>Proxy Proxy</p>
    <p>Proxy</p>
    <p>Domain B</p>
    <p>Proxy</p>
    <p>Domain E</p>
    <p>Domain C</p>
    <p>Domain D</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Traffic Profile  Five domains, 35 hosts per each domain and 100 users</p>
    <p>for each host  Average rate of 8 calls per minute  Neither the VSD nor the called-users have any idea</p>
    <p>regarding the call generation process.  Randomly select a set of users, hosts and domains as</p>
    <p>spammers before the start of the experiment  A button called SPAM included in each hard phone in</p>
    <p>the receiving domain for giving feedback to the VSD.  Randomly select a set of users, hosts and domains as</p>
    <p>spammers before the start of the experiment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trust Computation History regarding participating entities  x1, x2, xn</p>
    <p>pt =</p>
    <p>x1, x2, xn are updated after every call</p>
    <p>Initial Values Threshold</p>
    <p>Trust of x1, x2, xn pt</p>
    <p>= =</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>==</p>
    <p>==</p>
    <p>validspamk ni i</p>
    <p>ni i</p>
    <p>kxPkCP</p>
    <p>spamxPspamCP</p>
    <p>, ..1</p>
    <p>..1</p>
    <p>)()(</p>
    <p>)()(</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reputation Inference Reputation Coefficient R(a,b) - Reputation of b on a</p>
    <p>In the above figure R(a,c) =  (R(a,b),R(b,c)) for all b in trusted neighbors of a</p>
    <p>represents the Bayesian Inference function. This inference is carried out using inference graph as shown below.</p>
    <p>AP, BP, CP and DP are the proxies of domains A,B,C and D respectively</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>C B</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>C B</p>
    <p>Call from a host in Domain D to a host in Domain A.</p>
    <p>Reputation Inference</p>
    <p>Inference Graph of Network topology</p>
    <p>Domain Proxies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reputation Inference For a call from a domain The reputation is updated after every call based on user</p>
    <p>feedback. The update is positive for a valid call and negative for a spam call.</p>
    <p>Initial Values Threshold Reputation of B,C,D pr</p>
    <p>All the generating and intermediate domains routing the call are updated based on their respective learning.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Message Probability</p>
    <p>Message Probability p = f(pt,pr)</p>
    <p>If p&gt;T, call = spam else call = not spam Threshold</p>
    <p>pt Call accepted or Rejected</p>
    <p>pr</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Collaboration between different methodologies in the architecture</p>
    <p>Time(1 unit = 65 call durations)</p>
    <p>N o</p>
    <p>o f</p>
    <p>C al</p>
    <p>ls</p>
    <p>G en</p>
    <p>er at</p>
    <p>ed / F</p>
    <p>ilt er</p>
    <p>ed</p>
    <p>Total Calls Total Spam Calls</p>
    <p>Filtered Calls</p>
    <p>Time(1 unit = 65 call durations)</p>
    <p>Fi lte</p>
    <p>re d</p>
    <p>C al</p>
    <p>ls</p>
    <p>Actual Spam generated Black Listing</p>
    <p>Black Listing With Trust Black Listing With Trust &amp; Reputation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accuracy of VSD during learning and lock-in period</p>
    <p>Tim e(1 unit = 65 call durations)</p>
    <p>R at</p>
    <p>e o</p>
    <p>f S</p>
    <p>p am</p>
    <p>//F ilt</p>
    <p>er ed</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>al ls</p>
    <p>Rate of Spam Calls Rate of Filtered Calls</p>
    <p>Time(1 unit = 65 total call durations)</p>
    <p>N o</p>
    <p>o f</p>
    <p>S p</p>
    <p>am C</p>
    <p>al ls</p>
    <p>g</p>
    <p>en er</p>
    <p>at ed</p>
    <p>/F ilt</p>
    <p>er ed</p>
    <p>Total Spam Calls Filtered Calls</p>
    <p>Accuracy of VSD During Learning Period</p>
    <p>Accuracy of VSD During Lock-In Period</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sensitivity Analysis</p>
    <p>Percentage of spam generated</p>
    <p>% o</p>
    <p>f F</p>
    <p>al se</p>
    <p>A la</p>
    <p>rm s</p>
    <p>Accuracy of VSD Spam Volume Vs. Accuracy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sensitivity Analysis</p>
    <p>-10</p>
    <p>Tim e (1 unit = 65 call durations )</p>
    <p>F ilt</p>
    <p>er ed</p>
    <p>S p</p>
    <p>am C</p>
    <p>al ls</p>
    <p>Network Size(No of Domains)P er</p>
    <p>ce n</p>
    <p>ta g</p>
    <p>e o</p>
    <p>f F</p>
    <p>al se</p>
    <p>A la</p>
    <p>rm s False Alarms</p>
    <p>Network Size Vs. Accuracy Network Size Vs. False Alarms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Using Domain-specific knowledge</p>
    <p>-50</p>
    <p>Time(1 unit = 65 call durations)</p>
    <p>Fi lte</p>
    <p>re d</p>
    <p>S pa</p>
    <p>m C</p>
    <p>al ls</p>
    <p>Without Domain Knowledge With Domain Knowledge</p>
    <p>Learning From Others Experience</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>/ max</p>
    <p>Unsolicited Bulk Calls</p>
    <p>Spam</p>
    <p>Opt-Out</p>
    <p>Opt-In</p>
    <p>Telemarketer</p>
    <p>Spammer Correlation</p>
    <p>Phisher</p>
    <p>Opt-In Spammers</p>
    <p>Spammer Classification based on their correlation and spam distribution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions  An architecture based on collaboration between different</p>
    <p>functional elements is proposed  We have used open source proxy server, soft clients and</p>
    <p>hard phones for the experiments  A combinations of black/white lists, trust and reputation</p>
    <p>functions and media quarantining are used  Spammer classification technique is developed and</p>
    <p>supplemented with the above results  From our observation of the logs it takes 3 spam calls to</p>
    <p>confirm it is a spam and the 4th call can be accurately identified as the spam.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
