<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Case for Comprehensive Diagnostics</p>
    <p>CyDAT - Cyber-center for Diagnostics, Analytics and Telemetry</p>
    <p>Chas DiFatta (chas@cmu.edu) Dan Klein (dvk@lonewolf.com) Mark Poepping (poepping@cmu.edu)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Diagnostics? You discover your car has a flat tire...  You fix it you move on</p>
    <p>Its flat again a week later...  Valve problem?  Nails in the driveway?  Neighbor kid?</p>
    <p>Can you check all failure possibilities?  Might help if you knew when air started leaking</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cars Computers You discover your Sendmail daemon crashed...  You restart it and you move on</p>
    <p>It crashes again a day later...  Configuration problem?  Performance or resource problem?  New bug or integration problem with spam</p>
    <p>engines?  Security vulnerability? Is it really my sendmail</p>
    <p>running or a rogue daemon?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Diagnostics?  Things break, in complicated, partial ways  and it matters  Systems built to get it working, not to be fixed</p>
    <p>Meter/maintain/fix after installation?  The maintainer learns how but its a struggle</p>
    <p>Software reuse and layered infrastructures create dynamic dependencies  Diagnostic data may not be available at all  Certainly doesnt follow service path  Minimally out of band, often out of question</p>
    <p>Service Plane + Management Plane + Diagnostic Plane</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Who are the Diagnosticians?</p>
    <p>In IT (lots of other diagnostic domains):  Applications Support Personnel  Systems Administrators  Network Support Staff  Security Response Folks  Managers of Computing Infrastructure  Help Desk  Ordinary Users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Who are the Diagnosticians?</p>
    <p>In IT (lots of other diagnostic domains):  Applications Support Personnel  Systems Administrators  Network Support Staff  Security Response Folks  Managers of Computing Infrastructure  Help Desk  Ordinary Users</p>
    <p>Everybody</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Banes of Diagnosticians Validated through Interviews  Limited access to slices of diagnostic data  Discovering valuable information in a sea of data  Correlating different diagnostic data types  Providing evidence for non-repudiation of a</p>
    <p>diagnosis  Finding time to create tools to transfer diagnostic</p>
    <p>knowledge to less skilled organizations and/or individuals (automation)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Illustration Someone reports the payroll application seemed slow at 2pm  You look around, but it seems fine and you move on.</p>
    <p>Someone else reports the problem again a week later...  Configuration or firmware problem?  Downstream congestion problem caused by large file</p>
    <p>transfers?  Networking problem?  How many potential failure scenarios?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Illustration (2)</p>
    <p>Whats Involved?  Peer network routers/switches  RAID and SAN devices  Application servers</p>
    <p>CRM, Payroll, patient records  Maybe:</p>
    <p>Configuration problem  Resource contention  Intermittent device failure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Illustration (3)</p>
    <p>Present day manual process for resolution  Map DNS/DHCP/IP address/MAC address  Inspect historical network statistics on all devices</p>
    <p>in the path  Interface information: byte, packet and error counts  Device health: CPU, memory, power supply, etc.  Network flow records of devices in question</p>
    <p>Manually inspect logs/statistics on server and client applications and middleware systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UPS/PDU</p>
    <p>Separate Event Domains</p>
    <p>Network B</p>
    <p>Network A</p>
    <p>Routers Switches</p>
    <p>System Log Info</p>
    <p>Application</p>
    <p>Routers Switches</p>
    <p>DB</p>
    <p>Network Info Application Info</p>
    <p>RAID/ SAN ApplicationHost A</p>
    <p>Host B</p>
    <p>Host C</p>
    <p>Environmental Info</p>
    <p>UPS/PDUUPS/PDU</p>
    <p>UPS/PDU</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UPS/PDU</p>
    <p>Collecting Event Domains</p>
    <p>Network B</p>
    <p>Network A</p>
    <p>Routers Switches</p>
    <p>System Log Info</p>
    <p>Application</p>
    <p>Routers Switches</p>
    <p>DB</p>
    <p>Network Info Application Info</p>
    <p>RAID/ SAN ApplicationHost A</p>
    <p>Host B</p>
    <p>Host C</p>
    <p>Environmental Info</p>
    <p>UPS/PDUUPS/PDU</p>
    <p>UPS/PDU</p>
    <p>Networking Security SystemsApplicationsEnvironmental</p>
    <p>Diagnostic Apps</p>
    <p>First Order</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UPS/PDU</p>
    <p>Integrating Event Domains</p>
    <p>Network B</p>
    <p>Network A</p>
    <p>Routers Switches</p>
    <p>System Log Info</p>
    <p>Application</p>
    <p>Routers Switches</p>
    <p>DB</p>
    <p>Network Info Application Info</p>
    <p>RAID/ SAN ApplicationHost A</p>
    <p>Host B</p>
    <p>Host C</p>
    <p>Environmental Info</p>
    <p>UPS/PDUUPS/PDU</p>
    <p>UPS/PDU</p>
    <p>Networking Security SystemsApplicationsEnvironmental</p>
    <p>Diagnostic Apps</p>
    <p>First Order</p>
    <p>Conformance Auditing Power ManagementSpecialized ApplicationsSANSecond Order</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Administrator Questions  Why was the payroll application slow?  The redundant power supply failed on the</p>
    <p>RAID (using the SAN) caused by a PDU failure and the RAID was cycling between write through and write back mode.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thinking about the Problem [A Layered Architecture for Diagnostic Infrastructure]</p>
    <p>Instrumentation data you want  In the format that you need  Where you want it</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thinking about the Problem [A Layered Architecture for Diagnostic Infrastructure]</p>
    <p>Instrumentation data you want  In the format that you need  Where you want it</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EDDY Capabilities [Orchestrate Data and Create Generic Information]</p>
    <p>Enable correlation  Common Event Record (CER)  a way to format event information to</p>
    <p>make it easier to process  TTL, timestamp, observation point, normalizer location, event type,</p>
    <p>GUID, severity, user defined tags  Extensible payload, leverage domain data formats</p>
    <p>Provide transport  Diagnostic Backplane  a way to move CERs around to make it easier</p>
    <p>to automate processing  High performance and XMPP</p>
    <p>Some simple event orchestration methods  Normalize, transform, visualize, store, anonymize</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EDDY Extensibility and Scalability</p>
    <p>You dont need all the data, pick off only what you need...</p>
    <p>SNMP/RMON events</p>
    <p>Network Flow events</p>
    <p>Email logs</p>
    <p>Application events</p>
    <p>MS-MOM events</p>
    <p>System logs</p>
    <p>Snort/IDS events</p>
    <p>Web logs</p>
    <p>Environmental events</p>
    <p>Normalization Transformation</p>
    <p>Header Raw</p>
    <p>payload</p>
    <p>Header</p>
    <p>Targeted Payload</p>
    <p>Transformation Second Order</p>
    <p>Header</p>
    <p>Diagnostic Hypothesis</p>
    <p>Header</p>
    <p>Targeted Payload</p>
    <p>Header</p>
    <p>Specialized Payload</p>
    <p>Header Raw</p>
    <p>payload Header</p>
    <p>Raw Payload</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EDDY Agent Appliance Anatomy</p>
    <p>Transform: to name few.... Anonymize , store, archive, morph (many flavors), join, transfer (external communication), aggregation, normalize, etc.</p>
    <p>Filter Route</p>
    <p>Management</p>
    <p>Acquire Query/Response Consume</p>
    <p>Event Channel</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Appling domain agnostic methods to domain specific solutions</p>
    <p>Types)</p>
    <p>Normalize Transform Anonymize Aggregate</p>
    <p>Aggregate</p>
    <p>Snort Records, 20/sec</p>
    <p>Normalize Transform</p>
    <p>Store (20 min of data)</p>
    <p>Aggregate</p>
    <p>Combined Snort with Associated network flow</p>
    <p>records, 20/sec</p>
    <p>Normalize/ CER/Factory</p>
    <p>IDS Records, 20/sec</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Visualization</p>
    <p>EDDY Agent Framework Functionality (filter/action/route)</p>
    <p>Security</p>
    <p>Network</p>
    <p>Application</p>
    <p>System</p>
    <p>Environmental</p>
    <p>NMS</p>
    <p>AMS</p>
    <p>Alert</p>
    <p>Tools</p>
    <p>API</p>
    <p>API</p>
    <p>API</p>
    <p>APINormalizers Storage Analysis</p>
    <p>Application (in/out band) Transformation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What EDDY is  Architecture for cross domain diagnostics  An enabling technology that provides</p>
    <p>Event ledger  Dissemination and correlation infrastructure,</p>
    <p>Afford research access to event data (anonymized)  A development platform for diagnostic research</p>
    <p>Domain specific  Domain agnostic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What EDDY is not  A system/network/application/security</p>
    <p>management platform  The analysis engine, it enables the analysis</p>
    <p>to happen with domain expertise</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Carnegie Mellon CyDAT Cyber-center for Diagnostics Analytics and Telemetry</p>
    <p>Architecture and Standards  Design and define specifics for the IT Diagnostic Plane  Standards for data format and transport</p>
    <p>Open Source Prototype  A reference implementation for experimentation with the Diagnostic Plane</p>
    <p>Observatory  Leverage a large-scale event facility at Carnegie Mellon for engineering</p>
    <p>and research collaboration on real data  Computing Services provides data, needs engineering analyses  Facilitate data export to other researchers  Research on structure and behavior of the Diagnostic facility  Engage corporate collaboration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observatory Service Infrastructure</p>
    <p>Network Events</p>
    <p>Application/System Events</p>
    <p>Security Events</p>
    <p>Researcher Analysis Applications</p>
    <p>Data orchestration/storage agents</p>
    <p>Firefly Networks</p>
    <p>Robotics, MOTES,</p>
    <p>etc.</p>
    <p>Data flow:  publish/subscribe (EDDY/XMPP) &lt;1K/s  high performance push API (EDDY/HP) 14K/s+</p>
    <p>Query: under development  Common data format: EDDY Version II</p>
    <p>Real data from experimental sensor networks</p>
    <p>Real data from production enterprise systems, networks, and environmental information. Custom probes, syslog aggregation, network flows</p>
    <p>Data orchestration/storage agents</p>
    <p>Data orchestration services (translation, storage, etc.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observatory Services Multi-Campus Infrastructure</p>
    <p>Import services Sources: researcher sensors, computing services data from servers</p>
    <p>and networks, from facilities management Access to data (stored and streams)  leverage Andrew</p>
    <p>authentication/authorization Data Translation</p>
    <p>Anonymization, aggregation, domain agnostic and domain specific from researcher requests</p>
    <p>Leverage CyDAT Observatory compute cluster Enforcing policies in concert with ISO and IRB</p>
    <p>Global Campus Collaborative data access to global campus</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Want to Learn More?  Web sites</p>
    <p>www.cmu.edu/eddy  www.cylab.cmu.edu/research/cydat.html</p>
    <p>Principal Investigators  Chas DiFatta (chas@cmu.edu)  Mark Poepping (poepping@cmu.edu)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions/Comments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Case for Comprehensive Diagnostics</p>
    <p>CyDAT - Cyber-center for Diagnostics, Analytics and Telemetry</p>
    <p>Chas DiFatta (chas@cmu.edu) Dan Klein (dvk@lonewolf.com) Mark Poepping (poepping@cmu.edu)</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
