<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best Practices 09/28/20  2008 IBM Corporation</p>
    <p>Best Practices for the Care and Feeding of a Program Committee, and Other Thoughts on</p>
    <p>Conference Organization</p>
    <p>Fred Douglis</p>
    <p>IBM T.J. Watson Research Center</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2008 IBM Corporation2 Best Practices 09/28/20</p>
    <p>WOW  Its WOWCS</p>
    <p>First reaction: what a great idea!</p>
    <p>Second reaction: will anyone actually submit?</p>
    <p>Immediate fear: spend time writing something up, only to find out its been canceled</p>
    <p>Final reaction: duty</p>
    <p>Ive chaired USENIX98, USITS99, and a few other conferences</p>
    <p>Most went well but there were some issues</p>
    <p>End goal: guidebook (wiki) for program/general chairs</p>
    <p>https://wiki.usenix.org/bin/view/Main/Conference/CollectedWisdom</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2008 IBM Corporation3 Best Practices 09/28/20</p>
    <p>Wiki</p>
    <p>Goals</p>
    <p>Living document</p>
    <p>Allow discussion</p>
    <p>Two types of info eventually</p>
    <p>Guide for new program chairs or conference organizers  Review management software  Best practices</p>
    <p>Ideas for new ways to do things  How well do rebuttals work? Ratings? Bidding?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2008 IBM Corporation4 Best Practices 09/28/20</p>
    <p>Problem 1: Bad Reviewers</p>
    <p>Not everyone is a good PC member</p>
    <p>Some never do anything</p>
    <p>Some do really crummy reviews</p>
    <p>Some are too argumentative, dominate the rest of the PC, or have other personality issues</p>
    <p>How to find who is a known bad reviewer?</p>
    <p>Past experience</p>
    <p>Word of mouth but people tend not to know to ask</p>
    <p>How to expand word of mouth?</p>
    <p>Reviewer database?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2008 IBM Corporation5 Best Practices 09/28/20</p>
    <p>Problem 2: Inexperienced Reviewers</p>
    <p>Always want to bring some new blood into a PC  Search for repeat authors who havent served (need a script</p>
    <p>to scour Google Scholar for this)  Caveat: not everyone knows what to expect and may not be</p>
    <p>cut out for it. Dont take too many people you dont know if you can help it</p>
    <p>Tips for ensuring the best PC  Set expectations early (# reviews, timing,  no surprises!)</p>
    <p>Have multiple deadlines: force people to miss early rather than all at once just before the decisions</p>
    <p>Help with calibration (average scores of reviewers compared to the scores of their peers on same papers)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2008 IBM Corporation6 Best Practices 09/28/20</p>
    <p>Problem 3: PC Composition</p>
    <p>Avoid inbreeding, or the appearance of it</p>
    <p>Overlap from year to year</p>
    <p>Institutional overlap</p>
    <p>There are enough people who will have published at an established conference that a chair should draw on them rather than outside the conference community</p>
    <p>Best fit</p>
    <p>Reward participation</p>
    <p>Avoid problems with calibration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2008 IBM Corporation7 Best Practices 09/28/20</p>
    <p>PC Bells and Whistles</p>
    <p>Options for running a PC</p>
    <p>Rebuttals (Seem to be a nice idea, but add lead time)</p>
    <p>Reviewer ratings (hard to calibrate; dont want to insult)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2008 IBM Corporation8 Best Practices 09/28/20</p>
    <p>Running a Conference</p>
    <p>Sponsorship  Some institutions make it a pleasure to run a conference, and some</p>
    <p>make it much harder  Doing it alone has risks (e.g., liability): who owns the conference risks?</p>
    <p>Setting expectations  Its hard to know just how many submissions a new conference will get:</p>
    <p>better to be swamped (and add PC members) than miss all your targets  Publicity is amazingly critical (who knew?)</p>
    <p>Scheduling  Watch for conflicts and hope the others watch too  Consider the impact of rejected papers from one conference being</p>
    <p>routed to another. (Feed reviews?)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2008 IBM Corporation9 Best Practices 09/28/20</p>
    <p>Backup</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2008 IBM Corporation10 Best Practices 09/28/20</p>
    <p>Problem 4: (Self)plagiarism</p>
    <p>Simultaneous submission seems to be a big problem</p>
    <p>Least publishable units</p>
    <p>True plagiarism</p>
    <p>We need a better mechanism for detecting</p>
    <p>Serendipity doesnt cut it</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2008 IBM Corporation11 Best Practices 09/28/20</p>
    <p>Concrete Proposals/Challenges</p>
    <p>Plagiarism</p>
    <p>Neutral agent to collect papers and analyze for overlap</p>
    <p>Get multiple organizations to buy in</p>
    <p>Reviewer database</p>
    <p>Neutral agent to collect feedback, and if someone gets multiple negative reports, somehow blacklist</p>
    <p>See Internet Computing columns Sept-Oct/NovDec 2007</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
