<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Daniel Gildea, Min-Yen Kan, Nitin Madnani, Christoph Teichmann, Martin Villalba</p>
    <p>The ACL Anthology Current State and Future Directions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summarize the history and current state of efforts related to the Anthology</p>
    <p>Illustrate the challenges of maintaining a community Project</p>
    <p>Invite the community to extend the capabilities of the Anthology</p>
    <p>Call you to join the Anthology team</p>
    <p>HistorySummary Future-proofing Upcoming Future</p>
    <p>What is this presentation about?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Anthology in summary</p>
    <p>HistorySummary Future-proofing Upcoming Future</p>
    <p>Open access service for all ACL-Sponsored publications</p>
    <p>Also hosts posters and additional data  Paper search and author pages  45K papers and 4.5K daily hits  Open Source  Maintained by volunteers  New papers added in collaboration</p>
    <p>with proceedings editors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HistorySummary Future-proofing Upcoming Future</p>
    <p>A brief History of the Anthology  Proposed in 2001 by Steven Bird</p>
    <p>First version online in 2002, with Steven Bird as editor</p>
    <p>Min-Yen Kan becomes the new editor in 2008</p>
    <p>A new version of the Anthology with extra functionality is released in 2012</p>
    <p>Hosting of the Anthology moves from the National University of Singapore to Saarland University</p>
    <p>Steven Bird Min-Yen Kan</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary Future-proofing Upcoming FutureHistory</p>
    <p>How to Future-proof the Anthology</p>
    <p>Challenges  Limited resources for day-to-day code maintenance  Dependencies become outdated  Maintainer churn</p>
    <p>Solutions  Docker container for easier set-up and sandboxing  Collaborative documentation efforts to ease</p>
    <p>onboarding  Migration plan on the pipeline, including upgrades</p>
    <p>and test cases</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Upcoming major steps</p>
    <p>HistorySummary Future-proofing Upcoming Future</p>
    <p>Hosting the Anthology within the main ACL website</p>
    <p>Recruit a new Anthology editor</p>
    <p>(possibly) pay for extra support for the Anthology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exercise: Importing of your slides</p>
    <p>HistorySummary Future-proofing Upcoming Future</p>
    <p>We import slides, datasets, videos from your own</p>
    <p>Currently done by email (try it yourself! yes, now)</p>
    <p>Better workflow: pull request against the Anthology XML ( la csrankings.org)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Possible future directions</p>
    <p>HistorySummary Future-proofing Upcoming Future</p>
    <p>Contains useful information both for CL researchers and about CL researchers. Useful for identifying suitable reviewers.</p>
    <p>Move focus from day-to-day operations towards development</p>
    <p>Establish a network of mirrors</p>
    <p>Host anonymized pre-prints</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HistorySummary Future-proofing Upcoming Future</p>
    <p>Come and visit our poster</p>
    <p>Comments? Questions?</p>
    <p>Ideas for future directions?</p>
    <p>Interested in joining the Anthology team?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
