<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Probing the Front Lines: Pollworker Perceptions of</p>
    <p>Security &amp; Privacy</p>
    <p>Hall (NYU), Barabas, Shapiro, Cheshire, Mulligan (UC Berkeley)</p>
    <p>EVT/WOTE12  August 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation  Methodology  Findings  Discussion/Recommendations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Pollworkers literally are the front line  Much scrutiny of machines, processes  Relatively little study of pollworkers  Training is important!  But not everyone is trained. :(</p>
    <p>Voter confidence / pollworker perceptions  Integrity of voting systems, processes are at</p>
    <p>the mercy of pollworker competence</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Goal: explore voters mental models of polling place security and privacy.</p>
    <p>Two-part qualitative methodology:  Observe issues in a live election  Interview pollworkers about those issues.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Note on Qualitative Methods</p>
    <p>Our reviewers need a primer on qualitative methods.</p>
    <p>Qualitative methods seek to discover phenomena, not measure them.  Rarely test hypotheses  Rarely result in generalizable findings  But help us know where to look further!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology: Observations</p>
    <p>Sought to observe a wide range of polling places in a single county</p>
    <p>Observed 4 polling places: 2 high SES and 2 low SES</p>
    <p>Spend about 2 hours at each  Observers trained to notice security and</p>
    <p>privacy issues</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology: Interviews</p>
    <p>Interviewed 20 pollworkers from observed, plus 4 additional sites</p>
    <p>First, primed interviewees  Second, lead them through 10 vignettes  Third, general questions about security</p>
    <p>and privacy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings: Observations</p>
    <p>Leadership Models  Site 1: Micromanaged hierarchy  Site 2: Anarchy!!!  Site 3: Delegated hierarchy  Site 4: Cooperative, network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings: Observations</p>
    <p>Security and Privacy issues  Open auxiliary scanner door  Misplaced scanner head  Managing auxiliary bin overflow  Photography in the polling place  Smartphone usage in the polling place  Pollworkers looking at marked ballot faces</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Close-up: Auxiliary Bin</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Close-up: Tamper Seal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings: Interviews</p>
    <p>Security Perceptions  Pollworkers not familiar with security issues  Except for two-person rule</p>
    <p>Dont understand why we seal  Dont view the scanner as vulnerable asset  First order security is physical safety  Chain-of-command is not important  Created their own modifications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings: Interviews</p>
    <p>Privacy Perceptions  Much more intuitive grasp of privacy  Desire to help can trump privacy  Clearly had problems with photography  Mixed perceptions of smartphones</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>Security vs. Privacy:  Security: distributed value, rarely triggered  Privacy: is more individual, often encounter  Smartphones are reference tools  Worrisome in terms of undue influence  Is influence is gone from collective memory?</p>
    <p>Ad-hoc reactions could be useful  Not clear how to train/develop such skills</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>Leadership models  With just four sites, we saw four models!  Correlated with S&amp;P issues</p>
    <p>Leadership model seems to drive how Chief PI seeks to instill a sense of trust in actors.</p>
    <p>Hierarchy controls and centralizes risk  Micromanagement can undermine team trust</p>
    <p>Cooperative seems promising  But lacks clear checks and balances</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations</p>
    <p>Training designed around risks, not just managing bureaucracy  Team needs to be trained to recognize risks</p>
    <p>to privacy and security</p>
    <p>Leadership models may be key  Only need to train one leader very well to</p>
    <p>manage delegation</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
