<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Hybrid Touch Interface</p>
    <p>for Prt  Voter</p>
    <p>Chris Culnane, University of Surrey</p>
    <p>Trustworthy Voting Systems Project</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>Brief Introduction to Prt  Voter  Motivation  Hybrid Touch Concept  Implementation Prototypes  Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voting in Prt  Voter</p>
    <p>Fill in ballot form  Detach and destroy Left Hand Side  Submit Right Hand Side to the system (scan)  Receive signed receipt from Web Bulletin</p>
    <p>Board (WBB)</p>
    <p>Right Hand Side is published on WBB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Properties</p>
    <p>Privacy  The Right Hand Side does not reveal how you voted</p>
    <p>No machine learns how you voted</p>
    <p>End-to-end verifiability  Voters can check the inclusion of their vote  3rd parties can check each operation</p>
    <p>Strong integrity guarantees  Accessibility?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accessibility of Voting in the UK</p>
    <p>Limited  Tactile Voting Device (2001)</p>
    <p>Polls Apart Campaign  Reports after each election</p>
    <p>Works with Electoral Commission</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Accessibility is a requirement of any new voting scheme in the UK</p>
    <p>Round table discussion with Polls Apart 2010  Polls Apart Report 2010 recommendation:</p>
    <p>Ensure disabled people can vote independently and in secret by diversifying voting methods...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>We often have to make a pragmatic choice about accessibility and privacy</p>
    <p>If we want the system to help the voter cast their vote, it generally has to learn how they vote</p>
    <p>Can we develop a front-end, for Prt  Voter, which does not compromise on privacy?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Previous Ideas</p>
    <p>Previously suggestions have been to line up a left hand side paper ballot with a touch screen</p>
    <p>Not really usable, let alone accessible</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hybrid Touch Concept</p>
    <p>Maintains the concept of two halves of a ballot paper</p>
    <p>Left hand side is paper based  Right hand side is digital</p>
    <p>rendered on a touch screen or Surface Computer</p>
    <p>How it works:  Detect location and orientation of left hand side  Render right hand side in appropriate location  User interacts by touching virtual right hand side</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What are the advantages?</p>
    <p>Machine does not learn how voter has voted  Additional accessibility equipment can be</p>
    <p>added to assist in the vote casting (Large</p>
    <p>buttons, sip and puff, voice control, etc.)</p>
    <p>Automatic validation of correct entry  No scanners</p>
    <p>No need to interpret human handwriting/OCR</p>
    <p>The process of voting is entirely completed within the booth</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation - Microsoft Surface</p>
    <p>Natural User Interface  Interacting with everyday objects  Microsoft Surface consists of:</p>
    <p>direct interaction</p>
    <p>multi-touch contact (50 touches)  a multi-user experience</p>
    <p>object recognition via Identity Tags</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How Does Microsoft Surface Work?</p>
    <p>http://www.popularmechanics.com/technology/industry/4217348.html?page=2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Microsoft Surface  Ballot Paper</p>
    <p>Easy to construct  Standard Prt  Voter ballot paper</p>
    <p>Additional Identity Tag on underside  Contains same information as Right Hand Side</p>
    <p>barcode</p>
    <p>Identity Tag used for orientation and location</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Front Back</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Microsoft Surface</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation - Microsoft Surface</p>
    <p>Expensive  approximately 10,000  Large and immobile</p>
    <p>Practical issues of locating them  No easy way to adjust height</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>3M Multi-Touch can handle 20 touches (M2256PW)</p>
    <p>Similar technology as on modern mobile phones  Two layers of perpendicular wires</p>
    <p>A charge is applied creating capacitance at the intersections</p>
    <p>Bringing a finger or conductive stylus within the electrostatic field causes a change in the capacitance</p>
    <p>This change is used to identify the location of the touch</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Projected Capacitance Technology</p>
    <p>How we could use it:  Use conductive ink/foil marks on the underside to</p>
    <p>simulate touches</p>
    <p>Define a template of simultaneous touches that indicate a ballot (currently a rectangle of a specific</p>
    <p>size)</p>
    <p>Use these touches to determine location and orientation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Projected Capacitance</p>
    <p>Foil backed card</p>
    <p>Conductive foam pads (6mm)  Able to locate and orientate a left hand side</p>
    <p>Display virtual right hand side</p>
    <p>Screen</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Projected Capacitance Ballot</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Projected Capacitance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Projected Capacitance</p>
    <p>Cheaper and more flexible  Currently still need to scan a barcode to</p>
    <p>acquire serial number</p>
    <p>Looking into using multiple conductive pads in a sparse matrix on the underside to provide that</p>
    <p>information</p>
    <p>Ballot paper is more difficult to construct</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Microsoft Surface  Version 2</p>
    <p>Samsung SUR40 with Microsoft PixelSense  Only 103mm thick</p>
    <p>Can be mounted on an arm for adjustment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Developed an interface that provides some accessibility without compromising privacy</p>
    <p>Proof of concept  Microsoft Surface  Multi-touch screen</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Further work needed to polish user interface  Reduce size of conductive pads  User Trials</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>QUESTIONS?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
