<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sequential Hypothesis Testing</p>
    <p>under Stochastic Deadlines</p>
    <p>Peter Frazier, Angela Yu</p>
    <p>Princeton University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sequential</p>
    <p>Hypothesis</p>
    <p>Testing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>under</p>
    <p>Stochastic</p>
    <p>Deadlines</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Peter Frazier &amp; Angela Yu</p>
    <p>Princeton University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We consider the sequential hypothesis testing problem and generalize the sequential probability ratio test (SPRT) to the case with stochastic deadlines.</p>
    <p>This causes reaction times for correct responses to be faster than for errors, as seen in behavioral studies.</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Both decreasing the deadlines mean and increasing its variance causes more response urgency.</p>
    <p>Results extend to the general case with convex continuation cost.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sequential Hypothesis Testing</p>
    <p>A B A B A B</p>
    <p>wait wait</p>
    <p>At each time, the subject decides whether to act (A or B), or collect more information. This requires balancing speed vs. accuracy.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We observe a sequence of i.i.d. samples x1,x2,... from some density.</p>
    <p>The underlying density is unknown, but is known to equal either f0 or f1.</p>
    <p>We begin with a prior belief about whether f0 or f1 is the true density, which we update through time based on the samples.</p>
    <p>We want to maximize accuracy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Let  be the index of the true distribution.  Let p0 be the initial belief, P{=1}.  Let pt := P{=1 | x1,...,xt}.  Let c be a cost paid per-sample.  Let d be a cost paid to violate the deadline</p>
    <p>(used later)  Let  be time-index of the last sample</p>
    <p>collected.  Let  be the guessed hypothesis.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Posterior probabilities may be calculated via Bayes Rule:</p>
    <p>pt = f 1 (x t )pt  1</p>
    <p>f 1 (xt )pt  1 +f 0 (xt )pt  1 .</p>
    <p>Time (t)</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>b ab</p>
    <p>ility (p</p>
    <p>t)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>inf;P f 6= g+ c &lt;  &gt;</p>
    <p>Probability of Error</p>
    <p>Time Delay Penalty</p>
    <p>The objective function is:</p>
    <p>where we require that the decisions  and  are non-anticipative, that is, whether  &lt;= t is entirely determined by the samples x1,...,xt, and  is entirely determined by the samples x1,...,x.</p>
    <p>Objective Function</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Time (t)</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>b ab</p>
    <p>ility ( p</p>
    <p>t)</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>Optimal Policy (SPRT)</p>
    <p>Wald &amp; Wolfowitz (1948) showed that the optimal policy is to stop as soon as p exits an interval [A,B], and to choose the hypothesis that appears more likely at this time.</p>
    <p>This policy is called the Sequential Probability Ratio Test or SPRT.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A classic sequential hypothesis testing task is detecting coherent motion in random dots. One hypothesis is that monkeys and people behave optimally and according to the SPRT.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(Roitman &amp; Shadlen, 2002)</p>
    <p>Broadly speaking, the model based on the classic SPRT fits experimental behavior well.</p>
    <p>Accuracy vs. Coherence Reaction Time vs. Coherence</p>
    <p>There is one caveat, however</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accuracy Mean RT RT Distributions</p>
    <p>(Data from Roitman &amp; Shadlen, 2002; analysis from Ditterich, 2007)</p>
    <p>SPRT fails to predict the difference in response time distributions between correct and error responses. Correct responses are more rapid in experiments. SPRT predicts they should be identically distributed.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deadlines</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(Data from Roitman &amp; Shadlen, 2002)</p>
    <p>(Analysis from Ditterich, 2006)</p>
    <p>Monkeys occasionally abort trials without responding, but it is always better to guess than to abort under the assumed objective function.</p>
    <p>To explain the discrepancy, we hypothesize a limit on the length of time that monkeys can fixate the target.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>inf;P f 6= ;  &lt; Dg+ c &lt;  &gt; +d P f   Dg</p>
    <p>Error Penalty Deadline Penalty</p>
    <p>Hypothesizing a decision deadline D leads to a new objective function:</p>
    <p>Time Penalty</p>
    <p>We will assume that D has a non-decreasing failure rate, i.e. P{D=t+1 | D&gt;t} is non-decreasing in t.</p>
    <p>This assumption is met by deterministic, normal, gamma, and exponential deadlines, and others.</p>
    <p>Objective Function</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The resulting optimal policy is to stop as soon as pt exits a region that narrows with time.</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>b ab</p>
    <p>il it</p>
    <p>y (</p>
    <p>p t )</p>
    <p>Generalized SPRT</p>
    <p>Classic SPRT Deadline</p>
    <p>Time (t)</p>
    <p>Optimal Policy</p>
    <p>= inff t  0 j pt =2 C t g</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reaction Time</p>
    <p>F re</p>
    <p>q u</p>
    <p>e n</p>
    <p>cy o</p>
    <p>f O</p>
    <p>cc u</p>
    <p>rr e</p>
    <p>n c e</p>
    <p>Correct Responses Error Responses</p>
    <p>Under this policy, correct responses are generally faster than error responses.</p>
    <p>Response Times</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Influence of the Parameters Deadline Uncertainty Deadline Mean</p>
    <p>Time Penalty Deadline Penalty</p>
    <p>Plots of the continuation region Ct (blue), and the probability of a correct response P{=|=t} (red). D was gamma distributed, and the default settings were c=.001, d=2, mean(D)=40, std(D)=1. In each plot we varied one while keeping the others fixed.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theorem: The continuation region at time t for the optimal policy, Ct, is either empty or a closed interval, and it shrinks with time (Ct+1  Ct).</p>
    <p>Proposition: If P{D&lt;1} = 1 then there exists a T &lt; 1 such that CT = ;. That is, the optimal reaction time is bounded above by T.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proof Sketch</p>
    <p>Lemma 1: The continuation cost of the optimal policy, Q(t,p), is concave as a function of p.</p>
    <p>Q(t  1; pt 1)  Q(t; pt)  c.</p>
    <p>Lemmas 2 and 3: Wasting a time period incurs an opportunity cost in addition to its immediate cost c.</p>
    <p>Q(t; 0) = Q(t; 1) = c(t + 1) + d P f D = t + 1 j D &gt; tg</p>
    <p>Lemma 4: If we are certain which hypothesis is correct (p=0 or p=1), then the optimal policy is to stop as soon as possible. Its value is:</p>
    <p>Define Q(t,pt) to be the conditional loss given pt of continuing once from time t and then behaving optimally.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ct+1</p>
    <p>Proof Sketch</p>
    <p>Ct</p>
    <p>p0 1</p>
    <p>E xp</p>
    <p>e c te</p>
    <p>d L</p>
    <p>o s s</p>
    <p>Q(t+1,p)-c</p>
    <p>Q(t,p)</p>
    <p>min(p,1-p)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References</p>
    <p>Elementary Mental Org. Oxford Univ. Press. 5. Mozer et al (2004). Proc. Twenty Sixth Annual Conference of</p>
    <p>the Cognitive Science Society. 981-86. 6. Poor, H V (1994). An Introduction to Signal Detection and</p>
    <p>Estimation. Springer-Verlag. 7. Ratcliff, R &amp; Rouder, J N (1998). Psychol. Sci. 9: 347-56. 8. Roitman J D, &amp; Shadlen M N (2002). J. Neurosci. 22: 9475</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
