<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Efficient Multidimensional Blocking for Link Discovery without losing Recall</p>
    <p>Robert Isele , Freie Universitt Berlin</p>
    <p>Anja Jentzsch, Freie Universitt Berlin</p>
    <p>Christian Bizer, Freie Universitt Berlin</p>
    <p>Web and Databases, Athens, Greece, June 12, 2011</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Problem Statement</p>
    <p>MultiBlock</p>
    <p>Silk Link Discovery Framework</p>
    <p>Evaluation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem</p>
    <p>The Web of Data is a single global data space because data sources are connected by links</p>
    <p>28 billion triples published as Linked Open Data and growing</p>
    <p>But:</p>
    <p>Less than 400 million links</p>
    <p>Most publishers only link to one other dataset</p>
    <p>http://lod-cloud.net/state/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interlinking Data Sources</p>
    <p>Tools enable data publishers to set links</p>
    <p>Most tools generate links based on user-defined link specifications</p>
    <p>A link specification typically aggregates several different similarity measures.</p>
    <p>Naive solution: Evaluate the link specification for the complete cartesian product</p>
    <p>Not feasable for large datasets</p>
    <p>Idea: Dismiss definitive non-matches prior to comparison</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Requirements</p>
    <p>Linked Data is heterogenous and uses a variety of datatypes</p>
    <p>Should be flexible</p>
    <p>We dont want to lose recall</p>
    <p>No false dismissals</p>
    <p>Some similarity measures are no metrics (e.g. Jaro-Winkler )</p>
    <p>Support non-metric similarity measures</p>
    <p>Linked Data application architectures usually want to integrate a incoming stream of entities (e.g. Silk Server)</p>
    <p>Should not require any pre- or postprocessing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparison</p>
    <p>Method Lossless Non-Metrics Online</p>
    <p>Traditional Blocking No Yes Yes</p>
    <p>Sorted-Neighborhood No Yes No</p>
    <p>Sorted Blocks No Yes No</p>
    <p>FastMap No No No</p>
    <p>MetricMap No No No</p>
    <p>SparseMap No No No</p>
    <p>StringMap No No No</p>
    <p>Modified SparseMap Yes No No</p>
    <p>MultiBlock Yes Yes Yes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MultiBlock</p>
    <p>Map all entities to a multidimensional space preserving the distances of the entities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Approach</p>
    <p>Defines the workflow of the indexing</p>
    <p>Does not define a specific similarity measure or aggregation</p>
    <p>Instead: Defines the properties a similarity measure/aggregation must</p>
    <p>adhere to</p>
    <p>Can be plugged into the general framework</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Indexing Workflow</p>
    <p>Index Generation</p>
    <p>Build an index for each similarity measure in the link specification</p>
    <p>Idea: Preserve the distances of the entities</p>
    <p>Index Aggregation</p>
    <p>Aggregate all indexes into one compound multidimensional index</p>
    <p>Comparison Pair Generation</p>
    <p>Generate a comparison pair for each two entities which share an index</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Index Generation</p>
    <p>Generate an (multidimensional) index for each similarity measure</p>
    <p>Basic function of a similarity measure:</p>
    <p>Indexing function:</p>
    <p>All similarity measures must adhere to:</p>
    <p>(For all entities ,  and a threshold  )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Index aggregation</p>
    <p>Aggregate all indices into a single compound index</p>
    <p>Example:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparison pair generation</p>
    <p>Generate pairs based on overlapping blocks</p>
    <p>Two entities which share the same block will be compared:</p>
    <p>* ,  ;  =  ,     ,     ,   ,   +</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Silk Link Discovery Framework</p>
    <p>Open source link discovery framework, running on all major platforms</p>
    <p>Flexible, declarative language for specifying link conditions</p>
    <p>Scalability and high performance through efficient data handling</p>
    <p>Reduction of network load by caching and reusing of SPARQL result</p>
    <p>sets</p>
    <p>Multi-threaded computation of the data item comparisons</p>
    <p>Blocking of data items using MultiBlock</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Link Conditions</p>
    <p>Specify which conditions two entities must fulfill in order to be interlinked.</p>
    <p>A link condition is expressed as a combination of:</p>
    <p>RDF paths</p>
    <p>Similar to SPARQL 1.1 Property Paths</p>
    <p>Examples:</p>
    <p>?movie/dbpedia:director/rdfs:label</p>
    <p>?person/label[@lang=en]</p>
    <p>Transformations</p>
    <p>Transforms the result set of an RDF paths</p>
    <p>Variety of built-in transformations</p>
    <p>Examples:</p>
    <p>LowerCase</p>
    <p>RegexReplace</p>
    <p>Stem</p>
    <p>Similarity Metrics</p>
    <p>Similarity of two inputs based on a userdefined metric.</p>
    <p>Examples:</p>
    <p>Various string similarity metrics</p>
    <p>Geographic similarity</p>
    <p>Date similarity</p>
    <p>Aggregations</p>
    <p>Aggregates multiple similarity metrics</p>
    <p>Examples:</p>
    <p>Min, Max, Average</p>
    <p>Quadratic Mean</p>
    <p>Geometric Mean</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>&lt;LinkCondition&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Aggregate type=&quot;average&quot;&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Compare metric=&quot;levenshtein&quot; &gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Input path=&quot;?a/rdfs:label[@lang='en']&quot;/&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Input path=&quot;?b/rdfs:label[@lang='en']&quot;/&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Param name=&quot;maxDistance&quot; value=&quot;10&quot;/&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/Compare&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Compare metric=&quot;wgs84&quot; required=&quot;true&quot;&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Input path=&quot;?a/wgs84:geometry&quot;/&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Input path=&quot;?b/wgs84:geometry&quot;/&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Param name=&quot;unit&quot; value=&quot;km&quot;/&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Param name=&quot;threshold&quot; value=&quot;50&quot;/&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/Compare&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/Aggregate&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/LinkCondition&gt;</p>
    <p>Compare city names</p>
    <p>Aggregate</p>
    <p>results</p>
    <p>Silk  Linking Specification</p>
    <p>Compare coordinates</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Silk Versions</p>
    <p>Silk Single Machine</p>
    <p>Generate links on a single machine</p>
    <p>Local or remote data sets</p>
    <p>Silk MapReduce (from Silk 2.2)</p>
    <p>Generate RDF links using a cluster of multiple machines</p>
    <p>Based on Hadoop (Can be run on Amazon Elastic MapReduce)</p>
    <p>Silk Server (from Silk 2.1)</p>
    <p>Provides an HTTP API for matching instances from an incoming</p>
    <p>stream of RDF data while keeping track of known entities</p>
    <p>Can be used as an identity resolution component within</p>
    <p>applications that consume Linked Data from the Web</p>
    <p>Can be used for instance together with a Linked Data crawler to</p>
    <p>populate a local duplicate-free cache with data from the Web</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Silk Linking Engine</p>
    <p>Loading</p>
    <p>Loads the data from the configured data sources</p>
    <p>Supported sources: SPARQL endpoints. Planned: RDF dumps</p>
    <p>MultiBlock</p>
    <p>Indexes the instances. Only instances with the same index will be matched.</p>
    <p>This avoids matching the complete Cartesian product.</p>
    <p>Matching</p>
    <p>Computes a similarity value for each pair of instances from the same cluster.</p>
    <p>The similarity value is based on a user-defined link condition.</p>
    <p>Filtering</p>
    <p>Removes all links with a lower confidence than the user-defined threshold</p>
    <p>Only a limited number of links from the same subject are yielded</p>
    <p>Output</p>
    <p>Writes the generated links to a user-defined destination</p>
    <p>Supported formats: N-Triples, OAEI Alignments, Planned: EDOAL Alignments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Evaluation</p>
    <p>Interlinking 204,109 settlements from DBpedia and 530,606 settlements from LinkedGeoData</p>
    <p>Compared MultiBlock with traditional blocking by labels with an overlapping factor of 0.2</p>
    <p>MultiBlock reduces the number of comparisons by a factor of 2,875 and is over 700 times faster than the full evaluation</p>
    <p>Method Comparisons Runtime (*) Links</p>
    <p>Full Evaluation 108,301,460,054 305,188s 70,037</p>
    <p>Blocking, 100 blocks 3,349,755,846 22,453s 69,403</p>
    <p>Blocking, 1000 blocks</p>
    <p>MultiBlock 37,667,462 420s 70,037</p>
    <p>* 3GHz Intel(R) Core i7 CPU with 4 core and 8GB of RAM.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>MultiBlock uses a multidimensional index to increase its efficiency significantly</p>
    <p>It guarantees that no false dismissals can occur</p>
    <p>It does not require the similarity space to form a metric space</p>
    <p>MultiBlock has been implemented as part of the Silk Link Discovery Framework</p>
    <p>Speedup factor of several 100 for large datasets compared to the full evaluation without losing recall</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks!</p>
    <p>Get Silk from: http://www4.wiwiss.fu-berlin.de/bizer/silk</p>
    <p>This work was supported in part by Vulcan Inc. as part of its Project Halo</p>
    <p>(www.projecthalo.com) and by the EU FP7 project LOD2 - Creating Knowledge out</p>
    <p>of Interlinked Data (http://lod2.eu/, Ref. No. 257943).</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
