<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modelling Protagonist Goals and Desires in First-Person Narrative Elahe Rahimtoroghi, Jiaqi Wu, Ruimin Wang, Pranav Anand and Marilyn A Walker</p>
    <p>University of California Santa Cruz</p>
    <p>NSF IIS 1302668, Nuance SC14-74, NSF HCC 1321102</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  Humans appear to organize and remember everyday</p>
    <p>experiences by imposing a narrative structure on them</p>
    <p>Thus many genres of natural language exhibit narrative structure</p>
    <p>Widely agreed that narrative understanding requires</p>
    <p>Modelling protagonist goals</p>
    <p>Tracking their outcomes</p>
    <p>First person social media stories full of expressions of desires and outcome descriptions</p>
    <p>First-person blog story</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>First Person Story: Live Journal</p>
    <p>I dropped something and it was dark, he bent with his cell phone light to help me look for it. We spoke a little, but it was loud and not suited for conversation there. I had hoped to ask him to join me for a drink or something after the show (if my courage would allow such a thing) but he left before the end and I didnt see him after that. Maybe Ill try missed connections lol.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goal</p>
    <p>Identify goal and desire expressions in first-person narratives</p>
    <p>E.g. had hoped to</p>
    <p>Infer from the surrounding text whether the desire is</p>
    <p>Fulfilled</p>
    <p>Unfulfilled</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>First Person Story: Live Journal</p>
    <p>I dropped something and it was dark, he bent with his cell phone light to help me look for it. We spoke a little, but it was loud and not suited for conversation there. I had hoped to ask him to join me for a drink or something after the show (if my courage would allow such a thing) but he left before the end and I didnt see him after that. Maybe Ill try missed connections lol.</p>
    <p>Unfulfilled</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>First Person Desires</p>
    <p>People did seem pleased to see me but all I [wanted to] do was talk to a particular friend.</p>
    <p>I [wished to] meet new people and to get out of my own made misery and turn myself into a more sociable human being for the sake of mental health alone.</p>
    <p>I'm off this weekend and had really [hoped to] get out and dance.</p>
    <p>We [decided to] just go for a walk and look at all the sunflowers in the neighborhood.</p>
    <p>I [couldn't wait to] get out of our cheap and somewhat charming hotel and show James a little bit of Paris.</p>
    <p>We drove for just over an hour and [aimed to] get to Trinity beach to set up for the night.</p>
    <p>She called the pastor, and he had time, too, so, we [arranged to] meet Saturday at 9am.</p>
    <p>Even though my deadline wasn't until 4 p.m., I [needed to] write the story as quickly as possible.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>First Person Story: Live Journal</p>
    <p>I dropped something and it was dark, he bent with his cell phone light to help me look for it. We spoke a little, but it was loud and not suited for conversation there. I had hoped to ask him to join me for a drink or something after the show (if my courage would allow such a thing) but he left before the end and I didnt see him after that. Maybe Ill try missed connections lol.</p>
    <p>Unfulfilled</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Computational model of Lehnerts plot units (Goyal and Riloff, 2013)</p>
    <p>Identify and track affect states to model plot units</p>
    <p>Dataset: Aesops fables  Manual annotation: examine different</p>
    <p>types of affect expressions in the narratives</p>
    <p>Affect states arise from the expression of goals and their outcomes</p>
    <p>Model desire fulfillment (Chaturvedi et al., 2016)</p>
    <p>MCTest: 660 crowd-sourced stories understandable by 7-year olds</p>
    <p>SimpleWiki: Simple English Wikipedia</p>
    <p>Desire statements: matching three verb phrases (wanted to, hoped to, and wished to)</p>
    <p>Context: five or fewer sentences following the desire expression</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions  New Corpus: DesireDB</p>
    <p>3,500 first-person informal narratives with annotations  Download: https://nlds.soe.ucsc.edu/DesireDB</p>
    <p>Modeling goals and desires  Classification models: Predict desire fulfillment status  Feature analysis  Study the effect of prior and post context in predicting desire fulfillment  Compare to previous models and datasets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DesireDB Corpus</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Patterns for Desires and Goals  Many different linguistic ways to express desires</p>
    <p>FrameNet 1.7: Needing, Offer, Purpose, Request, ...</p>
    <p>Frequent and high-precision representative instances in English Gigaword</p>
    <p>37 verbs  constructed past forms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Collection</p>
    <p>Extracted 600K stories containing the verbal patterns of desire</p>
    <p>Desire-Expression Sentence</p>
    <p>Prior-Context (Labov &amp; Waletzky, 67)</p>
    <p>Post-Context</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Annotations  Sample 3,680 instances for annotation  16 verbal patterns  Sample skewed as per distribution in the original dataset</p>
    <p>Mechanical Turk  Specified the desire expression verbal pattern using square brackets in the data  3 Prequalified workers per instance  Label the desire expression sentence based on the prior and post context:</p>
    <p>Fulfilled, Unfulfilled, and Unknown from the context  Mark a span of text as the evidence for the label they had chosen</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Creating Gold-Standard Data</p>
    <p>Total agreement rate</p>
    <p>Fulfilled  75%</p>
    <p>Unfulfilled  67%</p>
    <p>Unknown from the context  41%</p>
    <p>Marking evidence</p>
    <p>79% of the data all three annotators marked overlapping spans</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DesireDB Data Instance</p>
    <p>Testbed for modeling desires in personal narrative and predicting their fulfillment</p>
    <p>Open domain first-person narratives</p>
    <p>Prior and post context</p>
    <p>Reliable annotations</p>
    <p>Download: https://nlds.soe.ucsc.edu/DesireDB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modeling Desire Fulfillment  Define feature sets motivated by narrative structure</p>
    <p>Some features motivated by prior work</p>
    <p>Classification experiments  LSTM models to generate sentence embeddings  Three-layer RNN classifier  Feature analysis  Explore using different parts of context  Comparison to previous work (both models and datasets)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Desire Expression Features</p>
    <p>Properties of the desire expression</p>
    <p>Desire verb pattern</p>
    <p>Focal words and their synonym/antonym mentions in the context</p>
    <p>Desire subject and its mentions</p>
    <p>First-person subject 17</p>
    <p>Eventually, I just decided to speak, and I can't even remember what I said, but people were very happy and proud of me for saying what I wanted to say.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discourse Features</p>
    <p>Discourse relation markers in the Penn Discourse Treebank as:</p>
    <p>Violated-Expectation (31): e.g. although, rather, yet, but</p>
    <p>Meeting-Expectation (15): accordingly, so, ultimately, finally</p>
    <p>Neutral : none of these appear 18</p>
    <p>I wanted to regroup and prepare for battle so I laid him down while I pseudo relaxed.</p>
    <p>I wanted to do visual editing and management very much, but one of the core courses is such that it requires a prereq.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Features</p>
    <p>Connotation Features</p>
    <p>Connotation Lexicon (Feng et al., 2013)</p>
    <p>Polarity agreement of context words with focal words  Connotation-Agree  Connotation-Disagree</p>
    <p>So, we decided to go together and play backgammon in between loads.I usually win at the game and today was no exception. We had a fine time.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sentiment Flow Features</p>
    <p>Detect a change in sentiment in the surrounding context</p>
    <p>Could be the mention of a thwarted effort or a victory  Sentiment-Agree  Sentiment-Disagree</p>
    <p>N eg at iv e</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Classification Models  Four types of features</p>
    <p>Motivated by narrative characteristics  Ablation experiments</p>
    <p>Method  LSTM for sentence embeddings  Three-layer RNN for classification</p>
    <p>Suitable for sequence learning  Encode the order of the sentences to distinguish between prior and post</p>
    <p>context</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Generating Sentence Embeddings  Two approaches</p>
    <p>Skip-Thought: Using pre-trained skip-thought model (Kiros et al., 2015) as the embeddings  Concatenates features, if any, with embeddings  Uses LSTM to generate a single representation</p>
    <p>CNN-RNN: Using 1-dimensional convolution with max-over-time pooling introduced (Kim, 2014) to generate the sentence embedding  Uses LSTM to generate a single representation  Used Google News Vectors (Mikolov et al., 2013) for word embedding</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LSTM with Skip-Thoughts Embeddings &amp; RNN Classifier</p>
    <p>... Evidence sentences embeddings using Skip- Thought vectors</p>
    <p>Desire sentence embedding using Skip-Thoughts vectors</p>
    <p>LSTM</p>
    <p>Classification Output</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments  A subset of DesireDB: Simple-DesireDB</p>
    <p>In order to compare more directly to previous work</p>
    <p>Five verbal patterns  wanted to, hoped to, wished to, couldnt wait to, decided to</p>
    <p>Fulfilled: 1,366</p>
    <p>Unfulfilled: 953</p>
    <p>Train (1,656), Dev (327), and Test (336) sets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Classification Experiments: Study the Robustness of Features</p>
    <p>BOW: Bag of Words features</p>
    <p>ALL: All four sets of features</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Effects of Prior and Post Context</p>
    <p>Using best-performing model</p>
    <p>Skip-Thoughts embeddings</p>
    <p>ALL features</p>
    <p>Adding features from prior context alone improves the results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments on DesireDB</p>
    <p>Comparing BOW, ALL, and Discourse features (best among 4 sets)</p>
    <p>Baselines: Logistic Regression (best-performing on Dev set), Naive Bayes, and SVM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Identifying Unfulfillment is Harder</p>
    <p>Similar features and methods achieve better results for the Fulfilled class as compared to Unfulfilled</p>
    <p>Same in annotations  Data labeled Fulfilled by two annotators</p>
    <p>64% labeled Unknown from the context  only 36% labeled Unfulfilled</p>
    <p>Data labeled Unfulfilled  49% labeled Unknown from the context  51% labeled Fulfilled</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparison to Previous Work Datasets</p>
    <p>Previous work methods (Chaturvedi et al., 2016)  BOW  Logistic Regression  Structured Model: LSNM (best</p>
    <p>performing)</p>
    <p>Our methods:  LR with Discourse features  Skip-thought embeddings</p>
    <p>BOW features  ALL features</p>
    <p>Results on Fulfilled Class</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>DesireDB corpus: to study goals and their fulfillment in narrative discourse</p>
    <p>Modeling goals fulfillment  Features motivated by narrative structure are effective  Both prior and post context are useful</p>
    <p>Future work  Explore richer features  Apply other sequential classification models  Explore using evidence data  Detecting hypothetical goals (e.g., If I had wanted to buy a book)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Creating Gold-Standard Data</p>
    <p>Three annotators assigned to each data instance</p>
    <p>Majority vote to create gold-standard label  Cases with no agreement labeled as None</p>
    <p>Average Kappa between each annotator and the majority vote: 0.88</p>
    <p>66% of the data labeled with total agreement  32% of data was labeled by two agreements and one</p>
    <p>disagreement 32</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
