<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The RDF Book Mashup</p>
    <p>From Web APIs to a Web of Data</p>
    <p>Chris Bizer, Freie Universitt Berlin Richard Cyganiak, Freie Universitt Berlin</p>
    <p>Tobias Gau, Freie Universitt Berlin</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Web APIs</p>
    <p>A growing number of Web data sources provide query APIs.</p>
    <p>ProgrammableWeb.com lists 445 Web APIs</p>
    <p>Most popular Web APIs GoogleMaps GoogleBase Flickr YouTube Amazon eBay Yahoo</p>
    <p>Mashups</p>
    <p>Mashups combine and visualize data from multiple sources.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations of Web APIs</p>
    <p>They provide diverse interfaces using REST or SOAP web services Return XML, JSON or ATOM feeds</p>
    <p>They use proprietary schemata to represent information</p>
    <p>Therefore, Web APIs can not be accessed using generic data browsers their content can not be crawled by search engines Mashups must be implemented against a fixed number of data sources</p>
    <p>Approach to Overcome these Limitations</p>
    <p>Linked Data Principles (Tim Berners-Lee, 2007) 1. Use URIs as names for things 2. Use HTTP URIs so that people can look up those names 3. When someone looks up a URI, provide useful RDF information 4. Include RDF statements that link to other URIs so that they can</p>
    <p>discover related things</p>
    <p>Integrate Web APIs into the Semantic Web via Linked Data wrappers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Benefits of the Linked Data Approach</p>
    <p>Data is accessible to generic data browsers</p>
    <p>Data is accessible to generic data crawlers</p>
    <p>It is possible to interlink data items between data sources</p>
    <p>Clients can work against an un-bound set of data sources</p>
    <p>It is easier to map between different schemata and to use mappings on term level</p>
    <p>The RDF Book Mashup</p>
    <p>is a small PHP script (300 lines of code)</p>
    <p>demonstrates how Web 2.0 data sources like Amazon, Google and Yahoo can be integrated into the Semantic Web</p>
    <p>applies the Linked Data principles to two Web APIs (Amazon and Google Base) which supply information about books.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The RDF Book Mashup</p>
    <p>assigns HTTP URIs to books, authors, reviews, online bookstores and purchase offers</p>
    <p>makes these URIs dereferenceable by querying Google Base API Amazon API</p>
    <p>Architecture of the RDF Book Mashup</p>
    <p>Description of a Book</p>
    <p>&lt;http://www4.wiwiss.fu-berlin.de/bookmashup/books/006251587X&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;scom:Book rdf:about=&quot;/bookmashup/books/006251587X&quot;&gt; &lt;dc:title&gt;Weaving the Web&lt;/dc:title&gt; &lt;dc:creator rdf:resource=&quot;/bookmashup/persons/Tim+Berners-Lee&quot;/&gt; &lt;dc:date&gt;2000-11-01&lt;/dc:date&gt; &lt;dc:format&gt;Paperback&lt;/dc:format&gt; &lt;dc:identifier rdf:resource=&quot;urn:ISBN:006251587X&quot;/&gt; &lt;dc:publisher&gt;Collins&lt;/dc:publisher&gt; &lt;foaf:depiction rdf:resource=</p>
    <p>&quot;http://ec2.images-amazon.com/images/P/006251587X.jpg&quot;/&gt; &lt;rev:hasReview rdf:resource=</p>
    <p>&quot;/bookmashup/reviews/006251587X_EditorialReview1&quot;/&gt; &lt;scom:hasOffer rdf:resource=</p>
    <p>&quot;/bookmashup/offers/006251587XamazonOffer&quot;/&gt; &lt;/scom:Book&gt;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Description of an Author</p>
    <p>&lt;http://www4.wiwiss.fu-berlin.de/bookmashup/persons/Tim+Berners-Lee&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;foaf:Person rdf:about=&quot;/bookmashup/persons/Tim+Berners-Lee&quot;&gt; &lt;foaf:name&gt;Tim Berners-Lee&lt;/foaf:name&gt; &lt;owl:sameAs rdf:resource=</p>
    <p>&quot;http://www4.wiwiss.fu-berlin.de/dblp/resource/person/100007&quot;/&gt; &lt;/foaf:Person&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;scom:Book rdf:about=&quot;/bookmashup/books/006251587X&quot;&gt; &lt;dc:creator rdf:resource=&quot;/bookmashup/persons/Tim+Berners-Lee&quot;/&gt; &lt;rdfs:label&gt;Weaving the Web&lt;/rdfs:label&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/scom:Book&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;scom:Book rdf:about=&quot;/bookmashup/books/8432310409&quot;&gt; &lt;dc:creator rdf:resource=&quot;/bookmashup/persons/Tim+Berners-Lee&quot;/&gt; &lt;rdfs:label&gt;Tejiendo La Red - El Inventor del WWW&lt;/rdfs:label&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/scom:Book&gt;</p>
    <p>Use Cases</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UC1: Annotate HTML Pages with Book Mashup URIs</p>
    <p>UC2: Enrich other Data Sources Mashup Data</p>
    <p>Example: DBpedia community effort to extract structured information from Wikipedia make this information available on the Web under an open license interlink the DBpedia dataset with other datasets on the Web</p>
    <p>Contributors Freie Universitt Berlin (Germany) Universitt Leipzig (Germany) OpenLink Software (UK) Linking Open Data Community (W3C SWEO)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extracting Infobox Data</p>
    <p>&lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Calgary&gt;</p>
    <p>dbpedia:native_name Calgary ;</p>
    <p>dbpedia:altitude 1048 ;</p>
    <p>dbpedia:population_city 988193 ;</p>
    <p>dbpedia:population_metro 1079310 ;</p>
    <p>mayor_name</p>
    <p>dbpedia:Dave_Bronconnier ;</p>
    <p>governing_body</p>
    <p>dbpedia:Calgary_City_Council ;</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>Altogether 9,100,000 RDF triples extracted from 754,000 infoboxes</p>
    <p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calgary</p>
    <p>Multi-Lingual Abstracts</p>
    <p>The dataset contains a short and a long abstract for each concept. Short abstracts</p>
    <p>English: 1,637,622 German: 246,791 French: 206,085 Dutch: 133,746 Polish: 118,874 Italian: 113,950 Spanish: 112,417 Japanese: 106,610 Portuguese: 104,842 Swedish: 100,267 Chinese: 54,991</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The DBpedia Dataset</p>
    <p>including 58,000 persons 70,000 places 35,000 music albums 12,000 films 9,000 books</p>
    <p>described by 93 million triples</p>
    <p>using 8,141 different properties.</p>
    <p>DBpedia is interlinked with the Book Mashup</p>
    <p>RDF Link within the DBpedia dataset</p>
    <p>Altogether 9000 RDF links from DBpedia to the Book Mashup.</p>
    <p>Links are generated automatically using ISBN numbers from within Wikipedia.</p>
    <p>&lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Harry_Potter_and_the_Half-Blood_Prince&gt;</p>
    <p>owl:sameAs</p>
    <p>&lt;http://www4.wiwiss.fu-berlin.de/bookmashup/books/0747581088&gt; .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data from DBpedia and from the</p>
    <p>RDF Book Mashup</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UC3: Form a Part of the Emerging Web of Data</p>
    <p>Over one billion RDF triples served as Linked Data Around 120,000 RDF links between data sources</p>
    <p>Accessing the Web of Data</p>
    <p>Semantic Web Browsers, like DISCO Hyperdata Browser Tabulator Browser OpenLink RDF Browser</p>
    <p>Semantic Web Crawlers, like SWSE (DERI, Ireland) Zitgist (Zitgist LLC, USA) Swoogle (UMBC, USA )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participating in the Linking Open Data Project</p>
    <p>Publish more RDF datasets as Linked Data Interlink your datasets with other datasets</p>
    <p>Wiki Page http://esw.w3.org/topic/SweoIG/TaskForces/CommunityProjects/ LinkingOpenData</p>
    <p>Mailing List http://simile.mit.edu/mailman/listinfo/linking-open-data</p>
    <p>Participating in the project Put your name on the Wiki page Subscribe to the mailing list</p>
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>OpenLink SPONGER and /proxy REST service General framework to wrap Web APIs as Linked Data</p>
    <p>- Extractors, Mappers Already wrapped Data Sources</p>
    <p>- Google Base - Flickr - HTML Web (page meta information/GRDDL??)</p>
    <p>http://docs.openlinksw.com/virtuoso/ rdfsparqlprotocolendpoint.html#rdfproxyservice</p>
    <p>D2R Server Solution for publishing relational databases as Linked Data</p>
    <p>- Declarative Mapping Language Already wrapped Data Sources</p>
    <p>- DBLP Bibliography, Project Gutenberg, CIA World Fact Book, DBtune http://sites.wiwiss.fu-berlin.de/suhl/bizer/d2r-server/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks!</p>
    <p>RDF Book Mashup Website http://sites.wiwiss.fu-berlin.de/suhl/bizer/bookmashup/</p>
    <p>Linking Open Data Project Website http://esw.w3.org/topic/SweoIG/TaskForces/CommunityProjects/ LinkingOpenData</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
