<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Access Characteristic Guided Read and Write Cost Regulation for Performance Improvement on Flash Memory</p>
    <p>Qiao Li, Liang Shi, Chun Jason Xue Kaijie Wu, Cheng Ji, Qingfeng Zhuge, and Edwin H.M. Sha</p>
    <p>p y</p>
    <p>College of Computer Science, Chongqing University Department of Computer Science, City University of Hong Kong</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Background D i Design</p>
    <p>Evaluation  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background  NAND flash memory is widely used from USB to big data centers.</p>
    <p>USB eMMC SSD Data Center</p>
    <p>Flash memory development  bit density: from 1 bit to 6 bits</p>
    <p>Performance bit density: from 1 bit to 6 bits</p>
    <p>technology scaling: from 65nm to 10nm  Performance degradation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flash Write (Programming)  Incremental Step Pulse Programing (ISPP) is used to program Flash page  The program voltage is increased by the step size  Finished when the voltage exceeds the threshold voltage Vth  Program time  write cost RBER: Raw Bit Error Rate</p>
    <p>V h</p>
    <p>finer step size</p>
    <p>higher write cost</p>
    <p>lower RBER</p>
    <p>Vth</p>
    <p>V</p>
    <p>coarser step size lower</p>
    <p>write cost higher RBER</p>
    <p>Write cost is related to RBER (Raw Bit Error Rate) 4</p>
    <p>Vth</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flash Read  LowDensity Parity Code (LDPC) is applied in Flash for strong ECC capability  The decoding strength of LDPC depends on the accuracy of input information</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flash Read  LowDensity Parity Code (LDPC) is applied in Flash for strong ECC capability  The decoding strength of LDPC depends on the accuracy of input information</p>
    <p>To decode data with higher RBER higher read cost is needed Flash read: Step1. Sensing Step2. Transfer</p>
    <p>To decode data with higher RBER, higher read cost is needed. Read cost is related to RBER (Raw Bit Error Rate)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Read and Write Cost Regulation  Read and write costs can be regulated</p>
    <p>lowcost write coarse step size</p>
    <p>highcost write fine step size</p>
    <p>high RBER low RBER</p>
    <p>highcost read LDPC with more</p>
    <p>lowcost read LDPC with less</p>
    <p>LDPC with more reference voltage</p>
    <p>LDPC with less reference voltage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Preliminary Study  Experiments are conducted to investigate the difference between different write</p>
    <p>and read costs in real workloads, including PROJ, USR, HM from MSR  3 combinations of read and write costs are evaluated</p>
    <p>LowCost Write/HighCost Read MediumCost Write/MediumCost Read HighCost Write/LowCost Read</p>
    <p>LCW/HCR MCW/MCR HCW/LCR</p>
    <p>Comparing LCW/HCR and HCW/LCR: Compared to the default MCW/MCR: The performance gap indicates that the read and write</p>
    <p>Normalized Read Latency Normalized Write Latency</p>
    <p>read difference is 114%  write difference is 61%</p>
    <p>HCW/LCR improves read performance by 54%  LCW/HCR improves write performance by 26%</p>
    <p>The performance gap indicates that the read and write cost regulation should be applied carefully</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ideal Case  All reads are performed with lowcost read  All Writes are performed with lowcost write  Ideal but impossible!  How to regulate cost for performance improvement?</p>
    <p>Our approach is based on the access h t i ti f kl dcharacteristic of workloads</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observation  Key Observation of Access Characteristics:</p>
    <p>Most read requests access readonly pages, more than 85% on average!Most read requests access read only pages, more than 85% on average!  Most write requests access writeonly pages, more than 91% on average!  Only a small part of reads and writes access interleavedaccess pages</p>
    <p>Distribution of Reads Distribution of Writes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Approach Access Cost Regulation</p>
    <p>R d l l t dReadonly pages  lowcost read Writeonly pages  lowcost write Interleavedaccess pages  mediumcost access (default)</p>
    <p>Identification ReWrite</p>
    <p>Identify readonly pages and writeonly pages</p>
    <p>The cost of read is determined by the write on the data.</p>
    <p>Re rite read onl pages that</p>
    <p>Rewrite readonly pages that are accessed by highcost read.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Access Characteristic Identification  Access history per page</p>
    <p>R R WR W W WR W R W</p>
    <p>History window</p>
    <p>R R WR W W WR W R W    readonly writeonly interleavedaccess</p>
    <p>Upcoming access + most recent access  Rewrite Readonly pages with highcost during idle time  Each mapping entry in the FTL is extended with two fields Each mapping entry in the FTL is extended with two fields</p>
    <p>1bit lowcost write tag, and the access history</p>
    <p>Physical Page Address</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments  Simulator: SSDSim [15][16]  12 workloads from MSR [17]  8 channels, 8 chips per channel and 4 planes per chip  Default FTL, page mapping, garbage collection and wear leveling  Comparing these 3 techniques</p>
    <p>Traditional: Normal Flash without Cost Regulation  Li et. al: Cost Regulation for Access Conflict Minimization  AGCR : The Proposed Technique</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment Results  Read and write performance are evaluated.</p>
    <p>Normalized Read Latency Normalized Write Latencyy y</p>
    <p>Compared to the stateoftheart approach:  AGCR improves read performance by 32% on average</p>
    <p>And at the same time  AGCR improves write performance by 22% on average</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment Results  The distributions for operations of different costs.</p>
    <p>C i t Li t l  k AGCR i id bl l t Comparing to Li et al.s work, AGCR issues considerably more lowcost reads and writes</p>
    <p>The percentage of re write operations is no more than 1% of all The percentage of rewrite operations is no more than 1% of all accesses issued by the host</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Identification Accuracy  Impact of window size on identification accuracy.</p>
    <p>Only Upcoming Request Upcoming Request + Most Recent RequestUpcoming Request + Most Recent Request Upcoming Request + Two Most Recent Requests</p>
    <p>The Identification method achieves high accuracy Identification Accuracy(%)</p>
    <p>The Identification method achieves high accuracy.  A larger window results in higher accuracy.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion Preliminary Study Observation</p>
    <p>We presented a preliminary study to show the potential performance improvement of our approach.</p>
    <p>We made the observation that most reads (writes) access read only (writeonly) pages.</p>
    <p>Approach Evaluation</p>
    <p>We proposed a comprehensive approach to regulate the cost of reads and writes.</p>
    <p>Results show that the proposed approach achieves significant performance improvement.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Th k !Thank you!</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
