<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flash Reliability in Produc4on: The Expected and the Unexpected</p>
    <p>Bianca Schroeder University of Toronto</p>
    <p>Raghav Lagisetty, Arif Merchant Google Inc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why flash?  More and more data is living on flash =&gt; data reliability depends on flash reliability  Worry about flash wear-out</p>
    <p>LiGle prior work on produc'on systems  Lab studies using accelerated tes4ng  Only one field study (Sigmetrics15)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Google fleet</p>
    <p>of error types</p>
    <p>Data on repairs, replacements, bad blocks &amp; bad chips</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Percentage of drives replaced annually due to suspected hardware problems over the first 4 years in the field:</p>
    <p>~1-2% of drives replaced annually, much lower than hard disks!  0.5-1.5% of drives developed bad chips per year</p>
    <p>Would have been replaced without methods for toleraBng chip failure</p>
    <p>MLC-A MLC-B MLC-C MLC-D SLC-A SLC-B SLC-C SLC-D</p>
    <p>Average annual replacement</p>
    <p>rates for hard disks (2-20%)</p>
    <p>Pe rc en</p>
    <p>ta ge (%</p>
    <p>)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Timeout error</p>
    <p>Meta error</p>
    <p>Final write error</p>
    <p>Uncorrectable error</p>
    <p>Erase error</p>
    <p>Write retry</p>
    <p>Read retry</p>
    <p>Correctable error</p>
    <p>Tr an sp ar en</p>
    <p>t er ro rs</p>
    <p>N on</p>
    <p>-t ra ns pa re nt</p>
    <p>er ro rs</p>
    <p>..</p>
    <p>..</p>
    <p>Percentage of drives with errors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Timeout error</p>
    <p>Meta error</p>
    <p>Final write error</p>
    <p>Uncorrectable error</p>
    <p>Erase error</p>
    <p>Write retry</p>
    <p>Read retry</p>
    <p>Correctable error</p>
    <p>Non-transparent errors common:  26-60% of drives with uncorrectable errors  2-6 out of 1,000 drive days experience uncorrectable errors  Much worse than for hard disk drives (3.5% experiencing sector errors)!</p>
    <p>Tr an sp ar en</p>
    <p>t er ro rs</p>
    <p>N on</p>
    <p>-t ra ns pa re nt</p>
    <p>er ro rs</p>
    <p>..</p>
    <p>..</p>
    <p>Percentage (%) of drives with errors</p>
    <p>Symptoms of bad blocks or</p>
    <p>bad chips</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Wear-out (limited program erase cycles)  Technology (MLC, SLC)  Lithography  Age  Workload</p>
    <p>What reliability metric to use?  Raw bit error rate (RBER)  Probability of uncorrectable errors  Why not UBER? We shall see</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Common expecta4on: Exponen4al increase of RBER with PE cycles</p>
    <p>--- Exponential growth</p>
    <p>PE cycles</p>
    <p>R B E R</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Big differences across models (despite same ECC)  Linear rather than exponential increase  No sudden increase after PE cycle limit</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Common expecta4on: Lower error rates under SLC ($$$) than MLC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RBER is lower for SLC drives than MLC drives  Uncorrectable errors are not consistently lower for SLC drives  SLC drives dont have lower rate of repairs or replacement</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Common expecta4on: Higher error rates for smaller feature size</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Smaller lithography =&gt; higher RBER  Lithography has no clear impact on uncorrectable errors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lab studies demonstrate workload induced error modes  Read disturb errors  Program disturb errors  Incomplete erase opera4ons</p>
    <p>Evidence of read disturb affecting RBER for some models  No effect of erases and writes</p>
    <p>Workload does not affect uncorrectable errors  UBER (uncorrectable bit error rate) is not a meaningful metric</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Different RBER for same model in different clusters  Other factors at play</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The main purpose of RBER is as a metric for overall drive reliability</p>
    <p>Allows for projec4ons on uncorrectable errors</p>
    <p>[Mielke2008]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Drives (or drive days) with higher RBER dont have higher frequency of uncorrectable errors</p>
    <p>RBER is not a good predictor of field reliability  Uncorrectable errors caused by other mechanisms than corr. errors?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prior errors highly predictive of later uncorrectable errors  Potential for prediction?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Significant rate of non-transparent errors  Higher than hard disk drives  To some degree predictable  Need to protect against those!</p>
    <p>Many aspects different from expecta4ons  Linear rather than exponen4al increase with PE cycles  RBER not predic4ve of non-transparent errors  SLC not generally more reliable than MLC</p>
    <p>Many other results not covered in talk   Bad chips, bad blocks, factory bad blocks, rate of repair and replacement,</p>
    <p>comparison of projec4ons with field RBER,</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
