<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Improving Prediction Accuracy of Matrix Factorization Based Network Coordinate</p>
    <p>Systems</p>
    <p>Yang Chen1, Peng Sun2, Xiaoming Fu1, Tianyin Xu1,3</p>
    <p>yang.chen@cs.uni-goettingen.de</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction and Related Work  Study on Prediction Accuracy for Short Links  System Design of Pancake  Performance Evaluation  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Distance (RTT) estimation can be used to optimize large scale distributed systems (P2P systems):  Server selection  Application level multicast/anycast  Overlay Routing  BitTorrent (P2P File Sharing)</p>
    <p>Problems with direct measurement:  Bad scalability: slow, high overhead</p>
    <p>measurementsNN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background (cont.)</p>
    <p>Network Coordinate (NC) systems: Lightweight and Scalable Internet distance prediction  Only requires O(N) measurements to predict the</p>
    <p>distances  Just like a uniform, lightweight, high scalability real-time</p>
    <p>Internet Map with open API</p>
    <p>NN</p>
    <p>B. Donnet, B. Gueye, M. A. Kaafar. A Survey on Network Coordinates Systems, Design, and Security. In IEEE Communication Surveys and Tutorial, accepted for publication.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>SIGCOMM Vivaldi Secure NC</p>
    <p>Htrae</p>
    <p>SIGMETRICS Suitability of Euclidean Embedding</p>
    <p>Sequoia</p>
    <p>NSDI Pyxida Peerwise</p>
    <p>IMC ICS, VL IDES Accuracy of Embedding s</p>
    <p>TIV aware NC</p>
    <p>Stable &amp; Secure NC</p>
    <p>RTT and TIV variation</p>
    <p>USENIX ATC NPS Census, Veracity</p>
    <p>CoNEXT Attack on Vivaldi/NPS</p>
    <p>INFOCOM GNP BBS Overlay/Tree Construction</p>
    <p>Min-plus NC for bandwid th</p>
    <p>NC for Hops</p>
    <p>ICDCS PIC Pyxida, 2-level GNP</p>
    <p>Hyperbol ic Vivaldi</p>
    <p>Networking SVivaldi HVivaldi Phoenix, TIV Detection, Pyxida Measureme nt</p>
    <p>NC System | NC Security | Accuracy &amp; Triangle Inequality Violation (TIV) | Other Network Parameters | Deployment | Applications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Euclidean distance model</p>
    <p>dN</p>
    <p>N d</p>
    <p>NN</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>N</p>
    <p>tMeasuremenNO NN</p>
    <p>rrr</p>
    <p>rrr</p>
    <p>rrr</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>M</p>
    <p>)(</p>
    <p>The ith row denotes the NC of host i</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>j k</p>
    <p>i kji</p>
    <p>E</p>
    <p>i k</p>
    <p>i d</p>
    <p>ii i</p>
    <p>rrxxjiM</p>
    <p>dkRrrrrx</p>
    <p>),(</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Triangle Inequality Violation (TIV)</p>
    <p>M(A,C)+M(C,B)&lt;M(A, B) ME(A,C)+ME(C,B)&gt;ME(A, B)</p>
    <p>Any three hosts with TIV cannot be embedded into Euclidean space within some level of accuracy, for the distances among them in Euclidean space must obey triangle inequality.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Matrix Factorization (MF) based NC systems</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>j k</p>
    <p>i kji</p>
    <p>E</p>
    <p>i k</p>
    <p>i d</p>
    <p>ii i</p>
    <p>i k</p>
    <p>i d</p>
    <p>ii i</p>
    <p>T</p>
    <p>dN</p>
    <p>N d</p>
    <p>NN</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>dN</p>
    <p>N d</p>
    <p>NN</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>T</p>
    <p>dNNdNN</p>
    <p>NN</p>
    <p>dNNdNN</p>
    <p>rementO(N) Measu NC System</p>
    <p>NN</p>
    <p>YXjiM</p>
    <p>dkRYg vectorl incomindimensionad</p>
    <p>dkRXg vectorl outgoindimensionad</p>
    <p>host iThe NC of</p>
    <p>Y</p>
    <p>Y</p>
    <p>Y</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>M</p>
    <p>dN</p>
    <p>Y</p>
    <p>Y</p>
    <p>Y</p>
    <p>and</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>M</p>
    <p>),(</p>
    <p>M(i,j) represents the measured distance from host i to host j ME(i,j) represents the predicted distance from host i to host j</p>
    <p>Internet distance matrix has low rank nature [Tang et al., ACM IMC03]</p>
    <p>ME(A,C)+ME(C,B)&gt;ME(A, B)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimization Goal &amp; Existing Systems</p>
    <p>Overall Optimization Goal</p>
    <p>Existing Systems  IDES (IMC 04, JSAC 06)  Phoenix (Networking 09)  DMF (Networking 10)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Metric</p>
    <p>Relative Error  RE of the distance between host i and host j is defined</p>
    <p>as</p>
    <p>where smaller RE indicates higher prediction accuracy. When the predicted distance equals to the measured distance, the RE value will be 0.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main Focus</p>
    <p>Prediction accuracy is vital for NC systems  Breakthrough point</p>
    <p>Relationship between link distance and relative error  MF based NC: Poor prediction accuracy of short links,</p>
    <p>i.e., the distances less than or equal to 50ms</p>
    <p>We observed similar phenomenon while improving all the three MF based NC systems using our approach Only the results with Phoenix are shown in this paper</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relative Error of Short Links</p>
    <p>Phoenix (All Links) Vivaldi (All Links) Phoenix (Short Links) Vivaldi (Short Links)</p>
    <p>Target: reduce the prediction error of short links without increasing the prediction error of other links</p>
    <p>* Vivaldi (ACM SIGCOMM04) is the most widely NC system so far, which is based on Euclidean distance model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Local Phoenix vs Global Phoenix</p>
    <p>Which way is more accurate??</p>
    <p>Suppose applications only interested in a subset of hosts, i.e., hosts in Germany</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Decentralized Groupping</p>
    <p>Group these N hosts into u clusters in a decentralized way  Step 1: The u hosts are selected randomly as anchors</p>
    <p>among all N hosts, which will guide the decentralized clustering.</p>
    <p>Step 2: For each ordinary host, it will measure its distance to every anchor and join the cluster represented by the nearest anchor.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Median Distances: Intra and Inter Clusters</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Local Phoenix vs Global Phoenix (cont.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Design of Pancake</p>
    <p>Prediction of Intra Cluster Link: Local NC</p>
    <p>Prediction of Inter Cluster Link: Global NC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithm</p>
    <p>Every even round</p>
    <p>Every odd round</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extra Measurement Overhead</p>
    <p>For each ordinary host  measure its RTTs to every anchor once per hour  Compared with the measurement overhead for the NC</p>
    <p>calculation, it is negligible</p>
    <p>For the anchors  Anchors just need to be able to reply the ICMP PING</p>
    <p>passively, this causes very light load to the anchors  One million ordinary hosts in the system, the load of</p>
    <p>each anchor is approximately 2700 PINGs per second</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Evaluation</p>
    <p>Relative Error of Distance Prediction  Convergence Behavior of Pancake  Evaluation through Dynamic Data Set</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relative Error</p>
    <p>DataSet Pancak e</p>
    <p>Phoenix Pharos Vivaldi</p>
    <p>PL 0.50 0.67 0.73 0.92</p>
    <p>King 0.33 0.41 0.44 0.50</p>
    <p>Dimension= 8, Reference Hosts = 32, Anchor Number = 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Convergence Behavior of Pancake</p>
    <p>Compared with Phoenix, Pancake converges faster and the stabilized prediction error is smaller</p>
    <p>Fair Comparison Phoenix: each update round, its NC will be updated once Pancake: each update round, Pancake will only update either its global NC or its local NC, instead of updating both of them</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation through Dynamic Data Set</p>
    <p>D1,1(t1) D1,2(t3) D1,3(t1)</p>
    <p>D2,1(t2) D2,2(t1) D2,3(t3)</p>
    <p>D3,1(t3) D3,2(t2) D3,3(t1)</p>
    <p>Aggregate Data Set (min or median): The elements of the data matrix are taken at different time for the simulation</p>
    <p>Reflect the real time RTT values in the matrices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation through Dynamic Data Set (cont.)</p>
    <p>Pancake Phoenix Pharos Vivaldi</p>
    <p>Average 90th RE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main Contributions</p>
    <p>Intra Cluster MF based NC  Forming clusters in a decentralized way based on locality  Employing MF based NC algorithms such as Phoenix in local</p>
    <p>clusters achieves better prediction accuracy for intra-cluster links than merely relying on global NC algorithms.</p>
    <p>Pancake System  A two-level NC system which can significantly improve the prediction</p>
    <p>accuracy of existing NC systems  Compatible with existing deployments  Negligible extra communication overhead for end users</p>
    <p>Extensive Evaluation  Evaluation based on widely used real Internet data sets  Evaluation based on dynamic data set which reflects the RTT</p>
    <p>variations over time for all end-to-end links (first work to consider RTT variations)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Theoretical study  Understand why the local NC can have better</p>
    <p>prediction accuracy</p>
    <p>Better decentralized clustering algorithm  Forming the clusters effectively and understand the</p>
    <p>relationship between cluster forming and prediction accuracy</p>
    <p>Applications  Potential applications: download mirror selection,</p>
    <p>match making in online gaming, server placement, etc</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Backup Slides</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Triangle Inequality Violation (TIV)</p>
    <p>D(A,C)+D(C,B)&lt;D(A, B) DE(A,C)+DE(C,B)&gt;DE(A, B)</p>
    <p>Any three hosts with TIV cannot be embedded into Euclidean space within some level of accuracy, for the distances among them in Euclidean space must obey triangle inequality.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
