<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Towards Automated Performance Towards Automated Performance Diagnosis in a Large IPTV NetworkDiagnosis in a Large IPTV Network</p>
    <p>Ajay Ajay MahimkarMahimkar, , ZihuiZihui GeGe, , AmanAman ShaikhShaikh, , JiaJia Wang, Wang, Jennifer Yates, Yin Zhang, Jennifer Yates, Yin Zhang, QiQi ZhaoZhao</p>
    <p>UTUT--Austin and AT&amp;T LabsAustin and AT&amp;T Labs--ResearchResearch mahimkar@cs.utexas.edumahimkar@cs.utexas.edu</p>
    <p>ACM ACM SigcommSigcomm 20092009 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Internet Protocol Television Internet Protocol Television (IPTV)(IPTV)</p>
    <p>Television delivered through IP network  Encoded in series of IP packets</p>
    <p>Rapid deployment by telecom companies  New services: quadruple-play (digital voice, TV, data &amp; wireless)  More flexibility and interactivity for users</p>
    <p>One of the largest commercial IPTV deployments in US  By 2008, more than 1 million customers spanning 4 time-zones  Supports advanced features</p>
    <p>Digital video recording (DVR), Video on demand (VoD)  High definition (HD) channels, Choice programming</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IPTV Service ArchitectureIPTV Service Architecture</p>
    <p>SHO</p>
    <p>VHO</p>
    <p>IO</p>
    <p>CO</p>
    <p>DSLAM</p>
    <p>Customer Home Network</p>
    <p>Pr ov</p>
    <p>id er</p>
    <p>N et</p>
    <p>w or</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>Servers</p>
    <p>RG</p>
    <p>PC</p>
    <p>STB</p>
    <p>TVPhone</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IPTV CharacteristicsIPTV Characteristics  Stringent constraints on reliability and performance</p>
    <p>Small packet loss or delay can impair video quality</p>
    <p>Scale  Millions of devices (routers, servers, RG, STB)  Number is growing</p>
    <p>Complexity  New service  New application for native IP multicast  Operational experience with IP multicast is limited</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem StatementProblem Statement  Characterize faults and performance in IPTV networks</p>
    <p>What are the dominant issues?  Is there spatial correlation between different events?  Is there daily pattern of events?</p>
    <p>Detect and troubleshoot recurring conditions  Temporal  repeating over time  E.g., recurring poor picture quality at TV</p>
    <p>Spatial  re-occurring across different spatial locations  E.g., software crashes at multiple set-top-boxes within a region</p>
    <p>Lots of alarms. How do you identify recurring conditions of interest to network operators?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IPTV Measurement DataIPTV Measurement Data  Customer care call records</p>
    <p>Trouble tickets related to billing, provisioning, service disruption</p>
    <p>Home network performance / activities  User activities: STB power on/off, STB resets, RG reboots  Performance/Faults: STB software crashes</p>
    <p>Provider network performance  Syslogs at SHO, VHO  SNMP (CPU, memory, packet counts) at SHO, VHO, IO, CO  Video quality alarms at monitors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IPTV CharacterizationIPTV Characterization</p>
    <p>Data analyzed over 3 months</p>
    <p>Customer Trouble Tickets  Performance related issues  Sample Live TV video tickets  Blue screen on TV  Picture freezing  Poor video quality</p>
    <p>Small degree of spatial correlation</p>
    <p>Ticket</p>
    <p>Live TV Video</p>
    <p>Requested info</p>
    <p>DVR</p>
    <p>Remote control</p>
    <p>Equipment</p>
    <p>High definition (HD)</p>
    <p>Audio</p>
    <p>Program guide</p>
    <p>Video on demand (VoD)</p>
    <p>Parental Control Decreasing in frequency.</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Daily Pattern of EventsDaily Pattern of Events</p>
    <p>Lot of activity between: - 00:00 and 04:00 GMT (evening prime time) - 12:00 and 23:59 GMT (day time)</p>
    <p>Relatively quiet period between - 4:00 and 12:00 GMT (customers are sleeping) - Number of syslogs at SHO/VHO is high. (provisioning and maintenance)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GizaGiza  First multi-resolution infrastructure</p>
    <p>Detect and troubleshoot spatial locations that are experiencing serious performance problems</p>
    <p>Detection  Output locations (e.g. VHO, or STB) that have significant event counts</p>
    <p>Troubleshooting  Output list the other event-series that are the potential root-causes</p>
    <p>Giza Symptom</p>
    <p>E.g., video quality degradation</p>
    <p>Root-causes for symptom E.g., STB Crash</p>
    <p>Spatial locations E.g., VHO or Customer network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mining ChallengesMining Challenges  Massive scale of event-series</p>
    <p>Each device (SHO, VHO, RG) can generate lots of event-series  Blind mining could easily lead to information snow of results</p>
    <p>Skewed event distribution  Small frequency counts for majority of events  Insufficient sample size for statistical analysis</p>
    <p>Heavy hitters do not contribute to majority of issues</p>
    <p>Imperfect timing information  Propagation delay: From event location to measurement process  Distributed events: From root of tree (SHO) towards RG</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GizaGiza</p>
    <p>Symptom</p>
    <p>Other Network Events</p>
    <p>Hierarchical Heavy Hitter</p>
    <p>Detection</p>
    <p>Root-Causes for Symptom</p>
    <p>Spatial locations</p>
    <p>(scalability and skewed event distribution )</p>
    <p>(Event impact) (Imperfect timing)</p>
    <p>(Sparsity)</p>
    <p>Spatial Proximity</p>
    <p>Model</p>
    <p>Unified Data Model</p>
    <p>Statistical Correlation</p>
    <p>(Filter irrelevant events)</p>
    <p>Learn Edge Directionality</p>
    <p>Remove Spurious EdgesCausality Discovery</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hierarchical Heavy Hitter Hierarchical Heavy Hitter DetectionDetection</p>
    <p>Identify spatial regions where symptom count is significant  E.g., customers in Texas have poor</p>
    <p>video quality</p>
    <p>Significance test  Account for (i) event frequency and</p>
    <p>(ii) density concentration  Null hypothesis: children are drawn</p>
    <p>independently and uniformly at random from lower locations</p>
    <p>SHO</p>
    <p>VHO</p>
    <p>IO</p>
    <p>CO</p>
    <p>DSLAM</p>
    <p>STB / RG</p>
    <p>IPTV Pyramid Model</p>
    <p>Region</p>
    <p>Metro</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Causal Graph DiscoveryCausal Graph Discovery  First, learn edge directionality  Idea: use approximate timing to test statistically precedence</p>
    <p>Using lag correlation  Compute cross-correlations at different time-lags  Compare range of positive lags with negative lags</p>
    <p>Addresses  Imperfect timing  Auto-correlation within each event-series</p>
    <p>Second, condense correlation graph  Idea: identify smallest set of events that best explains symptoms</p>
    <p>Using L1-norm minimization and L1-regularization  L1-regularization achieves sparse solution</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>A statistically precedes B</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Giza ExperimentsGiza Experiments  Validation</p>
    <p>Select customer trouble tickets as input symptom  Apply Giza to identify potential root causes  Ground truth: mitigation actions in customer trouble tickets  Result: Good match between ground truth and Giza output</p>
    <p>Case Study: Provider network events  Identify dependencies with customer trouble tickets  Result: Giza discovered unknown causal dependency</p>
    <p>Causality Discovery Comparison  Ground truth: networking domain knowledge  Result: Giza performs better than WISE (Sigcomm08)</p>
    <p>Majority of tickets explained by home network issues</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study: Provider Network Case Study: Provider Network EventsEvents</p>
    <p>Layer-1 Alarms</p>
    <p>VRRP Packet Discards</p>
    <p>Link Down</p>
    <p>Configuration Changes</p>
    <p>OSPF Interface State Down</p>
    <p>Multicast (PIM) Neighbor Loss</p>
    <p>MPLS Interface State ChangesSAP Port</p>
    <p>State Changes</p>
    <p>SDP Bind State Changes</p>
    <p>MPLS Path Re-routes</p>
    <p>VRRP Packet Discards</p>
    <p>Multicast (PIM) Neighbor Loss</p>
    <p>- Dependency between VRRP packet discards and PIM timeouts was unknown - Behavior more prevalent within SHO and VHOs near SHO - We are investigating with operations team</p>
    <p>Shadow edges are spurious correlations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparison to Related Comparison to Related LiteratureLiterature</p>
    <p>Sherlock Kandula et al. Sigcomm07</p>
    <p>WISE Tariq et al. Sigcomm08</p>
    <p>Orion Chen et al. OSDI08</p>
    <p>NICE Mahimkar et al.</p>
    <p>CoNEXT08</p>
    <p>NetMedic Kandula et al. Sigcomm09</p>
    <p>Giza Mahimkar et al.</p>
    <p>Sigcomm09</p>
    <p>Original Focus Enterprise Networks</p>
    <p>Content Distribution Networks</p>
    <p>Enterprise Networks</p>
    <p>ISP Backbone Networks</p>
    <p>Enterprise Networks</p>
    <p>IPTV Networks</p>
    <p>Eliminate spurious dependencies</p>
    <p>YES YES</p>
    <p>Achieve sparse solution</p>
    <p>YES</p>
    <p>Automated edge directionality</p>
    <p>YES YES YES YES YES</p>
    <p>Multi-resolution analysis</p>
    <p>YES</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ConclusionsConclusions  First characterization study in operational IPTV networks</p>
    <p>Home networks contribute to majority of performance issues</p>
    <p>Giza - Multi-resolution troubleshooting infrastructure  Hierarchical Heavy Hitter detection to identify regions  Statistical correlation to filter irrelevant events  Lag correlation to identify dependency directionality  L1-norm minimization to identify best explainable root-causes</p>
    <p>Validation and case studies demonstrate effectiveness</p>
    <p>Future Work  Troubleshooting home networks  Network-wide change detection 17</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You !</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
