<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dissecting Video Server Selection Strategies in the YouTube CDN</p>
    <p>Ruben Torres, Alessandro Finamore, Marco Mellia, Maurizio Munaf and Sanjay Rao</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Video Traffic is Dominant</p>
    <p>More than 20% of the Internet traffic is video  Popularity of video-on-demand services</p>
    <p>New ways to access video (mobile devices,etc)  Critical to characterize this new trend</p>
    <p>Cisco Visual Networking Index 2010</p>
    <p>Video Others</p>
    <p>Sandvine Global Broadband Phenomena 2009</p>
    <p>Video Other</p>
    <p>Arbor Networks 2009</p>
    <p>Video Other</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The main source of video on the Internet</p>
    <p>3 billion videos viewed per day **  48 hours of videos uploaded every minute **  100's of thousand videos uploaded daily **  3rd most popular website after Google and Facebook</p>
    <p>[Alexa Ranking]  20-30% of all incoming traffic in some of our datasets</p>
    <p>**http://youtube-global.blogspot.com/2011/05/thanks-youtube-community-for-two-big.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Internet Video Distribution</p>
    <p>ISP1 ISP2 ISP3</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>v</p>
    <p>Typical CDN design</p>
    <p>What factors affect server selection in the YouTube CDN?</p>
    <p>How do these factors affect user performance?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why is this Work Important?</p>
    <p>Motivation for the design of new architectures for video delivery</p>
    <p>Stepping stone for what-if analysis:</p>
    <p>Changes in DC placement, video popularity distribution or video quality:</p>
    <p>How may ISP traffic patterns be impacted?</p>
    <p>What is the impact on user performance?  Inform ISPs of YouTube traffic patterns and user</p>
    <p>performance, which may not be obvious to operators</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions of this Work  Shed some light on the mechanisms used by YouTube to direct</p>
    <p>clients to content servers:</p>
    <p>DNS based load balancing</p>
    <p>Application layer redirections</p>
    <p>Unlike prior work, we show that latency between clients and DCs plays a role in server selection</p>
    <p>Several other factors can play a role:</p>
    <p>Load balancing</p>
    <p>Popular videos causing hot spots</p>
    <p>Availability of rare content</p>
    <p>DNS server queried</p>
    <p>Show the impact server selection has on user performance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Unique Datasets from Large Networks</p>
    <p>Week-long traffic traces from 5 large networks in September 2010</p>
    <p>Deep Packet Inspection (DPI) with Tstat  Associates TCP flow with YouTube video that triggers it</p>
    <p>Extracts per video information (video ID, resolution, duration, size)</p>
    <p>Details</p>
    <p>Simultaneous collection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Finding DC Locations</p>
    <p>Data Center Locations</p>
    <p>Previously used techniques do not work</p>
    <p>Reverse lookup on servers' IP addresses does not provide any information [IMC2010]</p>
    <p>Maxmind and IP2location locate most servers in California [NOSSDAV2008]</p>
    <p>Active measurement-based methodology to find DC locations</p>
    <p>Used CBG [ToN 2007]  Based on RTT and triangulation  Median error &lt; 100 km</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Closest DC Serves Most Videos but there are Exceptions</p>
    <p>Unlike published work [NOSSDAV'08,IMC'10], RTT does play a role on DC selection</p>
    <p>More interestingly, there are departures from the RTT policy:</p>
    <p>For EU2, traffic splits mostly between two DCs</p>
    <p>For other networks, 10%-15% of traffic comes from far DCs</p>
    <p>Some traffic was served by other DCs</p>
    <p>Traffic from the preferred DC</p>
    <p>DCs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mechanisms for Accesses to Non-preferred DCs</p>
    <p>Local DNS</p>
    <p>ISP</p>
    <p>Application-level redirection sends the client to a non-preferred DC</p>
    <p>DNS resolution sends the client to a non-preferred DC</p>
    <p>Local DNS</p>
    <p>ISP Non-preferred DC</p>
    <p>video stream</p>
    <p>GET video</p>
    <p>Preferred DC</p>
    <p>redirection</p>
    <p>GET video</p>
    <p>Non-preferred DC video stream</p>
    <p>GET video</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>YouTube Video Sessions  Video Session: group together related video flows</p>
    <p>The same source IP</p>
    <p>The same video ID requested</p>
    <p>Interleaved by less than 1 second</p>
    <p>Small interleave time to group flows triggered by the system</p>
    <p>One flow sessions =&gt; DNS resolution</p>
    <p>Represent 70-80% of all sessions  Two or more flows sessions =&gt; application-level redirection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Effectiveness of DNS in Mapping Requests to the Preferred DC</p>
    <p>In most cases the local DNS maps server names to the preferred DC</p>
    <p>But in EU2, half of the videos downloaded from a non-preferred DC</p>
    <p>Video data from the preferred DC</p>
    <p>Video data from the non-preferred DC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EU2</p>
    <p>DNS-level Load Balancing</p>
    <p>Load Balancing between the Local DC and the external DC affects server selection</p>
    <p>Local DC External DC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Application-level Redirection</p>
    <p>20-30% of sessions in this category  Many redirections to non-preferred DCs</p>
    <p>Hypothesis: Unpopular videos</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Does Video Popularity Causes Application-level Redirection?</p>
    <p>CDF of videos with one or more requests to the non-preferred DC</p>
    <p>Popular videos</p>
    <p>Unpopular videos</p>
    <p>Both popular and unpopular videos cause application-level redirections to non-preferred DCs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Popular Video Flash Crowd</p>
    <p>Redirection occurs due to overload of the preferred server for a popular video</p>
    <p>EU1-ADSL Trace</p>
    <p>Downloads for Video1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Availability of Unpopular Videos  It is not easy to identify unpopular videos in our traces</p>
    <p>Active experiment with Planetlab:</p>
    <p>Nodes around the world download rare video (generated by us)</p>
    <p>Latency measurements (RTT) from each node to the content server</p>
    <p>Experiment repeated every 30 minutes for 12 hours</p>
    <p>Sample Number</p>
    <p>In general, only the first access is to a non-preferred DC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Do Redirections Impact User Performance?</p>
    <p>Two performance metrics:</p>
    <p>RDP &lt; 1, the video stalled</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Large Start Delays on Redirections</p>
    <p>Without redirections, delay in the order of milliseconds  With redirections, delay can increase by orders of</p>
    <p>magnitude, up to 10 seconds!</p>
    <p>S ta</p>
    <p>rt D</p>
    <p>e la</p>
    <p>y [</p>
    <p>s ]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Users Watch Less when Videos Stall</p>
    <p>Downloading from non-preferred DCs may have an impact on user performance</p>
    <p>Users only watch 30-50% of videos with RDP&lt;1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>By extensive measurement we shed light on the infrastructure deployed by YouTube</p>
    <p>Expose modern CDNs mechanism for redirection:</p>
    <p>DNS-level redirection and application-level redirection</p>
    <p>Unlike prior work, we show that latency between clients and DCs plays a role in server selection</p>
    <p>Departing from conventional wisdom, several factors deviates from the latency policy:</p>
    <p>Load balancing, DNS server queried, popular videos causing hot spots, availability of rare content</p>
    <p>Redirections can negatively impact user performance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You! Any Questions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>YouTube videos characterization studies:</p>
    <p>Hill [IMC2007], Cha [IMC2007], Chen [IWQoS2008], Zink [COMNET2009]</p>
    <p>YouTube infrastructure characterization studies</p>
    <p>Saxena [NOSSDAV2008], Adhikari [IMC2010]</p>
    <p>Earlier design was relatively simple</p>
    <p>[NOSSDAV2008]: Most videos served from one data center (DC) located in US</p>
    <p>[IMC 2010]: The DC selection is proportional to the DC size</p>
    <p>New design more mature and complex</p>
    <p>Important to understand state-of-art systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background on YouTube</p>
    <p>GET video</p>
    <p>Video Stream</p>
    <p>v6.lscache4.c.youtube.com</p>
    <p>I want to see this video</p>
    <p>Search: AT&amp;T</p>
    <p>List of videos</p>
    <p>Time Local DNS</p>
    <p>www.youtube.com</p>
    <p>youtube.com authoritative DNS server</p>
    <p>v6.lscache4.c.youtube.com</p>
    <p>Local DNS</p>
    <p>youtube.com authoritative DNS server</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CDF of videos with one or more requests to the non-preferred DC</p>
    <p>CDF of videos with one or more requests to the preferred DC</p>
    <p>CDF of video requests</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Variations Across DNS Servers in a Network</p>
    <p>Depending on the internal DNS server queried, the redirection may be different</p>
    <p>Net-3 DNS servers resolve to a different preferred DC</p>
    <p>US-Campus Trace</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Server Flash Crowd</p>
    <p>Server assigned to popular video gets overloaded</p>
    <p>The number of redirections from this server increases because of the video flash crowd</p>
    <p>EU1-ADSL Trace</p>
    <p>Load on server handling video1</p>
    <p>Client is redirected to the non-preferred DC</p>
    <p>Video is served or client is redirected inside preferred DC</p>
    <p>Other cases</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
