<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conficker and Beyond:</p>
    <p>A Large-Scale Empirical Study</p>
    <p>Seungwon Shin and Guofei Gu</p>
    <p>SUCCESS LAB</p>
    <p>Texas A&amp;M University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contents</p>
    <p>Background  Introduction  Measurement Results  Limitation  Limitation  Summary</p>
    <p>SUCCESS LAB, Texas A&amp;M University 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Botnet  Collection of bots, which runs automatically to</p>
    <p>perform malicious operations</p>
    <p>Most serious threat</p>
    <p>Image from wikipedia</p>
    <p>Why is it serious?  Bot-master (owner of the Botnet)</p>
    <p>has Power  to control huge amount of</p>
    <p>machines</p>
    <p>has Motivation  to earn some money</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Understanding Botnet</p>
    <p>Why is it needed?  If you know the enemy and know yourself, you need</p>
    <p>not fear the result of a hundred battles.</p>
    <p>If we know Botnet, we can</p>
    <p>from Art of War</p>
    <p>If we know Botnet, we can  Discover its current trend  Predict its future trend</p>
    <p>This will give us clues to detect/prevent botnet</p>
    <p>Main goal of this paper  To understand current powerful Botnet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Target</p>
    <p>Conficker  Why ?</p>
    <p>The most recent and powerful  Nov. 2008  Known as infected more than 10 million PCs</p>
    <p>They are still active They are still active  Several companies/organizations are</p>
    <p>trying to remove it</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Conficker binary analysis  SRI [porras et al.,]</p>
    <p>Analyze several variants of Conficker binary  Reveal how it,</p>
    <p>infects victims, evades detection, updates itself and etc.</p>
    <p>Honeynet Project [watson et al.,] Honeynet Project [watson et al.,]  Analyze Conficker binary  Provide scanning tools for detecting Conficker victims</p>
    <p>Conficker victim analysis  CAIDA [http://www.caida.org/research/security/ms08-067/conficker.xml]</p>
    <p>Show Conficker victims propagation (location)  Cymru [kristo et al.,]</p>
    <p>Display Conficker victims distribution on the Internet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What We Want To Provide</p>
    <p>What we want to provide in this work  Large-Scale analysis of Conficker victims</p>
    <p>around 25,000,000 victims</p>
    <p>More detailed analysis of Conficker victims  Cross-comparison with previous popular bots/worms Cross-comparison with previous popular bots/worms  Cross-checking current detection systems  Other notable characteristics of Conficker victims</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Collection</p>
    <p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT : We thank Shadowserver.org and Chris Lee for providing the data of Conficker</p>
    <p>Our Collection : 24,912,492 unique IP address of Conficker victims</p>
    <p>Malware Type Data source Collection time</p>
    <p>Conficker Bot Sinkhole server</p>
    <p>Shadowserver.org</p>
    <p>Jan.1, 2010 - Jan.8, 2010</p>
    <p>Previous Data for Comparison</p>
    <p>Malware Type Data source Collection time</p>
    <p>Botnet 1 [Ramachandran et al.,] Bot Sinkhole server Aug. 2004 - Jan. 2006</p>
    <p>Botnet 2 [Xie et al.,] Bot Hotmail Jun. 2006 - Sep. 2006</p>
    <p>Botnet 3 [Xie et al.,] Bot Spamhaus Nov. 2006 - Jun. 2007</p>
    <p>Waledac [Stock et al.,] Bot Infiltration into Waledac Aug. 2008 - Sep. 2009</p>
    <p>CodeRed [Moore et al.,] Worm Measurement Jul. 2001 - Oct. 2001</p>
    <p>Slammer [Moore et al.,] Worm Measurement Jan. 2003</p>
    <p>Witty [Shannon et al.,] Worm Measurement Mar. 2004</p>
    <p>Previous Data for Comparison</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Who Are Victims ?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distribution Over IP Address Space</p>
    <p>Insight : We may need to monitor a limited number of specific ranges of network, not the whole network, and it might be more efficient</p>
    <p>Result : Conficker victims are concentrated in several specific IP address spaces</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distribution Over ASes - 1</p>
    <p>ASN # Host AS Name Country</p>
    <p>Result : Top 2 ASes account for 28.37% of all victims and top 20 ASes cover 52.16%</p>
    <p>Insight : Focusing on specified ASes may be an efficient way to detect malware</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distribution Over ASes - 2 Conficker Bonet 1 Botnet 2 Botnet 3</p>
    <p>ASN Country ASN Country ASN Country ASN Country</p>
    <p>Result : Top 2 ASes were also sources of previous botnets, but other ASes are newly emerged</p>
    <p>Insight : Infection Trend is changing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distribution Over Domain Names</p>
    <p>Conficker CodeRed Slammer Witty</p>
    <p>Top Level Percentage Top Level Percentage Top Level Percentage Top Level Percentage</p>
    <p>unknown 48.81 unknown 47.22 unknown 59.49 net 33</p>
    <p>br 8.83 net 18.79 net 14.37 com 20</p>
    <p>net 8.65 com 14.41 com 10.75 unknown 15</p>
    <p>cn 6.94 edu 2.37 edu 2.79 fr 3</p>
    <p>ru 5.01 tw 1.99 tw 1.29 ca 2</p>
    <p>it 2.36 jp 1.33 au 0.71 jp 2</p>
    <p>ar 1.54 ca 1.11 ca 0.71 au 2</p>
    <p>in 1.35 it 0.86 jp 0.65 edu 1</p>
    <p>com 1.21 fr 0.75 br 0.57 nl 1</p>
    <p>mx 1.16 nl 0.73 uk 0.57 ar 1</p>
    <p>Result : .net domain is still prevalent, but new CC (country code) domains have recently emerged</p>
    <p>Insight : Watch out ! Newly registered domains</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distribution Over Bandwidth</p>
    <p>Result : Most victims use ADSL or Modem, and low bandwidth networks are more likely to have more Conficker victims</p>
    <p>Insight : Hosts with ADSL or Modem connections are still vulnerable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reputation-based</p>
    <p>Detection SystemsDetection Systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reputation-Based Detection Systems</p>
    <p>Reputation-based detection system  Detect malicious hosts or networks based on their reputation  How to get the reputation</p>
    <p>By using their previous records  Did they host malicious web sites ?  Did they send spam emails ?  Did they try to scan network ? Did they try to scan network ?</p>
    <p>E.g.,  DNS blacklist  FIRE [http://maliciousnetworks.org/]  Dshield [http://www.dshield.org/]</p>
    <p>Question  How well do they detect Conficker infected hosts ?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DNS Blacklist</p>
    <p>What we have tested  DNSBL, SORBS, Spamhaus, and SpamCop  Query all 24,912,492 hosts to them  4,281,069 hosts are on blacklists (only 17.18%) 4,281,069 hosts are on blacklists (only 17.18%)</p>
    <p>Insight : Unfortunately, DNS blacklists are not enough to detect Conficker victims</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FIRE And Dshield</p>
    <p>FIRE  Detect malicious ASes  Most heavily infected ASes by Conficker are not shown in</p>
    <p>the top 500 malicious ASes of FIRE</p>
    <p>Dshield Dshield  Detect malicious hosts or ASes  82,856 (only 0.33%) hosts and 83 ASes (only cover 0.2% of</p>
    <p>victims) are reported by Dshield as malicious</p>
    <p>Insight : FIRE and Dshield did not detect large portions of Conficker victims as well. We may need other complementary detection approach such as anomaly detection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Watch Your Neighbor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infection Preference</p>
    <p>Conficker infection vectors  Infecting random hosts by</p>
    <p>Random network scanning  Infecting nearby hosts by</p>
    <p>Scanning local subnets  Infecting portable storage (USB storage) Infecting portable storage (USB storage)</p>
    <p>Which approach is more effective ?  Some research points out infecting nearby hosts is more</p>
    <p>dominant [Krishana et al.,] [Porras et al.,]</p>
    <p>Question  Is infecting nearby hosts really dominant ?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test For Neighborhood Infection - 1</p>
    <p>Definition  Camp: group of /24 subnets whose /16 subnet is the same and locations are</p>
    <p>close together</p>
    <p>Neighbor: each /24 subnet in the same Camp is a Neighbor to each other</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>Camp (10.11.*.*)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test For Neighborhood Infection - 2</p>
    <p>Test Scenario All Conficker victims</p>
    <p>Camp 1 Camp 2 Camp 3</p>
    <p>Camp n</p>
    <p>/24 /24 /24 /24</p>
    <p>SUCCESS LAB, Texas A&amp;M University 22</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>Camp2</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>How many victims in each /24 subnetHow many victims in each /24 subnet</p>
    <p>Mean and variance of # of victimsMean and variance of # of victims</p>
    <p>Mean = 5.25, Variance = 1</p>
    <p>Find VMR (Variance / Mean)Find VMR (Variance / Mean)</p>
    <p>VMR = 1 / 5.25 = 0.19 &lt;&lt; 1</p>
    <p>If VMR is less than 1, they are evenly distributed,</p>
    <p>and this represents each /24 network in the Camp</p>
    <p>has similar number of infected victims</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test Results</p>
    <p>Within distance # of all Camps # of Camps whose /24 subnet members are</p>
    <p>similar to each other (VMR &lt; 1)</p>
    <p>~ 100km 85,246 62,121 (72.87%)</p>
    <p>~ 200km 65,748 44,633 (67.88%)</p>
    <p>~ 300km 54,415 36,495 (67.06%)</p>
    <p>Insight : From this result, we think that a large portion of victims are infected by their neighbor hosts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can We Use This More ?  Based on this knowledge, we propose a Conficker prediction approach</p>
    <p>Employ K-NN (K-Nearest Neighbor) (K =3, in this experiment)  Detection granularity</p>
    <p>/24 subnet  Define class</p>
    <p>Benign : /24 subnet which does not have any infected hosts  Malicious : /24 Subnet which has Conficker infected hosts</p>
    <p>How to define nearest  Physical Distance between each subnet Physical Distance between each subnet</p>
    <p>SUCCESS LAB, Texas A&amp;M University 24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24 /24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24 Benign subnet</p>
    <p>Malicious subnet</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24 /24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24 Test subnet</p>
    <p>/24</p>
    <p>/24</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Detection Result</p>
    <p>Data for training and evaluation  20 % for training (randomly selected)  Other 80 % for evaluation</p>
    <p>Detection Accuracy TP rate FP rate</p>
    <p>SUCCESS LAB, Texas A&amp;M University 25</p>
    <p>Insight : Watching neighborhood can help us predict unknown malicious networks</p>
    <p>And this insight implies that further research is needed for developing new detection/defending approaches based on co-operated/shared information</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitation And Discussion</p>
    <p>Dynamic IP address or NAT(Network Address Translation)  Each reported IP may not represent unique victims  However, we believe that our observation can show overall characteristics</p>
    <p>or statistics of Conficker victims</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary And Future Work</p>
    <p>Summary  Observe around 25,000,000 Conficker victims data to show</p>
    <p>their identities</p>
    <p>Compare previous bots/worms and show the difference among them</p>
    <p>Check current reputation-based detection systems  Check current reputation-based detection systems  Propose a prediction/early warning approach of Conficker</p>
    <p>infected networks</p>
    <p>Future Work  Analyze more Conficker data  Compare with more data (other recent bots)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Q &amp; A</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References</p>
    <p>[1] SRI-International. An analysis of Conficker C. http://mtc.sri.com/Conficker/addendumC/</p>
    <p>[2] D. Watson. Know Your Enemy: Containing Conficker. http://www.honeynet.org/papers/conficker</p>
    <p>[3] CAIDA. Conficker/Conficker/Downadup as seen from the UCSD Network Telescope. http://www.caida.org/research/security/ms08-067/conficker.xml</p>
    <p>[4] J. Kristo et al., Experiences with Conficker C Sinkhole Operation and Analysis. In Proceedings of Australian Computer Emergency Response Team Conference, May 2009</p>
    <p>[5] A. Ramachandran and N. Feamster. Understanding the Network-Level Behavior of Spammers. In Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM, Sep. 2006</p>
    <p>[6] Y. Xie, F. Yu, K. Achan, E. Gillum, M. Goldzmidt, and T. Wobber. How Dynamic are IP Addresses? In Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM, Aug. 2007SIGCOMM, Aug. 2007</p>
    <p>[7] Y. Xie, F. Yu, K. Achan, R. Panigraphy, G. Hulte, and I. Osipkov. Spamming Botnets: Signatures and Characteristics. In Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM, Aug. 2008</p>
    <p>[8] B. Stock, M. E. Jan Goebel, F. C. Freiling, and T. Holz. Walowdac Analysis of a Peer-to-Peer Botnet. In Proceedings of European Conference on Computer Network Defense (EC2ND), Nov. 2009</p>
    <p>[9] D. Moore, C. Shannon, and K. Calffy. Code-red: a case study on the spread and victims of an internet worm. In Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM Workshop on Internet Measurement, Nov. 2002</p>
    <p>[10] D. Moore, V. Paxson, S. Savage, C. Shannon, S. Staniford, and N. Weaver. Inside the Slammer Worm. In Proceedings of IEEE Security and Privacy, May 2003</p>
    <p>[11] C. Shannon and D. Moore. The Spread of the Witty Worm. In Proceedings of IEEE Security and Privacy, May 2004</p>
    <p>[12] S. Krishnan and Y. Kim. Passive identification of Conficker nodes on the Internet. In University of Minnesota Technical Document, 2009.</p>
    <p>[13] P. Porras, H. Saidi, and V. Yegneswaran. A Foray into Conficker's Logic and Rendezvous Points. In Proceedings of USENIX LEET, Apr. 2009</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
