<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Challenge of Cloud control</p>
    <p>Maria Kihl, Erik Elmroth, Johan Tordsson, Anders Robertsson,</p>
    <p>Karl Erik rzn</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vision of cloud data centers</p>
    <p>Self-managed, dynamic, and dependable infrastructure, constantly delivering expected QoS with reasonable operation costs and acceptable carbon footprint for large-scale services with sometimes dramatic variations in capacity demands.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Very basic concept of clouds</p>
    <p>VMVM</p>
    <p>VM VM</p>
    <p>VM</p>
    <p>VM</p>
    <p>VM VM</p>
    <p>VM</p>
    <p>VM VM</p>
    <p>VM</p>
    <p>Services Virtual machines</p>
    <p>Infrastructure</p>
    <p>Requests</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges of Cloud Control</p>
    <p>Services</p>
    <p>Virtual machines</p>
    <p>Physical machines</p>
    <p>Power &amp; Cooling</p>
    <p>Service Admission</p>
    <p>Control</p>
    <p>Elasticity control</p>
    <p>VM Placement</p>
    <p>control</p>
    <p>Energy optimization</p>
    <p>and control</p>
    <p>H o</p>
    <p>li s ti c m</p>
    <p>a n</p>
    <p>a g</p>
    <p>e m</p>
    <p>e n</p>
    <p>t c o</p>
    <p>n tr</p>
    <p>o l</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Project Cloud Control</p>
    <p>Large Framework grant from the Swedish Research Council.</p>
    <p>Cloud Research group at Ume University (Prof. Erik Elmroth, Assoc. Prof Johan Tordsson, Prof. Bo Kgstrm)</p>
    <p>Lund Center for Control of Complex Engineering Systems (Prof. Karl Erik rzn, Prof. Anders Rantzer, Prof. Anders Robertsson, Assoc. Prof. Maria Kihl)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lund Center for Control of Complex Engineering Systems (LCCC)</p>
    <p>Research center at Lund University, Sweden, funded by the Swedich Research Council.</p>
    <p>LCCC is developing theory, methods and tools for control of large-scale engineering systems.</p>
    <p>Main research areas:  Distributed Decision-Making and Control</p>
    <p>Implementation in Networked and Embedded Systems</p>
    <p>Modeling Support for Design and Verification</p>
    <p>Read more: http://www.lccc.lth.se/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LCCC Research on Networked and Embedded Systems</p>
    <p>In LCCC, we have a high competence in control of computing systems.</p>
    <p>Performance modelling and load control.</p>
    <p>Prediction based and stochastic control mechanisms.</p>
    <p>Adaptive resource management for embedded systems.</p>
    <p>Experimental validation and testbeds.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ume University</p>
    <p>The Ume University distributed systems' research focuses on flexible and scalable IT infrastructures, and covers a range of topics central to cloud and grid computing.</p>
    <p>+ several senior researchers, postdocs and PhD students</p>
    <p>Web: cloudresearch.se</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UU competence</p>
    <p>The group focuses on systems-oriented research on cloud management with industrial partners like IBM, SAP, ATOS, Telefonica, and British Telecom.</p>
    <p>Their competence is based on profound understanding of the challenges of future cloud infrastructures and the technology required to make them reality.</p>
    <p>The Ume group is central to three of Europes leading industry-driven cloud research projects.</p>
    <p>The team includes the director for the High Performance Computing Center North (HPC2N).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main vision of project</p>
    <p>Cross-disciplinary project based on the &quot;perfect match&quot; of complementing expertise on cloud management and control of computing systems.</p>
    <p>A control theoretic approach to a range of cloud management problems.</p>
    <p>Main aim to transform todays static and energy consuming cloud data centers into self-managed, dynamic, and dependable infrastructures, constantly delivering expected quality of service with acceptable operation costs and carbon footprint for large-scale services with varying capacity demands.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Performance models</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance models</p>
    <p>Example: Computing systems with CPUintensive workload can be modelled as single server queues (M/M/1 dynamics).</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>m</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges for clouds</p>
    <p>Traffic performance monitoring of large distributed systems</p>
    <p>Workload models</p>
    <p>Scalability effects</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Stochastic elasticity control</p>
    <p>Accurate models needed!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other topics</p>
    <p>VM placement control  Optimization of the mapping of virtual resources to</p>
    <p>the infrastructure</p>
    <p>Data center energy optimization</p>
    <p>Holistic management  How do different optimization and control</p>
    <p>mechanisms interact with each other?</p>
    <p>A global control system that monitors the complete system behavior and optimizes the local management systems.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Testbeds and experiments</p>
    <p>One important goal is to validate theories in experiments.</p>
    <p>Available testbeds:</p>
    <p>Umes cloud infrastructure (40+ servers)</p>
    <p>Green server farm at University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</p>
    <p>Energy monitoring!</p>
    <p>Small cloud testbed at Lund University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Focus period on Cloud Control</p>
    <p>LCCC will host a focus period and workshop on Cloud Control in April/May 2014.</p>
    <p>Some planned topics:</p>
    <p>Management and control of cloud infrastructures (e.g. elasticity control)</p>
    <p>Heat and power control in data centers</p>
    <p>Distributed Mobile Clouds</p>
    <p>More information will follow...</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
