<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Energy Efficient Soft Real-Time Computing through Cross-Layer Predictive</p>
    <p>Control</p>
    <p>Guangyi Cao and Arun Ravindran Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</p>
    <p>University of North Carolina at Charlotte</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Organization of Talk  Motivation  Related Work  Cross-Layer Control Framework  Evaluation Methodology  Experimental Results  Future Directions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  Related Work  Cross-Layer Control Framework  Evaluation Methodology  Experimental Results  Future Directions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Center Energy Consumption  In 2012, data centers consumed equivalent of 30GW of power</p>
    <p>Servers typically operate between 10% to 50% of their maximum utilization level</p>
    <p>Server idle power is 50%-60% of the peak power</p>
    <p>Source: BalticServers, Wikimedia</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Energy Efficient Computing</p>
    <p>Resource Allocation</p>
    <p>Feedback Control</p>
    <p>Scheduling</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  Related Work  Cross-Layer Control Framework  Evaluation Methodology  Experimental Results  Future Directions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What we mean by cross layer From a computing systems point of view</p>
    <p>Application</p>
    <p>Operating System</p>
    <p>Hardware</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cross layer optimization and control  Several work on single layer feedback control  Fu et. al. (2011) used Model Predictive Control for cache aware utilization control  Hoffman et. al. (2013) proposed a control framework for controlling multiple</p>
    <p>hardware parameters  Reed et. al. (2013) proposed an application level controller for Apache webserver  Among cross layer approaches that influenced our work</p>
    <p>Illinois GRACE project (2006)  DVFS, CPU budget, frame rate and dithering for video decoding  Hierarchical optimization</p>
    <p>Cucinotta et. al. (2010)  Cross-layer feedback approach with separate feedback loops  Internal loop for resource allocation by controlling scheduling parameters  External loop for application quality</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  Related Work  Cross-Layer Control Framework  Evaluation Methodology  Experimental Results  Future Directions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Control Framework</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Soft Real Time Schedulers</p>
    <p>Multiprocessor Earliest Deadline First Algorithm  Previous research (Devi and Anderson) have shown that for soft real</p>
    <p>time tasks, bounded tardiness with utilization of m (# of cores) is possible for multi-processor EDF</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Model  LTI State space model x(k+1) = Ax(k) + Buu(k) + Bvv(k) + Bdd(k) ym(k) = Cmx(k) + Dvmv(k) + Ddmd(k)</p>
    <p>x(k) is the nx-dimensional state vector of the plant u(k) is the nu-dimensional vector of manipulated variables v(k) is the nv-dimensional vector of measured disturbances d(k) is the nd-dimensional vector of unmeasured disturbances ym(k) is the ny-dimensional vector of measured outputs</p>
    <p>Plant Model</p>
    <p>ym(k)</p>
    <p>Unmeasured Disturbance</p>
    <p>model Gaussian white noise</p>
    <p>v(k) u(k)</p>
    <p>d(k)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model Predictive Control</p>
    <p>Source: Bemporad, Morari and Ricker, Users Guide, Model Predictive Control Toolbox  For use with Matlab</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  Related Work  Cross-Layer Control Framework  Evaluation Methodology  Experimental Results  Future Directions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Benchmarks  x264 video Encoder (from FFMEPG)</p>
    <p>Application quality control variable  per frame video resolution  Bodytrack track human movement (from Parsec benchmark)</p>
    <p>Application quality control variable  annealing layers and number of particles  Visual quality determined the relative mean square error in the magnitude of position</p>
    <p>vectors  Benchmarks modified to satisfy Soft Real-Time task model and allow for</p>
    <p>application quality control</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Setup</p>
    <p>Dual socket Intel Clovertown (X5365) quadcore  DVFS levels: 2.0 GHz, 2.33 GHz, 2.67 GHz, and 3.0 GHz  Application quality levels: 4 each for x264 encoder and bodytrack  Linux 2.6.36 kernel patched with Litmus-RT-2011</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sensors and Actuators  DVFS (actuator)</p>
    <p>Low transition latency (~ 10 us)  Cpufreq used to dynamically scale operational frequency  Modulated using a delta-sigma modulator (uses feedback)</p>
    <p>Application quality (actuator)  Higher transition latency (~ 500 us)  Global variables protected by FMLP read-write lock  Modulated using a pulse-width modulator (no feedback)</p>
    <p>Utilization (sensor)  custom system call that aggregates average per-core execution time</p>
    <p>measured using a high resolution timer, and divides it by the control period</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Controller Design  System Identification  MATLAB SI toolbox</p>
    <p>First order model  fit 84.8% for x264 and 87.4% for bodytrack  nx = 1, nu = 2, nv = 1, and nd = 1</p>
    <p>Controller design  MATLAB MPC toolbox  C code generation  MATLAB Embedded Coder</p>
    <p>x264 bodytrack</p>
    <p>Control horizon 2 4</p>
    <p>Prediction horizon 10 12</p>
    <p>Input weight 0, 0 0, 0</p>
    <p>Output weight 1 1</p>
    <p>Blocking step 5 3</p>
    <p>Disturbance model 1  + 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  Related Work  Cross-Layer Control Framework  Evaluation Methodology  Experimental Results  Future Directions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Avg. FPS vs Number of Tasks bodytrack x264</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Controller Step Response  Input step Step change in the number of tasks from 5 to 9 at t = 50s for bodytrack</p>
    <p>% steady state error 5% % peak overshoot 30% settling time 3.8 seconds</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Controller step response  output step</p>
    <p>% steady state error 5% % peak overshoot 22% settling time 1.8 seconds</p>
    <p>Step change utilization from 4 to 5 at t = 50s for bodytrack</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other benefits  For light task load potential to save power while meeting</p>
    <p>performance goals  P  f3</p>
    <p>To evaluate power savings, we compare the cross-layer control vs. the non-control case for different tasks loads from ranging to light to heavy and calculate the average.</p>
    <p>Average power saving is 31% for x264 and 21% for body track  Obtained at average application quality of 70% for x264 and 65% for</p>
    <p>bodytrack</p>
    <p>Fault tolerance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Task Heterogeneity and Scheduling</p>
    <p>C-EDF vs G-EDF  C-EDF better data locality  G-EDF better load balancing</p>
    <p>G-EDF performs better when one application has much more tasks than other  C-EDF performs better when both applications are more evenly matched  Scheduling algorithm  potentially another control variable ?</p>
    <p>Number of tasks FPS of x264 FPS of bodytrack</p>
    <p>x264 bodytrack C-EDF G-EDF C-EDF G-EDF</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How good is the LTI model?</p>
    <p>X264 controller built with the Hubble video input  Evaluate performance of controller against other popular videos</p>
    <p>drawn from YouTube  Found to perform well if Kolmogorov-Smirnov test of distribution of</p>
    <p>average execution times returns a high significance level</p>
    <p>Video index % steady state error</p>
    <p>Significance level of K-S test</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Controller overheads</p>
    <p>About 0.5% of one control period</p>
    <p>bodytrackx264</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  Related Work  Cross-Layer Control Framework  Evaluation Methodology  Experimental Results  Future Directions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What next?</p>
    <p>Non-linear control  Adaptive control  Power models  Increased Control variables  User space control  Scalability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions and Suggestions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
