<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Model-based Approach to Self- Protec4on in SCADA Systems</p>
    <p>Sherif Abdelwahed, Qian Chen Electrical and Computer Engineering</p>
    <p>Mississippi State University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p Introduc4on and Related Works p Self-protec4ng SCADA Systems p Case Study of the Water Storage Tank p Conclusion and Future Work</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduc4on</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p Supervisory Control and Data Acquisi4on (SCADA) systems are a type of industrial control system (ICS) that adopts many aspects of Informa4on and Communica4ons Technology (ICT/IT) to monitor and control physical (cyber-physical) processes. n A SCADA system includes: sensors, actuators, programmable logic</p>
    <p>controllers (PLCs), remote terminal units (RTUs), human machine interfaces (HMIs), and master terminal units (MTUs).</p>
    <p>n Field devices such as PLCs and RTUs collect and convert sensor sourced analog measurements to digital data. The digital data are then sent back to MTUs via communica4on links (e.g., Internet, radio, microwave, and satellite).</p>
    <p>n In near real-4me this data is processed by MTUs and displayed on HMIs to enable operators to make intervening control decisions.</p>
    <p>SCADA System</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p Stuxnet Worm (2010): A root kit compromised PLCs to subvert the enrichment facili4es ICS to temporally derail Irans nuclear program by destroying roughly 1000 centrifuges. n Social engineering was used to carry a flash drive infected by the</p>
    <p>worm into the secure facili4es. n Using stolen legi4mate digital cer4ficates from reputable companies,</p>
    <p>the worm implanted itself into the vic4ms compu4ng environment. n Using four different zero-day vulnerabili4es to distribute and exploit</p>
    <p>Windows based computers. n Once detec4ng an installed HMI (e.g., Siemens SIMATIC PCS 7,</p>
    <p>WinCC, and STEP 7), carrying out a man-in-the-middle a\ack for sending fake commands to increase the opera4ng speed of the Iranian IR-1 centrifuge from 1,064 hertz to 1,410 hertz for 15 minutes before returning to its normal running frequency.</p>
    <p>Cyber Security Concerns of SCADA Systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p Vulnerabili4es residing in: n Open and standardized protocols (e.g., Modbus, ICCP, and DNP) n Internet-based cyber communica4ons.</p>
    <p>p Security issues inherited from ICT/IT systems: n Opera4ng System n Commercial-off-the-shelf applica4ons</p>
    <p>Cyber Threats Facing SCADA Systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p Intrusion detec4on systems (IDSs): detect and classify SCADA-specific a\acks n Anomaly detec-on: comparing real-4me system performance with</p>
    <p>the normal system model to detect known and zero-day a\acks. p Mahalanobis distance p Neural networks</p>
    <p>n Signature detec-on: matching observa4ons to misuse pa\erns of SCADA system behavior. This approach solely iden4fies and classifies known a\acks.</p>
    <p>p Snort</p>
    <p>p Most IDSs respond to a\acks passively and suffer from the problem of high false alarm rates, which lead to improper responses and high performance overheads.</p>
    <p>Related Works</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p Designing a self-protec4ng SCADA system n Using the model-based approach to develop process control system</p>
    <p>model n Switching between fully-autonomous and semi-autonomous modes n Simple to configure and deploy n Suppor4ng reliable, sustainable, and resilient self-protec4on</p>
    <p>performance p Using a case study to validate the self-protec4on property</p>
    <p>n System Model n Intrusion Es4ma4on n Intrusion Detec4on n Live Forensics Analysis n Intrusion Response</p>
    <p>Contribu4ons</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p Generic approach n Extending to protect various domain with few modifica4ons n Without rebuilding the system or network architecture</p>
    <p>Contribu4ons (Contd)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Self-protec4ng SCADA Systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p Autonomic compu4ng aims at self-protec4ng SCADA systems from cyber a\acks with minimal human interven4on. n es4ma4ng upcoming a\acks and</p>
    <p>sending early warnings n detec4ng and classifying a\acks n Inves4ga4ng causes and impacts</p>
    <p>of zero-day a\acks n autonomously or semi-</p>
    <p>autonomously implemen4ng responses to eliminate cyber a\acks.</p>
    <p>The Outline of Self-Protec4ng SCADA System</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Self-Protec4ng SCADA System Architecture</p>
    <p>Field Devices</p>
    <p>Legal Command</p>
    <p>Response</p>
    <p>Criteria Ranking Unit</p>
    <p>Intrusion Estimation</p>
    <p>MAC/Intrusion Response</p>
    <p>Front VM</p>
    <p>Legal Replies</p>
    <p>Switch Firewall</p>
    <p>HMI</p>
    <p>MTU</p>
    <p>Front VM</p>
    <p>Data Processing</p>
    <p>IDS/Forensics Analysis</p>
    <p>Protocol</p>
    <p>Converter TCP2RTU/ RTU2TCP</p>
    <p>Firewall Switch Request</p>
    <p>Communication Link</p>
    <p>Protocol Converter</p>
    <p>PLC</p>
    <p>Monitor</p>
    <p>Communication Link</p>
    <p>Replies</p>
    <p>Commands</p>
    <p>Messages from Field Devices</p>
    <p>Legal Replies</p>
    <p>Legal Replies</p>
    <p>Commands</p>
    <p>Commands</p>
    <p>Control Network</p>
    <p>Security State Estimation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p The monitor module collects real-4me data of the physical system performance and SCADA system security performance. n For a water storage tank, the selected feature includes:</p>
    <p>p water levels n For the security of SCADA systems, selected features include:</p>
    <p>p Modbus TCP/IP packet header p Protocol data units p TCP connec4on rates</p>
    <p>p The data processing module processes measurements collected by the monitor module. The forma\ed and pre- processed datasets are then forwarded to the intrusion es4ma4on and intrusion detec4on modules.</p>
    <p>Monitor and Data Processing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p The es4ma4on module uses the historical observa4ons of controlled variables of a physical model and selected security features of the SCADA system to determine future performance of the physical system.</p>
    <p>Intrusion Es4ma4on</p>
    <p>),1( rk</p>
    <p>)),1(()( rkk k =</p>
    <p>),1( rk</p>
    <p>)),1(()( rkk k =</p>
    <p>Predicted Value of Control Variable (e.g. Water Level), and Security Features (e.g. TCP TCP/IP packet rates and TCP connec4on rates)</p>
    <p>Historical Datasets</p>
    <p>))(),(),(()k(x kkkxf =Predicted Security State of the SCADA System</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p Intrusion detec4on is the second line of defense p The intrusion detec4on system adop4ng anomaly and</p>
    <p>signature detec4on techniques can detect known and unknown a\acks in real 4me</p>
    <p>p Live forensics analysis learning unknown a\ack pa\erns without disrup4ng system opera4ons is added to protect against zero-day and evolving a\acks n Monitoring and analyzing network traffic, front VM system</p>
    <p>performance, and audi4ng files using forensics tools (e.g., Wireshark) and sta4s4cal theories (e.g., Naive Bayesian Network)</p>
    <p>n Upda4ng detec4on algorithms of the IDS and ac4ve response library so that the zero-day a\acks can be prevented in the future</p>
    <p>Intrusion Detec4on and Live Forensics Analysis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p The intrusion response system selects a proper response to recover the physical system behavior back to normal.</p>
    <p>p The mul4-criteria analysis controller (MAC) implements the evalua4on of recommended responses. The assessment of each response must take into account four criteria, and they are: n Criterion 1: Enhancement of Security n Criterion 2: Opera4onal Costs n Criterion 3: Maintenance of Normal Opera4ons n Criterion 4: Impacts on Proper4es, Finance, and Human Safety</p>
    <p>Intrusion Response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fuzzy-logic Decision Making Method</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>= 3</p>
    <p>j jijii CWS</p>
    <p>The total Score for a recommended Response</p>
    <p>iR</p>
    <p>Criterion j {1,2,3}</p>
    <p>Weight of Criterion j for Response i</p>
    <p>Value of Criterion j for Response i</p>
    <p>e.g. Response: Replacement of Compromised Devices. Weight values for each criterion are the same: 1/3</p>
    <p>Criterion One</p>
    <p>Criterion Two</p>
    <p>Criterion Three</p>
    <p>Criterion Four</p>
    <p>Total Score</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Case Study of the Water Storage Tank</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p The water storage tank is modeled by a laboratory-scale control system in Mississippi State University SCADA Security Laboratory.</p>
    <p>p The MTU is connected to a Human-Machine-Interface (HMI) server via a RS-232 serial port</p>
    <p>p The MTU connects to the RTU wirelessly</p>
    <p>Virtual Testbed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p We injected a malicious command that modified the register values of the water storage tank alarm condi4on when the water storage tank was set to the Auto control mode</p>
    <p>p Auto control mode: n The pump was turned on when the water level reached the low alarm</p>
    <p>condi4on (represented by L); when the water level increased to the high alarm condi4on (denoted by H), the pump was turned off automa4cally</p>
    <p>n The a\ack first evaded the authen4ca4on process n Then sent an illicit command to change L setpoint from 50.00% to</p>
    <p>SCADA System Exploits</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p A linear physical system of the water storage tank was modeled relying on the observa4ons of the physical system when it was automa4cally controlled</p>
    <p>Physical Model of the Water Storage Tank</p>
    <p>Bk += k*A)( Water Level</p>
    <p>Coefficients when 1 t 35: A = 0.256 and B =51.181 when 36 t 39: A = -1.976 and B =62.090 When 40 t 45: A = 0.032 and B =56.718 When 46 t 80: A = -0.202 and B =56.686</p>
    <p>Sampl es</p>
    <p>))(),*(),(()k(x ^</p>
    <p>kBkAkxf +=</p>
    <p>Observa4ons and Es4ma4ons of the Water Level Without Self-Protec4on</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evalua4on of Recommended Responses</p>
    <p>The op4mal response evaluated by the MAC to defend against malicious command injec4on a\ack is Replacement of Compromised Devices.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p It shows that at sample 94, the malicious command injec4on a\ack modified alarm condi4ons</p>
    <p>p The water level was abnormally increased to 65.99%. p At sample 104 when Replacement of Compromised Devices was implemented,</p>
    <p>a replica PLC containing original ladder-logic programs replied to the MTU and sent commands to control water level of the water storage tank.</p>
    <p>p The water level was returned back to normal rapidly and efficiently with the applica4on of autonomic compu4ng technology</p>
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
    <p>Self-Protec4ng Property</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p This research applied autonomic compu4ng technology to protect the SCADA system from cyber a\acks.</p>
    <p>p This new technology integrates current security solu4ons so that the system can proac4vely monitor, es4mate, detect, and react to known and unknown a\acks with li\le or no human interven4on.</p>
    <p>p It also ensures the SCADA system is accessible 24/7. p The self-protec4on property has been validated through an experiment</p>
    <p>of protec4ng a water storage tank from malicious command injec4on a\ack n The self-protec4ng SCADA system maintained normal infrastructure</p>
    <p>opera4ons and regulated the water level back to the normal opera4on region when alarm condi4ons were changed by a\ackers.</p>
    <p>n The overhead 4me for iden4fying and protec4ng the SCADA system was short.</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p In the future, we will simulate more sophis4cated cyber a\acks to validate the efficiency of the approach.</p>
    <p>p We will also employ autonomic compu4ng technology to self-protect the next genera4on SCADA systems from cyber assaults.</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
