<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Minimum Expected Distortion in Gaussian Source Coding with Uncertain</p>
    <p>Side Information</p>
    <p>Chris T. K. Ng1, Chao Tian2</p>
    <p>Andrea J. Goldsmith1, Shlomo Shamai (Shitz)3</p>
    <p>ITW September 2007, Lake Tahoe, CA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Lossy data compression: Side information at the decoder can help reduce the distortion.</p>
    <p>Side information may be acquired over unreliable wireless channels.</p>
    <p>E.g., wireless sensor network: a helper sensor transmits correlated measures over the wireless channel to be used as side information at the decoder.</p>
    <p>We consider the Gaussian source coding problem where: There is a fading analog side-information channel. Decoder knows the realization of the side-information channel. Encoder knows only the fading distribution.</p>
    <p>Want to allocation the Heegard-Berger source coding rate among the fading states:</p>
    <p>To minimize the expected distortion.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Source Coding with Uncertain Analog Side Information</p>
    <p>Digital Channel</p>
    <p>Fading Analog Channel</p>
    <p>Side Information</p>
    <p>Combine digital transmission with analog transmission. The analogy side information is correlated with the digital description. The digital transmitter does not know the fading realization of the analog channel.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Wireless sensor networks. Compression of sensor measurements. Side information is transmitted by a cooperative sensor over a fading wireless channel.</p>
    <p>Hybrid digital-analog communications.</p>
    <p>Systematic lossy source-coding over a fading channel without CSI at the transmitter.</p>
    <p>Upgrading of legacy communications systems A digital channel is added to augment an existing analog channel. The analog reception is used as side information.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Works Without side information:</p>
    <p>Standard rate-distortion function. Side-information channel has no fading [Wyner-Ziv 78].</p>
    <p>Side-information is also available at the encoder [Gray 73, Zamir 96]. Combination of decode and encode side information [Fleming, Effros 06]. Systematic lossy source channel coding [Shamai, Verdu, Zamir 98].</p>
    <p>Source coding with degraded side information at the decoder [Heegard, Berger 85, Kaspi 94]. Successive refinement/scalable source coding with degraded side information [Steinberg, Merhav 04, Tian, Diggavi 07].</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Model  Fading Analog Side Information Channel</p>
    <p>Encoder: rate constraint . Decoder: side information over uncoded analog channel subject to slow fading. Decode knows fading realization but encoder knows only distribution. Motivation: E.g., wireless sensor network. Minimize expected squared error distortion:</p>
    <p>Optimally allocate rate among the layers (M fading states) in the HeegardBerger rate-distortion function.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Heegard-Berger Rate-Distortion Function</p>
    <p>Rate required to simultaneously satisfy a set of distortion constraints. For a set of degraded side-information random variables:</p>
    <p>Heegard-Berger rate distortion function:</p>
    <p>Minimization over W1M such that:</p>
    <p>Side information can be statistically degraded. Squared error distortion measures:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Gaussian Source under Squared Error Distortion</p>
    <p>Two discrete fading states: S = {s1, s2}.</p>
    <p>For Gaussian source:</p>
    <p>Pick W1, W2 such that the distortion constraints are satisfied.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimal Distortion Trade-off and Rate Allocation</p>
    <p>Need to find optimal operating point on the distortion region: For a given fading distribution. To minimize expected distortion.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two Discrete Fading States - Optimal Rate Allocation</p>
    <p>Optimal Rate Allocation Minimum Expected Distortion</p>
    <p>Rate allocated to the better fading state, R2*, is not monotonic. When s2 is large, R2* declines as E[D]* is dominated by worse fading state. Optimal rate heavily skewed toward to worse fading state; R2* &gt; 0 only when p2 is large.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multiple Discrete Fading States</p>
    <p>The Heegard-Berger rate-distortion function extends directly to the case when the side-information channel has multiple discrete fading states (M &gt; 2).</p>
    <p>For M &gt; 2, we did not find closed-form expressions for the optimal rate allocation and the corresponding minimum expected distortion E[D]*.</p>
    <p>However, E[D] minimization can be formulated as a convex optimization problem.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Expected Distortion Minimization Convex optimization problem:</p>
    <p>Can be computed efficiently.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Numerical Results  Discretized Rayleigh Fading</p>
    <p>Rate-distortion (no side information)</p>
    <p>Wyner-Ziv (constant side Information channel)</p>
    <p>Optimal rate allocation concentrates at lowest layer: R*1 = RX. When the source coding rate is large:</p>
    <p>Uncertain side information is almost no more useful than no side information.</p>
    <p>Reduce analog channel uncertainty.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Continuous Fading Distribution</p>
    <p>Consider the expected-distortion--rate function:</p>
    <p>We consider the limiting process as si+1 - si tends to 0:</p>
    <p>Boundary conditions:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimal Continuous Rate Distribution</p>
    <p>Necessary condition for optimality as given by the Euler-Lagrange equation:</p>
    <p>The condition evaluates to:</p>
    <p>We suppose in general for the given fading distribution, ; 0)(' then no u(s) satisfies the Euler-Lagrange condition.</p>
    <p>We conjecture that the optimal rate allocation is discrete even when the fading distribution is continuous and smooth.</p>
    <p>sf S</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conservative Rate Allocation</p>
    <p>Under Rayleigh fading, assume the rate allocation concentrates at the worse fading state (s = 0), i.e., .)()( sRsR X=</p>
    <p>Under such conservative rate allocation, the expected distortion is: .</p>
    <p>When RX is large: .</p>
    <p>Uncertain side information is almost no more useful than no side information. .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>We considered the problem of Gaussian source coding under squared error distortion:</p>
    <p>With uncertain side information at the decoder.</p>
    <p>When the side-information channel has two discrete fading states:</p>
    <p>Derived the optimal rate allocation between the fading states, and the corresponding minimum expected distortion.</p>
    <p>Optimal rate allocation is conservative: Rate is allocated to the better fading state only if it is highly probable. The risk of the better fading state not being realized dominates the expected distortion.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions  continued</p>
    <p>When the side-information channel has multiple discrete fading states:</p>
    <p>The expected distortion minimization can be formulated as a convex optimization problem. Can be computed efficiently.</p>
    <p>Discretized Rayleigh fading: Optimal rate allocation concentrates at the worst fading state (s = 0). Uncertain side information is negligibly more useful then no side information when the source coding rate is large.</p>
    <p>Continuous fading distribution: We conjecture that the optimal rate allocation is discrete even when the fading distribution is continuous and smooth.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
