<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NAIST at WAT 2015</p>
    <p>Graham Neubig, Makoto Morishita, Satoshi Nakamura Nara Institute of Science and Technology (NAIST)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Statistical Translation Frameworks Symbolic Models</p>
    <p>Phrase-based MT [Koehn+ 03]</p>
    <p>Tree-to-String MT [Liu+ 06]</p>
    <p>Encoder-Decoder [Sutskever+ 14]</p>
    <p>Attentional [Bahdanau+ 15]</p>
    <p>he has a cold</p>
    <p>he</p>
    <p>has</p>
    <p>a cold</p>
    <p>he</p>
    <p>has</p>
    <p>a cold</p>
    <p>he has a cold</p>
    <p>PRP VBZ DET NN</p>
    <p>VP</p>
    <p>NP</p>
    <p>S</p>
    <p>Continuous-space (Neural) Models</p>
    <p>he has a cold &lt;s&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;s&gt;</p>
    <p>he has a cold</p>
    <p>g 1 ,...,g</p>
    <p>a 1</p>
    <p>a 2</p>
    <p>a 3</p>
    <p>a 4</p>
    <p>h i-1</p>
    <p>h i</p>
    <p>r i-1</p>
    <p>P(e i |F,e</p>
    <p>i-1 )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relative Merits/Demerits</p>
    <p>Symbolic Models  Inner workings well understood  Better at translating low-frequency words</p>
    <p>Continuous-space Models  Easier to implement  Produce more fluent output  Probabilistic model  can score output of other systems!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reranking with Neural MT Models</p>
    <p>he has a cold</p>
    <p>Input</p>
    <p>T2S/ PBMT</p>
    <p>N-best w/MT Features</p>
    <p>Neural Model</p>
    <p>Neural Features</p>
    <p>nmt=-5.8</p>
    <p>nmt=-5.5</p>
    <p>nmt=-3.4</p>
    <p>nmt=-5.2</p>
    <p>Rescored/Reranked N-best</p>
    <p>Reranking</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Do We Know About Reranking?</p>
    <p>Reranking greatly improves BLEU score, even over strong baseline systems:</p>
    <p>Sutskever+ 2014 Alkhouli+ 2015</p>
    <p>en-fr BLEU</p>
    <p>Base 33.3 Rerank 36.5</p>
    <p>de-en BLEU</p>
    <p>ar-en BLEU</p>
    <p>Baseline 30.6 26.4 Reranked 32.3 27.0</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Don't We Know About Reranking?</p>
    <p>Does reranking improve subjective impressions of results?</p>
    <p>What are the qualitative differences before/after reranking with neural MT models?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Setup</p>
    <p>Data: ASPEC Scientific Abstracts  Japanese  English, Chinese</p>
    <p>Baseline: NAIST WAT2014 Tree-to-String System  Strong baseline achieving high scores  Implemented using Travatar (http://phontron.com/travatar)</p>
    <p>Neural MT Model: Attentional model  Trained ~500k sent., 256 hidden nodes, 2 model ensemble  Use words occurring 3+ times (vocab 50,000~80,000)  Trained w/ lamtram (http://github.com/neubig/lamtram)</p>
    <p>Automatic Evaluation: BLEU, RIBES</p>
    <p>Manual Evaluation: WAT 2015 HUMAN Score</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>en-ja ja-en zh-ja ja-zh 0</p>
    <p>B L</p>
    <p>E U</p>
    <p>en-ja ja-en zh-ja ja-zh 70</p>
    <p>Base</p>
    <p>Rerank</p>
    <p>R IB</p>
    <p>E S</p>
    <p>Confirm what we know: Neural reranking helps automatic evaluation.</p>
    <p>en-ja ja-en zh-ja ja-zh 0</p>
    <p>Base</p>
    <p>Rerank</p>
    <p>H U</p>
    <p>M A</p>
    <p>N</p>
    <p>Show what we didn't know: Also help manual evaluation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is Getting Better?</p>
    <p>Perform detailed categorization of the changes in Japanese-English results:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main Types of Errors Corrected/Caused</p>
    <p>Type Improved Degraded % Impr.</p>
    <p>Reordering 55 9 86%</p>
    <p>Deletion 20 10 67%</p>
    <p>Insertion 19 2 90%</p>
    <p>Substitution 15 11 58%</p>
    <p>Conjugation 8 1 89%</p>
    <p>Total 117 33 78%</p>
    <p>Overall improvements re-confirmed</p>
    <p>In particular fixing reordering, insertion, and conjugation errors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>#1 Detailed Improvement Category: Phrasal Reordering (+26, -4)</p>
    <p>Source</p>
    <p>Base</p>
    <p>Rerank</p>
    <p>Ref</p>
    <p>2</p>
    <p>In case 2, reddening, induration, and skin ulcer appeared during chemical therapy for liver metastasis of rectal cancer.</p>
    <p>In case 2, occurred during chemotherapy for liver metastasis of rectal cancer, flare, induration, skin ulcer.</p>
    <p>In case 2, the flare, induration, skin ulcer was produced during the chemotherapy for hepatic metastasis of rectal cancer.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>#2 Detailed Improvement Category: Auxiliary Verb Ins./Del. (+15, -0)</p>
    <p>Source</p>
    <p>Base</p>
    <p>Rerank</p>
    <p>Ref</p>
    <p>Governing equation derived by this method is useful for turbulent shear flow like turbulent flow near wall.</p>
    <p>The governing equation is obtained by this is also useful for such as wall turbulence shear flow.</p>
    <p>The governing equation obtained by this is also useful for shear flow such as wall turbulence.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>#3 Detailed Improvement Category: Coordinate Structures (+13, -2)</p>
    <p>Source</p>
    <p>Base</p>
    <p>Rerank</p>
    <p>Ref</p>
    <p>Laser work is done by local heating and ablation with high density light flux.</p>
    <p>The laser processing is carried out by local heating by highdensity luminous flux and ablation.</p>
    <p>The laser processing is carried out by local heating and ablation by high-density flux.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>#4 Detailed Improvement Category: Verb Agreement (+6, 0)</p>
    <p>Source</p>
    <p>Base</p>
    <p>Rerank</p>
    <p>Ref</p>
    <p>Langmuir-Blodgett method and inclusion compounds are mentioned.</p>
    <p>Langmuir-Blodgett method and inclusion is also discussed.</p>
    <p>Langmuir-Blodgett method and inclusion are also mentioned.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Wasn't Helped: Terminology (+2, -4)</p>
    <p>Source</p>
    <p>Base</p>
    <p>Rerank</p>
    <p>Ref</p>
    <p>Infrared ray applied measurement using radiant heat is useful for stress analysis.</p>
    <p>The infrared application measurement using radiant heat is useful in the stress analysis.</p>
    <p>Infrared ray application measurement using radiation heat is useful for stress analysis.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Do We Know Now?</p>
    <p>Neural reranking improves subjective quality of machine translation output.</p>
    <p>Main gains are from grammatical factors, and not lexical selection.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Do We Still Not Know Yet?</p>
    <p>How do neural translation models compare with neural language models?</p>
    <p>How does reranking compare with pure neural MT?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
