<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Whiskey, Weed, and Wukan on the World Wide Web: On Measuring</p>
    <p>Censors' Resources and Motivations</p>
    <p>Nicholas Aase and Jedidiah R. Crandall, University of New Mexico; Alvaro Diaz, Universidad de Granada, Spain; Jeffrey Knockel, University of New Mexico; Jorge Ocana Molinero,</p>
    <p>Universidad de Granada, Spain; Jared Saia, University of New Mexico; Dan Wallach, Rice University; Tao Zhu, Independent</p>
    <p>Researcher</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Internet censorship measurement studies...</p>
    <p>vs.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why do we do Internet censorship measurement</p>
    <p>studies?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case studies</p>
    <p>Albuquerque, New Mexico</p>
    <p>Chat programs (SinaUC and TOM-Skype)</p>
    <p>Microblogging (Weibo)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Albuquerque, New Mexico</p>
    <p>No filtering detected: DSL, Lobo-Guest, Lobo-WiFi, Lobo-Sec, Albuquerque Police Dept., Albuquerque Convention Center, Albuquerque Town Hall, Hookah Star, Papa John's, Brickyard, McDonald's, Starbucks, Bank of America</p>
    <p>Filtering of pornography detected: Albuquerque Public Library, Sun International Airport</p>
    <p>Filtering of peer-to-peer websites: Satellite Coffee</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What does censorship that's more advanced</p>
    <p>than this look like?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Chat programs</p>
    <p>Censorship built into the client</p>
    <p>TOM-Skype since March 2011 SinaUC since August 2011</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some interesting stuff...  - McDonald's in front of Chunxi</p>
    <p>road</p>
    <p>- Harbin cinema entrance</p>
    <p>- 27th street department store</p>
    <p>- Confuse its footing</p>
    <p>- Bo Xilai  - Occupy Chang An Street</p>
    <p>- Occupy Wenzhou</p>
    <p>- Occupy Shangha</p>
    <p>- Occupy Shangdong</p>
    <p>- Rong Shoujing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some interesting stuff... but... 6 April 2012</p>
    <p>flg, fuck, , , , , ,  , , , , , ,</p>
    <p>, , , , , ,</p>
    <p>,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>flg, fuck, , , , , ,  , , , , , ,</p>
    <p>, , , , , ,</p>
    <p>,</p>
    <p>Falun Gong, , one-party dictatorship, 89 pro-democracy movement, June 4th, communist bandit, Liu Xiaobo, Orkesh Dolet, Epoch times, escort, erotic June day, fuck your mother, Fang Lizhi, River Elegy, the eternal wheel, beautiful woman passion video, Hu Jintao, nude video chat, Zhao Ziyang, Charter 08, Huang Ju</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Anaconda in the Chandelier: Chinese Censorship Today. Perry Link. The New York Review of Books. April, 2002.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>niaokan =  wukan =</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jun n mi</p>
    <p>Donate your sister</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An analogy...</p>
    <p>Human immune system  Distributed  Multi-tiered  Adaptive  Robust to new threats</p>
    <p>Picture by CDC/Douglas Jordan</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data and source code</p>
    <p>Albuquerque, New Mexico Source code, documentation, URLs</p>
    <p>Chat programs http://www.cs.unm.edu/~jeffk/</p>
    <p>Weibo Source code</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgments We would like to thank the FOCI anonymous reviewers for valuable feedback. This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under Grant Nos. #0644058, #0844880, #0905177, and #1017602. Any opinions, findings, conclusions or recommendations presented in this material are only those of the presenter grantee/researcher, author, or agency employee; and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation. Jed Crandall is also supported by the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is the &quot;chess&quot; of Internet censorship</p>
    <p>measurement?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What about policy implications?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>niaokan =  wukan =</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
