<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimal Power Distribution and Minimum Expected Distortion in Gaussian Layered</p>
    <p>Broadcast Coding with Successive Refinement</p>
    <p>Chris T. K. Ng1, Deniz Gunduz2</p>
    <p>Andrea J. Goldsmith3, Elza Erkip2</p>
    <p>ISIT 2007</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Source-Channel Coding</p>
    <p>Ideal conditions: Separation between compression (source coding) and transmission (channel coding).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Layered Broadcast Coding with Successive Refinement</p>
    <p>???????</p>
    <p>Superposition Coding</p>
    <p>Base Layer</p>
    <p>Refinement Layer</p>
    <p>How to allocate transmit power among the layers?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Real-time communication systems Delay-constrained traffic. Difficult for the transmitter to learn the channel condition. Performance metrics: distortion as defined by applications instead of channel capacity. E.g., satellite voice communication systems.</p>
    <p>Broadcasting Users experience different channel conditions.</p>
    <p>Uncertainty in channel estimation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Broadcast strategy [Cover 72]. Maximize expected capacity [Shamai 97]. High SNR regime optimality [Gunduz&amp;Erkip 05].</p>
    <p>Distortion exponent [Laneman et al. 05]. Uncoded transmission is optimal when sending one source symbol per channel use [Goblick 65].</p>
    <p>Hybrid analog-digital schemes [Shamai et al. 98, Mittal et al. 02, Reznic et al. 06].</p>
    <p>Numerical approximate solutions: Optimize power allocation with constant rate for each layer [Sesia,Caire&amp;Vivier 05].</p>
    <p>Approximate solutions in the high SNR regime: Optimize power and rate [Zachariadis,Honig,Katsaggelos 05].</p>
    <p>Optimize power allocation by the calculus of variations method [Tian et al. 07].</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Source-Channel Coding without CSI at the Transmitter</p>
    <p>Transmission of Gaussian source without CSIT. Quasi-static block fading. Decoding is delay-limited. Channel is non-ergodic: separation is suboptimal. Transmitter knows the fading distribution.</p>
    <p>Minimize expected distortion EH [D] of reconstruction. Squared error distortion. Power constraint P. Bandwidth ratio: b channel uses per source symbol.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Layered Broadcast Coding System Model</p>
    <p>Gaussian source is successively refinable: Each layer successively refines the description in the lower layer.</p>
    <p>Layered broadcast coding: Superposition coding: one layer for each fading state.</p>
    <p>Receiver decodes the layers supported by the channel realization.</p>
    <p>Undecodable layers are treated as noise.</p>
    <p>Successive decoding is capacityachieving for single-antenna Gaussian broadcast channel.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two-Layer Power Allocation Optimization Superposition coding:</p>
    <p>Karush-Kuhn-Tucker (KKT) optimality condition:</p>
    <p>Allocate power to the higher layer: Up to a fixed power ceiling that depends only on the fading distribution.</p>
    <p>P ow</p>
    <p>er</p>
    <p>Base Layer</p>
    <p>Refinement Layer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two-Layer Optimal Power Allocation and Minimum Expected Distortion</p>
    <p>Small : power allocation increases with channel condition. Large : power allocation decreases.</p>
    <p>Expected distortion dominated by the bottom layer.</p>
    <p>Expected distortion is same as one layer with effective channel gain and effective probability.</p>
    <p>Two layers can be represented by a single aggregate layer.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Aggregate Layer with Effective Channel Gain and Probability</p>
    <p>Recursively apply the two-layer optimization step between an aggregate layer and the next lower layer.</p>
    <p>P ow</p>
    <p>er</p>
    <p>Base Layer</p>
    <p>Refinement Layers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multiple-Layer Optimal Power Allocation</p>
    <p>Discretized Rayleigh fading: 25 layers.</p>
    <p>SNRs P = 0, 5, 10 dB. As SNR increases, power allocation is extended down to the lower layers.</p>
    <p>No power allocated beyond = 1. Bandwidth ratios: b = 0.5, 1, 2. Higher b (more channel uses per source symbol):</p>
    <p>Spreads power allocation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multiple-Layer Minimum Expected Distortion</p>
    <p>Low SNR: Negligible improvement from having more layers.</p>
    <p>High SNR: Distortion dominated by outage probability.</p>
    <p>Low SNR: Quantized CSIT nearly as good as perfect CSIT.</p>
    <p>High SNR: Quantized CSIT marginally better than no CSIT.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Continuous Fading Distribution</p>
    <p>Limiting process as the spacing between two layers tends to 0. Optimal power distribution for a continuum of infinite layers.</p>
    <p>Solution given by a set of first-order linear differential equations:</p>
    <p>Optimal power distribution:</p>
    <p>: pdf of the fading distribution</p>
    <p>: cumulative power allocation Power allocated to layer and above</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimal Power Distribution</p>
    <p>Power distribution converges to the one that maximizes expected capacity as b  0.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reducing Distortion: CSIT vs. Diversity</p>
    <p>CSI at the Transmitter:</p>
    <p>CSI Feedback</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>Diversity: Multiple antennas to combine independent fading paths.</p>
    <p>Time</p>
    <p>Fading Channel</p>
    <p>Channel Gain</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Benefits of Diversity vs. CSIT</p>
    <p>Optimal power distribution for different diversity order L.</p>
    <p>Distortion exponent:</p>
    <p>At high SNR performance benefit from diversity exceeds that from CSIT, especially when b is large.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Transmission of a Gaussian source without CSIT. Layered broadcast coding with successive refinement source coding. Optimized power allocation for minimum expected distortion.</p>
    <p>Two-layer power allocation: Allocate power to higher layer up to a power ceiling.</p>
    <p>Multiple layers: Recursively apply two-layer optimization.</p>
    <p>Continuous fading distribution: Limiting process as spacing between layers tends to 0.</p>
    <p>Minimum expected distortion: At high SNR, large benefits from diversity.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
