<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Anatomy of Web Censorship in Pakistan</p>
    <p>Zubair Nabi zubair.nabi@cantab.net</p>
    <p>Information Technology University, Pakistan*</p>
    <p>Presented by: Mobin Javed UC Berkeley</p>
    <p>* Now at IBM Research, Dublin</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>This website is not accessible in Pakistan!</p>
    <p>First study of the cause, effect, and mechanism of Internet censorship in Pakistan</p>
    <p>Upgrade to centralized system in the middle of the study (May 2013)</p>
    <p>Censorship mechanism varies across websites: some blocked at the DNS level; others at the HTTP level</p>
    <p>Public VPN services and web proxies popular tools to bypass restrictions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background: Pakistan and related work  Methodology  Results  Alternative circumvention methods  Summary  Future work  Qs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Internet in Pakistan</p>
    <p>16 million users or 9% of total population (World Bank, 2012)</p>
    <p>Out of the total Internet users, 64% access news websites (YouGov, 2011)</p>
    <p>Largest IXP (AS17557) owned by the state  Internet, fixed-line telephony, cable TV, and</p>
    <p>cellular services regulation by the Pakistan Telecommunication Authority (PTA)  Also in charge of censorship</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>History of Censorship</p>
    <p>2006: 12 websites blocked for blasphemous content</p>
    <p>2008: A number of YouTube videos blocked  IP-wide block via BGP</p>
    <p>misconfiguration</p>
    <p>YouTube rendered inaccessible for the rest of the world for 2 hours</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>History of Censorship (2)</p>
    <p>2010: Facebook, YouTube, Flickr, and Wikipedia blocked in reaction to Everybody Draw Muhammad Day  PTA sanctioned to terminate any telecom service</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>History of Censorship (3)</p>
    <p>2012 (March): Government requests proposals for gatewaylevel blocking system  Filtering from domain level</p>
    <p>to sub-folder level</p>
    <p>Blocking individual IPs and/or entire range</p>
    <p>Plug-and-play hardware units, capable of blocking 50 million URLs</p>
    <p>Latency &lt; 1ms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>History of Censorship (4)</p>
    <p>2012 (September): Infinite ban on YouTube in retaliation to Innocence of Muslims</p>
    <p>Disruption of other Google services due to IP sharing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Verkamp and Gupta  PlanetLab nodes and volunteer machines, 11</p>
    <p>countries</p>
    <p>Key insight: censorship mechanisms vary across countries</p>
    <p>Mathrani and Alipour  Private VPNs and volunteer nodes, 10 countries</p>
    <p>Key insight: restrictions applicable to all categories of websites: political, social, etc.</p>
    <p>Dainotti et al.  Internet blockage during the Arab Spring</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology: Dataset</p>
    <p>Publicly available list with 597 websites  Compiled in 2010  Not exhaustive but a fairly rich of complete</p>
    <p>domains and subdomains  Dataset after cleaning: 307 websites</p>
    <p>Redundant, broken, and duplicates removed</p>
    <p>Checked with a public VPN beforehand to ensure connectivity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology: Script</p>
    <p>Modified version of the CensMon system (FOCI '11)</p>
    <p>and Norton)</p>
    <p>404 Not Found under normal operation</p>
    <p>Also, logs transient connectivity errors, such as timeouts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology: Networks</p>
    <p>ID Nature Location</p>
    <p>Network1 University Lahore</p>
    <p>Network2 University Lahore</p>
    <p>Network3 Home Lahore</p>
    <p>Network4 Home Islamabad</p>
    <p>Network5 Cellular (EDGE)</p>
    <p>Islamabad</p>
    <p>Network1 and 2: gigabit connectivity</p>
    <p>Network5 only used for post-April testing</p>
    <p>Tests performed at night time to minimize interaction with normal traffic</p>
    <p>Performed on multiple occasions for precision</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Pre-April</p>
    <p>Most websites blocked at DNS-level  Local DNS: Non-Existent Domain (NXDOMAIN)</p>
    <p>Public DNS: NXDOMAIN for Google DNS and Level3</p>
    <p>NXDOMAIN redirector in case of Norton DNS, Comodo, and OpenDNS</p>
    <p>No evidence of IP or URL-keyword filtering</p>
    <p>Some websites filtered through HTTP 302 redirection</p>
    <p>Triggered by hostname and object URI</p>
    <p>Done at the ISP level</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ISP-level Warning Screens</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Post-April</p>
    <p>HTTP 302 redirection replaced with IXP-level 200 packet injection  Triggered by hostname and URI</p>
    <p>Because of the 200 code, the browser believes it's a normal response</p>
    <p>Stops it from fetching content from the intended destination</p>
    <p>Original TCP connection times out</p>
    <p>Same response packet and screen across ISPs  Except Network4 (still under the influence of pre</p>
    <p>April censoring)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IXP-level Warning Screen</p>
    <p>Same results reported by The Citizen Lab in parallel in June, 2013</p>
    <p>System attributed to the Canadian firm Netsweeper Inc.  Also applicable to Qatar, UAE, Kuwait, and Yemen</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Survey</p>
    <p>67 respondents  Results biased</p>
    <p>towards individuals with above-average computer skills</p>
    <p>Public VPN services, such as Hotspot Shield, most popular</p>
    <p>Web proxies also popular</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Survey</p>
    <p>67 respondents  Results biased</p>
    <p>towards individuals with above-average computer skills</p>
    <p>Public VPN services, such as Hotspot Shield, most popular</p>
    <p>Web proxies also popular</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alternative Circumvention: Web-based DNS</p>
    <p>Generally, web-based service can also be used for lookup</p>
    <p>Results show that same websites also blocked at HTTP-level</p>
    <p>Similar to South Korea  DNS filtering used for websites that resolve to a</p>
    <p>single site</p>
    <p>HTTP-level mechanism exclusively used for websites with IPs shared across hostnames and filtering needs to be selective</p>
    <p>YouTube, Wikipedia, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alternative Circumvention: CDNs and Search Engine Caches</p>
    <p>No URL-keyword filtering  Blocked websites accessible via CoralCDN  Cached pages of blocked content also</p>
    <p>accessible on Google, Bing, and Internet Archive</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Pakistan has undergone an upgrade from ISPlevel to centralized IXP-level censorship</p>
    <p>Most websites blocked at the DNS level, while a small number at the HTTP level</p>
    <p>Websites blocked at the DNS level also blocked at HTTP-level</p>
    <p>Most citizens use public VPNs and web proxies to circumvent restrictions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Expansion in the number of websites and networks</p>
    <p>Deeper analysis of DNS blockage  For instance, not clear if censoring module</p>
    <p>maintains a list of all resolvers and their redirectors or it queries the actual resolver each time</p>
    <p>Examination of side-effects of DNS injection (similar to China)</p>
    <p>Analysis of Streisand Effect in Pakistan  Early results look promising!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Q?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
