<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Towards a Censorship Analyser for Tor</p>
    <p>Philipp Winter The Tor Project &amp; Karlstad University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tor and censorship</p>
    <p>I Some countries, corporate firewalls, captive portals and ISPs block Tor.</p>
    <p>I Blocks become known through users and dropping usage statistics.</p>
    <p>I Incidents are then analysed to either modify Tor or motivate new censorship-resistant protocol (see obfsproxy et al.).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: pre-election censorship in Iran</p>
    <p>Jan 01 Jan 15 Feb 01 Feb 15 Mar 01 Mar 15</p>
    <p>Date</p>
    <p>N u m</p>
    <p>b e r</p>
    <p>o f u se</p>
    <p>rs in</p>
    <p>I ra</p>
    <p>n</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation for this paper</p>
    <p>I Analysis of censorship incidents not always straightforward.</p>
    <p>I Two typical analysis scenarios I Obtain shell inside censoring network and debug Tor</p>
    <p>handshake.</p>
    <p>I Obtain network trace of Tor bootstrapping and study it.</p>
    <p>I Problems I No shells.</p>
    <p>I No network traces.</p>
    <p>I Dependence on technical volunteers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our approach to the problem</p>
    <p>I How about (unskilled) users do the censorship analysis for us?</p>
    <p>I Provide a small tool which automatically gathers analysis-relevant data.</p>
    <p>I Comes with novel technical and ethical challenges.</p>
    <p>I Important: respect users privacy and security.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What our analyser does</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis steps (1/3)</p>
    <p>I Create a network trace of analysis I Should be optional.</p>
    <p>I Must only cover analysis.</p>
    <p>I Obfuscate tests I Randomise order of executed tests.</p>
    <p>I Use random sleep periods between tests.</p>
    <p>I Probe the website I Try to download the index page.</p>
    <p>I Resolve www.torproject.org and check A records.</p>
    <p>I Experiment with TLS SNI and perhaps HTTP Host header.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis steps (2/3)</p>
    <p>I Probe the directory authorities I Authorities are a popular choke</p>
    <p>point. I Try to download the consensus. I If it fails, ping and traceroute the</p>
    <p>authorities.</p>
    <p>I Test relay reachability I Connect to relay found in consensus. I Step through TLS handshake. I Send Tor-specific TLS client hello to</p>
    <p>unrelated machine.</p>
    <p>I Test bridge reachability I Bridges are relays not listed in the</p>
    <p>consensus. I See if pluggable transport protocols</p>
    <p>work.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis steps (3/3)</p>
    <p>I Gather debug information I What ISP does the user have?</p>
    <p>I What is the autonomous system number?</p>
    <p>I Is the user behind a captive portal?</p>
    <p>I Is all traffic routed through an HTTP proxy?</p>
    <p>I Anonymising reports I Network traces, IP addresses, ASNs, whois and traceroutes can</p>
    <p>be discarded.</p>
    <p>I However, anonymous submission is hard  Tor unavailable.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Think about the users</p>
    <p>I Analyser must be as easy to use as possible.</p>
    <p>I Provide user-friendly output with little jargon.</p>
    <p>I Cover our analysers tracks and delete reports after submission.</p>
    <p>I Informed consent: analyser should inform users about analysis steps and make it easy to abort process.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Create usage diversity</p>
    <p>I Based on analysis results, we can recommend further steps.</p>
    <p>I Therefore, our tools only purpose is no longer to assist in censorship circumvention.</p>
    <p>I Usage diversity should make having a copy of our tool less suspicious.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Report submission</p>
    <p>I We end up with a text file containing YAML-like data.</p>
    <p>I Report could be submitted using email or instant messaging.</p>
    <p>I Hard-coded OpenPGP public key could be used to encrypt report.</p>
    <p>I Report content can be anonymised but report submission hard to do anonymously.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>No need to reinvent the software wheel!</p>
    <p>I OONI is a modular framework for censorship analysis and network interference (see FOCI12 paper): https://ooni.torproject.org.</p>
    <p>I We implement our analyser as several OONI tests.</p>
    <p>I Finally, bundle OONI with our tests to a click-and-go executable.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>class TestTorDNSEntries( DNSTest ):</p>
    <p>a_records = [ &quot;38.229.72.14&quot;, &quot;38.229.72.16&quot;,</p>
    <p>&quot;86.59.30.40&quot;, &quot;93.95.227.222&quot; ]</p>
    <p>domains = [ &quot;www.torproject.org&quot;,</p>
    <p>&quot;bridges.torproject.org&quot; ]</p>
    <p>def test_domains( self ):</p>
    <p>def gotResult( result , domain ):</p>
    <p>self.report[&quot;a_records&quot;] = result</p>
    <p>if set(result ). intersection(self.a_records) ==</p>
    <p>set(self.a_records ):</p>
    <p>print &quot;Host names resolved as expected.&quot;</p>
    <p>else:</p>
    <p>print &quot;WARNING: unexpected resolved host names!&quot;</p>
    <p>for domain in self.domains:</p>
    <p>d = self.performALookup(domain , (&quot;8.8.8.8&quot;, 53))</p>
    <p>d.addCallback(gotResult , domain)</p>
    <p>return d</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>I Our analyser is not unobservable!</p>
    <p>I Users with very strong threat models should not use the analyser.</p>
    <p>I Additional desirable features I Grammatical inference algorithm to uncover DPI fingerprints.</p>
    <p>I Identify/cluster exact model of DPI hardware if possible.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contact</p>
    <p>Email philwint@kau.se</p>
    <p>OpenPGP 2A9F 5FBF 714D 42A9 F82C 0FEB 268C D15D 2D08 1E16</p>
    <p>Twitter @ phw</p>
    <p>Thanks to Anonymous reviewers Arturo Filasto Simone Fischer-Hubner George Kadianakis Karsten Loesing Tobias Pulls Runa Sandvik</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
