<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Every Rose Has Its Thorn Censorship and Surveillance on Social Video Platforms in China</p>
    <p>Citizen Lab, Munk School of Global Affairs, University of Toronto Dept. of Computer Science, University of New Mexico</p>
    <p>USENIX FOCI 2015, August 10, Washington DC</p>
    <p>Jeffrey Knockel, Masashi Crete-Nishihata, Jason Q. Ng Adam Senft, Jedidiah R. Crandall</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Problem</p>
    <p>What are the underlying mechanisms and motivations behind censorship / surveillance on Chinese social media?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Previous work shows inconsistencies in censorship / surveillance of Chinese social media (Crandall et al. 2013, MacKinnon 2008, Villeneuve 2008)</p>
    <p>Suggest general directives may be given by government, but companies have flexibility in implementation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>We reverse engineer four of the most popular Social Video Platforms in China: YY, 9158, Sina Show, GuaGua</p>
    <p>Found client-side keyword censorship in each SVP, and keyword surveillance in YY</p>
    <p>We reveal dataset of 17,547 unique keywords, largest currently available to researchers!</p>
    <p>Previously largest dataset 4,256 unique keywords TOMSkype + Sina UC (Knockel et al. 2012, Crandall et al. 2013)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Source: TianGe Corporate Presentation http://www.tiange.com/Upload/TiangeCorporatePPTLongVersion_en.pdf</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Company Public / Private Product Registered</p>
    <p>Users</p>
    <p>Monthly Active Users</p>
    <p>YY Inc. Nasdaq YY 861.4 mn 117.4 mn</p>
    <p>Tian Ge SEHK 9158, Sina Show 245 mn 14.4 mn</p>
    <p>Jinhua Changfeng Private GuaGua 70 mn N/A</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Endangering state security  Divulging state secrets  Subverting state power  Jeopardizing state religious policy  Spreading rumors  Disrupting social order and stability pornography  Gambling  Violence  Humiliating or slandering others source: http://www.china.org.cn/government/whitepaper/node_7093508.htm</p>
    <p>Prohibited Topics on the Chinese Internet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We would like to express our deep regret to the public. Sina is willing to work with other website operators to make vigorous efforts in the countrys anti-porn campaign and create a clean Internet environment - Sina Corporation source: http://english.cntv.cn/2014/04/27/ARTI1398608144072100.shtml</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>YY: Content posted or displayed on our platform may be found objectionable by PRC regulatory authorities and may subject us to penalties and other severe consequences</p>
    <p>Source: http://files.shareholder.com/downloads/AMDA-NICNI/358818291x0x824505/036DB329-9796-4EED-B792BE55BF114D54/YY-2014_Annual_Report_-_Final.pdf</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Content Filtering and Management</p>
    <p>Strict Terms of Service for users and performers</p>
    <p>Violations lead to fines, account suspensions</p>
    <p>Content Monitoring Teams</p>
    <p>Automated Content Monitoring</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Keyword Censorship Technical Analysis</p>
    <p>YY, 9158, Sina Show, GuaGua perform client-side censorship</p>
    <p>VV, Six Room, BoBo perform server-side censorship</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>YY Keyword Censorship</p>
    <p>YY v7.1 downloads 3 different keyword lists: Finance, Normal, High</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>YY Keyword Censorship  Finance Keyword List (keywords related to phishing</p>
    <p>scams)</p>
    <p>http://do.yy.duowan.com/financekwordlist</p>
    <p>Plain text in UTF8-encoded XML</p>
    <p>When received, YY prints the following warning in the chat window: YY</p>
    <p>[YY Security Tip: This chat seems to involve managing assets; please be sure to verify the identity of a friend to avoid being cheated!]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>YY Keyword Censorship</p>
    <p>Normal Keyword List (sensitive keywords)</p>
    <p>Source: http://do.yy.duowan.com/NormalKWordlist.txt</p>
    <p>Base64-encoded list of UTF16-encoded keywords</p>
    <p>Keywords are asterisked out in the message before the message is sent</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>YY Keyword Censorship  High Keyword List (sensitive keywords)</p>
    <p>Source: http://do.yy.duowan.com/HighKWordlist.txt</p>
    <p>Base64-encoded list of UTF16-encoded keywords</p>
    <p>Keywords are never sent. If a message containing one of these keywords is somehow received, then that message will show in the chat window as a blank message.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>md5(&lt;seconds since unix epoch&gt;/1000+ &quot;;username=report&quot;+</p>
    <p>&quot;;password=pswd@1234&quot;).</p>
    <p>YY Keyword Surveillance http://sere.hiido.com/do.action?</p>
    <p>id=&lt;id&gt;&amp;content=&lt;content&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;id&gt; is a hex encoding of a hash computed as</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>type=2 ;uid=&lt;sending user id#&gt;</p>
    <p>;touid=&lt;receiving user id#&gt; ;keyword=&lt;triggering keyword&gt; ;txt=&lt;entire triggering message&gt;</p>
    <p>YY Keyword Surveillance &lt;content&gt; is a base64 encoding of the following string:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sina Show Keyword Censorship</p>
    <p>SinaShow v3.4 includes:</p>
    <p>Built-in and pre-installed keyword lists</p>
    <p>Downloaded lists</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sina Show Keyword Censorship Outgoing censored message warning:</p>
    <p>, , ! [System filter: the message you sent contains illegal words; please re-enter!]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sina Show Keyword Censorship Incoming censored message warning:</p>
    <p>, [The message sent contains illegal vocabulary; it has been automatically blocked]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sina Show Keyword Censorship  Installed with binary keyword database in Word_410.ucw</p>
    <p>Downloads updates from http://www.51uc.com/uc_ interface/down_policy/Word_410.ucw</p>
    <p>Custom binary container stores GBK-encoded keywords</p>
    <p>Encryption: Blowfish in ECB mode with 8-byte key Dey,1b1E</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sina Show Keyword Censorship</p>
    <p>Sina Show has keywords built into many of its binary files, stored in the plain GBK-encoded</p>
    <p>SinaShow.exe, ChatRoom.dll, Props.dll</p>
    <p>UCClient.dll</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Installed with two keyword lists: filnick.xml filter.xml</p>
    <p>filnick.xml replaces keywords with asterisks in usernames</p>
    <p>filter.xml replaces keywords with asterisks in incoming and outgoing messages. Downloads updates: http:// mimtenroom.9158.com/ web9158/filter.zip</p>
    <p>If chat message contains 6+ English letters all of the letters are replaced with asterisks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GuaGua Keyword Censorship  Analyzed GuaGua v6.2.38</p>
    <p>Keywords built into RuleCenterPlug.dll</p>
    <p>Plain text, GBK-encoded</p>
    <p>Outgoing messages containing keywords are not sent, displaying warning message:</p>
    <p>,!  [Failed to send message; it may contain illegal or</p>
    <p>uncivilized words!]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>List Keywords Unique</p>
    <p>YY Finance 48 18</p>
    <p>YY Normal 20 20</p>
    <p>YY High 13,482 13,242</p>
    <p>Sina Show SinaShow.exe 1,224 910</p>
    <p>Sina Show UCClient.dll 910 910</p>
    <p>Sina Show Downloaded 3,711 3,206</p>
    <p>GuaGua 58 58</p>
    <p>Keyword List Size (May 17 2015)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Keyword lists clustered by Jaccard Similarity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Keyword lists clustered by similarity(x, y) = max(% of x in y, % of y in x)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Content Analysis</p>
    <p>Keywords human / machine translated, contextual analysis</p>
    <p>Grouped into 80 content categories under six themes based on code book developed by Crandall et al. (2013)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Gambling. e.g.,  Toronto casino</p>
    <p>Drugs, firearms, other illicit goods, e.g.,  Methamphetamine production</p>
    <p>Prostitution, sexual interests. e.g,  Prostitute  Sexual partner</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Political Theme</p>
    <p>37 content categories e.g., CPC, religious movements, ethnic minorities, corruption, democracy groups, and terrorism</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CPC General:  Communist Party</p>
    <p>CPC Critical:  Communist gangsters</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Includes references to Islam, Uyghur groups and culture, terrorism, and general terms</p>
    <p>English: uyghurcanadian</p>
    <p>Chinese:  Turkestan</p>
    <p>Uyghur: trkistan Turkestan</p>
    <p>Arabic script:    instructions to make explosives</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CPC Leaders:  x jnpng</p>
    <p>Homonyms:  x jn png</p>
    <p>Nicknames:  Steamed Bun Xi</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Steamed Bun Xi</p>
    <p>source: http://chinadigitaltimes.net/2014/01/sensitive-words-steamed-buns-rumor-dictatorship/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>YY: references largest number of events (18) 90% of YY event keywords related to June 4 1989</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recent Events in Keyword Lists</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion  Inconsistencies in the content</p>
    <p>and implementation in keyword lists across companies and platforms</p>
    <p>Very limited overlap within SVPs and in comparison to chat clients</p>
    <p>Supports theories that companies are under general pressure from the government to perform censorship and surveillance, but have flexibility in implementation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion  Targeted content relates to government criticism and</p>
    <p>collective action</p>
    <p>King et al. analyze post censorship in 1,382 Chinese social media sites.</p>
    <p>Contend content related to collective action censored but content critical of government permitted</p>
    <p>Our results reveal sensitive keywords in SVPs and chat clients related to collective action and government criticism</p>
    <p>Calls into question generalizability of King et al. theory</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Collective Action Keywords</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General / Critical Government Keywords</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Keyword List Updates  Hourly data collection: YY (Feb. 7, 2015), 9158</p>
    <p>(Feb. 24 2015), Sina Show (March 11 2015)</p>
    <p>YY Normal (3 updates), YY High (21 updates)</p>
    <p>9158 Chat (8 updates)</p>
    <p>Sina Show Downloaded (0 updates)</p>
    <p>GuaGua does not download updates</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>YY Updates  32 keywords referencing</p>
    <p>names of Christian songs added April 23, removed April 30 (YY Normal)</p>
    <p>e.g,  Jesus is always with me</p>
    <p>May have been in response to controversy over recent church demolitions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>May 28 2015</p>
    <p>Dai Jianyong (name of Shanghai artist)</p>
    <p>Paralysis brother</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data: https://github.com/citizenlab/chat-censorship</p>
    <p>Special Thanks: Jakub Dalek, Mamatjan Juma, Greg Fay, Zubayra Shamseden, and Greg Wiseman</p>
    <p>Sponsors: Open Technology Fund Information Controls Fellowship Program John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
