<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measuring Decentralization of Chinese Keyword Censorship via Mobile Games</p>
    <p>Jeffrey Knockel, Lotus Ruan, and Masashi Crete-Nishihata</p>
    <p>Citizen Lab, Munk School of Global Affairs, University of Toronto Dept. of Computer Science, University of New Mexico</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>1989 (1989 Year Democracy Movement)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Xi Jinping Era)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Baby Mama Drama</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Baby Mama Drama (A keyword appearing in a chat client)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Who determines whats censored in Chinese apps?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementations are uniform  What is censored necessarily</p>
    <p>reflects CPC strategies  e.g., collective action targeted,</p>
    <p>government criticism permitted (King, Pan, Roberts; 2013, 2014)</p>
    <p>Centralized and Monolithic?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Intermediary liability  Censorship laws and policy can be</p>
    <p>intentionally vague  Responsibility for implementing</p>
    <p>censorship pushed down to companies  Anaconda in the Chandelier (Perry Link)</p>
    <p>Decentralized and Fragmented?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How can we understand which is right?  Analyzing censorship in apps used in China  Client-side censorship offers research opportunities  Extract entire keyword lists used to trigger censorship  Compare across apps and industries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Previous work Chat (IM) clients</p>
    <p>TOM-Skype  Sina UC  LINE</p>
    <p>Found no central blacklist among lists</p>
    <p>n = 3</p>
    <p>(Knockel et al, 2011, Crandall et al 2013, Hardy 2013)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Previous work Live streaming platforms</p>
    <p>YY  Sina Show  9158  GuaGua</p>
    <p>Keyword similarities explained by developer similarities</p>
    <p>n = 4 (or 7)</p>
    <p>(Knockel et al, 2015)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China has the worlds largest and most lucrative mobile gaming market</p>
    <p>Estimated value of over 27.5 billion US$ in 2017</p>
    <p>Source: https://newzoo.com/insights/articles/the-global-games-market-will-reach-108-9-billion-in-2017-with-mobile-taking-42/, Apr 2017</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Registration Approval</p>
    <p>Ministry of Culture</p>
    <p>Publication License</p>
    <p>State Administration of Press, Publication, Radio, Film and Television</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prohibited Content in Online Games 1. violating basic principles set by the</p>
    <p>Constitution; 2. jeopardizing national unity, state</p>
    <p>sovereignty and territorial integrity; 3. leaking state secrets, endangering state</p>
    <p>security or damaging state honor and interests;</p>
    <p>and stability; 7. disseminating obscenity, pornography,</p>
    <p>gambling, violence or abetting crime; 8. humiliating or slandering others,</p>
    <p>infringing the lawful rights of others; 9. transgressing social morality;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mobile Games in China There are a lot more Chinese games than Chinese chat platforms!</p>
    <p>n &gt; 200</p>
    <p>Allows us to test new hypotheses.</p>
    <p>Commonly censor in game chat and usernames.</p>
    <p>Many of these games are international games adapted for the Chinese market.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Initiating banned keywords data~!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Please enter your user name: Xi Jinping</p>
    <p>User name does not comply with regulations, please re-enter.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sampling methodology  Collected first 500 results from Hi Market using search query that only</p>
    <p>returned highly downloaded Chinese-developed games  Same for internationally developed games  Searched APKs for sensitive words</p>
    <p>falun,  (falun), fuck,  (fuck)</p>
    <p>Searched for censorship-related strings</p>
    <p>blacklist, censor, dirty, filter, forbid, illegal, keyword, profan, sensitiv</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hypotheses Censorship keyword lists are:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Keyword Lists From 836 games, found 132 lists from 113 games (152,114 unique keywords)</p>
    <p>XML, JSON, CSV  Compiled Lua, C++  Encrypted files</p>
    <p>Turned each list into a vector of word counts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hypotheses Censorship keyword lists are:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Statistical testing Mantel test  a test for statistical correlation between similarity matrices X and Y</p>
    <p>r statistic</p>
    <p>a correlation statistic between -1 and 1</p>
    <p>p value</p>
    <p>probability that at least as extreme correlation would arise from chance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Statistical testing Mantel test  a test for statistical correlation between similarity matrices X and Y</p>
    <p>Y is the matrix of cosine similarities</p>
    <p>X is different depending on what we want to test</p>
    <p>same genre  same publisher city  same developer city  similarity in approval dates  same publisher  same developer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Variable r statistic p value</p>
    <p>Same publisher city 0.014 0.65</p>
    <p>Same developer city 0.0069 0.58</p>
    <p>Same genre 0.013 0.65</p>
    <p>Similar approval date 0.16 0.0067</p>
    <p>Same publisher 0.15 &lt; 0.001</p>
    <p>Same developer 0.17 &lt; 0.001</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Repeated experiment Different sampling methodology this time</p>
    <p>Many didnt share the same publisher (50%) or developer (62%) with any other</p>
    <p>Selected from five popular publishers</p>
    <p>Giant, Happy Elements, iDreamSky, Netease, Tencent</p>
    <p>And from eight popular developers</p>
    <p>CatCap, Chukong, Joymeng, Ourpalm, Smile, Ultralisk, Xiao Ao</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Keyword Lists From 574 unique games, we found</p>
    <p>167 lists from 129 games  171,150 unique keywords</p>
    <p>We compared the lists in the same way as before.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Variable r statistic p value</p>
    <p>Similar approval date -0.056 0.83</p>
    <p>Same publisher 0.21 &lt; 0.001</p>
    <p>Same developer 0.23 &lt; 0.001</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hypotheses Censorship keyword lists are:</p>
    <p>Determined at the city or provincial level  Determined for specific genres of games ? Related to the date that games are released  Largely determined by the publisher or developer</p>
    <p>This suggests that the responsibility of determining what to censor is pushed down as far as possible.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Content analysis Sampled 7,000 keywords from 183,111 (1.1% margin with 95% confidence)</p>
    <p>Theme Examples</p>
    <p>Event Anniversaries, Current Events</p>
    <p>Political Communist Party of China, Religious Groups</p>
    <p>People Government officials, Dissidents</p>
    <p>Social Gambling, Prurient Interests</p>
    <p>Technology Online Games, URLs</p>
    <p>Miscellaneous No Clear Context</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interesting Keywords Criticism of Censorship Policies</p>
    <p>(a society where sensitive keywords are blocked)</p>
    <p>Multilingual Keywords</p>
    <p>(Iljinhoe), a nationwide pro-Japan organization that operated in Korea in the 1900s</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interesting Keywords Coded Language</p>
    <p>(dio jng png), referencing state leader  (x jnpng)</p>
    <p>(a person who is unable to receive the award), referring to Chinas Nobel Laureate and dissident Liu Xiaobo</p>
    <p>Competitor Names</p>
    <p>(World of Knights)</p>
    <p>(Ragnarok Online)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work  Explore application of other statistical techniques  Complete keyword content analysis (manual / machine</p>
    <p>learning techniques)  Compare keyword list content across games and industry</p>
    <p>segments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgments This material is based upon work supported by the U.S. National Science Foundation under Grant Nos. #1314297, #1420716, #1518523, and #1518878. We thank Professor Ron Deibert and Professor Jedidiah Crandall for supervision and guidance. We are also grateful to the anonymous FOCI reviewers for valuable feedback.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Keyword data available at</p>
    <p>https://github.com/citizenlab/chat-censorship/</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
