<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rawad N. Al-Haddad, Carthik A. Sharma, Ronald F. DeMara University of Central Florida</p>
    <p>Rawad N. Al-Haddad, Carthik A. Sharma, Ronald F. DeMara University of Central Florida</p>
    <p>Performance Evaluation of Two Performance Evaluation of Two Allocation Schemes for Combinatorial Allocation Schemes for Combinatorial</p>
    <p>Group Testing Fault IsolationGroup Testing Fault Isolation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Agenda</p>
    <p>Overview of Group Testing AlgorithmsOverview of Group Testing Algorithms</p>
    <p>Overview of Fault Handling TechniquesOverview of Fault Handling Techniques</p>
    <p>Multi-stage Adaptive Group TestingMulti-stage Adaptive Group Testing</p>
    <p>Equal Share Allocation SchemeEqual Share Allocation Scheme</p>
    <p>Interleaved Allocation SchemeInterleaved Allocation Scheme</p>
    <p>Performance Comparison of Allocation Performance Comparison of Allocation StrategiesStrategies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Group Testing Algorithms</p>
    <p>Origin  World War II Blood testingOrigin  World War II Blood testing  ProblemProblem: Test samples from millions of new : Test samples from millions of new</p>
    <p>recruitsrecruits  SolutionSolution: Test blocks of sample before testing : Test blocks of sample before testing</p>
    <p>individual samplesindividual samples  Problem DefinitionProblem Definition</p>
    <p>Identify subset Identify subset QQ of defectives from set of defectives from set PP  Minimize numberMinimize number of tests of tests  Test Test v-subsetsv-subsets of of PP  Form suitable blocksForm suitable blocks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Failure</p>
    <p>Duration:</p>
    <p>Target:</p>
    <p>Detection:</p>
    <p>Isolation:</p>
    <p>Diagnosis:</p>
    <p>Recovery:</p>
    <p>Transient: SEU Permanent: SEL, Oxide Breakdown, Electron Migration, LPD</p>
    <p>Repetitive Readback</p>
    <p>Device Configuration</p>
    <p>Approach: TMR BIST</p>
    <p>Processing Datapath</p>
    <p>Device Configuration</p>
    <p>Processing Datapath</p>
    <p>Bitwise Comparison</p>
    <p>Invert Bit Value</p>
    <p>Ignore Discrepancy</p>
    <p>Majority Vote</p>
    <p>STARS</p>
    <p>Supplementary Testbench</p>
    <p>Cartesian Intersection</p>
    <p>Worst-case Clock Period</p>
    <p>Dilation</p>
    <p>Replicate in Spare Resource</p>
    <p>Characteristics</p>
    <p>Methods CED</p>
    <p>Duplex Output</p>
    <p>Comparison</p>
    <p>Fast Run-time Location</p>
    <p>Select Spare Resource</p>
    <p>Duplex Output</p>
    <p>Comparison</p>
    <p>unnecessary</p>
    <p>Repetitive Intersections</p>
    <p>Evolutionary Algorithm using Intrinsic Fitness</p>
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>Fault-Handling Techniques</p>
    <p>Dueling</p>
    <p>CGT-Based</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Isolation Problem Outline</p>
    <p>ObjectivesObjectives  Locate faulty logic and/or interconnect resource: a single stuck-Locate faulty logic and/or interconnect resource: a single stuck</p>
    <p>at fault model is assumedat fault model is assumed  Online Fault Isolation: device not entirely removed from serviceOnline Fault Isolation: device not entirely removed from service</p>
    <p>Two Schemes:Two Schemes:  Equal Share:Equal Share:</p>
    <p>Suspect resources are divided into equal subsets, each Suspect resources are divided into equal subsets, each subset is assigned to one individual in the population, subset is assigned to one individual in the population,</p>
    <p>Each suspect resource is guaranteed to be covered by at Each suspect resource is guaranteed to be covered by at least one individualleast one individual</p>
    <p>Interleaved:Interleaved:  Suspect subsets are shared among individuals, Suspect subsets are shared among individuals,  Coverage Factor (CF)Coverage Factor (CF) determines the minimum number of determines the minimum number of</p>
    <p>individuals (individuals ( 1) which utilize each resource in the suspect 1) which utilize each resource in the suspect poolpool</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Equal Share Allocation</p>
    <p>Allocation StrategyAllocation Strategy  Suspect poolSuspect pool of of NN LUTs LUTs  Population Population of of RR individuals individuals  Each individual gets Each individual gets MM suspect resources, where suspect resources, where M = N/RM = N/R..  Maximal possible gain if the fault is articulated by the test Maximal possible gain if the fault is articulated by the test</p>
    <p>vectors is a factor of vectors is a factor of RR (from (from NN suspect resources to suspect resources to MM))  Minimal possible testing phase gain: No gain at all if fault is not Minimal possible testing phase gain: No gain at all if fault is not</p>
    <p>articulatedarticulated</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Experimental SetupExperimental Setup  DES-56 encryption circuitDES-56 encryption circuit  Xilinx ISE design tools to place and route the designXilinx ISE design tools to place and route the design  Virtex II Pro FPGA deviceVirtex II Pro FPGA device  Fault Injection and Analysis Toolkit (FIAT)Fault Injection and Analysis Toolkit (FIAT)</p>
    <p>Application Programmer Interfaces (APIs)Application Programmer Interfaces (APIs) to interact with to interact with the Xilinx ISE tools to inject and evaluate faultsthe Xilinx ISE tools to inject and evaluate faults</p>
    <p>Editing the design file rather than the configuration Editing the design file rather than the configuration bitstreamsbitstreams to introduce stuck-at-faultsto introduce stuck-at-faults</p>
    <p>Editing Editing User Constraint Files (UCF) User Constraint Files (UCF) to control resource to control resource usageusage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Equal Share Results</p>
    <p>Total number of runs for each group count Number of test vectors required in each run</p>
    <p>Results of three CGT experiments with different population size</p>
    <p>Population Isolation results Number of groups</p>
    <p>Required Test vectors</p>
    <p>Discrepancies Success Fail 3 4 5 6 Mean SD</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interleaved Allocation</p>
    <p>Allocation SchemeAllocation Scheme  Each LUT in the suspect pool is utilized by more Each LUT in the suspect pool is utilized by more</p>
    <p>than one individual in the population than one individual in the population  Implies interleaving of individuals over each LUT.Implies interleaving of individuals over each LUT.  Interleaving degree decided by Coverage Factor.Interleaving degree decided by Coverage Factor.  Coverage factor (CF): Number of individuals Coverage factor (CF): Number of individuals</p>
    <p>utilizing each resource in the suspects pool utilizing each resource in the suspects pool  Example: Example: CF = 2CF = 2 means that each suspected LUT means that each suspected LUT</p>
    <p>is covered by two different individuals.is covered by two different individuals.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interleaved Allocation Scheme</p>
    <p>NN LUTs divided into LUTs divided into MM subgroups where subgroups where M = N/RM = N/R  Each individual utilizes Each individual utilizes 22MM LUTs LUTs  Discrepancy will reduce the number of suspects to Discrepancy will reduce the number of suspects to 2M2M rather rather</p>
    <p>than than MM  However, (100/However, (100/CF)% CF)% less chance of unarticulated faults.less chance of unarticulated faults.</p>
    <p>Interleaved Allocation scheme with CF = 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two-Pass Algorithm</p>
    <p>Pass one:Pass one:  Reduce suspect list from Reduce suspect list from NN to to CFCFN/R,N/R, where where CFCF is the is the</p>
    <p>coverage factor coverage factor  Isolation granularity gain is reduced when Isolation granularity gain is reduced when CFCF is increased. is increased.  Terminated once the first discrepant output is observed.Terminated once the first discrepant output is observed.</p>
    <p>Pass TwoPass Two  Reduce suspect list from Reduce suspect list from CFCFN/R N/R to to N/RN/R (same gain as (same gain as</p>
    <p>Equal Share)Equal Share)  New data structure is introduced to expedite the process.New data structure is introduced to expedite the process.  CalledCalled Interleaved Individuals Set Interleaved Individuals Set (IIS)(IIS)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interleaved Individuals Set</p>
    <p>Purpose:Purpose:  Keep track of the interleaved individuals in a specific Keep track of the interleaved individuals in a specific</p>
    <p>CGT configuration CGT configuration</p>
    <p>Example:Example:</p>
    <p>In pass two, individuals interleaving with the one In pass two, individuals interleaving with the one which articulated the fault in pass one will be tested.which articulated the fault in pass one will be tested.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Equal Share:Equal Share:  Best Case: Suspect List reduced from N to N/RBest Case: Suspect List reduced from N to N/R  Worst Case: Zero gain (unarticulated fault)Worst Case: Zero gain (unarticulated fault)  One pass onlyOne pass only</p>
    <p>InterleavedInterleaved  Best Case: Suspect List reduced from N to N/RBest Case: Suspect List reduced from N to N/R  Performed in two passes (NPerformed in two passes (N CFCFN/RN/R  N/R) N/R)  IIS minimizes overhead in Pass twoIIS minimizes overhead in Pass two  Worst Case: Zero gain also. Worst Case: Zero gain also.  BUT, less chance to occur than Equal share scheme BUT, less chance to occur than Equal share scheme</p>
    <p>(because of interleaving)(because of interleaving)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References</p>
    <p>Sharma, C. A. and R. F. DeMara (2006), A Combinatorial Group Testing Method for FPGA Fault Location, in Proceedings of the International Conference on Advances in Computer Science and Technology (ACST 2006), Puerto Vallarta, Mexico, 2006</p>
    <p>Du D and Hwang, F. K (2000), &quot;Combinatorial Group Testing and its Applications,&quot; Series on Applied Mathematics volume 12, World Scientific.</p>
    <p>Sharma, C. A. (2007), &quot;FPGA Fault Injection and Analysis Toolkit (FIAT).&quot;</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
