<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From Russia With Crypto: A Political History of Telegram</p>
    <p>in Use Signal, Use Tor? The Political Economy of Digital Rights Technology</p>
    <p>Nathalie Marchal, PhD 2018 University of Southern California</p>
    <p>Annenberg School for Communication and Journalism @MarechalPhD</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is Telegram?</p>
    <p>Smartphone &amp; desktop app combining messaging (encryption optional) with elements of social media (Channels)</p>
    <p>Privately owned by Durov brothers, legal structure hidden by a network of shell companies</p>
    <p>Peculiar business model: self-funding + cryptocurrency scheme</p>
    <p>Cypherpunk libertarianism combined with idiosyncratically Russian understanding of politics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Brothers Durov, from Vkontakte to Telegram</p>
    <p>VK  Facebook copycat  Telegram created in reaction to</p>
    <p>Kremlin crackdown</p>
    <p>Forcible buy-out &amp; exile  Telegram launched in August</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Telegrams Russian roots  Telegram is the product of its founders</p>
    <p>contentious relationship with the Russian state</p>
    <p>Information &amp; internet as a threat to political elites</p>
    <p>Information controls intensifying since 2012</p>
    <p>2016 Yarovaya laws, including requirement to preemptively make decryption keys available to authorities</p>
    <p>Telegram banned and (sort of) blocked in April 2018</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ideology  Cyber-libertarian  Cypherpunk  Rejection of the nation-state  Commitment to privacy &amp;</p>
    <p>rejection of surveillance capitalism</p>
    <p>Unaccountable to anyone except Pavel Durov himself</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Crypto controversial</p>
    <p>Reputation as the terrorists app of choice</p>
    <p>Secret chats not enabled by default</p>
    <p>They rolled their own crypto  Only sort-of open source</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Telegram ICO  Telegram was self-funded by Durov</p>
    <p>until this year (USD$300 million from VK sale)</p>
    <p>Pre-sales brought in USD$1.7 billion, then the ICO itself was cancelled</p>
    <p>Intended to fund the development of the Telegram Open Network</p>
    <p>White Paper promises a cryptocurrency (the Gram) and inapp marketplace, encrypted file storage &amp; more.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Cyber-libertarianism vs. human rights</p>
    <p>Control vs. accountability  Cypherpunk, open-source</p>
    <p>optional ?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data, Sources, &amp; Methods</p>
    <p>Content analysis of Telegrams publications (including website) &amp; public statements by the Durov brothers</p>
    <p>Secondary sources (academic &amp; popular)</p>
    <p>Interviews with encryption experts</p>
    <p>Walk-through method (Light et al. 2016)</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
