<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measuring I2P Censorship at a Global Scale</p>
    <p>Nguyen Phong Hoang, Sadie Doreen, Michalis Polychronakis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I2P  The Invisible Internet Project</p>
    <p>Measurement method</p>
    <p>Experimental results</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Outline 0</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Online surveillance and Internet censorship 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Circumvention tools 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Many prior studies have measured censorship</p>
    <p>on other circumvention tools</p>
    <p>None has investigated the blocking status of I2P at a large scale</p>
    <p>Motivation 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>https://geti2p.net OR http://i2p-projekt.de/</p>
    <p>I2P typical installation 4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reseed Server Reseed Server</p>
    <p>New Router</p>
    <p>ot str</p>
    <p>ap</p>
    <p>tiv e</p>
    <p>ro ute</p>
    <p>rs</p>
    <p>I2P Bootstrapping 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What to test?  The official site (https://geti2p.net)</p>
    <p>The mirror site (http://i2p-projekt.de)  Reseed servers</p>
    <p>Active I2P routers</p>
    <p>Methodology 6</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>What to test? DNS SNI TCP Block page Official site</p>
    <p>Mirror site    Reseed servers</p>
    <p>Active I2P routers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to test?</p>
    <p>Methodology 8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DNS-based blocking China is dominant in terms of DNS-based blocking, poisoning the official domain and 3 reseed servers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Leakage of DNS Injection Similar poisoned DNS responses were also detected at two network locations in South Korea:</p>
    <p>AS38676 flexnetworks</p>
    <p>AS9848 Sejong Telecom</p>
    <p>Only responses from open resolvers were poisoned, those from local recursive resolvers were not</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SNI-based blocking SNI-based blocking was detected in Oman and Qatar when visiting the official homepage (https://geti2p.net)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SNI-based blocking China, however, doesnt block the official homepage (https://geti2p.net) using SNI-based blocking</p>
    <p>OONI recently reported that China employs both DNSbased and SNI-based blocking to censor Wikipedia</p>
    <p>The Great Firewall applies different blocking techniques on different domains and services</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TCP Packet Injection TCP packet injection was detected in Iran, Oman, Qatar, and Kuwait when visiting the mirror site (http://i2p-projekt.de)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Block page Omans block page delivered through TCP injection when visiting the mirror site (http://i2p-projekt.de)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Block page Qatars block page delivered through TCP injection when visiting the mirror site (http://i2p-projekt.de)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Block page AS47589 Kuwait Telecom Companys block page delivered through TCP injection when visiting the mirror site (http://i2p-projekt.de)</p>
    <p>No block page was detected at other 5 networks: AS3225, AS42961, AS9155, AS6412, and AS196921</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary of censored countries 17</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Encrypted domain name resolution can remedy DNS-based blocking in China</p>
    <p>Encrypted Server Name Indication may change the way censors block sites</p>
    <p>Is IP-based blocking an effective next option?</p>
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>Hoang et al. IMC 18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Within a period of one month, we conducted a total of 54K measurements from 1.7K networks in 164 countries</p>
    <p>Using different techniques to detect DNS poisoning, SNI-based blocking, network packet injection, and block pages, we discovered I2P blocking attempts in China, Iran, Oman, Qatar, and Kuwait</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Q&amp;A</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
