<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity Loves Company: Usability and the network effect</p>
    <p>Roger Dingledine, Nick Mathewson The Free Haven Project</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>We design and deploy anonymity systems.  Version 1: You guys are studying this in</p>
    <p>academia, and we're building them. Please study us.</p>
    <p>Version 2: Economics of anonymity are still not considered by (many) researchers.</p>
    <p>Version 3: If you're thinking of building an anonymity system...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rump session follow-up.</p>
    <p>Yes, usability is an excellent idea. We're working towards that.</p>
    <p>But we're curious about the effects on security as we make progress on usability.</p>
    <p>(Our notion of usability is very broad  e.g. anything that grows the user base.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security is a collaboration</p>
    <p>Suppose two encryption programs:  HeavyCrypto is hard to use properly, but more secure if</p>
    <p>you do.  LightCrypto is easier to use, but can't provide as much</p>
    <p>security.</p>
    <p>Which should you ask your friends to use to send encrypted mail to you? What if you use both?</p>
    <p>Security is a collaboration between sender and receiver.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security affects usability</p>
    <p>There are many other cases where usability impacts security (badly labeled off switches, false sense of security, inconvenient security, bad mental models, ...)</p>
    <p>But let's talk about anonymity systems: many people aggregate their traffic to gain security. So now we're talking more than two participants.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Formally: anonymity means indistinguishability within an</p>
    <p>anonymity set</p>
    <p>Alice1</p>
    <p>Alice4</p>
    <p>Alice7</p>
    <p>Alice2</p>
    <p>Alice6</p>
    <p>Alice5</p>
    <p>Alice8</p>
    <p>Alice3</p>
    <p>.... Bob</p>
    <p>Attacker can't tell which Alice is talking to Bob</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We have to make some assumptions about what the attacker can do.</p>
    <p>Alice Anonymity network Bob</p>
    <p>watch (or be!) Bob!</p>
    <p>watch Alice!</p>
    <p>Control part of the network!</p>
    <p>Etc, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity serves different interests for different user groups.</p>
    <p>Anonymity</p>
    <p>Private citizens</p>
    <p>Governments Businesses</p>
    <p>It's privacy!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity serves different interests for different user groups.</p>
    <p>Anonymity</p>
    <p>Private citizens</p>
    <p>Governments Businesses</p>
    <p>It's network security!</p>
    <p>It's privacy!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity serves different interests for different user groups.</p>
    <p>Anonymity</p>
    <p>Private citizens</p>
    <p>Governments Businesses</p>
    <p>It's traffic-analysis resistance!</p>
    <p>It's network security!</p>
    <p>It's privacy!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The simplest designs use a single relay to hide connections.</p>
    <p>Bob2</p>
    <p>Bob1</p>
    <p>Bob3</p>
    <p>Alice2</p>
    <p>Alice1</p>
    <p>Alice3</p>
    <p>Relay</p>
    <p>Bob3,X</p>
    <p>Bob1, Y</p>
    <p>Bob 2,</p>
    <p>Z</p>
    <p>Y</p>
    <p>Z</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>(ex: some commercial proxy providers)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>So, add multiple relays so that no single one can betray Alice.</p>
    <p>BobAlice</p>
    <p>R1</p>
    <p>R2</p>
    <p>R3</p>
    <p>R4 R5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>But users need to be behave similarly.</p>
    <p>If two users behave entirely differently, they don't provide cover for each other.</p>
    <p>Some partitioning can be avoided by constructing a better anonymity system (see next workshop).</p>
    <p>But some is inevitable: using different protocols, speaking different languages, etc.</p>
    <p>#1: Users need to consider how usable others will find the system, to benefit from a larger anonymity set.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>But what about users with different security goals?</p>
    <p>Some designs are high-latency, others lowlatency. Protect against different threat models.</p>
    <p>So which should you use if you're flexible?  High-latency: against strong attackers we're in</p>
    <p>better shape.  But if few others choose high-latency, we're weak</p>
    <p>against both strong and weak attackers!  #2: Choosing the system with the strongest</p>
    <p>security model may not get you the best security.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Options can hurt anonymity.</p>
    <p>Options hurt security: users are often not the best people to make security decisions; and nondefault configurations don't get tested enough.</p>
    <p>They're even worse for anonymity, since they can splinter the anonymity set. E.g. Type I remailer padding settings.</p>
    <p>#3: Designers must set security parameters.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The default is safer than you think.</p>
    <p>Even when users' needs genuinely vary, adding options is not necessarily smart.</p>
    <p>In practice, the default will be used by most people, so those who need security should use the default even when it would not otherwise be their best choice.</p>
    <p>#4: Design as though the default is the only option.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Convenience vs. Security</p>
    <p>How should Mixminion handle MIME-encoded data? Hard to normalize all possible inputs. Demand that everybody use one mailer?</p>
    <p>Tor path selection: some users want quick paths (one hop), whereas two or three hops seems smarter.</p>
    <p>#5: If you don't support what users want, they'll do it anyway -- insecurely.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deployment matters too.</p>
    <p>Example: Since Tor is a SOCKS proxy, you need to configure your applications to point to it.</p>
    <p>This is not intuitive for novice users.  A larger user base doesn't help security-conscious</p>
    <p>users unless they can configure things right.  Need to bundle with support tools that configure</p>
    <p>everything automatically.  #6: The anonymity questions don't end with</p>
    <p>designing the protocol. AKA, ZKS was right.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Users want to know what level of security they're getting.</p>
    <p>JAP uses its anonym-o-meter. This is a great idea, but we don't think it's a good metric for low-latency systems.</p>
    <p>Tor doesn't really give users a metric. We don't know what they use.</p>
    <p>#7: Give users a security metric, or they'll infer it from something else.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bootstrapping</p>
    <p>Most security systems start with high-needs users (early adopters).</p>
    <p>But in anonymity systems, the high-needs users will wait until there's a user base.</p>
    <p>Low-needs users can break the deadlock.  #8: If you start your system emphasizing security</p>
    <p>rather than usability, you will never get off the ground.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perception and Confidence</p>
    <p>Our analysis so far relies on users' accurate perceptions of present and future anonymity set size.</p>
    <p>#9: Expectations themselves can produce trends: the metric is not just usability, but perceived usability.</p>
    <p>So marketing can improve security??  (This is made messier because there aren't good</p>
    <p>technical metrics to guess the number of users.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reputability: the perception of social value based on current users.</p>
    <p>The more cancer survivors on Tor, the better for the human rights activists. The more script kiddies, the worse for the normal users.</p>
    <p>Reputability impacts growth/sustainability of the network. It also dictates how many strong attackers are attracted.</p>
    <p>#10: Reputability affects anonymity, and a network's reputation can be established early.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity's network effect vs. other network effects.</p>
    <p>Say I have a ham radio and a telephone. I lose nothing other than my investment in the ham radio. Same with VHS and Beta.</p>
    <p>Whereas if I participate in a secure and an insecure anonymity network, even if I make all my decisions well, I still am worse off.</p>
    <p>People use number of customers as a signal -&quot;But if more customers actually improve the quality of the burger...&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Bad loop: unusability means insecurity.  Good loop: usability means security.  We can't just wait to build the most usable and</p>
    <p>most secure system: people are going to take their actions anyway, on less safe systems.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
