<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Florida State University, {fox, lojpur,Florida State University, {fox, lojpur, awang@cs.fsu.edu}awang@cs.fsu.edu}</p>
    <p>Quantifying Temporal and SpatialQuantifying Temporal and Spatial LocalitiesLocalities</p>
    <p>Florida State University</p>
    <p>fox, lojpur, awang@cs.fsu.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quantifying LocalititesQuantifying Localitites</p>
    <p>Describe workloadsDescribe workloads __ Compare different workloadsCompare different workloads</p>
    <p>__ Create accurate synthetic workloadsCreate accurate synthetic workloads</p>
    <p>Understand locality transformationsUnderstand locality transformations __ How are workloads transformed by caching?How are workloads transformed by caching? __ Do workloads properly stress data path components?Do workloads properly stress data path components? __ What opportunities remain for further data path optimizations?What opportunities remain for further data path optimizations?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current MetricsCurrent Metrics</p>
    <p>__ Cache hit ratiosCache hit ratios  Measures the effectiveness of cachingMeasures the effectiveness of caching</p>
    <p>Does not cleanly separate temporal and spatial localityDoes not cleanly separate temporal and spatial locality</p>
    <p>Does not show transformationsDoes not show transformations</p>
    <p>Only applies to cacheOnly applies to cache</p>
    <p>__ Reference distanceReference distance  Reference distance is the number of unique blocks referencedReference distance is the number of unique blocks referenced</p>
    <p>before accessing the same blockbefore accessing the same block</p>
    <p>__ Block distanceBlock distance  Block Distance is the difference between block locations on diskBlock Distance is the difference between block locations on disk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>New MetricsNew Metrics</p>
    <p>__ AffinityAffinity  Builds on block and reference distanceBuilds on block and reference distance  0%-100% easy to understand0%-100% easy to understand  Less sensitive to generations of hardwareLess sensitive to generations of hardware</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example useExample use Web-trace Synthetic</p>
    <p>Shuffled references, same inter-arrival rate, reference distribution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future WorkFuture Work</p>
    <p>__ Study how each storage componentStudy how each storage component transforms locality characteristicstransforms locality characteristics</p>
    <p>__ Verify fidelity of various benchmarksVerify fidelity of various benchmarks __ Improve storage components andImprove storage components and</p>
    <p>benchmarksbenchmarks</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
