<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>On the non-optimality of LAS within the class IMRL</p>
    <p>Samuli Aalto (Helsinki University of Technology) Urtzi Ayesta (LAAS-CNRS)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scheduling in a M/G/1 Queue</p>
    <p>Poisson arrivals with rate . Service requirements are i.i.d. with distribution F(x)=P[X  x].</p>
    <p>Attained service is known (total service requirement unknown)</p>
    <p>Optimality criterion: Mean number of jobs in the system</p>
    <p>service requirement</p>
    <p>server</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Monotonous Hazard Rate</p>
    <p>Hazard rate of a distribution function: h(x)dx=P[x&lt; X  x+dx | X &gt; x]</p>
    <p>IHR: Non-preemptive discipline (FCFS etc.)  Exponential: M/M/1 Mean number of jobs is policy independent  DHR: Least Attained Service (LAS) is optimal. The job(s) who has</p>
    <p>attained the least amount of service is served.</p>
    <p>( ) ( ) ( )xF</p>
    <p>xf xh</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>x 1/x for Pareto</p>
    <p>cons. exponential</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Which scheduling when HR not monotonous?</p>
    <p>Mean Residual Life</p>
    <p>Distribution is IMRL if and only if H(x) is non-decreasing for all x0</p>
    <p>Larger class of distributions: DFR  IMRL</p>
    <p>Claim: LAS is optimal within the class IMRL  Known flaw on the proof  Does the result hold?  What is the optimal policy?</p>
    <p>( ) [ ] ( )( )</p>
    <p>( )xF</p>
    <p>duuF xXxXExH x</p>
    <p>=&gt;=</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FCFS+LAS(c)</p>
    <p>Classify jobs into two classes depending on the amount of attained service</p>
    <p>High Priority: Jobs that have obtained less service than c  Low Priority: Jobs that have obtained more service than c</p>
    <p>High Priority jobs served according to FCFS and Low Priority with LAS</p>
    <p>Low Priority</p>
    <p>High PriorityNew arrivals</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LAS is not Optimal within IMRL</p>
    <p>Theorem: There exists a service requirement distribution belonging to IMRL and discipline  such that</p>
    <p>Sketch of the proof: Consider the distribution (CHR+DHR)</p>
    <p>Belongs to IMRL but not to DHR if 1&lt;c&lt;e</p>
    <p>LASNN &lt;</p>
    <p>( )</p>
    <p>&gt; &lt;</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>cxx cxc</p>
    <p>xF c</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>, 0,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>x</p>
    <p>H(x)</p>
    <p>c x</p>
    <p>h(x)</p>
    <p>c</p>
    <p>xx</p>
    <p>Hazard Rate and Mean Residual Life</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>There exists &gt;0 such that, for any 0&lt;&lt;</p>
    <p>LAScFBFCFS NN &lt;++ )(</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>h(x)</p>
    <p>c</p>
    <p>&lt;</p>
    <p>= ++</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p>+ 0lim )(</p>
    <p>)(</p>
    <p>cLASFCFS</p>
    <p>LAScLASFCFS</p>
    <p>N NN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimal discipline for general service requirements</p>
    <p>Gittins index policy.  To each job present in the system, assign an index equal to</p>
    <p>where</p>
    <p>Pick the job with highest index value, and assign him a service quota *(a)</p>
    <p>Introduced by Sevcik [1974] for static scheduling. Optimality in Stochastic setting by Gittins [1989].</p>
    <p>( ) ( )= &gt;</p>
    <p>,sup 0</p>
    <p>aJaG ( ) ( )</p>
    <p>( )</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p>+ =</p>
    <p>af aJ</p>
    <p>( ) ( ) ( ){ }== ,|0inf* aJaGa</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Gittins index policy</p>
    <p>For non-anticipative disciplines, the hazard rate suffices to characterize the optimal scheduling discipline.</p>
    <p>Theorem: For any attained service a0,</p>
    <p>Sketch of the proof:</p>
    <p>( ) ( )( )aahaG *+=</p>
    <p>( ) ( )( ) ( )( )aahaaJaJ **,0, +==</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Gittins index policy</p>
    <p>For a distribution CHR+DHR(k)</p>
    <p>Optimal policy is FCFS+LAS(*)</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>J(x)</p>
    <p>c</p>
    <p>*(x)</p>
    <p>* x*</p>
    <p>h(x)</p>
    <p>c x</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimal policy for CHR+DHR distribution</p>
    <p>Theorem: For a CHR+DHR(k) type of distribution, there exists a * &lt;k, such that</p>
    <p>NN LASFCFS &lt;+ )( *</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion and future research</p>
    <p>In the set of non-anticipative disciplines, the hazard rate characterizes completely the optimal policy.</p>
    <p>Application of index policy for scheduling with multiple nodes?  How to cope with non work conserving property of networks?</p>
    <p>Influence of maximum size. Assume that F(x)=1 for all xk</p>
    <p>h(x)</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
