<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>You Go to Elections with the Voting System You Have: Stop-Gap Mitigations for Deployed Voting Systems</p>
    <p>J. Alex Halderman Eric Rescorla Princeton University RTFM, Inc.</p>
    <p>Hovav Shacham David Wagner University of California, San Diego University of California, Berkeley</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>All electronic voting systems studied have serious vulnerabilities</p>
    <p>Election officials have been deploying mitigations  Designed under tight time pressure</p>
    <p>Limited input from security experts</p>
    <p>Not clear how well these work</p>
    <p>Can we do better?</p>
    <p>With new but realistic procedures; with no changes to existing</p>
    <p>hardware; and with few and modest changes to existing software, how</p>
    <p>can we best secure elections?</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Assumptions</p>
    <p>Threats  Software will remain vulnerable</p>
    <p>Hardware will remain only modestly resistant to physical attack</p>
    <p>Polling places have little physical security</p>
    <p>Compromise is undetectable and irreversible</p>
    <p>Unfortunate limitations  County headquarters is kept physically secure</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main concern is viruses</p>
    <p>EMS Memory</p>
    <p>Card</p>
    <p>Polling Place</p>
    <p>Device</p>
    <p>Ballot Definition Ballot Definition</p>
    <p>Results Results</p>
    <p>All studied systems can be subverted with minimal unsupervised access</p>
    <p>Polling place devices are poorly protected  Voters; poll workers; sleepovers</p>
    <p>Subverting a single machine isnt very useful  Too expensive to individually subvert every machine</p>
    <p>But viruses allow a single attacker to compromise the entire county</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Managing Viral Spread</p>
    <p>We cant harden the polling place devices  Must assume that they will get infected</p>
    <p>Objective is to prevent spread</p>
    <p>Vectors  EMS, Memory cards, Polling-place networks</p>
    <p>General principle: break dataflow cycles  All external machines assumed dirty</p>
    <p>Avoid connecting dirty machines to clean machines</p>
    <p>Once a machine is dirty, its always dirty</p>
    <p>Build safe(r) replacements for potential vectors</p>
    <p>Need to handle both in and out directions</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Election Phases</p>
    <p>Device initialization</p>
    <p>Voting</p>
    <p>Early reporting</p>
    <p>Tabulation</p>
    <p>Auditing</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 6</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Initialization</p>
    <p>Devices need to be programmed before each election  Load ballot definitions</p>
    <p>Zero vote counters</p>
    <p>Generally done with a memory card  Program cards with EMS</p>
    <p>Disseminate cards to field</p>
    <p>Cards get recycled through EMS</p>
    <p>This is an obvious infection vector</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Initialization With Single-Use Memory Cards</p>
    <p>Use a new card for each election  Buy fresh cards</p>
    <p>Initialize with trusted EMS</p>
    <p>Deploy to field</p>
    <p>When finished, discard or archive</p>
    <p>Logistical issues  Cost: $20-$100/card ($10 for CF + adaptor) = $0.10/vote</p>
    <p>Brittle if cards if are not handled carefully</p>
    <p>Many systems use custom/legacy cards</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Living With Reusable Cards: Initialization Gadgets</p>
    <p>Instead of an eraser, use a special purpose initialization gadget  EMS produces card images on CD</p>
    <p>Initialization gadget copies CD to card</p>
    <p>Gadget requires a hardware reset between cards</p>
    <p>Gadgets is not a vector for viral spread (unlike EMS)  Even if it has vulnerabilities, the reset clears infection</p>
    <p>No guarantee that malicious cards get cleared  Cards must be mated to their devices</p>
    <p>... otherwise we get increased infection each cycle</p>
    <p>This is logistically extremely tricky</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 9</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why not just erase the cards?</p>
    <p>Eraser EMS</p>
    <p>From field To field</p>
    <p>Recommended by [Cal07a, Cal07b, CFH+07]</p>
    <p>Not possible to guarantee erasure  Memory cards are flash memory + a microcontroller</p>
    <p>Some have replaceable firmware  Fake card?</p>
    <p>What about bugs in the eraser?</p>
    <p>This does not guarantee safety of the EMS</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to build stateless gadgets</p>
    <p>Best case: new hardware  Firmware lives in ROM</p>
    <p>Simple interface with hardware reset</p>
    <p>More likely: single-purpose computers  Boot from read-only media</p>
    <p>We still have to worry about BIOS infection</p>
    <p>Need to guarantee hard power switch</p>
    <p>What about VMs?  Now were depending on security of the VM [VMw08]</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Early Reporting</p>
    <p>Many jurisdictions want election-night results  One of the major value propositions of e-voting</p>
    <p>AV -TSX</p>
    <p>Memory Card</p>
    <p>Memory Card</p>
    <p>Download AV -TSX GEMS 1</p>
    <p>CD-R</p>
    <p>Upload AV -TSX GEMS 2</p>
    <p>Air Gap</p>
    <p>Polling Place Election HQ</p>
    <p>Figure 6.1: Adopting a segregated dual-GEMS architecture would help protect against certain kinds of viruses. Officials use one GEMS server and set of central-office voting machines to create memory cards before the election. They use a second, physically separate GEMS server and set of voting machines after the election to tabulate results. The GEMS database is transferred from the first GEMS server to the second GEMS server using a write-once medium, such as a CD-R.</p>
    <p>two systems would be carefully segregated and air-gapped1 to ensure that there are no crossconnections. The sacrificial GEMS installation would be treated as presumed-to-be-infected, so any machine or equipment that is ever connected to the sacrificial GEMS system must never again be connected to the permanent GEMS installation. Strict procedural controls must be applied to ensure that any media that has been connected to the sacrificial GEMS installation is securely erased or reformatted before being used with the permanent GEMS installation.</p>
    <p>Before the election, system administrators would reformat and reinstall all the machines and software on the sacrificial GEMS installation, to bring up a clean sacrificial installation. County staff would use the permanent GEMS installation to lay out the ballot, define the election, and program all of the AV-OS and AV-TSX memory cards. Then county staff would write a backup of the GEMS database from the permanent GEMS installation onto write-once media (e. g., CD-R or DVD-R), carry the media by hand to the sacrificial GEMS installation, and install that GEMS database onto the sacrificial GEMS. After this point, the permanent GEMS installation would not be used for the remainder of the election.</p>
    <p>On election night, as memory cards or other equipment are returned from the field, they would be taken to the sacrificial GEMS installation (not the permanent GEMS installation). Memory cards would be read using the central-office AV-TSX and AV-OS units that are part of the sacrificial installation. The sacrificial GEMS would be used to accumulate and tabulate election results, produce reports, and calculate the official election results.</p>
    <p>Finally, after the election is over, all memory cards would be erased and reformatted using a separate laptop (not connected to either GEMS installation) that is used only for this purpose. This ensures that if the memory cards were carrying data infected with a virus, they have been returned to a clean uninfected state. Some mechanism would have to be devised to securely reformat the AV-OS memory cards.</p>
    <p>System administrators could optionally reformat all devices that are part of the sacrificial GEMS installation, including the GEMS PC. System administrators could then reinstall all of the software on the sacrificial GEMS installation, in preparation for the next election. This ensures a clean copy of the GEMS software. Unfortunately, there seems to be no reliable way to clean the sacrificial AV-TSX machines, so reformatting the sacrificial GEMS PC may not be worth the effort.</p>
    <p>From [CFH+07]</p>
    <p>Use a sacrificial EMS [CFH+07] and wipe after election</p>
    <p>No guarantee of correct results  A single infected card can compromise the EMS and all results</p>
    <p>Only safe with single-use cards  Requires extraordinarily careful procedures</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tabulation With Sanitization</p>
    <p>Trusted EMS</p>
    <p>Central Count</p>
    <p>OPSCAN</p>
    <p>Paper Ballots</p>
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Sanitization</p>
    <p>Device Results</p>
    <p>Safe Results</p>
    <p>Sanitize the results prior to reading into EMS  Narrow input envelope</p>
    <p>Tabulate/aggregate the results as normal</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sanitization Options</p>
    <p>Transcribe results tapes  Estimated cost: $1-$10/tape  $0.10/vote  What about latency?</p>
    <p>Can this be contracted out?  Information density too low to carry shellcode</p>
    <p>OCR?  Current tapes cannot be reliably scanned [Fel08a]</p>
    <p>Maybe add error correction/2-d bar code</p>
    <p>What about vulnerabilities in image processing/OCR code?</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Auditing (1)</p>
    <p>Objectives  High confidence in accuracy</p>
    <p>Transparency</p>
    <p>Preserve vote privacy</p>
    <p>We dont have improvements here  Current precinct-based audits are less statistically powerful</p>
    <p>than we would like</p>
    <p>e.g., A 500 precinct election requires 28% auditing to get a 99% confidence level with a 1% margin of victory</p>
    <p>Ballot-based auditing [CHF07] might help for opscan  But its incompatible with current equipment</p>
    <p>And there are privacy issues</p>
    <p>This is an open problem</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 15</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Auditing (2)</p>
    <p>DRE with VVPAT  Auditing VVPATs is very inconvenient [GB07]</p>
    <p>Lots of attacks even when a VVPAT is used [Eve07]</p>
    <p>Some hope for spoiled ballot auditing</p>
    <p>Not completely worked out yet  Also some attacks [Cra06]</p>
    <p>DRE without VVPAT  No practical audit mechanisms</p>
    <p>Easy for attackers to harmonize electronic records</p>
    <p>And not clear what to do when they dont match [Fel08b]</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 16</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deployment Scenarios (descending order of security)</p>
    <p>Opscan + Electronic ballot markers  Scan twice: precinct + central count with harmonization</p>
    <p>Precinct count plus viral containment</p>
    <p>Pure central count</p>
    <p>Opscan + DRE for accessibility  Do 100% manual recount of VVPAT (DRE as EBM)</p>
    <p>Pure DRE  100% manual recount is impractical</p>
    <p>Viral containment becomes imperative</p>
    <p>If no VVPAT recovery seems unlikely</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 17</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Objective is to do the best we can with what we have</p>
    <p>So, how well did we do?  Containment of viral spread from polling place devices</p>
    <p>But not the other way around!  Correct tabulationeven if some devices are compromised</p>
    <p>Some detection of individual compromised devices</p>
    <p>Residual risks  Insider attack still possible</p>
    <p>Limited ability to recover from DRE compromise</p>
    <p>Auditing is still more expensive than we would like</p>
    <p>Still plenty more work to do</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 19</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References [Cal07a] California Secretary of State. Withdrawal of Approval of Diebold Election Systems, Inc.,</p>
    <p>GEMS 1.18.24/AccuVote-TSX/AccuVote-OS DRE &amp; Optical Scan Voting System and Conditional Reapproval of Withdrawal of Approval of Diebold Election Systems, Inc., GEMS 1.18.24/AccuVote-TSX/AccuVote-OS DRE &amp; Optical Scan Voting System. Part of [Cal07c], October 2007.</p>
    <p>[Cal07b] California Secretary of State. Withdrawal of Approval of Sequoia Voting Systems, Inc., WinEDS v 3.1.012/AVC Edge/Indsight/OPTECH 400-C DRE &amp; Optical Scan Voting System and Conditional Reapproval of Use of Sequoia Voting Systems, Inc., WinEDS v 3.1.012/AVC Edge/Indsight/OPTECH 400-C DRE &amp; Optical Scan Voting System. Part of [Cal07c], October 2007.</p>
    <p>[Cal07c] California Secretary of State D. Bowen. Top-To-Bottom Review of voting machines certified for use in California, 2007. Online: http://sos.ca.gov/elections/elections_vsr. htm.</p>
    <p>[CFH+07] Joseph A. Calandrino, Ariel J. Feldman, J. Alex Halderman, David Wagner, Harlan Yu, and William P. Zeller. Source code review of the Diebold voting system. Part of [Cal07c], August 2007.</p>
    <p>[CHF07] Joseph A. Calandrino, J. Alex Halderman, and Edward W. Felten. Machine-assisted election auditing. In Proc. 2007 USENIX/ACCURATE Electronic Voting Technology Workshop (EVT 07), August 2007.</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 19</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>[Cra06] Ronald E. Crane. Paper Trail Manipulation III. NIST Workshop on Developing an Analysis of Threats to Voting Systems, November 2006. http://vote.nist.gov/threats/ PaperTrailManipulationIII1.pdf.</p>
    <p>[Eve07] Sarah Peterson Everett. The Usability of Electronic Voting Machines and How Votes Can Be Changed Without Detection. PhD thesis, Rice University, 2007.</p>
    <p>[Fel08a] Ed Felten. Evidence of New Jersey Election Discrepancies. http://www. freedom-to-tinker.com/?p=1266, March 2008.</p>
    <p>[Fel08b] Ed Felten. NJ Election Discrepancies Worse Than Previously Thought, Contradict Sequoias Explanation. http://www.freedom-to-tinker.com/?p=1274, April 2008.</p>
    <p>[GB07] Stephen N. Goggin and Michael D. Byrne. An Examination of the Auditability of Voter Verified Paper Audit Trail (VVPAT) Ballots. In Proc. 2007 USENIX/ACCURATE Electronic Voting Technology Workshop (EVT 07), August 2007.</p>
    <p>[VMw08] VMware. VMware Security Advisory VMSA-2008-0005.1. http://www.vmware.com/ security/advisories/VMSA-2008-0005.html, March 2008.</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 19</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bonus Slides</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 20</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Diebold Virus [CFH+07]</p>
    <p>Voter inserts infected memory card into AV-TSX</p>
    <p>AV-TSX automatically installs new software (Issue 5.2.1)</p>
    <p>Infected AV-TSX writes infected memory card for results</p>
    <p>Infected memory card placed in central office AV-TSX, infecting it</p>
    <p>Infected AV-TSX attacks attached GEMS (running Windows) via network</p>
    <p>Infected GEMS writes infected memory cards for next election</p>
    <p>Infected memory cards inserted into precinct AV-TSXs, infecting them</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network Initialization</p>
    <p>Harts machines are also initialized via the network  Election definitions are on cards</p>
    <p>Counter resets and cryptographic keys set via network</p>
    <p>Need a stateless network initialization gadget</p>
    <p>eSlate initialization is through the JBC  Need to marry eSlates and JBCs to prevent spread through</p>
    <p>this network</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Firmware Updates</p>
    <p>We assume that election officials can verify correctness of firmware distribution</p>
    <p>Conventional procedure is to use a single memory card to update all devices</p>
    <p>Cant guarantee card contents after first device processed</p>
    <p>Read only cards  Needs hardware enforcement</p>
    <p>Cant trust card firmware</p>
    <p>Use same card management procedures as with initialization  Best to bring gadget to the machine</p>
    <p>No guarantees that this fixes compromised machines  They can refuse the update</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Double-Checking Tabulation</p>
    <p>Tabulate on a sacrificial EMS</p>
    <p>Emit summary results in machine readable format</p>
    <p>Compare results tapes to summary entries  This can be done with random sampling</p>
    <p>EVT 2008 You go to elections with the voting system you have 24</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
