<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementing Risk-Limiting</p>
    <p>Post-Election Audits in California</p>
    <p>J.L. Hall1,2 L.W. Miratrix3 P.B. Stark3 M. Briones4 E. Ginnold4</p>
    <p>F. Oakley5 M. Peaden6 G. Pellerin6 T. Stanionis5 T. Webber6</p>
    <p>The Electronic Voting Technology Workshop/ Workshop on Trustworthy Elections 2009</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 1/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits Defined What They Are What They Are Not</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in CA Marin County, Measure A (Feb. 2008) Yolo County, Measure W (Nov. 2008) Marin County, Measure B (Nov. 2008) Santa Cruz County, County Supervisor (Nov. 2008)</p>
    <p>Discussion Inadequacy of Election Management Systems (EMS) Importance of Auditor/Election Official Communication</p>
    <p>Simpler Risk-Limiting Audits? Can We Make Risk-Limiting Audits More Simple? Our Simpler Risk-Limiting Audit</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 2/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What They Are</p>
    <p>Post-Election Manual Tally (PEMT) Audits Defined</p>
    <p>Post-election audits require:</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 3/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What They Are</p>
    <p>Consensus Definition</p>
    <p>Risk-limiting audits have a large, pre-determined minimum chance of leading to a full recount whenever a full recount would show a different outcome.1</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 4/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What They Are</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits Defined</p>
    <p>To limit risk, an audit must have:2</p>
    <p>Practically, risk-limiting audits have two more aspects:</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 5/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What They Are Not</p>
    <p>Current Audits and Audit Policy Do Not Limit Risk</p>
    <p>Some problems:  Focus typically on initial sample size</p>
    <p>Not as important as measuring error and escalation</p>
    <p>Error should be contextualized at the contest level  Often, escalation applies to machines or geographical</p>
    <p>regions</p>
    <p>Often use ad hoc error bounds  For example, Within-Precinct Miscount (WPM) is bogus</p>
    <p>Must get both the legal and statistical wording correct  Often mix detection and confirmation paradigms</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 6/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What They Are Not</p>
    <p>But Some States Are Getting Closer. . .</p>
    <p>AK, HI, OR, TN, WV use fairly blunt methods to get closer</p>
    <p>CA, MN and NY have somewhat better schemes. . .  CO is relatively the best:</p>
    <p>risk-limiting audit means an audit protocol that makes use of statistical methods and is designed to limit to acceptable levels the risk of certifying a preliminary election outcome that constitutes an incorrect outcome.</p>
    <p>However, what are statistical methods?  Also, incorrect outcome specifies recount instead of full</p>
    <p>hand (re)count</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 7/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>County Total Winner Loser Margin # Ballots % Ballots Ballots Audited Audited</p>
    <p>Marin (A) 6,157 4,216 1,661 5.1% 4,336 74% Yolo 36,418 25,297 8,118 51.4% 2,585 7% Marin (B) 121,295 61,839 42,047 19.1% 3,347 3% Santa Cruz 26,655 12,103 9,946 9.6% 7,105 27%</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 8/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Marin County, Measure A (Feb. 2008)</p>
    <p>Marin A: The Election, Test and Sample</p>
    <p>The Election: Kentfield School District Measure A  9 precincts3, 5,877 ballots cast, 298-vote margin (5.1%)</p>
    <p>The Test and Sample:  Error measured as overstatement of margin, x.  Weight function, wp:</p>
    <p>wp(x) = (x  4)+ bp</p>
    <p>Stratified random sample of 6 precincts in 2 strata (IP/VBM)</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 9/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Marin County, Measure A (Feb. 2008)</p>
    <p>Marin A: Risk Calculation and Cost</p>
    <p>Risk Calculation:  If 1 batch overstated the margin, a random sample of 6/8</p>
    <p>batches would have missed it with probability:4( 7 6</p>
    <p>) (</p>
    <p>) = 25%.  Cost:</p>
    <p>Took 1 34 days, total cost: $1,501, $0.35 per ballot</p>
    <p>) is shorthand for the binomial coefficient x!/(y!(x y)!).</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 10/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Yolo County, Measure W (Nov. 2008)</p>
    <p>Yolo: The Election, Test and Sample</p>
    <p>The Election: Davis Joint Unified School District  57 precincts, 36,418 ballots, 17,179-vote margin (51.4%)</p>
    <p>The Test and Sample:  Stratified Random Sample (IP/VBM) with small precincts in</p>
    <p>one stratum treated entirely as error  Used maximum relative overstatement (MRO) of margins</p>
    <p>instead of weighted margin overstatement  MRO normalizes the overstatement by the reported</p>
    <p>margin. . . an overstatement in a contest with a small margin is weighted more</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 11/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Yolo County, Measure W (Nov. 2008)</p>
    <p>Yolo: Risk Calculation and Cost</p>
    <p>Risk Calculation:  To limit risk to 25% required sample of 6/103 batches  Found two errors (only one overstatement error), below the</p>
    <p>threshold to trigger expansion</p>
    <p>Cost: Not directly relevant  Two authors and one official did the counting!</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 12/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Marin County, Measure B (Nov. 2008)</p>
    <p>Marin B: The Election, Test and Sample</p>
    <p>The Election: Measure B (added two govt. admin. positions)  189 precincts, 121,295 ballots, 19,792-vote margin (19.1%)</p>
    <p>The Test and Sample:  Used trinomial bound based on taint, tp, of each batch</p>
    <p>tp  ep/up  1 (ep is MRO in p)  Compares tp to a pre-specified threshold, d  Batches have either non-positive tp; tp less than d; or, tp</p>
    <p>greater than d  Bounds risk based on category counts in each bin</p>
    <p>Trinomial bound uses weighted sampling with replacement probability proportional to an error bound (PPEB)</p>
    <p>With stratified random sampling, we would have had to count 44% more ballots</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 13/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Marin County, Measure B (Nov. 2008)</p>
    <p>Marin B: Risk Calculation and Cost</p>
    <p>Risk Calculation:  Chose d = 0.038 and n = 14 (number of draws) based on</p>
    <p>previously observed levels of error (see [1])  Because sampling is with replacement, we get an expected</p>
    <p>number of unique precincts:</p>
    <p>p</p>
    <p>( 1</p>
    <p>( 1</p>
    <p>up U</p>
    <p>)n) = 13.8</p>
    <p>Audit found no errors5</p>
    <p>Cost: 2 days, $1,723 or $0.51 per ballot</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 14/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Santa Cruz County, County Supervisor (Nov. 2008)</p>
    <p>Santa Cruz: The Election, Test and Sample</p>
    <p>The Election: Santa Cruz County Supervisor, 1st District  76 precincts, 26,655 ballots, 2,139-vote margin (8.0%)</p>
    <p>The Test and Sample:  PPEB sampling using the trinomial bound</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 15/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Santa Cruz County, County Supervisor (Nov. 2008)</p>
    <p>Santa Cruz: Risk Calculation and Cost</p>
    <p>Risk Calculation:  set n = 19 and d = 0.047  We did see some error:</p>
    <p>largest tp was 0.036, 1 ballot overstatement in small precint  largest overstatement was 4 ballots in a large precinct, tp</p>
    <p>here was 0.007  No tp was larger than d, so we could certify at 25% risk</p>
    <p>Cost: 3 days, cost $3,248, or $0.46 per ballot</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 16/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inadequacy of Election Management Systems (EMS)</p>
    <p>Ugh, EMSs</p>
    <p>A constant factor was the inadequacy of EMS output</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 17/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inadequacy of Election Management Systems (EMS)</p>
    <p>Ugh, EMSs</p>
    <p>We ended up re-keying batch-level data because of this  No way we can do this for many or big elections</p>
    <p>Unclear what EMSs are actually capable of  HTML?, XML?, EML?, CSV?, PDF? (yuk!), DB dumps?</p>
    <p>We had to do some strange DB reporting calisthenics  E.g., Marin EMS could not report results at batch-level  We modified DB reports to remove all but 1 batch, re-ran</p>
    <p>Wed like to see structured data (EML) with schema (XSD)</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 18/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Importance of Auditor/Election Official Communication</p>
    <p>Communication is key!</p>
    <p>Santa Cruz  The totals we used for calculations did not include</p>
    <p>provisional ballots  However, the audit did include them!  We had to treat all changes in totals due to provisional</p>
    <p>ballot changes as error</p>
    <p>Marin Measure B  One week ago, noticed a similar problem in Marin Measure B  Precincts in Marin smaller than 250 registered voters are</p>
    <p>forced to be VBM  However, the EMS lists these as IP  Used premature results for one precinct marked as IP that</p>
    <p>was forced-VBM</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 19/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can We Make Risk-Limiting Audits More Simple?</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits Dont Have to be as Complex</p>
    <p>Risk-limiting methods that use statistics based on observed audit discrepancy to decide to escalate are complex</p>
    <p>Even with an experienced statistician, the logistics are complex and can lead to to high uncertainty for election officials</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 20/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Simpler Risk-Limiting Audit</p>
    <p>Our Proposal</p>
    <p>Pr = fr 20 +</p>
    <p>Pr is the probability of a full hand count, fr is fraction of voters eligible to vote in the contest and mr is the margin in the race expressed as a fraction</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 21/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Risk-limiting audits are within reach</p>
    <p>Theyre cheap ( $0.44 per ballot)  Theyre difficult to administer</p>
    <p>Future?  Kaplan-Markoff [2] approach appears to be promising  Stratified sampling across Cong. districts is unsolved</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 22/23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Appendix</p>
    <p>Abridged Bibliography</p>
    <p>Some Further Reading I</p>
    <p>Luke W. Miratrix and Philip B. Stark Election Audits using a Trinomial Bound. University of California at Berkeley Department of Statistics, http://statistics.berkeley.edu/~stark/Preprints/ trinomial09.pdf</p>
    <p>Philip B. Stark Efficient Post-Election Audits of Multiple Contests: 2009 California Tests. University of California at Berkeley Department of Statistics, http://ssrn.com/abstract=1443314</p>
    <p>Joseph Lorenzo Hall EVT/WOTE 2009</p>
    <p>Risk-Limiting Audits in California 23/23</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
