<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Take Two So)ware Updates and See Me in the Morning:</p>
    <p>The Case for So,ware Security Evalua6ons of Medical Devices</p>
    <p>Steve Hanna1, Rolf Rolles4, Andres Molina-Markham2, Pongsin Poosankam1,3, Kevin Fu2, Dawn Song1</p>
    <p>University of California  Berkeley1, University of MassachuseMs Amherst2, Carnegie Mellon University3, Unaffiliated4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Changing Medical Device Landscape</p>
    <p>Increased so)ware complexity</p>
    <p>So)ware plays an increasing role in device failure  2005-2009 (18%) due to so)ware</p>
    <p>failure, compared to (6%) in 1980s  Increased aMack opportuniYes</p>
    <p>Medical device hardware and so)ware is usually a monoculture within device model</p>
    <p>Health Data Connected Devices</p>
    <p>Medical Device</p>
    <p>Automated External Defibrillators</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>To be clear</p>
    <p>AEDs ICDs</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Wisconsin requires daycare providers to be AED proficient</p>
    <p>Global Automated External Defibrillators (AED) Market: Demand to Drive Growth; June 2009 U.S., European and Japanese External DefibrillaOon (PAD) Market Report. Frost &amp; Sullivan. 2000. Valenzuela TD, et al. N Engl J Med. 2000;343:1206-1209. Caffrey S, et al. N Engl J Med. 2002;347:1242-1247.</p>
    <p>The PopulaOon of AEDs Has Increased Significantly Over the Past 5 Years</p>
    <p>Automated External Defibrillator Milestones</p>
    <p>A ED</p>
    <p>s W o rl d w id e</p>
    <p>First save on US airline</p>
    <p>New York requires AEDs in public places</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our ObjecYves</p>
    <p>Explore state of AED so)ware security  Examine for standard so)ware security flaws  Data handling, coding pracYces, developer assumpYons</p>
    <p>Give insight into state of medical device so)ware and potenYal for future abuse</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Desirable Medical Device ProperYes</p>
    <p>The device should:  Ensure that so)ware running on a</p>
    <p>system is the image that was verified</p>
    <p>Detect compromise</p>
    <p>Verify and authenYcate device telemetry</p>
    <p>Be robust: defenses and updates weighed with risks to paYent</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study  Analyzed Cardiac Science G3 Plus model 9390A  Performed staYc reverse engineering using IDA Pro  Analyzed: MDLink, AEDUpdate and device firmware</p>
    <p>Analysis using BitBlaze architecture  BitFuzz, the dynamic symbolic path exploraYon tool</p>
    <p>Remarks  Problems likely not isolated to the G3 Plus  PotenYal for abuse as devices become more connected</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VulnerabiliYes Discovered</p>
    <p>Vulnerabili8es were verified on Windows XP SP2.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Firmware Replacement  Firmware update uses custom</p>
    <p>CRC to verify firmware</p>
    <p>Modified firmware, with proper CRC, is accepted by AED and update so)ware</p>
    <p>Impact: Arbitrary firmware</p>
    <p>DEVICE COMPROMISED 9 Hanna, et al. The case for So)ware Security EvaluaYons of Medical Devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AEDUpdate Buffer Overflow</p>
    <p>During update device handshake, device version number exchanged</p>
    <p>AEDUpdate improperly assumes valid input</p>
    <p>Enables arbitrary code execuYon  Data sent from AED can be executed as code on the host PC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Malicious Update Computer</p>
    <p>Initial Malicious Firmware Update</p>
    <p>AED Infecting Security Officer's Laptop</p>
    <p>Malicious Firmware</p>
    <p>Safety Officer's Laptop</p>
    <p>AED Software Update</p>
    <p>Infected Device 0</p>
    <p>Infected Device N</p>
    <p>(Recalculated)</p>
    <p>Malicious Firmware</p>
    <p>Request for AED system status check</p>
    <p>AED</p>
    <p>AED AED</p>
    <p>AED</p>
    <p>AED</p>
    <p>Packet corruption leads to exploit</p>
    <p>Firmware Checksum</p>
    <p>Version Number</p>
    <p>Version String</p>
    <p>Maliciously corrupted data</p>
    <p>AED Software Update</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Improving Medical Device Security for Developers</p>
    <p>Lessons and open problems from the CS G3 Plus  Cryptographically secure device updates</p>
    <p>No security through obscurity, ensures firmware authenYcity  Device telemetry verified for integrity and authenYcity</p>
    <p>Defensively assume that data is not trusted  Passwords cryptographically secure and easily managed</p>
    <p>Private data and life criYcal funcYonality should be protected by well-established cryptographic algorithms</p>
    <p>Defenses and updates weighed with risks to paYent  Medical devices should fail open</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RecommendaYons</p>
    <p>Ensure the update machine is secure  Physical isolaYon, virtual machine for fresh install</p>
    <p>Follow FDA guidelines and advisories  Remain vigilant  Monitoring physical access, rouYnely updaYng afflicted devices, and monitoring advisories released about the device</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Final RecommendaYon</p>
    <p>We recommend conOnued use of AEDs because of their potenYal to perform lifesaving funcYons.</p>
    <p>The aMack potenYal is currently unmeasured and currently, these devices overwhelmingly</p>
    <p>save more lives than they imperil.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You</p>
    <p>QuesYons?  Contact:</p>
    <p>Steve Hanna (sch@eecs.berkeley.edu)  Dawn Song (dawnsong@cs.berkeley.edu)  Kevin Fu (kevinfu@cs.umass.edu)</p>
    <p>secure-medicine.org 15 Hanna, et al. The case for So)ware Security EvaluaYons of Medical Devices</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
