<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protecting Web-based Patient Portal for the Security and Privacy of Electronic Medical</p>
    <p>Records</p>
    <p>Xiaowei Li Yuan Xue</p>
    <p>Vanderbilt University USENIX HealthSec12</p>
    <p>Aug. 6 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Patient portals provide online access to a huge amount of patient record information.</p>
    <p>An essential link in securing patient medical record. A real-world case: In Aug. 2000, over 800 patient information was leaked through KPOnline, a web healthcare portal.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Development and deployment of a secure web patient portal is non-trivial.  Overcome all common web application vulnerabilities, e.g.,</p>
    <p>SQL injection, weak authentication.  Implementation of complex and dynamic security policies</p>
    <p>for restricting sensitive information access and enforcing clinical workflow.</p>
    <p>Integration between the portal and other components (e.g., billing, third-party service) while preventing data leakage via logic flaws or side channel.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study - OpenEMR  http://www.oemr.org/</p>
    <p>Includes a number of vulnerabilities: such as cross-site scripting, SQL injection. (http://www.exploitsdownload.com/search?q=emr)</p>
    <p>OpenEMR 3.2 contains an authorization flaw, which allows for an attacker to create an administrator account, because the user_add page fails to check the user role when being executed.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proposed Approach  A two-tier defense architecture:</p>
    <p>Request Blocker: inspect web requests, prevent sensitive information revealed to attackers.</p>
    <p>EMR protector: isolate EMR data from vulnerable patient portal at the SQL query level.</p>
    <p>Both of them consult Central Decision Engine.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proposed Approach  Security specifications, maintained by decision engine, are learnt by an</p>
    <p>inference engine from real web traffic, that reflect dynamic and complex security policies in clinical environment.  Rule-based: extract deterministic patterns, e.g., when user_add page is</p>
    <p>accessed, the current user must be an administrator.  Evidence-based: extract statistical features, e.g., it is very unlikely that the</p>
    <p>record of a patient with heart attack be accessed by a physician from an irrelevant department.</p>
    <p>Web Requests</p>
    <p>Web Responses</p>
    <p>Session Variables</p>
    <p>Symbolization</p>
    <p>Modeling</p>
    <p>Spec Inference</p>
    <p>SQL Queries SQL</p>
    <p>Responses</p>
    <p>SQL Signature Construction</p>
    <p>User Session</p>
    <p>Clinical Workflow</p>
    <p>Caregiver (Role)</p>
    <p>Treatment Guideline</p>
    <p>Patient (Diagnosis)Check</p>
    <p>lab test before prescri</p>
    <p>be</p>
    <p>Nancy</p>
    <p>Bill</p>
    <p>Bob</p>
    <p>Prescribe Bill</p>
    <p>Check Bob.lab</p>
    <p>Prescribe Bob</p>
    <p>Check Bill.lab</p>
    <p>Check lab Prescribe</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Benefits and Status  Benefits:</p>
    <p>Security implementation can be independent from a specific patient portal and verified and imported for others.</p>
    <p>Automatic inference scales for complex business logic and handles clinical dynamics.</p>
    <p>New security mechanisms/policies can be transparently integrated.</p>
    <p>Current:  Request Blocker and EMR Protector are based on BLOCK and SENTINEL</p>
    <p>systems, we have implemented for general-purpose web applications.  Support automatic inference of rule-based specification.</p>
    <p>Future:  Enhance the inference engine with evidence-based (statistical) features to</p>
    <p>handle clinical dynamics.  Better integrate Request Blocker and EMR Protector with central decision</p>
    <p>engine.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Q&amp;A</p>
    <p>This work was supported by NSF TRUST (The Team for Research in Ubiquitous Secure Technology) Science and Technology Center (CCF-0424422).</p>
    <p>Thank you</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
