<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Secure Logging and Auditing in Electronic Health Records Systems:</p>
    <p>What Can We Learn from the Payment Card Industry</p>
    <p>Jason King, Presenter Laurie Williams</p>
    <p>North Carolina State University August 7, 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Both industries involve the management of sensitive, protected information</p>
    <p>If your cardholder data is breached</p>
    <p>Maybe issue a new payment card</p>
    <p>Maybe remove fraudulent charges from accounts</p>
    <p>If your healthcare data is breached</p>
    <p>Issue a new health diagnosis to replace the old one?</p>
    <p>Give you a completely new health history?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Protected Health Information could/should be considered more sensitive than cardholder data</p>
    <p>So lets compare Healthcare to the Payment Card Industry</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Payment Card Industry (PCI)</p>
    <p>Founded by five global brands in 2006</p>
    <p>American Express</p>
    <p>Discover Financial Services</p>
    <p>JCB International</p>
    <p>MasterCard Worldwide</p>
    <p>Visa Inc.</p>
    <p>Promote mitigation of data breach and prevention of cardholder data fraud</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PCI Data Security Standard Requirements</p>
    <p>Requirement Description</p>
    <p>Requirement 1 Install and maintain a firewall configuration to protect cardholder data</p>
    <p>Requirement 2 Do not use vendor-supplied defaults for system passwords and other security parameters</p>
    <p>Requirement 3 Protect stored cardholder data</p>
    <p>Requirement 4 Encrypt transmission of cardholder data across open, public networks</p>
    <p>Requirement 5 Use and regularly update anti-virus software or programs</p>
    <p>Requirement 6 Develop and maintain secure systems and applications</p>
    <p>Requirement 7 Restrict access to cardholder data by business need to know</p>
    <p>Requirement 8 Assign a unique ID to each person with computer access</p>
    <p>Requirement 9 Restrict physical access to cardholder data</p>
    <p>Requirement 10 Track and monitor all access to network resources and cardholder data</p>
    <p>Requirement 11 Regularly test security systems and processes</p>
    <p>Requirement 12 Maintain a policy that addresses information security for all personnel</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Requirement 10: Track and monitor all access to network resources and cardholder data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Requirement 10: Track and monitor all access to network resources and cardholder data</p>
    <p>Non-repudiation</p>
    <p>Lists/Defines Auditable Events</p>
    <p>Timestamp Reliability</p>
    <p>Log Entry Content</p>
    <p>Immutability</p>
    <p>Log Backups</p>
    <p>Log Monitoring Log Retention</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Requirements</p>
    <p>Log Disposal</p>
    <p>Incident Response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bringing it together</p>
    <p>Ten requirement categories  Non-repudiation</p>
    <p>Defining auditable events</p>
    <p>Log entry content</p>
    <p>Timestamp reliability</p>
    <p>Immutability</p>
    <p>Log monitoring</p>
    <p>Log retention</p>
    <p>Log disposal</p>
    <p>Incident response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Healthcare</p>
    <p>HIPAA Security &amp; Privacy Rules</p>
    <p>Noncompliance may result in civil or criminal penalties, including fines up to $50,000 per violation</p>
    <p>HITECH Act of 2009</p>
    <p>Notion of meaningful use</p>
    <p>Professional and hospitals may qualify for incentive payments for adopting certified EHRs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Meaningful Use</p>
    <p>Stage 1 (2011)</p>
    <p>Criteria for electronic data capture and exchange</p>
    <p>Stage 2 (FY/CY 2014)</p>
    <p>Criteria for increasing patient safety and improving data portability</p>
    <p>Stage 3 (targeted for 2016)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparisons</p>
    <p>Concept PCI DSS HIPAA MU Stage 1 MU Stage 2</p>
    <p>Non-repudiation</p>
    <p>Auditable Events</p>
    <p>Log Entry Content</p>
    <p>Timestamp Reliability</p>
    <p>Immutability</p>
    <p>Log Backups</p>
    <p>Log Monitoring</p>
    <p>Log Retention</p>
    <p>Log Disposal</p>
    <p>Incident Response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example  Auditable Events</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example  Auditable Events</p>
    <p>PCI DSS incorporates security event logging</p>
    <p>All actions performed by administrative or root users</p>
    <p>Initialization &amp; access to audit logs</p>
    <p>Use of authentication mechanisms</p>
    <p>MU Stage 1</p>
    <p>Only creation, modification, access, or deletion of PHI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scenario</p>
    <p>Doctor creates a new prescription for a patient</p>
    <p>Doctor conspires with Administrative user to grant an unauthorized privilege</p>
    <p>PCI DSS MU Stage 1 Would this be logged</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Secure logging &amp; auditing involves more than just recording events</p>
    <p>What works in the PCI?</p>
    <p>What doesnt work in the PCI?</p>
    <p>What unique security vulnerabilities are not covered in the PCI DSS?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
