<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tragedy of the Anticommons in Digital Right Management of Medical Records</p>
    <p>Quanyan Zhu1, Carl Gunter2 and Tamer Baar1</p>
    <p>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</p>
    <p>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security and Privacy of EHRs  Digital Right Management SoluUon  Tragedy of AnUcommons  Game-TheoreUc Models</p>
    <p>- Non-cooperaUve Game Model - CooperaUve Game Model</p>
    <p>Conclusions and Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MoUvaUon  Modern healthcare communicaUon architectures tend to be</p>
    <p>open and interconnected.</p>
    <p>Electronic Health Record (EHR) system can reduce cost of the healthcare system and provide Umely access to informaUon.</p>
    <p>Decentralized accesses of paUent data are allowed for family doctors, medical specialists and even non-medical care providers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security and privacy are major concerns of EHRs. [h]p://www.oipc.ab.ca]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RMS Server</p>
    <p>Data Owner</p>
    <p>Recipient Data DistribuUon</p>
    <p>Digital Rights Management (DRM) is applied to protect EHRs.</p>
    <p>Owners can control the distribuUon and use of informaUon. [Petkovic et al. 2007]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Who owns the data?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>R ec ip ie n t</p>
    <p>Data Owner B</p>
    <p>Data Owner A RMS Server A</p>
    <p>RMS Server B</p>
    <p>Data ownership is fragmented.</p>
    <p>Requests</p>
    <p>Requests</p>
    <p>CerUficate</p>
    <p>CerUficate</p>
    <p>DistribuUon</p>
    <p>DistribuUon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tragedy of the Anticommons: CompeUng right holders foreclose each other from producUve use of a share of resources, which results in underutilization of resources.</p>
    <p>MulUple ownership of different pieces of a paUents medical history makes it difficult to assemble a complete record.</p>
    <p>The complete record has a greater value than sum of its parts.  The barrier is not just technological but also economic.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tragedy of the Commons Tragedy of the AnUcommons</p>
    <p>Self Environ Air Quality Land Labour Ca]le</p>
    <p>From Commons to AnUcommons</p>
    <p>[Hardin 1968, Heller 1998, Fennell 2009, Hall 2010]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tragedy of Commons: Prisoners Dilemma</p>
    <p>Both players are maximizers.  NE in pure strategies (D, D) vs. OpUmal team soluUon (C, C)  Loss of efficiency:</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>(G1)</p>
    <p>Social Welfare under NE =</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tragedy of AnUcommons: Game of Chicken</p>
    <p>Both players are maximizers: choose between S (Swerve) or D (Drive Ahead)</p>
    <p>NE in pure strategies (S, D), (D, S) vs. OpUmal team soluUon (S, S)</p>
    <p>Loss of efficiency:</p>
    <p>S</p>
    <p>S</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>(G2)</p>
    <p>Social Welfare under NE =</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consider two players P1 and P2.  Each player decides the level of access granted to its users.</p>
    <p>i [0,1], i =1, 2, are decision variables:  i = 1 : Access is denied.  i = 0 : Access is fully granted.  1-i is the access level.</p>
    <p>c [0,1] is a unit cost on the granted access.  p is a charge of access fee.</p>
    <p>Non-CooperaUve Game Model</p>
    <p>Ui (1, 2) = p + (2-1-2)i - c (1-i), i = 1, 2,</p>
    <p>The value of informaUon is proporUonal to total accesses granted.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A unique NE is 1= 2 = (2+c)/3.  Worst case is 1= 2 =1 when c =1, i.e., accesses are all denied.</p>
    <p>Nash Equilibrium vs. Team OpUmal SoluUon</p>
    <p>Ui (1, 2) = p + (2-1-2) i - c (1-i), i = 1, 2,</p>
    <p>U (1, 2) = U1 (1, 2) + U2 (1, 2)</p>
    <p>Team opUmal soluUon is 1= 2 = (2+c)/4.  Worst case is 1= 2 = 3/4 when c = 1, i.e., 1/4 accesses granted.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some form of coordinaUon is needed.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Coordinated Electronic Health Record System</p>
    <p>Data Owner A</p>
    <p>Consent Management System</p>
    <p>Data Owner B</p>
    <p>Health Record Database</p>
    <p>Consent</p>
    <p>PaUent PaUent Records</p>
    <p>PaUent Records</p>
    <p>[Sheppard, Safavi-Naini, Jafari, 2009]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to quanUfy the value of coordinaUon?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The characterisUc funcUon v is described by  v() = v({C}) = 0,  v({1}) = v({2}) =  (c-1)2 + p,  v({1, C}) = v({2, C}) =  (c-1)2 + p,  v({1, 2}) = 2p,  v({1, 2, C}) =  (c-2)2 +2p.</p>
    <p>CooperaUve Game Model: Shapley Value</p>
    <p>Data Owner A Data Owner B</p>
    <p>Coordinator</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The characterisUc funcUon v :  v() = v({C}) = 0,  v({1}) = v({2}) =  (c-1)2 + p,  v({1, C}) = v({2, C}) =  (c-1)2 + p,  v({1, 2}) = 2p,  v({1, 2, C}) =  (c-2)2 +2p.</p>
    <p>Value of CoordinaUon</p>
    <p>Shapley Values</p>
    <p>u1=1/3  c/3+ c2/12 +p  u2=1/3  c/3+ c2/12 +p  u3=1/3  c/3+ c2/12</p>
    <p>The coordinaUon is least valuable when c = 1, which yields u3 = 1/12.</p>
    <p>The coordinaUon is most valuable when c = 0, which yields u3 = 1/3.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions and Future Work</p>
    <p>The fractured ownership among medical service providers and insurers has created the tragedy of anticommons for DRM implementaUon.</p>
    <p>MulUple ownerships in DRM will lead to underutilization of HER resources even though security and privacy are guaranteed.</p>
    <p>The barrier is not just technical but also economic.</p>
    <p>CooperaUve and non-cooperaUve game-theoreUc models can be used to understand strategic behaviors of data owners and the value of coordinaUon.</p>
    <p>Game-theoreUc tools can provide a theoreUcal basis for implementaUon of DRM technologies, design of security policies and provision of incenUve mechanisms.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contacts:</p>
    <p>Quanyan Zhu zhu31@illinois.edu</p>
    <p>Carl Gunter cgunter@illinois.edu</p>
    <p>Tamer Baar basar1@illinois.edu</p>
    <p>Q. Zhu, C. Gunter and T. Baar, Tragedy of AnUcommons in Digital Right Management of Medical Records, Technical Report, CSL-UIUC, 2012.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
