<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Risks, Low-tech User Interfaces, and Implantable Medical Devices:</p>
    <p>A Case Study with Insulin Pump Infusion Systems Nathanael Paul</p>
    <p>University of Tennessee/ Oak Ridge National Laboratory</p>
    <p>Tadayoshi Kohno</p>
    <p>Univ. of Washington</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Same circle displayed for low pump reservoir and temporary basal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributing Factors to User Interface (UI) Security</p>
    <p>User Interface: Design tension between safety and security [Clark 2011]</p>
    <p>Authentication: Done through physical control of hardware [Cornelius 2012]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main idea: Change Stored Data to Affect Patient</p>
    <p>Delayed patient effects</p>
    <p>Non-lethal security breaches</p>
    <p>No technical sophistication required</p>
    <p>Targeted</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study: Insulin Pump Systems</p>
    <p>Precedent: Inject injection without detection</p>
    <p>Our Study results</p>
    <p>20 specific settings that could negatively impact patient</p>
    <p>50% of the identified issues pose a greater amount of risk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hypoglycemia</p>
    <p>Hyperglycemia</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Can Happen in 30 Seconds</p>
    <p>Less-risk</p>
    <p>Force a change to a new reservoir (large UI change)</p>
    <p>Add additional BG reading (little UI change)</p>
    <p>More risk</p>
    <p>Change permanent basal rate (no UI change)</p>
    <p>Change insulin-to-carbohydrate ratio (more significant UI change  likely ignored)</p>
    <p>More risk if patient just ate.</p>
    <p>More risk if multiple BG readings added.</p>
    <p>More risk if exercising/sleeping.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Lunch-time Security Issue</p>
    <p>Requirement:  Lunch-time food  predictable. Target blood glucose reading before lunch:  Change ratio of insulin for food intake  Adjust correction for high blood glucose</p>
    <p>One can issue a command to bolus 400+ units  more than double the insulin reservoir contents.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Potential Mitigations</p>
    <p>User-interface  Change interface: Up to 24 hours after critical setting</p>
    <p>change</p>
    <p>Authentication &amp; Authorization  Fail closed: Can duplicate settings in other device</p>
    <p>Measure important patient events (e.g., sleeping)</p>
    <p>Time-based: Stop undesired behaviors during these events</p>
    <p>Proximity-based: Allow changes when in same area</p>
    <p>Auditing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>http://web.eecs.utk.edu/~pauln/</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
