<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accountings of Relationships</p>
    <p>J. Hall (NYU), B. Callan (UT), H. Nissenbuam (NYU)</p>
    <p>HealthSec12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation  Approach  Proposal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>HIPAA Privacy Rule grounded in FIPs  There must be a way for an individual to</p>
    <p>find out what information about him is in a record and how it is used. (emph. added)</p>
    <p>Mechanism in Privacy Rule  Accounting of Disclosure (AOD)</p>
    <p>HHS OCR proposed a new mechanism  Access Report (AR)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis</p>
    <p>Public comments to NPRM = data!  Can extract frustrations/use cases  Initially, analyzed sample of 132/435  AODs arent heavily used  eDRS is a serious problem for scope  Employee privacy/safety problems</p>
    <p>Extending to a comprehensive analysis of all 435 comments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alternatives?</p>
    <p>From the point of contextual integrity:  What do patients care about?  What do they want to know about accesses?  What could patients do with information</p>
    <p>about flows of PHI?  Use cases:  Comparative medical information shopping  Across institutions, longitudinal comparison</p>
    <p>Artifacts that can support more sterile logs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proposal: the AOR</p>
    <p>Aggregate AODs across all patients  Essentially a data structure of aggregate</p>
    <p>information flow for a given time period  Nodes: sources and sinks of PHI  Edges: type of PHI, number of patients,</p>
    <p>purpose for which disclosure made</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Visualizing AORs</p>
    <p>Sankey Diagrams  Visualization of network flows</p>
    <p>Alluvial Diagrams  Visualization of flows over time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sankey Diagrams</p>
    <p>Example from: http://bost.ocks.org/mike/sankey/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alluvial Diagrams</p>
    <p>Example from: http://stanfordneuro.wordpress.com/2010/01/28/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related: TheDataMap</p>
    <p>Example from: http://thedatamap.org/maps.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Privacy in low-N flows  Some systems do not capture this info.  Large amount of flows  Highly dynamic flows  Comparing vocabularies across</p>
    <p>institutions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>joehall@gmail.com</p>
    <p>NYUs work was supported by Grant Number HHS 90TR0003/01 (SHARPS); it is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not represent the views of HHS.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
