<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>On XACMLs Adequacy to Specify and to Enforce HIPAA</p>
    <p>Omar Chowdhury1 Haining Chen2 Jianwei Niu1</p>
    <p>Ninghui Li2 Elisa Bertino2</p>
    <p>University of Texas at San Antonio1</p>
    <p>Purdue University2</p>
    <p>August 7, 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Organizations collect private information from their customer for performing their business operations</p>
    <p>Example: Healthcare providers collect private health information from their patient.</p>
    <p>Federal regulations mandate how the collected information can be used or disclosed</p>
    <p>Example: Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA), Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act (GLBA), etc.</p>
    <p>Violations of these regulations can bring down heavy financial penalties and sanctions for the organizations</p>
    <p>Violations might also be harmful to the organizations reputation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problem</p>
    <p>Researchers have proposed formalism to completely specify privacy regulations like HIPAA</p>
    <p>Organizations intended to enforce privacy regulations will have their own access control policies and business privacy policies</p>
    <p>Using different formalisms to capture each of these policies is cumbersome</p>
    <p>An action can be regulated by all of the policies of the organization</p>
    <p>Have to combine the decisions of the different policies manually</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Current Work</p>
    <p>OASISs eXtensible Access Control Markup Language (XACML) is a widely used access control formalism in both industry and academic research</p>
    <p>The current work evaluates the adequacy of XACMLs specification language and enforcement engine to specify and enforce HIPAA</p>
    <p>XACML has some rich enough features</p>
    <p>Example: attributes, policy/policy rule combination, etc.</p>
    <p>XACML naturally lacks some features to support HIPAA</p>
    <p>Example: event history, obligations, subjective beliefs, etc.</p>
    <p>We present high level designs to extend XACML with the missing features</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HIPAA</p>
    <p>HIPAA privacy regulations ensure that the consumers can access their health information and also make sure their information is protected from unauthorized disclosure</p>
    <p>It mandates the usage or disclosure of patients protected health information by the covered entities</p>
    <p>Example: health plans, health care providers, healthcare clearing houses, etc.</p>
    <p>Protected health information (phi) refers to the individually identifiable health information</p>
    <p>The purposes of a usage or disclosure phi is also regulated by HIPAA</p>
    <p>The role of the entity to whom the disclosure is made is also regulated by HIPAA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>eXtensible Access Control Markup Language (XACML) Specification Language</p>
    <p>Target</p>
    <p>Rules</p>
    <p>Obligations</p>
    <p>Target Condition</p>
    <p>Effect</p>
    <p>POLICIESObligations</p>
    <p>Target</p>
    <p>Policy Set</p>
    <p>Policy Combining Algorithm</p>
    <p>Rule Combining Algorithm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>eXtensible Access Control Markup Language (XACML) Enforcement Architecture</p>
    <p>Policy Enforcement Point (PEP)</p>
    <p>Obligation Service</p>
    <p>Policy Decision Point (PDP)</p>
    <p>Policy Information Point (PIP)</p>
    <p>Policy Database Policy Administration Point</p>
    <p>(PAP)</p>
    <p>Access Request</p>
    <p>Request Response</p>
    <p>Obligations</p>
    <p>Attribute query</p>
    <p>Attributes</p>
    <p>Administration</p>
    <p>Access appropriate policy</p>
    <p>Access Response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Necessary Features for HIPAA</p>
    <p>Attributes: sender, receiver, subject, message</p>
    <p>164.502(a)(1)(i): a covered entity is permitted to use or disclose phi to the individual</p>
    <p>Attribute Inference Policy: it regulates whether a principal has a particular attribute based on his current attributes</p>
    <p>164.502(g)(2): under what conditions a principal is considered another individuals personal representative</p>
    <p>Past Events: past events can influence the permissibility of an action</p>
    <p>164.502(e)(1)(i): a covered entity can disclose phi to its business associate provided that it has received satisfactory assurance about safeguarding the information</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Necessary Features for HIPAA (contd.)</p>
    <p>Obligations: the regulations can also impose obligatory requirements</p>
    <p>164.524(b)(2)(i): a covered entity must act on a request for access no later than 30 days after receiving the request</p>
    <p>Purpose: purpose of an action can also influence its permissibility</p>
    <p>164.506(c)(1): a covered entity may use or disclose phi for its own treatment, payment, or health care operations</p>
    <p>Subjective Beliefs: a subjects judgement can influence permissibility of an action</p>
    <p>164.512(f)(5): a covered entity can disclose phi to a law enforcement official if he thinks it can be used as evidence</p>
    <p>Reference to Other Laws/Rules: the regulations can refer to other laws or rules</p>
    <p>164.512(a)(1): a covered entity may use or disclose phi when it is required by other law</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Assumptions</p>
    <p>The actions we consider are: disclose, request, use, and access</p>
    <p>We only regulate communication messages containing phi of an individual</p>
    <p>The sending principal provides the purpose of the transmission</p>
    <p>It is the responsibility of the sending principal to tag the message with its appropriate attributes</p>
    <p>Any incurred obligations are consistent with the policies</p>
    <p>Patient policies are consistent with HIPAA</p>
    <p>We assume there exists an oracle that makes some decision about some request</p>
    <p>Example: whether certain action is prohibited by any applicable law</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Stateful Policies vs. Stateless Mechanism</p>
    <p>XACML policies are largely stateless</p>
    <p>The enforcement mechanism of XACML is also stateless</p>
    <p>Any stateful information is kept outside the policy engine</p>
    <p>The HIPAA privacy rules are stateful</p>
    <p>The enforcement mechanism for the HIPAA privacy rules needs to be stateful too</p>
    <p>The reason for HIPAA requiring stateful mechanisms are:</p>
    <p>Obligations Event history Policy-directed attribute retrieval Policy-directed policy retrieval</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interactive vs. Non-interactive Policy Evaluation</p>
    <p>XACMLs policy evaluation is non-interactive</p>
    <p>However, it seems for HIPAA an interactive policy evaluation is needed</p>
    <p>The necessity for the interactive policy evaluation:</p>
    <p>Subjective beliefs Reference to other policy rules and laws</p>
    <p>Determining them from the static context of a request is not always feasible</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other Considerations</p>
    <p>Attribute inference policy vs. privacy rules</p>
    <p>A disclosure or usage is allowed when the receiver is patients personal representative</p>
    <p>Example: is principal p a personal representative of the principal q?</p>
    <p>Quantification over the infinite domains</p>
    <p>Quantification is needed for concise policy specification</p>
    <p>Domains are: principals, message attributes, messages, etc.</p>
    <p>Example: a disclosure is allowed if the sender received a message containing the authorization before</p>
    <p>XACMLs specification language does not support quantification explicitly</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HIPAA Privacy Rules</p>
    <p>Required privacy rules and permitting privacy rules</p>
    <p>Permitting privacy rules are divided into two more types</p>
    <p>Allowing and prohibitive privacy rules</p>
    <p>Each privacy rule can regulate the following:</p>
    <p>Senders, recipients, and subjects attributes (e.g., role, etc.)</p>
    <p>Purpose of the disclosure (e.g., treatment, payment, etc.)</p>
    <p>The message attributes (e.g., phi, ssn, psychotherapy-notes etc.)</p>
    <p>Obligations</p>
    <p>Event history</p>
    <p>Other conditions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extensions</p>
    <p>Obligations</p>
    <p>We use the obligation model of Li et al. 2010 An obligation is modeled as a state machine that changes state with respect to events PEP keeps track of the obligations state</p>
    <p>Event history</p>
    <p>We propose a history manager Relation database that keeps track of the important events Manually inspect the policy to decide which events to store in the history manager Example: A covered entity can disclose the phi if it has received a court-order</p>
    <p>Interaction with users and the oracle</p>
    <p>Get information about subjective beliefs Obtain information that is not present in the state (e.g., reference to other laws, etc.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Details of Extensions</p>
    <p>&lt;PolicySet&gt; := &lt;Target&gt;&lt;Policy&gt;+[Obligations] Attributes: PolicySetId, PolicyCombiningAlgId &lt;Policy&gt; := &lt;Target&gt;&lt;Rule&gt;+[Obligations] Attributes: PolicyId, RuleCombiningAlgId &lt;Rule&gt; := [Target][Condition] Attributes: RuleId, Effect</p>
    <p>&lt;Policy&gt; := [RequiredAttributeList]&lt;Target&gt;&lt;Rule&gt;+[Obligations] Attributes: PolicyId, RuleCombiningAlgId &lt;RequiredAttributeList&gt; := &lt;RequiredAttributeSelector&gt;+</p>
    <p>&lt;RequiredAttributeSelector&gt; := [Keys] Attributes: AttributeId, DataType, Source,</p>
    <p>DatabaseId (optional), TableId (optional) &lt;Source&gt; :=  User  |  Database |  Oracle  &lt;Keys&gt; := &lt;Key&gt;+</p>
    <p>&lt;Key&gt; := &lt;KeyValue&gt; Attributes: KeyId</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Details of Extensions (contd.)</p>
    <p>&lt;Condition&gt; := &lt;Expression&gt;</p>
    <p>The &lt;Expression&gt; element substitution group includes: &lt;AttributeSelector&gt;, &lt;AttributeValue&gt;, &lt;VariableReference&gt;, &lt;ActionAttributeDesignator&gt;, &lt;ResourceAttributeDesignator&gt;, &lt;Function&gt;, &lt;SubjectAttributeDesignator&gt;, &lt;Apply&gt;, &lt;EnvironmentAttributeDesignator&gt;, &lt;EventSelector&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;EventSelector&gt; := Attributes: EventType, EventField, DataType</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Details of Extensions (contd.)</p>
    <p>&lt;Condition&gt; := &lt;Expression&gt;</p>
    <p>The &lt;Expression&gt; element substitution group includes: &lt;AttributeSelector&gt;, &lt;AttributeValue&gt;, &lt;VariableReference&gt;, &lt;ActionAttributeDesignator&gt;, &lt;ResourceAttributeDesignator&gt;, &lt;Function&gt;, &lt;SubjectAttributeDesignator&gt;, &lt;Apply&gt;, &lt;EnvironmentAttributeDesignator&gt;, &lt;EventSelector&gt;, &lt;AttributeInferencePolicyReference&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;AttributeInferencePolicyReference&gt; := &lt;Input&gt;+</p>
    <p>Attributes: AttributeInferencePolicyId</p>
    <p>Extension for handling attribute inference policy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Additional Policies</p>
    <p>Organizational access control policies</p>
    <p>Only the assigned doctors and nurses can access the phi of the patient</p>
    <p>It must be consistent with the HIPAA privacy rules</p>
    <p>Patient policies</p>
    <p>According to HIPAA 164.522, a covered entity can agree or disagree to comply with a patients policy</p>
    <p>When it agrees to comply with the patient policy, it has to satisfy the patient policy</p>
    <p>The patient policies must be consistent with the HIPAA privacy rules</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Policy Combination</p>
    <p>Required policy rules are combined using Permit-override</p>
    <p>Allowing policy rules are combined using Permit-override</p>
    <p>Prohibitive policy rules are combined using Deny-override</p>
    <p>Permitting policies are combined using Deny-override</p>
    <p>Required policies and Permitting policy is combined using Permit-override</p>
    <p>Combining additional policies:</p>
    <p>Ordered-deny-overrides policy combination algorithm is used</p>
    <p>Policies are ordered in the following order: access control policy, patient policy, HIPAA policies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extended XACML Enforcement Architecture</p>
    <p>HIPAA Compliance Checking Component External Environment</p>
    <p>PDP Response</p>
    <p>Timer</p>
    <p>Request</p>
    <p>Events</p>
    <p>Set</p>
    <p>PEP</p>
    <p>User</p>
    <p>Interface</p>
    <p>Decision</p>
    <p>Request</p>
    <p>Obligation</p>
    <p>Module</p>
    <p>.. .</p>
    <p>Obligation</p>
    <p>Module</p>
    <p>Events</p>
    <p>Events</p>
    <p>Interfaces</p>
    <p>O</p>
    <p>U</p>
    <p>T</p>
    <p>S</p>
    <p>I</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>E</p>
    <p>Attributes</p>
    <p>Events Events</p>
    <p>PIP</p>
    <p>Events</p>
    <p>Events</p>
    <p>Events</p>
    <p>Events</p>
    <p>Policies</p>
    <p>Histories</p>
    <p>Events</p>
    <p>Events</p>
    <p>Logs</p>
    <p>Events Events</p>
    <p>Events</p>
    <p>Events</p>
    <p>Events</p>
    <p>Events ORACLE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Tschantz et al. 2012: Enforcing the purpose restrictions in the privacy policies</p>
    <p>Garg et al. 2011: Formalized HIPAA and present an incremental auditing algorithm</p>
    <p>DeYoung et al. 2010: Formalized HIPAA and GLBA in the logical specification language PrivacyLFP</p>
    <p>Lam et al. 2009: Formalized HIPAA in a datalog based specification language pLogic</p>
    <p>May et al. 2006: Formalized HIPAA in HRU based specification language Privacy API and performed analysis</p>
    <p>Barth et al. 2006, 2007 : Formalized HIPAA and GLBA in the first order linear temporal logic (FOTL)</p>
    <p>Breaux et al. 2005, 2006, 2008: Tool support for formalizing legal regulations as requirements</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>We evaluate XACMLs adequacy to specify and enforce HIPAA</p>
    <p>XACML has some rich enough features</p>
    <p>XACML lacks some features for HIPAA</p>
    <p>We present high level designs for extending XACML to support HIPAA</p>
    <p>Future work:</p>
    <p>Develop a prototype with the proposed extensions</p>
    <p>Relax some of the restrictions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Thank you for your attention</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
