<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Analysis of HIPAA Breach Data</p>
    <p>Patrick Morrison, Laurie Williams North Carolina State University {pjmorris, lawilli3} @ ncsu.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Realsearch Group</p>
    <p>http://www.realsearchgroup.org</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>However beautiful the strategy, you should occasionally look at the results.</p>
    <p>Winston Churchill</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HIPAA Wall of Shame</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example</p>
    <p>Protected health information was released from the covered entity when an imposter, posing as representatives of the legitimate recycling service used by the covered entity, removed several barrels of purged x-ray films and film jackets.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Breach Fields Reported</p>
    <p>Name of Covered Entity  State  Individuals Affected  Date of Breach (Posted or Updated)  Type of Breach  Location of Breached Info  Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Three Fields Considered</p>
    <p>Breach Type  e.g. Theft, Loss, Hacking/IT Incident</p>
    <p>Breach Location  e.g. Laptop, Email, Backup tape</p>
    <p>Breach Summary  Text description of breach (102 summaries/392 records)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Table</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Summary</p>
    <p>Theft, Loss, and Improper Disposal, combined, account for almost 70% of breach instances ((235+62+23)/461).</p>
    <p>The most common media breached across Types was Paper, with 24% of breach instances (109/461).</p>
    <p>Encryption is almost non-existent in reported breach instances.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations</p>
    <p>Disable the print button  Encrypt PHI at its creation</p>
    <p>(and decrypt only for use)</p>
    <p>Limit data on portable devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Concerns</p>
    <p>A reviewer observed that our recommendations were not novel; we agree.</p>
    <p>It appears that these ideas are not yet universally implemented.</p>
    <p>Consider the entire workflow, not just the software.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Surely theres more we can do</p>
    <p>How do we translate what is known about security and privacy in to health care practice?</p>
    <p>Can we reshape the health care workflow through software design?  Can The Cloud help limit the number of copies of PHI?  Could we encrypt whats printed, and have providers wear</p>
    <p>Decoder glasses?  Your input is clearly needed here</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
