<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VIS--VIS CRYPTOGRAPHY : PRIVATE AND TRUSTWORTHY IN-PERSON CERTIFICATIONS</p>
    <p>IAN MIERS*, MATTHEW GREEN* CHRISTOPH U. LEHMANN, AVIEL D. RUBIN*</p>
    <p>*Johns Hopkins University Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A COMPELLING CASE FOR PRIVACY AND SECURITY</p>
    <p>STIs raise serious privacy concerns</p>
    <p>Something people actual use technology for now</p>
    <p>Something people will not share on Facebook</p>
    <p>Strong incentives exist to cheat.</p>
    <p>Fake a negative test to get sex  Fake a positive test to get revenge</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>STI NOTIFICATION</p>
    <p>Traditionally done</p>
    <p>In person, by phone, or mail  By a public health investigator</p>
    <p>Impractical because of</p>
    <p>Number of chlamydia and gonorrhea cases</p>
    <p>Reporting honesty  Anonymous encounters arranged</p>
    <p>online</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>INSPOT</p>
    <p>The First Online STD Partner Notification System Using Electronic Postcards</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>inSPOT ISSUES</p>
    <p>Privacy  Sensitive information</p>
    <p>Sexual Orientation  Sexual Partners  STI Status</p>
    <p>Disclosure risks  inSPOTs server compromise  Mail provider / account compromise  Targeted Advertising</p>
    <p>Security  Play a joke on a friend  Harass former sexual partner</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>STI CERTIFICATION</p>
    <p>Trust me  Ask them  Check profile on some dating</p>
    <p>site</p>
    <p>Somewhat verified  qpid.me  Bring test results with you</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TruSTI A protocol for STI status certification and exposure notification using mobile devices</p>
    <p>Relay IP address Shared secret</p>
    <p>Relay IP address Shared secret</p>
    <p>Relay IP address Shared secret</p>
    <p>Relay IP address Shared secret</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relay IP address Shared secret</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relay IP address Shared secret</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relay IP address Shared secret</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relay IP address Shared secret</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SECURITY GOALS Unforgeability</p>
    <p>Alice cannot convince Bob she has a positive or negative STI unless she has such a result from the clinic</p>
    <p>Deniability</p>
    <p>No one can convince a third party of someones STI result or even that the interaction took place</p>
    <p>Reciprocal anonymity</p>
    <p>Running these protocols should decrease Alice or Bobs anonymity no more than the an in person meeting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>STANDARD APPROACHES FAIL</p>
    <p>Digital Certificate</p>
    <p>Not anonymous  not deniable</p>
    <p>Physical ID Card</p>
    <p>Counterfeitable  Revocation is logistically</p>
    <p>problematic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ANONYMOUS CREDENTIALS FAIL  Present third party signed messages</p>
    <p>anonymously  Impose a tax on transfer via:</p>
    <p>All or nothing non-transferability  PKI assured non-transferability</p>
    <p>Real non-transferability implies cryptographic proof an encounter took place</p>
    <p>Does not work for notification</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OUR APPROACH</p>
    <p>Sign STI Status + Photo  Use clinics and testing labs as trusted</p>
    <p>authorities  Already exists and is trusted with</p>
    <p>sensitive data</p>
    <p>Already regulated by HIPAA</p>
    <p>Use a deniable construction for showing status and photo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Objects in this mockup may be prettier than they appear in the actual product</p>
    <p>UI MOCKUP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>One foot down the rabbit hole</p>
    <p>CRYPTOGRAPHIC BACKGROUND</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NON INTERACTIVE ZERO KNOWLEDGE PROOFS</p>
    <p>A proof of knowledge of values satisfying an equation that does not reveal those values:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SIGNATURES WITH EFFICIENT PROTOCOLS</p>
    <p>Standard digital signature scheme with one additional feature:</p>
    <p>Users can prove they have a signed message without revealing the signature</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>COMMITMENTS Allow you to commit and later reveal a value</p>
    <p>Csetup: generates parameters</p>
    <p>Commit: commits to a value</p>
    <p>Decommit: reveal the value</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>THE TECHNIQUE</p>
    <p>Alice wants to prove to Bob she has a negative STI test. They both have the app and are enrolled in the system</p>
    <p>Alice gives Bob a NIZKPoK that either</p>
    <p>She knows a number Bob committed to</p>
    <p>OR  She has a signature on her STI status and photo from the clinic.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CERTIFY PROTOCOL</p>
    <p>Bob Commits to a nonce n</p>
    <p>Alice commits to</p>
    <p>Bob reveals n</p>
    <p>Alice reveals</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PROGRESS/ FUTURE WORK</p>
    <p>Complete Application</p>
    <p>Mark users as exposed</p>
    <p>Propagating notifications</p>
    <p>Compute exposure risk for users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alt-text:Yet one more reason I'm barred from speaking at crypto conferences</p>
    <p>QUESTIONS?</p>
    <p>Randal Monroe xkcd.com/177</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
