<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Enabling Robust Information Accountability in E-healthcare Systems</p>
    <p>Daisuke Mashima Mustaque Ahamad</p>
    <p>College of Computing</p>
    <p>Georgia Institute of Technology Atlanta, GA, USA</p>
    <p>USENIX HealthSec 12 Bellevue, WA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background / Motivation</p>
    <p>User-centric Monitoring Agent System</p>
    <p>Enabling Actionable Accountability</p>
    <p>Prototype Implementation &amp; Performance</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Transition from paper-based records to electronic health (medical) record  Electronic Health Record (EHR)</p>
    <p>systems  Personal Health Record (PHR)</p>
    <p>systems</p>
    <p>Meaningful Use incentive program by CMS  HITECH Act in 2009</p>
    <p>Initiatives for large-scale health information exchange  Nationwide Health Information</p>
    <p>Network (NHIN)  NHIN Direct</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Misuse of Health Information</p>
    <p>In September, 2006, one front desk office coordinator at Cleveland Clinic in Weston, FL was indicted for committing healthcare fraud. She abused her access privilege to download healthcare records of more than 1,100 patients. She then sold them to her cousin, who owned a medical claims company in Florida and filed false claims to Medicare to gain approximately $2.8 million.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Breach by Insiders</p>
    <p>According to HHS, a large number of data breach cases are caused through lost or stolen devices used in healthcare organizations.</p>
    <p>Yet another possibility</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accountability for EHR Sharing / Usage</p>
    <p>Assurance of knowledge about how an EHR reaches a certain health record consumer</p>
    <p>Providing patients with verifiable evidence about who is involved in the sharing path of a certain EHR</p>
    <p>Provide patients with awareness and actionable information Discourage malicious / inappropriate handling by insiders</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work  Information accountability</p>
    <p>Weitzner et al. (2008)  The use of information should be transparent so it is possible to</p>
    <p>determine whether a particular use is appropriate  and that the system enables individuals and institutions to be held accountable for misuse.</p>
    <p>Visibility, under established rules, can encourage compliance.</p>
    <p>Auditing in healthcare organizations  King et al. (2012)</p>
    <p>Current EHR systems have major weakness with user-based nonrepudiation.</p>
    <p>Possibility of tampering or forgery by a system administrator</p>
    <p>Data provenance  Aldeco-Perez et al. (2008), Kifor et al. (2008) etc.  Derivation history of each data  Created based on a set of assertions.  Centralized assertion store is not often realistic.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User-centric Monitoring Agent for Enhancing Users Awareness</p>
    <p>(ACM IHI 2012)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User-centric Monitoring Agent</p>
    <p>User-controlled reference monitor to mediate accesses to data in a distributed setting  Reliable mediation under assumptions reasonable in</p>
    <p>recent e-healthcare settings</p>
    <p>An online service deployed on an entity trusted (chosen or managed) by each patient</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scope and Assumptions</p>
    <p>Allows patients to be aware of by whom and when their health records are meaningfully consumed.  Meaningful usage of health records is accompanied by</p>
    <p>integrity/authenticity verification.  Legitimate consumers (Medicare etc.) are naturally motivated to do so.  Adversaries can obtain meaningful gain only by presenting health data to</p>
    <p>legitimate consumers.  HIPAA Section 164.520 &quot;Notice of privacy practices&quot;</p>
    <p>A repository accepts new records (or update of record) only under patients awareness.  Justified by patients right noted in Section 164.524 of HITECH Act.</p>
    <p>PKI is established and every participant is assigned a key pair by one of trust anchors.  Under NHIN Direct standards, PKI is required.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Architecture Overview</p>
    <p>Monitoring Agent</p>
    <p>Doctor (Issuer)</p>
    <p>Repository Doctor (Consumer)</p>
    <p>Hospital A Hospital B</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Update of Health Record (Accountable Update)</p>
    <p>Issuer Repository</p>
    <p>Patients Monitoring Agent</p>
    <p>Request Authorization</p>
    <p>Authorization Proof</p>
    <p>Receipt is issued</p>
    <p>Submit Record</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Usage of Health Record (Accountable Usage)</p>
    <p>Repository</p>
    <p>Consumer</p>
    <p>Health record with encrypted issuer</p>
    <p>signature</p>
    <p>Patients Monitoring Agent</p>
    <p>Issuers signature designated to the specific consumer</p>
    <p>(UDVS)</p>
    <p>Leaked or shared</p>
    <p>Can not verify the issuer signature!</p>
    <p>When the record is meaningfully used,</p>
    <p>again monitoring agent is involved.</p>
    <p>Can verify the authenticity via the</p>
    <p>designated signature.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Enabling Actionable Accountability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Identifying The Source of Breach</p>
    <p>Awareness alone is not sufficient.  In case of misuse, it is often not possible to</p>
    <p>determine the responsible entities.</p>
    <p>Lack of actionable accountability would encourage insider threats.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accountability Tag</p>
    <p>Metadata that is attached to each copy of healthcare records.  Conveys information about the one-hop EHR</p>
    <p>sharing.  Accumulated tags enable a patient to re</p>
    <p>construct the complete sharing path.</p>
    <p>Verified and logged by a patients monitoring agent when:  Accountable Usage is run.  A shared record is submitted via</p>
    <p>Accountable Update.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accountability Tag</p>
    <p>Tag (Activated)  Signed by a source of healthcare record sharing (A) with the</p>
    <p>recipients (Bs) identity.</p>
    <p>CERTB</p>
    <p>CTag (Confirmed)  Signed with the designated recipients (Bs) private key.</p>
    <p>PreTag  Issued (signed) by a repository that releases a healthcare</p>
    <p>record and signed along with the downloaders (As) identity.</p>
    <p>CERTA : M</p>
    <p>3 stages of accountability tags:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analogy to Personal Check</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accountability Tag System</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>Ra</p>
    <p>B Rb</p>
    <p>[A]Ra</p>
    <p>[B,[A]Ra]A</p>
    <p>[[B,[A]Ra]A]B</p>
    <p>[[B,[A]Ra]A]B</p>
    <p>Accountable Usage</p>
    <p>Healthcare Organization A</p>
    <p>Healthcare Organization B</p>
    <p>Path: Ra - A - B - C</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accountability Tag System</p>
    <p>A Ra</p>
    <p>B Rb</p>
    <p>[A]Ra</p>
    <p>[B,[A]Ra]A</p>
    <p>Healthcare Organization A</p>
    <p>Healthcare Organization B</p>
    <p>[[B,[A]Ra]A]B</p>
    <p>Accountable Update</p>
    <p>[[B,[A]Ra]A]B</p>
    <p>Path: Ra - A - B - Rb</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accountability Tag System</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>Ra</p>
    <p>B Rb</p>
    <p>Healthcare Organization A</p>
    <p>Healthcare Organization B</p>
    <p>Path: Ra - A - B - Rb</p>
    <p>[B]Rb</p>
    <p>[X,[B]Rb]B</p>
    <p>[[X,[B]Rb]B]D [[X,[B]Rb]B]D</p>
    <p>Accountable Usage</p>
    <p>Path: Ra - A - B - Rb Rb - B - X - C</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study: Cleveland Clinic Case</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>Ra</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>[A]Ra</p>
    <p>[B,[A]Ra]A</p>
    <p>[[B,[A]Ra]A]B</p>
    <p>[[B,[A]Ra]A]B</p>
    <p>Accountable Usage</p>
    <p>Path: Ra - A - B - C</p>
    <p>Front Desk Clerk</p>
    <p>The Clerks Cousin</p>
    <p>Medicare</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prototype Implementation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Integration in NHIN Direct</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overhead for Robust Accountability</p>
    <p>Task Response Time w/o Acct. Tag [ms]</p>
    <p>Response Time w/ Acct. Tag [ms]</p>
    <p>Tag Activation 0 15.47 (4.08)</p>
    <p>Tag Confirmation 0 15.18 (4.29)</p>
    <p>Acct. Usage (3MB) 1,151.33 (113.99) 1,345.83 (106.3)</p>
    <p>Acct. Usage (6MB) 1,792.65 (41.58) 1,560.31 (149.28)</p>
    <p>Acct. Update (3MB) 4,957.17 (227.27) 4,530.44 (82.35)</p>
    <p>Acct. Update (6MB) 9834.60 (62.62) 9,117.53 (123.28)</p>
    <p>Overhead for additional accountability guarantee is far less than 1 second.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Assurance of information accountability  A patient can know how the record reached consumers</p>
    <p>from the source repository.  A patient can know which organization stores copies of</p>
    <p>her records.</p>
    <p>Mitigation of risks owing to lost / stolen health records  Absence of an accountability tag does not allow</p>
    <p>healthcare records to be meaningfully consumed.</p>
    <p>Patients control over EHR usage / update  Implemented through a black list on a patients</p>
    <p>monitoring agent.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you very much.</p>
    <p>mashima@cc.gatech.edu http://www.cc.gatech.edu/~mashima</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
