<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jure Leskovec, Lars Backstrom and Jon Kleinberg Computer science department Cornell University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Intersection of news media, technology, and the political process</p>
    <p>From its early stages, a tension between global effects from the mass media and local effects carried by social structure</p>
    <p>How does information transmitted by the media interact with the personal</p>
    <p>influence arising from social networks?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Internet, blogging, and social media:  Social media means the dichotomy between global</p>
    <p>and local influence is evaporating  Speed of media reporting and discussion has</p>
    <p>intensified: very rapid progression of stories, with no pauses</p>
    <p>The 24-hour news cycle:  Difficult to define, but associated with</p>
    <p>technological acceleration and a challenge to healthy civic discourse [Kovach-Rosenstiel 99]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sept. 11, 2008 (New York Times): Mr. McCain's increasingly aggressive campaign has sought to put Mr. Obama on the defensive in each news cycle, using any development at hand, like Mr. Obama's colloquial comment this week about putting lipstick on a pig.</p>
    <p>Oct. 10, 2008 (New York Times): Mr. McCain's traveling road show has veered from message to message ... . Each news cycle seems to bring another tactic as the campaign appears to be trying anything and everything to see what might work.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Question: Is the news cycle simply a metaphorical construct describing our perception of the news, or is it visible in data?</p>
    <p>And if it's visible, can we measure some of its basic properties?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What basic units make up the news cycle?  Cascasding hyper-links to articles: too fine-grained</p>
    <p>[Adar et al 04, Gruhl et al 04, Kumar et al 03, Leskovec et al]</p>
    <p>Topics as probabilistic term mixtures: too coarsegrained [Blei-Lafferty 06, Wang-McCallum 06, Wang et al 07]  Named entities: too coarse-grained</p>
    <p>Obama, McCain, Microsoft, Paris, Apple</p>
    <p>Common sequence of words: too noisy I love you, web 2.0, Oh my God, Made in China</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Need units that:  correspond to aggregates of articles,  vary over the order of days,  and can be handled at terabyte scale</p>
    <p>Plan: identify text fragments, phrases, memes that travel relatively unchanged through many articles.</p>
    <p>Idea: quoted phrases: .*  are integral parts of journalistic practices  tend to follow iterations of a story as it evolves  are attributed to individuals and have time and location</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data from Spinn3r on the 3 months leading up to the 2008 U.S. Presidential Election:  1 million news articles and blog posts per day  Essentially a complete online media coverage:  20,000 sites that are part of Google News  1.6 million blogs  From August 1 to October 31 2008  90 million documents from 1.65 million sites, 390GB  We extract 112 million quotes (phrases)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our opponent is someone who sees America, it seems, as being so imperfect, imperfect enough that hes palling around with terrorists who would target their own country. 11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BCD</p>
    <p>ABC</p>
    <p>CEF</p>
    <p>BDXCY</p>
    <p>ABCD</p>
    <p>ABCEF</p>
    <p>CEFP</p>
    <p>UVCEXF</p>
    <p>ABCDEFGH</p>
    <p>ABCEFG</p>
    <p>CEFPQR</p>
    <p>Nodes are quotes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BCD</p>
    <p>ABC</p>
    <p>CEF</p>
    <p>BDXCY</p>
    <p>ABCD</p>
    <p>ABCEF</p>
    <p>CEFP</p>
    <p>UVCEXF</p>
    <p>ABCDEFGH</p>
    <p>ABCEFG</p>
    <p>CEFPQR</p>
    <p>Nodes are quotes Edges are inclusion relations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BCD</p>
    <p>ABC</p>
    <p>CEF</p>
    <p>BDXCY</p>
    <p>ABCD</p>
    <p>ABCEF</p>
    <p>CEFP</p>
    <p>UVCEXF</p>
    <p>ABCDEFGH</p>
    <p>ABCEFG</p>
    <p>CEFPQR</p>
    <p>Nodes are quotes Edges are inclusion relations Edges have weights</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Objective: in directed acyclic graph (approx. quote inclusion), delete min total edge weight s.t. each connected component has a single sink node</p>
    <p>BCD</p>
    <p>ABC</p>
    <p>CEF</p>
    <p>BDXCYZ</p>
    <p>ABCD</p>
    <p>ABCEF</p>
    <p>CEFP</p>
    <p>UVCEXF</p>
    <p>ABCDEFGH</p>
    <p>ABCEFG</p>
    <p>CEFPQR</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observation: enough to know nodes parent  Heuristic: proceed top down and assign node to</p>
    <p>strongest cluster</p>
    <p>BCD</p>
    <p>ABC</p>
    <p>CEF</p>
    <p>BDXCYZ</p>
    <p>ABCD</p>
    <p>ABCEF</p>
    <p>CEFP</p>
    <p>UVCEXF</p>
    <p>ABCDEFGH</p>
    <p>ABCEFG</p>
    <p>CEFPQR</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quoted text Volume</p>
    <p>the fundamentals of our economy are strong 3654 the fundamentals of the economy are strong 988 fundamentals of our economy are strong 645 fundamentals of the economy are strong 557 if john mccain hadn't said that the fundamentals of our economy are strong on the day of one of our nation's worst financial crises the claim that he invented the blackberry would have been the most preposterous thing said all week 224 fundamentals of the economy 172 the fundamentals of the economy are sound 119 i promise you we will never put america in this position again we will clean up wall street 83 the fundamentals of our economy are sound 81 clean up wall street 78 our economy i think still the fundamentals of our economy are strong 75 fundamentals of the economy are sound 72 the fundamentals of our economy are strong but these are very very difficult times and i promise you we will never put america in this position again 68 the economy is in crisis 66 these are very very difficult times 63 the fundamentals of our economy are strong but these are very very difficult times 62 do you still think the fundamentals of our economy are strong genius 62 our economy i think still the fundamentals of our economy are strong but these are very very difficult times 60 mccain's first response to this crisis was to say that the fundamentals of our economy are strong then he admitted it was a crisis and then he proposed a commission which is just washington-speak for i'll get back to you later 55 i still believe the fundamentals of our economy are strong 53 i think still the fundamentals of our economy are strong 50 cut taxes for 95 percent of all working families 5017</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>is periodic, has no trends. Bandwidth of the online media is constant</p>
    <p>Can we extract any interesting temporal variations??</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Volume over time of top 50 largest total volume quote clusters August October</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What ingredients are essential to qualitatively reproduce the observed dynamics?  Temporal variation has potential connections with</p>
    <p>natural processes  Species competing for resources in an ecosystem.  Biological systems synchronize to favor small number of</p>
    <p>individuals [Lacker-Peskin 1981]</p>
    <p>N news sources, one new story per time step. Sources choice of what to cover controlled by:  Imitation: increasing in number of sources covering story  Recency: decreasing in time since story's appearance  Attractiveness: prefer more interesting stories</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Only imitation</p>
    <p>Only recency/attractiveness</p>
    <p>Imitation &amp; Recency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can study typical quote cluster volume curve  Peak behaves like a delta function. Phrases are</p>
    <p>very short lived.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Using Google News we label:  Mainstream media: 20,000 sites (44% vol.)  Blog (everything else): 1.6 million sites (56% vol.)</p>
    <p>Peak blog intensity comes about 2.5 hours after news peak.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can classify individual sources by their typical timing relative to the peak aggregate intensity</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>fe ss</p>
    <p>io na</p>
    <p>l b lo</p>
    <p>gs N</p>
    <p>ew s</p>
    <p>m ed</p>
    <p>ia</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can study oscillation of attention between news and media</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can formulate queries for different temporal signatures: e.g., stories catalyzed by blogs: [x; y; t]-query: between x and y frac. of total quote volume</p>
    <p>(fb) occurred on blogs at least t days before overall the peak</p>
    <p>In total 3.5% of phrases migrate from blogs to media 28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A framework for tracking memes through the news, to quantify the dynamics of the news cycle.</p>
    <p>Demo + Data: http://memetracker.org</p>
    <p>Many further questions:  Which elements of the news cycle do we miss?  Can this analysis of memes help identify dynamics of</p>
    <p>polarization? (cf. [Adamic-Glance, 2005])  How are these memes actually spreading among</p>
    <p>people? 29</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
