<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>STRATEGIC HEALTH IT ADVANCED RESEARCH PROJECTS ON SECURITY</p>
    <p>sharps.org Stanford</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UNDERSTANDING THE CHALLENGES WITH MEDICAL DATA SEGMENTATION Ellick M. Chan, Peifung E. Lam and John C. Mitchell 8/12/13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Federal  HIPAA  HITECH</p>
    <p>State laws on  Mental Health</p>
    <p>Substance Abuse  STDs</p>
    <p>Genetic testing</p>
    <p>Organizational</p>
    <p>Health Information Exchange Cloud</p>
    <p>Health Information Exchange (HIE)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Compliance approaches Automated Policy</p>
    <p>&gt;| %%Standard rules for &quot;uses and disclosures&quot; permitted_by_164_502_a(A) :is_from_coveredEntity(A), is_phi(A), (permitted_by_160_C(A); permitted_by_164_502_a_1(A); required_by_164_502_a_2(A)). permitted_by_164_502_a_1(A):permitted_by_164_502_a_1_i(A); permitted_by_164_502_a_1_ii(A); permitted_by_164_502_a_1_iii(A); permitted_by_164_502_a_1_iv(A); permitted_by_164_502_a_1_v(A); permitted_by_164_502_a_1_vi(A).</p>
    <p>164.502 Uses and disclosures of protected health information: general rules. (a) Standard. A covered entity may not use or disclose protected health information, except as permitted or required by this subpart or by subpart C of part 160 of this subchapter. (1) Permitted uses and disclosures. A covered entity is permitted to use or disclose protected health information as follows: (i) To the individual; (ii) For treatment, payment, or health care operations, as permitted by and in compliance with 164.506; (iii) Incident to a use or disclosure otherwise permitted or required by this subpart, provided that the covered entity has complied with the applicable requirements of 164.502(b), 164.514(d), and 164.530(c) with respect to such otherwise permitted</p>
    <p>HIPAA Law</p>
    <p>010110...</p>
    <p>Data segmentation</p>
    <p>compliantWithALaw( A )</p>
    <p>permittedBySomeClause( A ) notForbiddenBy AnyClause( A )</p>
    <p>AND</p>
    <p>permittedBy Clause1( A )</p>
    <p>clause1 Applicable( A )</p>
    <p>meetReq Clause1( A )</p>
    <p>permittedBySome RefOfClause1( A )</p>
    <p>permittedByClause Ref_I,J( A )</p>
    <p>AND</p>
    <p>notForbidden ByClause1( A )</p>
    <p>notForbidden ByClauseM( A )</p>
    <p>clauseM NotApplicable( A )</p>
    <p>AND</p>
    <p>IHI 2012</p>
    <p>According to research by the California HealthCare Foundation, 15 percent of patients who know their information will be shared would hide information from their doctor, and another 33 percent would consider hiding information[1].</p>
    <p>Health Record</p>
    <p>Medications  Previous</p>
    <p>diagnoses  Labs</p>
    <p>Sensitive conditions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example</p>
    <p>Medications</p>
    <p>1. Tylenol</p>
    <p>2. Sudafed</p>
    <p>3. AZT</p>
    <p>4. Bactrim</p>
    <p>Problem List</p>
    <p>1. Headache</p>
    <p>2. Sinus Infection</p>
    <p>3. HIV positive  4. UTI</p>
    <p>Adapted from J. Halamka, 2012</p>
    <p>Letter I hope you and your partner had a great weekend in Provincetown and that the thrush has improved with the mouthwash sample I gave you.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example</p>
    <p>Medications</p>
    <p>1. Tylenol</p>
    <p>2. Sudafed</p>
    <p>3. AZT</p>
    <p>4. Bactrim</p>
    <p>Problem List</p>
    <p>1. Headache</p>
    <p>2. Sinus Infection</p>
    <p>3. HIV positive</p>
    <p>4. UTI</p>
    <p>Letter I hope you and your partner had a great weekend in Provincetown and that the thrush has improved with the mouthwash sample I gave you.</p>
    <p>Hide HIV/AIDS ICD-9 code 042</p>
    <p>Adapted from J. Halamka, 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example</p>
    <p>Medications</p>
    <p>1. Tylenol</p>
    <p>2. Sudafed</p>
    <p>3. AZT</p>
    <p>4. Bactrim</p>
    <p>Problem List</p>
    <p>1. Headache</p>
    <p>2. Sinus Infection</p>
    <p>3. HIV positive  4. UTI</p>
    <p>Letter I hope you and your partner had a great weekend in Provincetown and that the thrush has improved with the mouthwash sample I gave you.</p>
    <p>Zidovudine (INN) or azidothymidine (AZT) is a type of antiretroviral drug used for the</p>
    <p>treatment of HIV/AIDS.</p>
    <p>Side effects: anemia, neutropenia, hepatotoxicity, cardiomyopathy, and</p>
    <p>myopathy</p>
    <p>+side effects</p>
    <p>Adapted from J. Halamka, 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example</p>
    <p>Medications</p>
    <p>1. Tylenol</p>
    <p>2. Sudafed</p>
    <p>3. AZT</p>
    <p>4. Bactrim</p>
    <p>Problem List</p>
    <p>1. Headache</p>
    <p>2. Sinus Infection</p>
    <p>3. HIV positive  4. UTI</p>
    <p>Letter I hope you and your partner had a great weekend in Provincetown and that the thrush has improved with the mouthwash sample I gave you.</p>
    <p>Trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole or cotrimoxazole (abbreviated SXT, TMP-SMX, TMP-SMZ or TMP-sulfa) is a sulfonamide</p>
    <p>antibiotic combination of trimethoprim and sulfamethoxazole, in the ratio of 1 to 5,</p>
    <p>used in the treatment of a variety of bacterial infections.</p>
    <p>+side effects</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>Adapted from J. Halamka, 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example</p>
    <p>Medications</p>
    <p>1. Tylenol</p>
    <p>2. Sudafed</p>
    <p>3. AZT</p>
    <p>4. Bactrim</p>
    <p>Problem List</p>
    <p>1. Headache</p>
    <p>2. Sinus Infection</p>
    <p>3. HIV positive  4. UTI</p>
    <p>Letter I hope you and your partner had a great weekend in Provincetown and that the thrush has improved with the mouthwash sample I gave you.</p>
    <p>Prophylaxis (preventative med) for immunocompromised patient?</p>
    <p>Patient has urinary tract infection (UTI),</p>
    <p>plausibly deniable case.</p>
    <p>+side effects</p>
    <p>Adapted from J. Halamka, 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example</p>
    <p>Medications</p>
    <p>1. Tylenol</p>
    <p>2. Sudafed</p>
    <p>3. AZT</p>
    <p>4. Bactrim</p>
    <p>Problem List</p>
    <p>1. Headache</p>
    <p>2. Sinus Infection</p>
    <p>3. HIV positive  4. UTI</p>
    <p>Letter I hope you and your partner had a great weekend in Provincetown and that the thrush has improved with the mouthwash sample I gave you.</p>
    <p>Highest rate of same-sec couples in Provincetown, MA.</p>
    <p>Karen Christel Krahulik,</p>
    <p>Provincetown: From Pilgrim Landing to Gay Resort, NYU Press, 2007, p. 51.</p>
    <p>+side effects</p>
    <p>Adapted from J. Halamka, 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example</p>
    <p>Medications</p>
    <p>1. Tylenol</p>
    <p>2. Sudafed</p>
    <p>3. AZT</p>
    <p>4. Bactrim</p>
    <p>Problem List</p>
    <p>1. Headache</p>
    <p>2. Sinus Infection</p>
    <p>3. HIV positive  4. UTI</p>
    <p>Letter I hope you and your partner had a great weekend in Provincetown and that the thrush has improved with the mouthwash sample I gave you.</p>
    <p>Candidiasis (thrush) - Candidiasis or thrush is a fungal infection (mycosis). Commonly</p>
    <p>causes mouth yeast infections, which manifest as white patches in the mouth.</p>
    <p>+side effects</p>
    <p>Adapted from J. Halamka, 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example</p>
    <p>Medications</p>
    <p>1. Tylenol</p>
    <p>2. Sudafed</p>
    <p>3. AZT</p>
    <p>4. Bactrim</p>
    <p>Problem List</p>
    <p>1. Headache</p>
    <p>2. Sinus Infection</p>
    <p>3. HIV positive  4. UTI</p>
    <p>Letter I hope you and your partner had a great weekend in Provincetown and that the thrush has improved with the mouthwash sample I gave you.</p>
    <p>Headaches &amp; HIV: 24/535 patients  4.5% CDC NHDS 2010 dataset. 115,000</p>
    <p>patients.</p>
    <p>Mononucleosis-like symptoms</p>
    <p>+side effects</p>
    <p>Adapted from J. Halamka, 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Disorders</p>
    <p>Manifestations Treatments Effects</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Threat Model</p>
    <p>Attacker has direct access to redacted health record, medical literature</p>
    <p>Attacker does not have the computational capability to circumvent security mechanisms that protect the primary sensitive codes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Treatments 15</p>
    <p>Concept Description Links Notes</p>
    <p>Risperidone</p>
    <p>Treats schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, and autism.</p>
    <p>schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, autism, weight gain, insomnia, alopecia</p>
    <p>Use of Risperidone usually implies treatment of a mental health disorder.</p>
    <p>Carbamazepine Anti-convulsant and moodstabilizing drug. Treats epilepsy and bipolar disorder.</p>
    <p>epilepsy, bipolar disorder, headaches, drowsiness</p>
    <p>Primarily used to treat mental health disorders. Could be used off-label to treat Complex regional pain syndrome(ICD9: 337.21)</p>
    <p>Citalopram</p>
    <p>Primarily used as an SSRI to treat depression. Can also be used to treat hot flashes.</p>
    <p>depression, hot flashes, anorgasmia, nausea, diarrhea</p>
    <p>Can treat both sensitive and non-sensitive conditions.</p>
    <p>Lamotrigine</p>
    <p>Primarily used as an anticonvulsant drug to treat epilepsy and bipolar disorder. Can also treat migraines.</p>
    <p>epilepsy, bipolar disorder, migraines</p>
    <p>Can be used to treat mental health disorders or migraines.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Formal model</p>
    <p>Hypothesis {d1, d3}</p>
    <p>{d2, d3}</p>
    <p>{d1, d2, d3}</p>
    <p>{d1, d2}</p>
    <p>d1 D</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>m1 M</p>
    <p>d2 d3</p>
    <p>m2 m3 m4</p>
    <p>Reggias set cover model  Plausibility  set cover  Likelihood  Occams razor and fitness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Formal model</p>
    <p>Hypothesis {d1, d3}</p>
    <p>{d2, d3}</p>
    <p>{d1, d2, d3}</p>
    <p>{d1, d2}</p>
    <p>d1 D</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>m1 M</p>
    <p>d2 d3</p>
    <p>m2 m3 m4</p>
    <p>Reggias set cover model  Plausibility  set cover  Likelihood  Occams razor and fitness</p>
    <p>d4</p>
    <p>m5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Explanation of manifestations</p>
    <p>Best explanation E of manifestations:  Covers all observed manifestations M+</p>
    <p>Is the simplest (parsimonious) definition</p>
    <p>Heuristics for best cover  Minimality - |E| is minimal  Criticism: minimal cardinality covers can be too restrictive</p>
    <p>n Occams razor vs Hickams dictum</p>
    <p>Irredundancy  removing any disorder results in a non-cover of M+</p>
    <p>Relevancy  Every d in D must be causally associated with some m in M+</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Medical concepts</p>
    <p>Sensitive Concepts</p>
    <p>u AIDS</p>
    <p>u Psychosis</p>
    <p>u Alcohol Abuse</p>
    <p>u Diseases</p>
    <p>Manifestations  Kaposis Sarcoma</p>
    <p>Cervical Cancer</p>
    <p>Stroke</p>
    <p>Delusions</p>
    <p>Memory Loss</p>
    <p>Rotavirus</p>
    <p>u Schizophrenia</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Delusion Hallucination Alcoholism HIV+ Stroke Memory loss</p>
    <p>Manifestations</p>
    <p>Psychosis Alzheimers Disease</p>
    <p>Diseases</p>
    <p>Source: PubMed, NIH.gov</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Predicate-Reducer definition 21</p>
    <p>Rhinovirus Mental health STDs Substance abuse X-ray [Free text] R</p>
    <p>Rhinovirus Mental health STDs Substance abuse X-ray [Free text]</p>
    <p>A  Medical algorithm   Policy determines sensitive code s M  Medical record Predicate P(M, )  Determines if s M Reducer R(M, )  Removes s from M</p>
    <p>Ideal reducer</p>
    <p>A(m) = A(R (m)) m  M</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inference approach</p>
    <p>Input: Reduce(Diseases U Manifestations U Treatments)  Output: Inferred Diseases</p>
    <p>1. For each input, evoke hypotheses  2. Evaluate hypotheses  3. Rank hypotheses according to fitness</p>
    <p>Hypothesis fitness  Competing hypotheses, e.g. d1 or d2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithm overview 23</p>
    <p>R(EHR)</p>
    <p>Salient Concepts</p>
    <p>Docs</p>
    <p>Hypotheses</p>
    <p>Extract Concepts</p>
    <p>Retrieve Documents</p>
    <p>Extract and rank Hypo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithm overview 24</p>
    <p>Hypothesis Rank HFI Notes {d1, d3} 1 0.91 This is the most supported hypothesis. {d2, d3} 2 0.88 This could be a competing solution, which</p>
    <p>can provide plausible deniability because the HFI support is similar.</p>
    <p>{d1, d2, d3} 3 0.35 This solution is not well supported, and not parsimonious.</p>
    <p>{d1, d2} 4 X m4 is not covered, so this is not a solution.</p>
    <p>Table 2: Fitness example for m1, m2, m3, m4</p>
    <p>Given a patients potentially segmented EHR, Algorithm 1 attempts to discover if some sensitive medical concepts may have been segmented based on the remaining non-sensitive manifestations that are observable to the algorithm.</p>
    <p>To do so, the algorithm selects combinations of manifestations from the health record as queries. For instance, queries corresponding to the hypotheses in Figure 1 could include:m1 AND m3,m2 AND m3, m1 AND m2 AND m3, and so on. Each query then searches for medical knowledge documents that contain these manifestations, and the search results are then used to generate hypotheses. These can correspond to the differential diagnosis hypothesis list (Section 3), and the hypotheses are evaluated using the techniques from Section 4.3.</p>
    <p>However, as Figure 3 illustrates, a naive approach to exploring the potentially large query space could be slow or intractable. In practice, we have encountered cases where the query was longer than six terms, and each term could be selected from a list of hundreds of manifestations. To address this difficulty, we use probabilistic sampling methods to help us comb the space effectively.</p>
    <p>On the other hand, a strict interpretation of the AND operator in the query may lead to a small result set that may be insufficient to support the hypotheses. Figure 4 illustrates this idea more concretely with an example where a hypothetical patients record contains three terms: Toxoplasmosis (TX), weight loss (WL), and cervical cancer (CC). The top query, TX ^ WL ^ CC00 identifies documents that concern all three terms, however, this may be too restrictive, as only 25 documents from PubMed Open Access are retrieved, and that may not provide sufficient perspective and support for the hypothesis. To expand the search, we relax the conditions slightly and perform subqueries that match all but one condition. E.g. TX ^ WL00, TX ^ CC00, WL ^ CC00. Each time this process is performed, the set of documents considered is expanded. In this example, expanding one level yields support from over 2,000 documents, much more than the original 25. In practice, weve seen that this greatly improves the ability of our algorithms to infer sensitive hypotheses.</p>
    <p>Inferring sensitive concepts from an EHR Given an EHR, our algorithms can be applied as follows. First, to generate the queries, we select query terms from the EHR with respect to a certain probability distribution. One way to do so is to use the frequency distribution of the underlying medical knowledge base. Intuitively, this is done as a heuristic to maximize the number of documents returned.</p>
    <p>To calculate this distribution, we take a set of documents from</p>
    <p>a given knowledge base, such as PubMed, and a set of medical terms from medical term databases such as MESH, SnoMed, or PubChem, and build a set containing the medical terms and their probability distribution within the knowledge base.</p>
    <p>Convergence is reached when the top k hypotheses in the cumulated results remain the same in successive iterations. Some studies show that human diagnosticians typically consider 4  1 hypotheses[11], and we choose to experiment with k in the range from 3 to 5. Experimentation with larger values of k is left as future work.</p>
    <p>hypotheses ;; repeat</p>
    <p>query ;; for j = 1 ! numTerms do</p>
    <p>/* select a concept from the EHR using a probability distribution */</p>
    <p>x select concept(concept probs, EHR) query query</p>
    <p>S x;</p>
    <p>end /* search for docs that contain the query</p>
    <p>terms */ sr search(query, knowledge base) ; /* Identifies hypotheses from medical</p>
    <p>concepts in documents */ hypotheses update hyp(hypotheses, sr); /* Evaluates hypotheses according to</p>
    <p>plausibility criteria */ results eval hypotheses(hypotheses)</p>
    <p>S results;</p>
    <p>until convergence; rank(results);</p>
    <p>Algorithm 1: Inference algorithm</p>
    <p>The next set of results illustrates an example found by our algorithm involving the inference of AIDS from four non-sensitive concepts, and testing the result across different data sources including PubMed, Google and Bing. We verified this result with medical experts, and they told us that two of the concepts were nondescript. Rotavirus is a common cause of diarrhea, and weight loss is nonspecific, so few inferences can be made based on those conditions alone. Furthermore, the presence of toxoplasmosis, a parasitic disease that is estimated to affect one third of the worlds population[19] does little to suggest the cause on its own. Considering the final term, cervical cancer alone also does little to narrow down the exact cause, as the symptom can have many possible causes. Combining all of these nondescript concepts together narrows the list of plausible hypotheses down to AIDS. Our medical experts have independently verified this result before we told them that the query would yield AIDS.</p>
    <p>Another notable example is the query for HIV involving Hepatitis and Hepatitis C. One might expect that these two concepts may be synonyms, but upon closer inspection, it turns out that the more specific version, Hepatits C produced more specific results. Hepatitis C is associated with intravenous drug use, unsafe blood</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Concept Support Index 25</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hypothesis Fitness Index 26</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results 27</p>
    <p>Condition Query Results Medical codes Notes</p>
    <p>Rett Syndrome</p>
    <p>wringing AND female AND constipation AND scoliosis</p>
    <p>F84.2, R09.0, K59.0, 737.0</p>
    <p>Pubmed</p>
    <p>Rett Syndrome</p>
    <p>wringing AND female AND constipation AND scoliosis</p>
    <p>F84.2, R09.0, K59.0, 737.0</p>
    <p>Google</p>
    <p>AIDS &quot;Toxoplasmosis&quot; AND &quot;Hepatitis B&quot; AND &quot;Encephalopathy&quot; AND &quot;Progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy&quot; AND &quot;Cryptococcosis</p>
    <p>Google</p>
    <p>AIDS ... 18,000 results. &gt;8 of top 10 suggest AIDS.</p>
    <p>Bing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Possible defenses 28</p>
    <p>Deniability through relative strengths of hypotheses  Hide non-sensitive EHR as well  Enhance competing hypothesis, e.g. Citalopram  Association rule hiding</p>
    <p>d1 D</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>m1 M</p>
    <p>d2 d3</p>
    <p>m2 m3 m4</p>
    <p>d4</p>
    <p>m5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A message from our sponsors 29</p>
    <p>We thank:</p>
    <p>Carl Gunter and Mike Berry - predicate-reducer model  James Reggia - formalization of the hypothetico-deductive model  Brad Malin - helpful resources  Ivan Handler - health information exchange level  Fisayo Ositelu - medical insight.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ask your doctor!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
