<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Aspects of Health Related Informa8on Sharing in Online Social Networks</p>
    <p>Presented by: Lujo Bauer</p>
    <p>Authors: Sadegh Torabi and Konstan8n Beznosov (University of Bri8sh Columbia, Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering) USENIX Workshop on Health Informa8on Technologies (HealthTech13), August 12, 2013.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presenta8on outline</p>
    <p>Introduc8on + Problem  Methodology  Results and discussion  Summary + Future work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Health Related Informa8on (HRI) sharing is beneficial for:</p>
    <p>Individuals and people in their social network.</p>
    <p>Examples:  Social pressure and losing weight [1].  Learning from others with similar condi8ons [2].  Social support during treatments [3].</p>
    <p>[1] F. Lupianez-villanueva, W. Lusoli, M. Bacigalupo, I. Maghiros, N. Andrade, and C. Codagnone, Health-related informa8on as personal data in Europe: Results from a representa8ve survey in EU27, Medicine 2.0 Ethical and legal issues, confiden8ality and privacy, 2012. [2] D. M. Zulman, K. M. Nazi, C. L. Turvey, T. H. Wagner, S. S. Woods, and L. C. An, Pa8ent interest in sharing personal health record informa8on a web-based survey, Annals of Internal Medicine, vol. 155, no. 12, pp. 805810, 2011. [3] M. M. Skeels, Sharing by design: Understanding and suppor8ng personal health informa8on sharing and collabora8on within social networks, Ph.D. disserta8on, University of Washington, 2010.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is HRI?</p>
    <p>Any informa8on related to the health of an individual and the health of people in her social network.</p>
    <p>Healthy living</p>
    <p>Medical Health Records</p>
    <p>Own experience</p>
    <p>Mental and physical health condi8ons</p>
    <p>Useful HRI resources</p>
    <p>Experience of others</p>
    <p>HRI of people in custody</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HRI sharing in OSNs  Highly inter-connected virtual networks, with lots of ac8ve users.  People share informa8on including HRI. Survey results (Pew Internet 2013):</p>
    <p>26% of online users have followed their friends personal health experiences during last year.</p>
    <p>16% went online to find others with similar health concern. Other studies:</p>
    <p>Sharing HRI is becoming a leading habit [1,2,4,5].</p>
    <p>[1] F. Lupianez-villanueva, W. Lusoli, M. Bacigalupo, I. Maghiros, N. Andrade, and C. Codagnone, Health-related informa8on as personal data in Europe: Results from a representa8ve survey in EU27, Medicine 2.0 Ethical and legal issues, confiden8ality and privacy, 2012. [2] D. M. Zulman, K. M. Nazi, C. L. Turvey, T. H. Wagner, S. S. Woods, and L. C. An, Pa8ent interest in sharing personal health record informa8on a web-based survey, Annals of Internal Medicine, vol. 155, no. 12, pp. 805810, 2011. [4] S. Fox and M. Duggan, Health online 2013, Pew Research Centers Internet and American Life Project, January 2013. [5] S. Fox, The social life of health informa8on, Pew Research Center Report, May 2011.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy</p>
    <p>It is a dynamic boundary regula8on process [6].</p>
    <p>Goal: Minimize the difference between achieved and desired privacy.</p>
    <p>How to achieve goal: By adjus8ng behaviours with respect to surrounding condi8ons.</p>
    <p>[6] I. Altman, Privacy regula8on: culturally universal or culturally specific? Journal of Social Issues, vol. 33, no. 3, pp. 6684, 1977.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy percep8ons and Behavioural responses</p>
    <p>Depending on their knowledge and previous experience:  People perceive risks differently,</p>
    <p>People behave differently in response to perceived risks.</p>
    <p>Examples: Younger pa8ents and Facebook [7].</p>
    <p>[7] M.Velden and K. ElEmam,not all my friends need to know: a qualita8ve study of teenage pa8ents, privacy, and social media, Journal of the American Medical Informa8cs Associa8on, vol. 20, no. 1, pp. 16 24, July 2012.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mo8va8on recap</p>
    <p>HRI sharing is beneficial to users and their social peers.</p>
    <p>Increasing number of users who share HRI in OSNs.</p>
    <p>People seek to maintain their privacy with respect to their perceived risks.</p>
    <p>People mi8gate risks differently.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research ques8ons</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology: Online survey</p>
    <p>Recruited 166 ac8ve OSN users through Amazon Mechanical Turk (MT).</p>
    <p>Surveyed the following:  Demographics and OSN usage.  HRI sharing prac8ces.  Perceived privacy risks when sharing HRI with different users.</p>
    <p>Risk-mi8ga8ng behaviours at different risk levels.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Par8cipant recruitment and survey execu8on</p>
    <p>Par8cipants used the assigned codes to submit the job (compensated with 1 USD upon submission)</p>
    <p>To validate submissions, each par8cipant was assigned with an alpha-numeric code at the end of survey</p>
    <p>Posted a job with instruc8ons and a link to the online survey web- site</p>
    <p>Recruited Amazon MT workers through CrowdFlower (required par8cipants from the US that are 19 years of age and older with at least 1 ac8ve OSN account)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results and Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HRI categoriza8on</p>
    <p>We categorized different HRI examples into 8 groups.</p>
    <p>To triangulate our categoriza8on, we performed a closed card sor8ng exercise with 11 par8cipants.</p>
    <p>For almost all HRI examples, more than 65% of par8cipants used similar categoriza8on to ours.</p>
    <p>Our categoriza8on was reasonable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HRI categories Examples Healthy living</p>
    <p>dietary and healthy ea8ng, physical exercise, environmental hazards</p>
    <p>Own Experience experience with: previous surgeries, treatments and their side effects, symptoms</p>
    <p>Useful found informa8on books, ar8cles, websites</p>
    <p>Mental and emo8onal health condi8ons</p>
    <p>sad, stressed, happy, excited, depressed, mental disorder</p>
    <p>Physical health condi8ons sick, injured, not feeling good, in good shape</p>
    <p>Medical health records personal informa8on and address, insurance related informa8on, x-rays, reports.</p>
    <p>Experience of somebody else experience with: previous surgeries, treatments and their side effects, symptoms</p>
    <p>HRI of people in your custody parents, children, and others</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Par8cipant demographics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Par8cipant demographics 166 ac8ve OSN users from 39 different states in the US</p>
    <p>Gender 49.4% Male 50.6% Female</p>
    <p>Age</p>
    <p>All 19-70 (=30.4, =10, median=28) 59% 19-29 24.7% 30-39 8.4% 40-49 7.9% 50+</p>
    <p>Completed educa8on</p>
    <p>Employment category</p>
    <p>More than 18 different categories: IT (10.6%), Educa8on (9%), Medical (7.9%), Banking (7.4%), and other categories including Student and Self-employed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Par8cipant demographics 166 ac8ve OSN users from 39 different states in the US</p>
    <p>Gender 49.4% Male 50.6% Female</p>
    <p>Age</p>
    <p>All 19-70 (=30.4, =10, median=28) 59% 19-29 24.7% 30-39 8.4% 40-49 7.9% 50+</p>
    <p>Completed educa8on</p>
    <p>Employment category</p>
    <p>More than 18 different categories: IT (10.6%), Educa8on (9%), Medical (7.9%), Banking (7.4%), and other categories including Student and Self-employed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Par8cipant demographics 166 ac8ve OSN users from 39 different states in the US</p>
    <p>Gender 49.4% Male 50.6% Female</p>
    <p>Age</p>
    <p>All 19-70 (=30.4, =10, median=28) 59% 19-29 24.7% 30-39 8.4% 40-49 7.9% 50+</p>
    <p>Completed educa8on</p>
    <p>Employment category</p>
    <p>More than 18 different categories: IT (10.6%), Educa8on (9%), Medical (7.9%), Banking (7.4%), and other categories including Student and Self-employed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Par8cipant demographics 166 ac8ve OSN users from 39 different states in the US</p>
    <p>Gender 49.4% Male 50.6% Female</p>
    <p>Age</p>
    <p>All 19-70 (=30.4, =10, median=28) 59% 19-29 24.7% 30-39 8.4% 40-49 7.9% 50+</p>
    <p>Completed educa8on</p>
    <p>Employment category</p>
    <p>More than 18 different categories: IT (10.6%), Educa8on (9%), Medical (7.9%), Banking (7.4%), and other categories including Student and Self-employed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Par8cipant demographics</p>
    <p>Is the sample representa8ve?  Can we generalize results?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OSN usage</p>
    <p>About 40% of par8cipants had 1 OSN account.</p>
    <p>140 par8cipants (84.3%) logged into their OSN accounts on a daily basis.</p>
    <p>Majority of par8cipants (96.4%) indicated having Facebook profiles.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How oten do you share HRI in OSN?</p>
    <p>!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>%!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>'!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>(!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>)!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>*!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>+!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>,-./012$/34356$ 785$9:;-&lt;3-5=-$ &gt;?-@A/$@BA5C$ 35@B&lt;D.EB5$</p>
    <p>F-50./$.5C$ -DBEB5./$</p>
    <p>G12?3=./$1-./01$ =B5C3EB5?$</p>
    <p>F-C3=./$1-./01$ &lt;-=B&lt;C?$</p>
    <p>,IJ$B@$;-B;/-$35$ 2BA&lt;$=A?0BC2$</p>
    <p># $B @$ ; .&lt; E =3 ; .5 0? $</p>
    <p>K-4-&lt;$ I.&lt;-/2$ LBD-ED-?$ M&lt;-NA-50/2$ O/8.2?$</p>
    <p>Par8cipants rated their response on a 5-point Likert scale: (Never  Rarely  Some8mes  Frequently  Always)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How oten do you share HRI in OSN?</p>
    <p>!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>%!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>'!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>(!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>)!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>*!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>+!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>,-./012$/34356$ 785$9:;-&lt;3-5=-$ &gt;?-@A/$@BA5C$ 35@B&lt;D.EB5$</p>
    <p>F-50./$.5C$ -DBEB5./$</p>
    <p>G12?3=./$1-./01$ =B5C3EB5?$</p>
    <p>F-C3=./$1-./01$ &lt;-=B&lt;C?$</p>
    <p>,IJ$B@$;-B;/-$35$ 2BA&lt;$=A?0BC2$</p>
    <p># $B @$ ; .&lt; E =3 ; .5 0? $</p>
    <p>K-4-&lt;$ I.&lt;-/2$ LBD-ED-?$ M&lt;-NA-50/2$ O/8.2?$ 63.3%</p>
    <p>% Never shared</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why do you share HRI?</p>
    <p>Par8cipants selected all that applied from a list of common reasons.</p>
    <p>!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>%!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>'!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>(!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>)!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>*!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>+!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>,-./012$/34356$ 785$9:;-&lt;3-5=-$ &gt;?-@A/$@BA5C$ 35@B&lt;D.EB5$</p>
    <p>F-50./$.5C$ -DBEB5./$</p>
    <p>G12?3=./$1-./01$ =B5C3EB5?$</p>
    <p>F-C3=./$1-./01$ &lt;-=B&lt;C?$</p>
    <p>,IJ$B@$;-B;/-$35$ 2BA&lt;$=A?0BC2$</p>
    <p># $B @$;</p>
    <p>.&lt; E =3 ;. 50 ?$</p>
    <p>K-4-&lt;$ I.&lt;-/2$ LBD-ED-?$ M&lt;-NA-50/2$ O/8.2?$</p>
    <p>Fig. 3. Frequency of sharing HRI in OSNs.</p>
    <p>Figure 2 for details. Out of the 140 participants who reported using their OSN account(s) every day, 135 (96.4%) were active Facebook users. We also asked about the preferred device for connecting to each OSN account (PC/Laptop, Tablet, or Smartphone). About 70% preferred to use a PC/Laptop and approximately 24% used their smartphones.</p>
    <p>B. HRI Sharing Practices</p>
    <p>To investigate sharing practices, we presented participants with eight HRI categories (Table I), and asked them to indicate on a 5-point Likert scale how regularly they shared information in each category. As shown in Figure 3, and summarized in Table III, 63.3% of participants never shared information about their medical health records (e.g., x-rays, treatments, name and address, insurance policy number). More than half of participants (54.8%) never shared HRI of people in their custody (e.g., children and elderly parents), while 41.6% indicated never sharing other peoples health related experience. Only 7 participants never shared any HRI in OSNs, while the rest (95.8%) indicated sharing.</p>
    <p>To answer the question why do you share HRI online?, participants selected all that applied from a list of common reasons obtained from the literature [57]. The provided list of</p>
    <p>TABLE III HRI CATEGORIES AND % OF PARTICIPANTS WHO NEVER SHARED HRI</p>
    <p>FROM EACH CATEGORY. THE THIRD COLUMN REPRESENTS THE MEDIAN RANKING FROM THE LIKERT SCALE</p>
    <p>HRI categories Participants Median</p>
    <p>Medical health records 63.3% 1 HRI of people in your custody 54.8% 1 Experience of somebody else 41.6% 2 Own Experience 21.1% 3 Mental and emotional health conditions 20.5% 3 Physical health conditions 16.3% 3 Healthy living 15.7% 3 Useful found information 9.0% 3</p>
    <p>reasons, both for and against sharing HRI (Tables IV and V), represent general sharing motivation and are not related to any specific HRI category. As shown in Table IV, more than half of participants (66.9%) shared their health related knowledge and experience to help others in their social network, followed by getting beneficial feedback and social support as other reasons for sharing HRI online (51.8% and 48.2% respectively). On the other hand, for the HRI that the participants did not share in their OSNs, approximately half of them (49.4%) indicated not sharing HRI due to the existence of different people among their OSN contacts, while 43.4% of all participants considered their HRI to be personal and did not want to share it with anyone (Table V). Since we do not have exact information about users actual behaviour, we can not assume that privacy-related issues were the only motivation preventing participants from sharing HRI online. However, the results indicate that about half of the participants did not share HRI in their OSN(s) due to its personal nature and due to the existence of different people in their social contacts, which might be an indication of privacy concerns.</p>
    <p>TABLE IV REASONS FOR SHARING HRI ONLINE.</p>
    <p>Reasons for sharing HRI Participants</p>
    <p>Help others by sharing personal experience and knowledge 66.9%</p>
    <p>Seek help or social support 51.8% Get benefits by receiving useful feedback from online contacts 48.2%</p>
    <p>Seek online interactions and make discussions 44.0% Alleviate anxiety (sharing HRI makes me feel better and less stressed) 38.6%</p>
    <p>Promote healthy living 37.3% Other reasons 6.6%</p>
    <p>C. Perceived Privacy Risks</p>
    <p>The subjective perception of privacy risks by technology users is highly context dependent [23]. In the context of HRI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>For HRI that par8cipants did not share</p>
    <p>!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!&quot;#</p>
    <p>%!&quot;#</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;#</p>
    <p>'!&quot;#</p>
    <p>(!&quot;#</p>
    <p>)!&quot;#</p>
    <p>*!&quot;#</p>
    <p>+!&quot;#</p>
    <p>,!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!!&quot;#</p>
    <p>-./0123# 045467#</p>
    <p>?@.AB0# ACB6D#</p>
    <p>G.61/0#/6D# .ECFC6/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>H23@4&gt;/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>G.D4&gt;/0# 2./012# =.&gt;C=D@#</p>
    <p>:;&lt;.=4.6&gt;.# CA#</p>
    <p>@CE.ICD3# .0@.#</p>
    <p>-JK#CA# &lt;.C&lt;0.#46# 3CB=#</p>
    <p>&gt;B@1CD3#</p>
    <p>&quot; #C A#&lt;</p>
    <p>/= F&gt; 4&lt; /6 1@ #</p>
    <p>L.=3#0C9#C=## 6C#=4@M#</p>
    <p>N&gt;&gt;.&lt;1/I0.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>GCD.=/1.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>-472# =4@M#</p>
    <p>:;1=.E.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>(a) Select individual(s)</p>
    <p>!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!&quot;#</p>
    <p>%!&quot;#</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;#</p>
    <p>'!&quot;#</p>
    <p>(!&quot;#</p>
    <p>)!&quot;#</p>
    <p>*!&quot;#</p>
    <p>+!&quot;#</p>
    <p>,!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!!&quot;#</p>
    <p>-./0123# 045467#</p>
    <p>?@.AB0# ACB6D#</p>
    <p>G.61/0#/6D# .ECFC6/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>H23@4&gt;/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>G.D4&gt;/0# 2./012# =.&gt;C=D@#</p>
    <p>:;&lt;.=4.6&gt;.# CA#</p>
    <p>@CE.ICD3# .0@.#</p>
    <p>-JK#CA# &lt;.C&lt;0.#46# 3CB=#</p>
    <p>&gt;B@1CD3#</p>
    <p>&quot; #C A#&lt;</p>
    <p>/= F&gt; 4&lt; /6 1@ #</p>
    <p>L.=3#0C9#C=## 6C#=4@M#</p>
    <p>N&gt;&gt;.&lt;1/I0.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>GCD.=/1.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>-472# =4@M#</p>
    <p>:;1=.E.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>(b) Select group(s)</p>
    <p>!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!&quot;#</p>
    <p>%!&quot;#</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;#</p>
    <p>'!&quot;#</p>
    <p>(!&quot;#</p>
    <p>)!&quot;#</p>
    <p>*!&quot;#</p>
    <p>+!&quot;#</p>
    <p>,!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!!&quot;#</p>
    <p>-./0123# 045467#</p>
    <p>?@.AB0# ACB6D#</p>
    <p>G.61/0#/6D# .ECFC6/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>H23@4&gt;/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>G.D4&gt;/0# 2./012# =.&gt;C=D@#</p>
    <p>:;&lt;.=4.6&gt;.# CA#</p>
    <p>@CE.ICD3# .0@.#</p>
    <p>-JK#CA# &lt;.C&lt;0.#46# 3CB=#</p>
    <p>&gt;B@1CD3#</p>
    <p>&quot; #C A#&lt;</p>
    <p>/= F&gt; 4&lt; /6 1@ #</p>
    <p>L.=3#0C9#C=## 6C#=4@M#</p>
    <p>N&gt;&gt;.&lt;1/I0.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>GCD.=/1.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>-472# =4@M#</p>
    <p>:;1=.E.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>(c) Entire contact list</p>
    <p>!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!&quot;#</p>
    <p>%!&quot;#</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;#</p>
    <p>'!&quot;#</p>
    <p>(!&quot;#</p>
    <p>)!&quot;#</p>
    <p>*!&quot;#</p>
    <p>+!&quot;#</p>
    <p>,!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!!&quot;#</p>
    <p>-./0123# 045467#</p>
    <p>?@.AB0# ACB6D#</p>
    <p>G.61/0#/6D# .ECFC6/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>H23@4&gt;/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>G.D4&gt;/0# 2./012# =.&gt;C=D@#</p>
    <p>:;&lt;.=4.6&gt;.# CA#</p>
    <p>@CE.ICD3# .0@.#</p>
    <p>-JK#CA# &lt;.C&lt;0.#46# 3CB=#</p>
    <p>&gt;B@1CD3#</p>
    <p>&quot; #C A#&lt;</p>
    <p>/= F&gt; 4&lt; /6 1@ #</p>
    <p>L.=3#0C9#C=## 6C#=4@M#</p>
    <p>N&gt;&gt;.&lt;1/I0.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>GCD.=/1.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>-472# =4@M#</p>
    <p>:;1=.E.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>(d) All other OSN users</p>
    <p>Fig. 4. Perceived privacy risks when sharing HRI with different user categories.</p>
    <p>TABLE V REASONS AGAINST SHARING HRI ONLINE.</p>
    <p>Reasons against sharing HRI Participants</p>
    <p>I have different people in my online contact list and I prefer not to share my HRI with all of them 49.4%</p>
    <p>My HRI is personal and I do not share it with anyone 43.4% I do not want to be treated as the sick person by my online contacts 39.2%</p>
    <p>I do not want my online contacts to worry about me by receiving bad news about my health 34.9%</p>
    <p>I do not want my online contacts to know about my HRI 34.9%</p>
    <p>I prefer to share my HRI with my doctor 30.1% I prefer to share my HRI offline 22.3% My online contacts are not interested in my HRI 20.5% Other reasons 4.8%</p>
    <p>sharing in OSNs, the key factors are as follows: (1) recipient of information; (2) HRI type and category; (3) the OSN where information is shared; and (4) the mental and physical health conditions of the individual at time of sharing. We asked participants to rate on a 5-point Likert scale how much each of the above four factors would affect their perceived privacy risks (responses varied between does not affect to strongly affects). While more than 85% of participants indicated that all four factors affect their perceived privacy risks, results showed that the HRI recipient and its type and category, strongly affected the perceived privacy risks of approximately 30% of the participants.</p>
    <p>Using results from our literature review on the effect of the recipient and the type of information on the perceived privacy</p>
    <p>risks, when sharing information in an OSN, we asked users to rate their perceived privacy risks, when sharing information from each HRI category with different user groups. We used a 5-point Likert scale (with responses varying from very low or no risk to extreme risk) and the following user groups: select individual(s), select group(s), entire contact list, and all other OSN users. Although it was not explicitly mentioned to the participants, select individual(s) and group(s) implied trusted user categories. We tried to avoid using the word trust in order to minimize response bias, while implying trust by presenting selective user choice when sharing HRI. Our aim was to capture users perceived privacy risk variations with respect to the HRI category and the number of trusted recipients, and compare it with the perceived privacy risks of sharing with other user groups that possibly include untrusted users such as the participants entire contact list or all other users in the OSN. Figure 4 shows the results.</p>
    <p>More than 66.9% of participants perceived very low or no risks when sharing useful found information with their entire contacts or all other OSN users (perceived privacy risks of sharing with select individual(s) and group(s) was 81.9% and 78.9% respectively). This low sensitivity toward sharing useful found information might be due to the nature of that type of HRI, which might not directly relate to a persons health. For other HRI categories such as healthy living, physical health conditions, own experience, and mental and emotional health conditions, the percentage of participants who perceived sharing HRI to be of very low or</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>For HRI that par8cipants did not share</p>
    <p>!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!&quot;#</p>
    <p>%!&quot;#</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;#</p>
    <p>'!&quot;#</p>
    <p>(!&quot;#</p>
    <p>)!&quot;#</p>
    <p>*!&quot;#</p>
    <p>+!&quot;#</p>
    <p>,!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!!&quot;#</p>
    <p>-./0123# 045467#</p>
    <p>?@.AB0# ACB6D#</p>
    <p>G.61/0#/6D# .ECFC6/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>H23@4&gt;/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>G.D4&gt;/0# 2./012# =.&gt;C=D@#</p>
    <p>:;&lt;.=4.6&gt;.# CA#</p>
    <p>@CE.ICD3# .0@.#</p>
    <p>-JK#CA# &lt;.C&lt;0.#46# 3CB=#</p>
    <p>&gt;B@1CD3#</p>
    <p>&quot; #C A#&lt;</p>
    <p>/= F&gt; 4&lt; /6 1@ #</p>
    <p>L.=3#0C9#C=## 6C#=4@M#</p>
    <p>N&gt;&gt;.&lt;1/I0.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>GCD.=/1.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>-472# =4@M#</p>
    <p>:;1=.E.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>(a) Select individual(s)</p>
    <p>!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!&quot;#</p>
    <p>%!&quot;#</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;#</p>
    <p>'!&quot;#</p>
    <p>(!&quot;#</p>
    <p>)!&quot;#</p>
    <p>*!&quot;#</p>
    <p>+!&quot;#</p>
    <p>,!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!!&quot;#</p>
    <p>-./0123# 045467#</p>
    <p>?@.AB0# ACB6D#</p>
    <p>G.61/0#/6D# .ECFC6/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>H23@4&gt;/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>G.D4&gt;/0# 2./012# =.&gt;C=D@#</p>
    <p>:;&lt;.=4.6&gt;.# CA#</p>
    <p>@CE.ICD3# .0@.#</p>
    <p>-JK#CA# &lt;.C&lt;0.#46# 3CB=#</p>
    <p>&gt;B@1CD3#</p>
    <p>&quot; #C A#&lt;</p>
    <p>/= F&gt; 4&lt; /6 1@ #</p>
    <p>L.=3#0C9#C=## 6C#=4@M#</p>
    <p>N&gt;&gt;.&lt;1/I0.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>GCD.=/1.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>-472# =4@M#</p>
    <p>:;1=.E.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>(b) Select group(s)</p>
    <p>!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!&quot;#</p>
    <p>%!&quot;#</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;#</p>
    <p>'!&quot;#</p>
    <p>(!&quot;#</p>
    <p>)!&quot;#</p>
    <p>*!&quot;#</p>
    <p>+!&quot;#</p>
    <p>,!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!!&quot;#</p>
    <p>-./0123# 045467#</p>
    <p>?@.AB0# ACB6D#</p>
    <p>G.61/0#/6D# .ECFC6/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>H23@4&gt;/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>G.D4&gt;/0# 2./012# =.&gt;C=D@#</p>
    <p>:;&lt;.=4.6&gt;.# CA#</p>
    <p>@CE.ICD3# .0@.#</p>
    <p>-JK#CA# &lt;.C&lt;0.#46# 3CB=#</p>
    <p>&gt;B@1CD3#</p>
    <p>&quot; #C A#&lt;</p>
    <p>/= F&gt; 4&lt; /6 1@ #</p>
    <p>L.=3#0C9#C=## 6C#=4@M#</p>
    <p>N&gt;&gt;.&lt;1/I0.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>GCD.=/1.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>-472# =4@M#</p>
    <p>:;1=.E.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>(c) Entire contact list</p>
    <p>!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!&quot;#</p>
    <p>%!&quot;#</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;#</p>
    <p>'!&quot;#</p>
    <p>(!&quot;#</p>
    <p>)!&quot;#</p>
    <p>*!&quot;#</p>
    <p>+!&quot;#</p>
    <p>,!&quot;#</p>
    <p>$!!&quot;#</p>
    <p>-./0123# 045467#</p>
    <p>?@.AB0# ACB6D#</p>
    <p>G.61/0#/6D# .ECFC6/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>H23@4&gt;/0# 2./012#</p>
    <p>&gt;C6D4FC6@#</p>
    <p>G.D4&gt;/0# 2./012# =.&gt;C=D@#</p>
    <p>:;&lt;.=4.6&gt;.# CA#</p>
    <p>@CE.ICD3# .0@.#</p>
    <p>-JK#CA# &lt;.C&lt;0.#46# 3CB=#</p>
    <p>&gt;B@1CD3#</p>
    <p>&quot; #C A#&lt;</p>
    <p>/= F&gt; 4&lt; /6 1@ #</p>
    <p>L.=3#0C9#C=## 6C#=4@M#</p>
    <p>N&gt;&gt;.&lt;1/I0.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>GCD.=/1.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>-472# =4@M#</p>
    <p>:;1=.E.# =4@M#</p>
    <p>(d) All other OSN users</p>
    <p>Fig. 4. Perceived privacy risks when sharing HRI with different user categories.</p>
    <p>TABLE V REASONS AGAINST SHARING HRI ONLINE.</p>
    <p>Reasons against sharing HRI Participants</p>
    <p>I have different people in my online contact list and I prefer not to share my HRI with all of them 49.4%</p>
    <p>My HRI is personal and I do not share it with anyone 43.4% I do not want to be treated as the sick person by my online contacts 39.2%</p>
    <p>I do not want my online contacts to worry about me by receiving bad news about my health 34.9%</p>
    <p>I do not want my online contacts to know about my HRI 34.9%</p>
    <p>I prefer to share my HRI with my doctor 30.1% I prefer to share my HRI offline 22.3% My online contacts are not interested in my HRI 20.5% Other reasons 4.8%</p>
    <p>sharing in OSNs, the key factors are as follows: (1) recipient of information; (2) HRI type and category; (3) the OSN where information is shared; and (4) the mental and physical health conditions of the individual at time of sharing. We asked participants to rate on a 5-point Likert scale how much each of the above four factors would affect their perceived privacy risks (responses varied between does not affect to strongly affects). While more than 85% of participants indicated that all four factors affect their perceived privacy risks, results showed that the HRI recipient and its type and category, strongly affected the perceived privacy risks of approximately 30% of the participants.</p>
    <p>Using results from our literature review on the effect of the recipient and the type of information on the perceived privacy</p>
    <p>risks, when sharing information in an OSN, we asked users to rate their perceived privacy risks, when sharing information from each HRI category with different user groups. We used a 5-point Likert scale (with responses varying from very low or no risk to extreme risk) and the following user groups: select individual(s), select group(s), entire contact list, and all other OSN users. Although it was not explicitly mentioned to the participants, select individual(s) and group(s) implied trusted user categories. We tried to avoid using the word trust in order to minimize response bias, while implying trust by presenting selective user choice when sharing HRI. Our aim was to capture users perceived privacy risk variations with respect to the HRI category and the number of trusted recipients, and compare it with the perceived privacy risks of sharing with other user groups that possibly include untrusted users such as the participants entire contact list or all other users in the OSN. Figure 4 shows the results.</p>
    <p>More than 66.9% of participants perceived very low or no risks when sharing useful found information with their entire contacts or all other OSN users (perceived privacy risks of sharing with select individual(s) and group(s) was 81.9% and 78.9% respectively). This low sensitivity toward sharing useful found information might be due to the nature of that type of HRI, which might not directly relate to a persons health. For other HRI categories such as healthy living, physical health conditions, own experience, and mental and emotional health conditions, the percentage of participants who perceived sharing HRI to be of very low or</p>
    <p>Might indicate privacy concerns</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key factors affec8ng perceived privacy risks</p>
    <p>How does each factor affect your perceived privacy risks? (Responses varied on a 5-point Likert scale from does not affect to strongly affects)  More than 85% of par8cipants indicated that all four factors affected their</p>
    <p>perceived privacy risks.</p>
    <p>HRI recipient and its type/category, strongly affected the perceived privacy risks of approximately 30% of all par8cipants.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Risk percep8ons</p>
    <p>HRI categories Healthy living Own Experience Useful found informa8on Mental and emo8onal health condi8ons Physical health condi8ons Medical health records Experience of somebody else HRI of people in your custody</p>
    <p>Rate risk percep8on on a 5-point Likert scale: (Very low  Acceptable  Moderate  High  Extreme)</p>
    <p>When sharing with:  Select individual(s)</p>
    <p>Select group(s)</p>
    <p>En8re contacts</p>
    <p>All other OSN users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Risk percep8ons (Sharing HRI among different user categories)</p>
    <p>Less concerned with healthy living and useful found informa8on.  No significant difference when sharing between en8re contacts and all other OSN users</p>
    <p>Moreover, for useful found informa8on:  No significant difference when sharing between select individual(s) and select group(s)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Risk percep8ons</p>
    <p>!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>%!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>'!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>(!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>)!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>*!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>+,-,./$ 012030245-678$</p>
    <p>+,-,./$9:;4&lt;678$ =1&gt;:,$.;1/5./$ -07/$</p>
    <p>?--$;/@,:$A+B$ 47,:7$</p>
    <p># $; C$&lt;</p>
    <p>D,5-/@E$-03019$</p>
    <p>AF1$=G&lt;,:0,1.,$</p>
    <p>H7,C4-$C;412$ 01C;:I5&gt;;1$</p>
    <p>J,1/5-$512$,I;&gt;;15-$ @,5-/@$.;120&gt;;17$</p>
    <p>K@E70.5-$@,5-/@$ .;120&gt;;17$</p>
    <p>J,20.5-$@,5-/@$ :,.;:27$</p>
    <p>=G&lt;,:0,1.,$;C$ 7;I,L;2E$,-7,$</p>
    <p>DMN$;C$&lt;,;&lt;-,$01$ E;4:$.47/;2E$</p>
    <p>Perceived as extreme risk</p>
    <p>Risk percep8ons increased by expanding the recipient base.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Risk percep8ons</p>
    <p>!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>%!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>'!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>(!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>)!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>*!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>+,-,./$ 012030245-678$</p>
    <p>+,-,./$9:;4&lt;678$ =1&gt;:,$.;1/5./$ -07/$</p>
    <p>?--$;/@,:$A+B$ 47,:7$</p>
    <p># $; C$&lt;</p>
    <p>D,5-/@E$-03019$</p>
    <p>AF1$=G&lt;,:0,1.,$</p>
    <p>H7,C4-$C;412$ 01C;:I5&gt;;1$</p>
    <p>J,1/5-$512$,I;&gt;;15-$ @,5-/@$.;120&gt;;17$</p>
    <p>K@E70.5-$@,5-/@$ .;120&gt;;17$</p>
    <p>J,20.5-$@,5-/@$ :,.;:27$</p>
    <p>=G&lt;,:0,1.,$;C$ 7;I,L;2E$,-7,$</p>
    <p>DMN$;C$&lt;,;&lt;-,$01$ E;4:$.47/;2E$</p>
    <p>Perceived as extreme risk</p>
    <p>Less concerns when sharing HRI with select individuals and select groups.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Risk percep8ons</p>
    <p>!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>%!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>&amp;!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>'!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>(!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>)!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>*!&quot;!#$</p>
    <p>+,-,./$ 012030245-678$</p>
    <p>+,-,./$9:;4&lt;678$ =1&gt;:,$.;1/5./$ -07/$</p>
    <p>?--$;/@,:$A+B$ 47,:7$</p>
    <p># $; C$&lt;</p>
    <p>D,5-/@E$-03019$</p>
    <p>AF1$=G&lt;,:0,1.,$</p>
    <p>H7,C4-$C;412$ 01C;:I5&gt;;1$</p>
    <p>J,1/5-$512$,I;&gt;;15-$ @,5-/@$.;120&gt;;17$</p>
    <p>K@E70.5-$@,5-/@$ .;120&gt;;17$</p>
    <p>J,20.5-$@,5-/@$ :,.;:27$</p>
    <p>=G&lt;,:0,1.,$;C$ 7;I,L;2E$,-7,$</p>
    <p>DMN$;C$&lt;,;&lt;-,$01$ E;4:$.47/;2E$</p>
    <p>Perceived as extreme risk</p>
    <p>Some HRI categories received higher concerns.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Behavioural responses at different risk levels (very low to extreme risks)</p>
    <p>Par8cipants selected all that applied from the following responses:  Avoid risks by not sharing.  Minimize risks by manipula8ng shared data.  Minimize risks by filtering recipients.  Minimize risks by changing OSN.  Accept risks and share without any preemp8ve ac8ons.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Behavioural responses</p>
    <p>Sharing profiles [1]:  Indifferent (always share)  Cau8ous (never share)  Self-revealing (use risk-mi8ga8ng techniques to share and get benefits)</p>
    <p>At acceptable risk level:  About 50% (self-revealing) minimized risks by manipula8ng shared data and/or filtering recipients.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Previous studies:  Focused on niche user categories.  Did not study ac8ve OSN users.</p>
    <p>Our contribu8ons:  Quan8fied HRI sharing prac8ces in OSNs.  Highlighted key factors affec8ng privacy percep8ons.</p>
    <p>Tried to build a solid ground for future studies.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Takeaways</p>
    <p>HRI sharing is a new applica8on of OSNs.</p>
    <p>More concerns with sharing medical health records and HRI of people in their custody.</p>
    <p>The recipient and the HRI category are the key factors affec8ng perceived privacy.</p>
    <p>Self-revealing users and risk-mi8ga8ng behaviours.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future work</p>
    <p>To capture users risk percep8ons and behavioural responses in more detail, we will:  Create realis8c scenarios for sharing HRI in OSNs.</p>
    <p>Place par8cipants in the context of sharing HRI.  Incorporate mo8va8ng factors (benefits).</p>
    <p>Thank you! Sadegh Torabi (sadeq@ece.ubc.ca) and Konstan8n Beznosov</p>
    <p>University of Bri8sh Columbia</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
