<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of the 2nd Workshop on Asian Transla7on</p>
    <p>Toshiaki Nakazawa Hideya Mino Isao Goto Graham Neubig Sadao Kurohashi Eiichiro Sumita</p>
    <p>WAT2015, 16 October, 2015, Kyoto</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Features of WAT2015</p>
    <p>MT evalua7on campaign focusing on Asian languages (Japanese, Chinese, Korean and English for this 7me)</p>
    <p>The first evalua7on for Chinese-Japanese and Korean-Japanese patent transla7on.</p>
    <p>Professional translators evaluate the outputs of the top systems based on JPO adequacy.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparison of WAT 2014 and 2015 WAT2014 WAT2015</p>
    <p>Task</p>
    <p>Scien7fic paper (ASPEC)  Japanese  English  Chinese  Japanese</p>
    <p>Scien7fic paper (ASPEC)  Japanese  English  Chinese  Japanese JPO Patent corpus (JPC)  Chinese  Japanese  Korean  Japanese</p>
    <p>Evalua7on</p>
    <p>Automa7c Evalua7on Human Evalua7on  Pairwise Crowdsourcing</p>
    <p>Automa7c Evalua7on Human Evalua7on  Pairwise Crowdsourcing  JPO Adequacy (Top 3 systems)</p>
    <p>Number of par7cipants</p>
    <p>New</p>
    <p>New</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Notable Findings at WAT2015</p>
    <p>Neural Network based re-ranking was effec7ve for human evalua7on (NAIST, Kyoto-U, naver)</p>
    <p>The top SMT outperformed RBMT for Chinese- Japanese and Korean-Japanese patent transla7on</p>
    <p>Korean-Japanese patent transla7on achieved high scores for automa7c and human evalua7ons.</p>
    <p>A problem of automaOc evaluaOon was found in the Korean-Japanese transla7on.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Par7cipants Team ID OrganizaOon</p>
    <p>ASPEC JPC JE EJ JC CJ CJ KJ</p>
    <p>NAIST Nara Ins7tute of Science and Technology</p>
    <p>Kyoto-U Kyoto University</p>
    <p>WEBLIO_MT Weblio, Inc.</p>
    <p>TMU Tokyo Metropolitan University</p>
    <p>BJTUNLP Beijing Jiaotong University</p>
    <p>Sense Saarland University &amp; Nanyang Technological University</p>
    <p>NICT Na7onal Ins7tute of Informa7on and Communica7on Technology</p>
    <p>TOSHIBA Toshiba Corpora7on</p>
    <p>WASUIPS Waseda University</p>
    <p>naver NAVER Corpora7on</p>
    <p>EHR Ehara NLP Research Laboratory</p>
    <p>nb NTT Communica7on Science Laboratories</p>
    <p>outside Japan company</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Baseline Systems</p>
    <p>4 types of SMT systems, 7 RBMT systems, and 2 online systems  The SYSTEM-IDs of the commercial RBMT and online systems are anonymized.  The transla7on procedures for the SMT systems were published on the WAT web site.</p>
    <p>System ID System Type</p>
    <p>ASPEC JPC</p>
    <p>JE EJ JC CJ CJ KJ SMT Phrase Moses' Phrase-based SMT</p>
    <p>SMT</p>
    <p>SMT Hiero Moses' Hierarchical Phrase-based SMT       SMT S2T Moses' String-to-Tree Syntax-based SMT and Berkeley parser   SMT T2S Moses' Tree-to-String Syntax-based SMT and Berkeley parser    RBMT X The Honyaku V15 (Commercial system)</p>
    <p>RBMT</p>
    <p>RBMT X ATLAS V14 (Commercial system)   RBMT X PAT-Transer 2009 (Commercial system)   RBMT X J-Beijing 7 (Commercial system)    RBMT X Hohrai 2011 (Commercial system)    RBMT X J Soul 9 (Commercial system)  RBMT X Korai 2011 (Commercial system)  Online X Google translate (August, 2015) (SMT)       Online X Bing translator (August and September, 2015) (SMT)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evalua7on Methods</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Automa7c Evalua7on</p>
    <p>BLEU, RIBES  The automa7c evalua7on server for WAT accepts transla7ons any 7me.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pairwise Crowdsourcing Evalua7on  Sentence-level evalua7on comparing to the baseline Phrase-based SMT output</p>
    <p>System output Baseline output VS</p>
    <p>The Lancers crowdsourcing plajorm (the same as that at WAT2014)  Evaluators judge win (1), loss (-1), or 7e (0)  5 evaluators assessed for each sentence.  The final judgment for each sentence is decided by vo7ng based on the</p>
    <p>sum of judgments:  Win: sum  2  Loss: sum  -2  Tie: otherwise</p>
    <p>This vo7ng criterion is different from that of WAT2014. The Crowd scores between WAT2014 and WAT2015 cannot be compared.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Crowd score</p>
    <p>Crowd score = 100 W L</p>
    <p>W +L+T</p>
    <p>W: the number of wins compared to the baseline L: the number of losses compared to the baseline T: the number of 7es</p>
    <p>(The score range is -100 to 100)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>JPO Adequacy  Sentence-level 5-scale criterion defined by Japan Patent Office</p>
    <p>Professional translators assessed.  Top 3 systems of the Crowd scores were evaluated.  One sentence was evaluated by two evaluators.  200 sentences were evaluated for each system. 10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Crowd Evalua7on Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Many par7cipants outperformed SMT S2T, which ranked at the second at WAT2014. 12</p>
    <p>Baseline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>$</p>
    <p>#</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>#</p>
    <p>$</p>
    <p>%</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>Many par7cipants outperformed the baselines of Online A and SMT T2S 13</p>
    <p>Baselines</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two teams outperformed SMT S2T, which ranked at the second at WAT2014. NAIST 1 ranked at middle. However this ranking was different from JPO adequacy. 14</p>
    <p>Baseline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NAIST team achieved the best score. 15</p>
    <p>Baseline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SMT systems outperformed the baseline RBMT for CJ patent transla7on. 16</p>
    <p>Baseline RBMT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SMT systems outperformed the baseline RBMT for KJ patent transla7on. Online A was top-ranked. However this rank was different from JPO adequacy. 17</p>
    <p>Baseline RBMT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>JPO Adequacy Evalua7on Results and Reliability of Crowd/BLEU/RIBES</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>&quot;'&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;%$</p>
    <p>&quot;% &quot;$$</p>
    <p>&quot;!$</p>
    <p>!$!$#  !!'( !!'(</p>
    <p>&amp;#(% &amp;!#% &amp; '$</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>#</p>
    <p>$</p>
    <p>%</p>
    <p>&amp;</p>
    <p>'</p>
    <p>&quot;#$</p>
    <p>&quot;$</p>
    <p>&quot;$$</p>
    <p>&quot;%</p>
    <p>&quot;%$</p>
    <p>&quot;&amp;</p>
    <p>&quot;&amp;$</p>
    <p>&quot;'</p>
    <p>&quot;'$</p>
    <p>!  !</p>
    <p>Comparison with JPO Adequacy (ASPEC-JE)</p>
    <p>The ranking of Crowd is consistent. The ranking of BLEU is par7ally consistent. The ranking of RIBES is consistent.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>$ $</p>
    <p>$</p>
    <p>#(!</p>
    <p>&amp;&quot;&quot;%</p>
    <p>%#&quot;% %#'%</p>
    <p>#%(# #$&amp;  ##&quot;#</p>
    <p>(!!% (   ( $'</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>#</p>
    <p>$</p>
    <p>%</p>
    <p>&amp;</p>
    <p>'</p>
    <p>(</p>
    <p>)</p>
    <p>#&amp;%</p>
    <p>#'</p>
    <p>#'%</p>
    <p>#(</p>
    <p>#(%</p>
    <p>#)</p>
    <p>#)%</p>
    <p>$</p>
    <p>$ %</p>
    <p>$!</p>
    <p>! &quot;   !</p>
    <p>Comparison with JPO Adequacy (ASPEC-EJ)</p>
    <p>The ranking of Crowd is par7ally consistent. The ranking of BLEU is consistent. The ranking of RIBES is par7ally consistent.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>&quot; &amp;</p>
    <p>!'&amp;</p>
    <p>!&amp;$</p>
    <p>&amp;</p>
    <p>% &amp;</p>
    <p>&quot; %  !((( &quot;&amp;</p>
    <p>'&quot;!' '&amp;  ' &amp;&quot;</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>#</p>
    <p>$</p>
    <p>%</p>
    <p>&amp;</p>
    <p>'</p>
    <p>(</p>
    <p>!$</p>
    <p>!%</p>
    <p>!&amp;</p>
    <p>!'</p>
    <p>!(</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;!</p>
    <p>&quot;&quot;</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>Comparison with JPO Adequacy (ASPEC-JC)</p>
    <p>The ranking of Crowd is not consistent. The ranking of BLEU is par7ally consistent. The ranking of RIBES is par7ally consistent.</p>
    <p>JC is difficult to evaluate! 21</p>
    <p>Different ranking from Crowd</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!&amp;&amp;</p>
    <p>!%&quot;</p>
    <p>! # !#%#</p>
    <p>&amp;# #%#</p>
    <p>&quot;%# !&amp;#! !%'</p>
    <p>&amp;## &amp;&quot;% &amp; $</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>#</p>
    <p>$</p>
    <p>%</p>
    <p>&amp;</p>
    <p>'</p>
    <p>'</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>!!</p>
    <p>!&quot;</p>
    <p>!#</p>
    <p>!$</p>
    <p>!%</p>
    <p>!&amp;</p>
    <p>!'</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>The ranking of Crowd scores is par7ally consistent. The ranking of BLEU scores is consistent. The ranking of RIBES scores is consistent.</p>
    <p>Comparison with JPO Adequacy (ASPEC-CJ)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!&quot;</p>
    <p>!!</p>
    <p>! # %#  &quot; #</p>
    <p>&quot;!# &quot;$ &quot;</p>
    <p>&amp; &amp;# &amp; % &amp;</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>#</p>
    <p>$</p>
    <p>%</p>
    <p>&amp;</p>
    <p>'</p>
    <p>!#</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>! #</p>
    <p>!!</p>
    <p>!!#</p>
    <p>!&quot;</p>
    <p>!&quot;#</p>
    <p>The ranking of Crowd was par7ally consistent. The ranking of BLEU was par7ally consistent. The ranking of RIBES was consistent.</p>
    <p>Comparison with JPO Adequacy (JPC-CJ)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>%() %('</p>
    <p>%&amp;$</p>
    <p>%$# &quot;%(&amp;</p>
    <p>&quot;!&amp;!</p>
    <p>$)(&amp;</p>
    <p>&quot;((&amp;</p>
    <p>(&quot;$) (!)&quot;</p>
    <p>&amp;&amp;!&amp;</p>
    <p>)&amp;#$ *%$) *%$&amp; *!*#</p>
    <p>*&amp;%&amp;</p>
    <p>#!</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>#!</p>
    <p>%!</p>
    <p>'!</p>
    <p>)!</p>
    <p>&quot;!!</p>
    <p>%!!</p>
    <p>%&quot;!</p>
    <p>%#!</p>
    <p>%$!</p>
    <p>%%!</p>
    <p>%&amp;!</p>
    <p>%'!</p>
    <p>%(!</p>
    <p>%)!</p>
    <p>%*!</p>
    <p># #  &quot;</p>
    <p>The best BLEU and RIBES scores. However, human evalua7on was not high.</p>
    <p>There might be a remaining problem in automa7c evalua7on.</p>
    <p>The highest automaOc scores</p>
    <p>Not high human scores</p>
    <p>The Crowd score of Online A is very high.</p>
    <p>Comparison with JPO Adequacy (JPC-KJ)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparison of Transla7on Quality between Languages</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Graph Format of JPO Adequacy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ASPEC-JE ASPEC-EJ ASPEC-JC</p>
    <p>ASPEC-CJ JPC-CJ JPC-KJ</p>
    <p>Low quality (Difficult language pair)</p>
    <p>High quality was achieved!</p>
    <p>The second high quality</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary of WAT2015  12 par7cipants for the evalua7on tasks  Including 4 companies and 3 teams outside Japan</p>
    <p>2 domains (scien7fic paper and patent) and 4 languages (Japanese, Chinese, Korean, and English)</p>
    <p>Human evalua7ons were performed  Pairwise Evalua7on by crowdsourcing  JPO Adequacy by professional translators</p>
    <p>Empirically confirmed that MT systems achieved high quality Korean-Japanese patent transla7on.</p>
    <p>Each idea used for the submissions will be presented by the par7cipants.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Perspec7ve</p>
    <p>Papers submibed to WAT will appear on the ACL Anthology.</p>
    <p>Automa7c evalua7on server will keep running even aser the workshop  promote con7nuous evolu7on of MT research</p>
    <p>WAT will be held annually  include more languages, domains...</p>
    <p>Need more inves7ga7on to acquire reliable human evaluaIon results at low cost</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you very much for abending WAT2015</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
