<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) Cloud</p>
    <p>Orna Agmon Ben-Yehuda Muli Ben-Yehuda Assaf Schuster Dan Tsafrir</p>
    <p>Department of Computer Science Technion  Israel Institute of Technology</p>
    <p>HotCloud 2012</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 1/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What will be the New Thing After IaaS?</p>
    <p>Recent IaaS Trends:</p>
    <p>The shrinking duration of rental periods</p>
    <p>The increasingly fine-grained resources offered for sale</p>
    <p>The provisioning of useful service level agreements (SLAs)</p>
    <p>These trends and the economy will drive IaaS to turning into RaaS.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 2/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trend: Granularity of Duration of Rent</p>
    <p>Months: web hosting</p>
    <p>Hours: EC2 on-demand (pay-as-you-go)</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 3/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extrapolation: Granularity of Duration of Rent</p>
    <p>Clients want to pay for resources only when they need them.</p>
    <p>Clients need extra resources to be allocated within seconds (e.g., when slashdotted)</p>
    <p>Phone charges are advancing from minutes to single seconds.</p>
    <p>Phone companies were driven by consumer pressure and court orders.</p>
    <p>We extrapolate that cloud resources will be rented by the second.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 4/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trend: Resource Granularity</p>
    <p>Most cloud providers sell fixed bundles, called instance types or server sizes.</p>
    <p>Amazon allows adding and removing of network instances and block instances, thus dynamically changing I/O resources. CloudSigma offers clients to compose a flexible bundle.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 5/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extrapolation: Resource Granularity</p>
    <p>As physical servers increase, an entire server may be too much for a single client.</p>
    <p>Renting a fixed bundle may waste client resources, even if its requirements stay the same over time. For example, if the client can only use 7 cores, why should it rent 8?</p>
    <p>We extrapolate that clients will rent a basic bundle, and dynamically supplement it with resources in fine granularity.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 6/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A job half done</p>
    <p>If only the first two trends culminate as described, then clients can finally optimize their resource use. However, this is not enough to guarantee a green, efficient cloud. Would they really optimize? Will they optimize the right target function for a green cloud?</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 7/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trend: Service Level Agreements</p>
    <p>Most cloud providers account for rigid availability only (the machine is accessible).</p>
    <p>GoGrid and CloudSigma provide guarantees in terms of minimal actual delivered capacity (latency, packet loss and jitter).</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 8/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Economy of Service Level Agreements</p>
    <p>Benchmarks show great variance in the performance of supposedly similar cloud instances. Different clients need different guarantees: a bank will pay for 100% availability. A small business may settle for a 95% guarantee. Client valuations of performance and resources differ and are private information. Some researchers (Padala09, Heo09, Nathuji10) argue for selling client performance and measuring it. This concept is impossible for a real commercial IaaS black box client.</p>
    <p>IaaS Providers cannot sell performance. They must keep selling resources.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 9/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extrapolation: Service Level Agreements</p>
    <p>We extrapolate that:</p>
    <p>Client pressure for efficiency will drive providers to supply levels of quality service: For 90% of the time or just for 80% of the time.</p>
    <p>Low-QoS clients will be willing to pay less than high-QoS clients.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 10/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Economic Forces Acting on the Provider</p>
    <p>Economic mechanisms will be required inside a machine.</p>
    <p>The provider must keep spare resources for high-QoS clients.</p>
    <p>The provider can let low-QoS clients use the spare resources, subject to availability.</p>
    <p>The provider must mix low QoS clients with high QoS clients.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 11/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Economic Forces Acting on the Client</p>
    <p>Clients aim to buy exactly what they need, to save on expenses.</p>
    <p>And since providers aim to sell clients what they want to buy, to gain and retain clients...</p>
    <p>CPU is rented by cycles, memory is rented by the page, I/O is rented by bandwidth.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 12/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Economic Forces Leading to the RaaS Cloud: Result</p>
    <p>Both clients and providers must continuously decide what to buy and when to buy it. The fine rent time granularity and bundle flexibility makes decision making a core function. Both providers and clients will use economic agent software to handle decision making and economic interaction.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 13/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The RaaS Cloud</p>
    <p>Application</p>
    <p>Resource</p>
    <p>Perf(resource)</p>
    <p>Value(perf)</p>
    <p>Strategy Adviser</p>
    <p>Strategic Agent</p>
    <p>Resource Controller</p>
    <p>Host Guest</p>
    <p>Host Agent</p>
    <p>Communicator</p>
    <p>Decision Maker</p>
    <p>Communicator</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 14/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Guest Agent</p>
    <p>Changes the desired amount of resources on a second-by-second basis.</p>
    <p>Negotiates</p>
    <p>Trades in the futures market.</p>
    <p>Sublets.</p>
    <p>Is not mandatory: dumb clients are still supported, with the same inefficiency of todays IaaS clouds.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 15/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Host Agent: Market Driven Resource Allocation</p>
    <p>Has a view of the global picture (total system resources, change predictions)</p>
    <p>Dictates economic mechanisms and protocols.</p>
    <p>Allocates resources according to agreements.</p>
    <p>Uses the resources to verify that high-QoS clients are satisfied, possibly at the expense of low-QoS clients on the same machine, and given the specific current needs of each client.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 16/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implications, Challenges, Opportunities</p>
    <p>A client software stack (applications, libraries, OS) that utilizes resources for short durations and trades them off.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 17/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implications, Challenges, Opportunities</p>
    <p>Economic (game theoretic) mechanisms for multi-resource allocation with different QoS levels.</p>
    <p>Realistic Incentive compatible Collusion-resistant Computationally efficient at large scale Optimizes the providers revenue or a social welfare function Minimizes the price of anarchy</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 17/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implications, Challenges, Opportunities</p>
    <p>Technical mechanisms for handling resource (re)allocation, metering and charging:</p>
    <p>efficient, reliable, and resistant to side channel attacks.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 17/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implications, Challenges, Opportunities</p>
    <p>Balancing guests across a data-center to create heterogeneous mixes of QoS levels on each machine.</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 17/18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Contact us at: {ladypine, muli, assaf, dan } at cs.technion.ac.il Thank You!</p>
    <p>Agmon Ben-Yehuda, Ben-Yehuda, Schuster, Tsafrir Resource-as-a-Service (RaaS) 18/18</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
