<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fan Guo, Steve Hanneke, Wenjie Fu, Eric P. Xing</p>
    <p>School of Computer Science, Carnegie Mellon University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>High School Dating</p>
    <p>The Internet</p>
    <p>Physicist Collaborations</p>
    <p>All the images are from http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mejn/networks/. That page includes original citations.02/05/19</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protein-Protein Interaction Network in S. cerevisiae Fig. 1 from (H. Jeong et al., Nature 411, 41-42, 3 May 2001)</p>
    <p>Model for the Yeast cell cycle transcriptional regulatory network Fig. 4 from (T.I. Lee et al., Science 298, 799-804, 25 Oct 2002)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infer the hidden network topology from node attribute observations.</p>
    <p>Methods: Optimizing a score function; Information-theoretic</p>
    <p>approaches; Model-based approach</p>
    <p>Most of them pool the data together to infer a static network topology.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network topologies and functions are not static:  Social networks can grow as we know more friends  Biological networks rewire under different conditions</p>
    <p>Fig. 1b from Genomic analysis of regulatory network dynamics reveals larg e topological changes N. M. Luscombe, et al. Nature 431, 308-312, 16 September 2004</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network topologies and functions are not always static.</p>
    <p>We propose probabilistic models and algorithms for recovering latent network topologies that are changing over time from node attribute observations.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Networks rewire over discrete timesteps</p>
    <p>Part of the image is modified from Fig. 3b (E. Segal et al., Nature Genetics 34, 166-176, June 2003).02/05/19</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transition Model</p>
    <p>Emission Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Latent network structures are of higher dimensions than observed node attributes  How to place constraints on the latent space?</p>
    <p>Limited evidence per timestep  How to share the information across time?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Energy-based conditional probability model (recall Markov random fields)</p>
    <p>Energy-based model is easier to analysis, but even the design of approximate inference algorithm can be hard.</p>
    <p>( , )</p>
    <p>( , ) 1</p>
    <p>( | ) exp ( , ) ( ) k</p>
    <p>k C k</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>E x y</p>
    <p>E x y e</p>
    <p>p x y x y Z ye</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Based on our previous work on discrete temporal network models in the ICML06 SNA-Workshop.  Model network rewiring as a Markov process.  An expressive framework using energy-based local</p>
    <p>probabilities (based on ERGM):</p>
    <p>Features of choice:</p>
    <p>1 1</p>
    <p>, t t t t</p>
    <p>i it i</p>
    <p>p A A A A Z A</p>
    <p>1 1</p>
    <p>, 1 1 ,</p>
    <p>t t t ij ik kj</p>
    <p>ijkt t t t t ij ij ij ij ij t t</p>
    <p>ij ij ik kj ijk</p>
    <p>A A A</p>
    <p>A A A A A A A</p>
    <p>(Density) (Edge Stability) (Transitivity)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Given the network topology, how to generate the binary node attributes?</p>
    <p>Another energy-based conditional model:</p>
    <p>All features are pairwise which induces an undirected graph corresponding to the time-specific network topology;</p>
    <p>Additional information shared over time is represented by a matrix of parameters ;</p>
    <p>The design of feature function  is application-specific.</p>
    <p>1</p>
    <p>, exp , , , , ,</p>
    <p>t t t t t ij i j ij ijt</p>
    <p>ij</p>
    <p>p x A x x A Z A</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The feature function</p>
    <p>If no edge between i and j,  equals 0;</p>
    <p>Otherwise the sign of  depends on ij and the empirical correlation of xi, xj at time t.</p>
    <p>2 1 2 1t t tij ij ij i jA x x</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Time-invariant parameters dictating the direction of pairwise correlation in the example</p>
    <p>Initial network to define the prior on A1</p>
    <p>Hidden rewiring networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A natural approach to infer the hidden networks A1:T is Gibbs sampling:  To evaluate the log-odds</p>
    <p>Conditional probabilities in a Markov blanket</p>
    <p>t t t t t ij ijt</p>
    <p>ij t t t t t ij ij</p>
    <p>P A A A A x</p>
    <p>P A A A A x</p>
    <p>Tractable transition model; the partition function is the product of per edge terms</p>
    <p>Computation is straightforward</p>
    <p>Given the graphical structure, run variable elimination algorithms, works well for small graphs</p>
    <p>1</p>
    <p>, exp , , , , ,</p>
    <p>t t t t t ij i j ij ijt</p>
    <p>ij</p>
    <p>p x A x x A Z A</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Grid search is very helpful, although Monte Carlo EM can be implemented.</p>
    <p>Trade-off between the transition model and emission model:  Larger  : better fit of the rewiring processes;  Larger  : better fit of the observations.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data generated from the proposed model.  Starting from a network (A0) of 10 nodes and 14 edges.  The length of the time series T = 50.</p>
    <p>Compare three approaches using F1 score:  avg: averaged network from ground truth</p>
    <p>(approx. upper bounds the performance of any static network inference algorithm)  htERG: infer timestep-specific networks  sERG: the static counterpart of the proposed algorithm</p>
    <p>Study the edge-switching events</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>F1 scores on different parameter settings (varying )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>F1 scores on different number of examples 1 2 30.5, 4, 4, 1,100 iterations of Gibbs sampling, 10 repetitionsk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary on capturing edge switching in networks  Three cases studied: offset, false positive, missing (false negative)  mean and rms of offset timesteps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The proposed model was applied to infer the muscle development subnetwork (Zhao et al., 2006) on Drosophila lifecycle gene expression data (Arbeitman et al., 2002).</p>
    <p>11 genes, 66 timesteps over 4 development stages  Further biological experiments are necessary for verification.</p>
    <p>Network in (Zhao et al. 2006)</p>
    <p>Embryonic Larval Pupal &amp; Adult</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A new class of probabilistic models to address the problem of recoving hidden, time-dependent network topologies and an example in a biological context.</p>
    <p>An example of employing energy-based model to define meaningful features and simplify parameterization.</p>
    <p>Future work  Larger-scale network analysis (100+?)</p>
    <p>Developing emission models for richer context</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Yanxin Shi CMU</p>
    <p>Wentao Zhao Texas A&amp;M University</p>
    <p>Hetunandan Kamisetty CMU</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
