<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Importance of Features for Statistical</p>
    <p>Anomaly Detection David Goldberg</p>
    <p>Yinan Shan</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>I had an anomaly detection problem</p>
    <p>I went to the literature, it didnt seem helpful</p>
    <p>So I invented my own algorithm</p>
    <p>I draw some conclusions from this experience</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Terminology</p>
    <p>Monitored Signals  These are continuously scanned, looking for trouble</p>
    <p>Disruption  The site is not working as designed</p>
    <p>Anomaly  A monitored signal has unusual behavior, suggesting a</p>
    <p>disruption</p>
    <p>Alert  What we do after detecting an anomaly</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summarizing terminology</p>
    <p>An anomaly is what we measure. We hope that it correlates with disruptions</p>
    <p>A disruption is a symptom  A human still needs to investigate and</p>
    <p>determine the root cause</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>I had an anomaly detection problem</p>
    <p>I went to the literature, it didnt seem helpful</p>
    <p>So I invented my own algorithm</p>
    <p>I draw some conclusions from this experience</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>My problem</p>
    <p>Finding disruptions in eBay search results</p>
    <p>Two types  Severe disruptions (e.g. no search results) are detected by</p>
    <p>other systems  Were mainly interested in more subtle disruptions</p>
    <p>Examples  Change in average price shown  Change in items from sellers with low feedback  Change in the category distribution of results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tool for Finding Disruptions</p>
    <p>We detect via monitoring  We regularly monitor search results</p>
    <p>But monitoring returns a lot of data  Not clear when to signal an alert</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Monitored Signals for Search</p>
    <p>There are 3000 reference queries</p>
    <p>They are repeatedly issued every 4 hours</p>
    <p>Consecutive results for the same query are usually different  eBay has auctions, and they expire  A lot of 1-off (single quantity) items, and they get sold  Ranking for multiple quantity items changes based on</p>
    <p>popularity</p>
    <p>How much change in monitored data is a disruption?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to measure change</p>
    <p>We compare two difference instances of the same query</p>
    <p>We measure change using metrics</p>
    <p>Sample metrics:  Recall size (number of returned items)  Percentage of used items in the result set  Median price of items in the result set</p>
    <p>There are about 50 metrics total</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HotCloud 15 July 6, 2015 10</p>
    <p>M et</p>
    <p>ric s</p>
    <p>Queries</p>
    <p>Time M</p>
    <p>et ric</p>
    <p>M1</p>
    <p>M2</p>
    <p>M3</p>
    <p>Q1 Q2 Q3 Q4 Q5 Q6 Q7 Q8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>When to signal alert</p>
    <p>Original system used rules</p>
    <p>Example  If the fraction of auctions metric for at least 10% of</p>
    <p>queries is 0, signal an alert</p>
    <p>Good rules are very hard to construct</p>
    <p>Rule based system was  Brittle  Missed disruptions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>I had an anomaly detection problem</p>
    <p>I went to the literature, it didnt seem helpful</p>
    <p>So I invented my own algorithm</p>
    <p>I draw some conclusions from this experience</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The literature</p>
    <p>Seems to focus on two situations</p>
    <p>Points in n-space  Represent my data a points in space, look for a point</p>
    <p>that doesnt belong</p>
    <p>Time Series  Represent my data as a time series, look for a point</p>
    <p>that doesnt belong</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HotCloud 15 July 6, 2015 14</p>
    <p>From Chandola et al Anomaly Detection: A Survey</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HotCloud 15 July 6, 2015 15</p>
    <p>From Chandola et al Anomaly Detection: A Survey</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The literature and our problem</p>
    <p>Neither of these approaches seems natural</p>
    <p>My data isnt a time series  Its 150,000 time series</p>
    <p>Not clear how to represent monitoring info as a point cloud</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>I had an anomaly detection problem</p>
    <p>I went to the literature, it didnt seem helpful</p>
    <p>So I invented my own algorithm</p>
    <p>I draw some conclusions from this experience</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithm philosophy</p>
    <p>Based on understanding the problem, rather than feeding into an black box anomaly detector</p>
    <p>Import advantage: disruptions must be investigated (to get root cause), so want help understanding why the alert was raised</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The algorithm idea</p>
    <p>For each time series, define surprise of the last point  This is deviation from expected value  Can do this using standard time series methods</p>
    <p>But.  With so many time series, you expect some very large</p>
    <p>surprise values</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The algorithm idea (2)</p>
    <p>For each time series, define surprise of the last point  This is deviation from expected value  Can do this using standard time series methods</p>
    <p>But.  With so many time series, you expect some very large</p>
    <p>surprise values</p>
    <p>So instead ask how many queries have large surprise</p>
    <p>And if alert if that number is surprising 20</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The algorithm, more formally</p>
    <p>Surprise is the deviation from a linear fit, normalized by median deviation  So there is a surprise for each (query, metric, end-time) triple</p>
    <p>Use this to define a new time series  For each fixed metric, compute the 90th percentile of surprise</p>
    <p>over all queries  Now there are 50 time series, instead of 50 x 3000</p>
    <p>Look for outliers in this new time series</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HotCloud 15 July 6, 2015 22</p>
    <p>M et</p>
    <p>ric s</p>
    <p>Queries</p>
    <p>Time M</p>
    <p>et ric</p>
    <p>Algorithm in Pictures</p>
    <p>M1</p>
    <p>M2</p>
    <p>M3</p>
    <p>Q1 Q2 Q3 Q4 Q5 Q6 Q7 Q8</p>
    <p>M et</p>
    <p>ric s M1</p>
    <p>M2</p>
    <p>M3</p>
    <p>Q1 Q2 Q3 Q4 Q5 Q6 Q7 Q8</p>
    <p>s1 s2 s3 s4 s5 s6 s7 s8</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>T</p>
    <p>s(1) s(2) s(3) s(4) s(5) s(6) s(7) s(8)</p>
    <p>S90(T)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HotCloud 15 July 6, 2015 23</p>
    <p>Algorithm in Pictures (2) M</p>
    <p>et ric</p>
    <p>s M1 M2</p>
    <p>M3</p>
    <p>Q1 Q2 Q3 Q4 Q5 Q6 Q7 Q8 S90(T)</p>
    <p>M et</p>
    <p>ric s M1</p>
    <p>M2</p>
    <p>M3</p>
    <p>Q1 Q2 Q3 Q4 Q5 Q6 Q7 Q8 S90(T)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Detecting Anomalies</p>
    <p>Each metric has a time series</p>
    <p>Declare anomaly if one or more of those series has a dramatic blip  3  from the median</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Actual anomaly</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>I had an anomaly detection problem</p>
    <p>I went to the literature, it didnt seem helpful</p>
    <p>So I invented my own algorithm</p>
    <p>I draw some conclusions from this experience</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons Learned</p>
    <p>Theres a tradeoff of features and statistics  Good features may eliminate need for subtle statistical</p>
    <p>tests</p>
    <p>Doubt existence of general purpose anomaly software  Not obvious how to adapt them for our problem</p>
    <p>Conclusion: features are important!  Perhaps even more important than statistics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Real-life anomaly detection might not easily map to time series or points in n-space.  Or in general, to black-box statistical tests.</p>
    <p>At least in one example, good features eliminate the need for sophisticated statistics  Side effect: features can help with root cause</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>For Discussion</p>
    <p>Your examples of anomaly detection?</p>
    <p>Other approaches for my data?</p>
    <p>Does trading features for statistics make sense to you?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
