<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mapping Cross-Cloud Systems: Challenges and Opportunities</p>
    <p>Yehia Elkhatib</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inevitability of cross-cloud computing 25% of enterprises will be deploying [] into some type of hybrid cloud Private cloud is the preferred option for the majority of enterprise workload types, followed closely by hybrid cloud deployments. Cloud Management Platforms, 451 Research, 2014</p>
    <p>82% of enterprises have a hybrid cloud strategy, up from 74% in 2014. State of the Cloud Report, RightScale, 2015</p>
    <p>Users are running applications in an average of 1.5 public and 1.7 private clouds. State of the Cloud Report, RightScale, 2016</p>
    <p>Most significant trends:  Security, Integrity and</p>
    <p>Data Privacy  Interoperability</p>
    <p>and Portability  Moving to the Cloud  Standards  Certification</p>
    <p>Cloud Computing Users Needs, ETSI, 2015</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Confusion  Non-convergent terminology  Lack of shared best practices  Unidentified research directions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions  Definition of CCC  Classification capturing major efforts  describe their modus operandi  comment on suitability and limitations</p>
    <p>Review of current challenges  Outlook on research+business opportunities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Disclaimers  Developer perspective, mostly on IaaS  Drawn from literature and CrossCloud events  Not professing an uber cloud  commercially unrealistic  diversity is healthy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Definition  A cross-cloud application is one that</p>
    <p>consumes more than one cloud API under a single version of the application.</p>
    <p>Instigated by  change to predetermined plan  need to be free from long-term commitment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dictionary</p>
    <p>Hybrid clouds</p>
    <p>Federated clouds</p>
    <p>Multiclouds</p>
    <p>Meta-/ interclouds</p>
    <p>Application Developer</p>
    <p>Clouds-R-Us</p>
    <p>Translation Libraries</p>
    <p>Common Programming</p>
    <p>Models</p>
    <p>Broker Common API</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges  Value-added services  e.g. AWS ElastiCache  drive usage up for more gravity, not revenue</p>
    <p>and attracting new users</p>
    <p>most developers take the path of least resistance  CCC becomes an academic exercise</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges  Brokerage market is rather slim  trusting a 3rd party?  expertise!  businesses that have it does not need brokerage  businesses that do not have other priorities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Opportunities  Strategic decision making  customers need assistance: entering, migrating</p>
    <p>Amazon EC2</p>
    <p>Joyent Compute</p>
    <p>RackSpace</p>
    <p>Microsoft Azure</p>
    <p>Google Compute Engine</p>
    <p>HP Cloud Compute</p>
    <p>DigitalOcean</p>
    <p>Number of Instance Types</p>
    <p>Ia aS</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>vi de</p>
    <p>r</p>
    <p>Instance_Type General Purpose Memory Intensive CPU Intensive I/O Optimised Other Types</p>
    <p>(as of Aug 25th 2015)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Opportunities  Strategic decision making  customers need assistance: entering, migrating  room for non-partisan consultancy and arbitrage  metrics available: ThousandEyes, CloudHarmony  gain knowledge in different domains (CSPs, appls)  quantifying migration costs  use ML for thrashing-free decision support</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Opportunities  Crowd-sourced cloud knowledge  progress on: metrics (get &amp; compare), billing APIs  share for informed users, market competitiveness  contextualize QoS metrics to appl. profiles  build community knowledge to auto. verify SLAs  effect of such evidence-based culture on market</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Opportunities  Migration vehicles  containers and unikernels ftw  opened up migration possibilities  suitability for migrating different workloads  life cycle management across disparate host clouds</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Opportunities  Edge market places  more hunger for the cloud: more devices, services  especially for DC-poor locations with potential  DCs being built, but a long-term solution at best  a solution: community clouds serving local markets  programming abstractions to bridge infrastructures  fog offerings by CSPs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Concluding remarks  Overview of cross-cloud computing  definition, classification, challenges, opportunities</p>
    <p>Cloud computing remains industry-driven  Plenty of room for system innovation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks  Participants of the CrossCloud event series  Faculty of Science &amp; Technology for travel fund</p>
    <p>Q&amp;A y.elkhatib@lancaster.ac.uk</p>
    <p>@yelkhatib</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
