<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How Not to Bid the Cloud Prateek Sharma, David Irwin, Prashant Shenoy</p>
    <p>HotCloud 2016</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transient Servers in the Cloud  Conventional cloud servers: on-demand servers</p>
    <p>Fixed price, user-controlled life-span</p>
    <p>Cloud operators sell surplus capacity as low-cost transient servers:</p>
    <p>Can be revoked at any time</p>
    <p>EC2 Spot instances, GCE Pre-emptible VMs</p>
    <p>70-90% lower costs  attractive for batch and delay tolerant applications</p>
    <p>Transient servers have different pricing models</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bidding in EC2 Spot Markets  Spot prices set by continuous second-price auction  Users place a bid representing their maximum hourly price  Spot price rises above bid  Server revoked after 2 minute warning</p>
    <p>e ($</p>
    <p>/h r)</p>
    <p>SSot Srice Bid Srice</p>
    <p>Bidding strategies important to optimize cost, availability  Zheng et.al. [SigComm 15], Zafer et.al., Tang et.al. [Cloud 12]  What is the impact of bidding on availability and cost?</p>
    <p>Bidding tradeoffs:  High bid  high availability  High bid  high costRevocation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Talk outline</p>
    <p>Motivation: spot markets and bidding  Comprehensive empirical analysis of effect of bidding  Beyond bidding</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology  Spot price traces published by Amazon  Use spot price traces from March-October 2015  1500 markets : 8 geographic region, ~2 availability zones, 15</p>
    <p>server types, 3 operating systems</p>
    <p>Prior work is restricted to developing bidding strategies for a few (~10) markets</p>
    <p>Metrics: Availability, Cost, Mean time between revocations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(5eODtive tR 2n-demDnd priFe)</p>
    <p>A vD</p>
    <p>iOD bi</p>
    <p>Oit y</p>
    <p>C D</p>
    <p>)</p>
    <p>g2.2xODrge F3.xODrge</p>
    <p>r3.ODrge m3.medium</p>
    <p>d2.8xODrge</p>
    <p>Availability</p>
    <p>Availability : fraction of time for which spot price less than bid price</p>
    <p>Spot prices mostly low, with occasional large spikes  High availability for wide range of bids</p>
    <p>Long tailed  Availability is high (&gt;90%)</p>
    <p>but does not reach 100%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(5eOative tR 2n-demand price)</p>
    <p>C Rs</p>
    <p>t (5</p>
    <p>eO at</p>
    <p>iv e</p>
    <p>tR 2</p>
    <p>nde</p>
    <p>m an</p>
    <p>d pr</p>
    <p>ic e)</p>
    <p>g2.2xOarge c3.xOarge</p>
    <p>r3.Oarge m3.medium</p>
    <p>d2.8xOarge</p>
    <p>Cost</p>
    <p>Long tailed  Cost of spot instances is low</p>
    <p>for wide range of bid prices</p>
    <p>Cost of spot instances (relative to on-demand price) at different bid prices</p>
    <p>Costs determined by spot prices, not the bid-price itself</p>
    <p>No cost penalty for high bid prices  Cost not particularly sensitive to bidding</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mean Time Between Revocations</p>
    <p>Long tailed</p>
    <p>Mean time between revocations : how long applications can run uninterrupted</p>
    <p>MTBRAvailability : Short, frequent spikes cause low MTBR</p>
    <p>Revocations are unavoidable if prices spike too high</p>
    <p>(5eOative tR 2n-demand price)</p>
    <p>hR ur</p>
    <p>s)</p>
    <p>g2.2xOarge c3.xOarge</p>
    <p>r3.Oarge m3.medium</p>
    <p>d2.8xOarge</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Availability, Cost, MTBR not particularly sensitive to bidding  Low-cost, highly available spot servers for wide range of bids</p>
    <p>Do we need sophisticated bidding strategies?</p>
    <p>Impact of Bidding</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analyzing 1500 markets</p>
    <p>90% of all bids yield availability, cost, and MTBR that are near optimal</p>
    <p>Vast majority of 1500 markets have long tails</p>
    <p>In the current spot markets, bidding has negligible impact  Different bidding strategies yield same practical end-result</p>
    <p>Percentage of all bids that yield availability, cost, MTBR that are 10% within the optimal</p>
    <p>Avail. CRst 0TBR 0</p>
    <p>Pe rc</p>
    <p>en ta</p>
    <p>ge R</p>
    <p>f ne</p>
    <p>ar -R</p>
    <p>pt iP</p>
    <p>al b</p>
    <p>id s</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Beyond Bidding  Look beyond bidding and focus on systems problems  Simple strategy: Bid the on-demand price, migrate when revoked</p>
    <p>Requires efficient migration and checkpointing</p>
    <p>Avoid simultaneous revocations by using multiple markets  Revocation gap: time difference between revocations in two markets</p>
    <p>S po</p>
    <p>t M ar</p>
    <p>ke t</p>
    <p>Revocation Gap (Hours)</p>
    <p>Many markets have large revocation gaps (&gt;24 hours)</p>
    <p>Independent failures  Distribute applications, migrate</p>
    <p>to uncorrelated markets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Spot instances : auction based pricing  Empirically study effect of bidding on cost, availability, and</p>
    <p>failure-rates</p>
    <p>Large range of bids have same effect  bidding is not crucial  Sophisticated bidding strategies do not outperform simple ones  Simple bidding strategies and using mutually uncorrelated</p>
    <p>markets : easier and practical alternative</p>
    <p>Beyond bidding: fault-tolerance and market selection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You prateeks@cs.umass.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why bidding strategies are not crucial</p>
    <p>Wide range of optimal bids  Resources always available  No penalty for high bids</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>When will bidding be relevant?</p>
    <p>Availability, cost CDFs not long tailed  More penalty for bidding too high  Higher market volatility  Users and systems exploiting arbitraging opportunities  Still need systems to handle the transiency gracefully</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spot market volatility over the years</p>
    <p>m1.large price range and skewness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transient cloud servers</p>
    <p>SpotCheck EuroSys 15</p>
    <p>Flint EuroSys 16</p>
    <p>SpotOn SoCC 15</p>
    <p>Bidding HotCloud 16</p>
    <p>Cluster Management Stay tuned</p>
    <p>Applications</p>
    <p>Interactive Batch-Interactive data intensive (Spark)</p>
    <p>Fault tolerance for batch jobs</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
