<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Towards a Network Marketplace in a Cloud</p>
    <p>Da Yu, Luo Mai, Somaya Arianfar, Rodrigo Fonseca, Orran Krieger, David Oran</p>
    <p>HotCloud 2016</p>
    <p>Denver, CO</p>
    <p>Brown University Imperial College London Boston University Cisco</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Public clouds today</p>
    <p>Few providers  Vertically integrated  Opaque control of lower layers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Elas%cMR EC2</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>Example: MapReduce on Amazon</p>
    <p>MapReduce! Be3er MapReduce!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Public clouds today</p>
    <p>Few providers  Vertically integrated  Opaque control of lower layers  Vendor lock-in</p>
    <p>Competition Innovation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Massachusetts Open Cloud</p>
    <p>Source: Wikimedia Commons by Khemkhaeng Source: Wikimedia Commons by Mtaylor444</p>
    <p>Open Cloud Exchange: public and open cloud</p>
    <p>Source: Chris%ne und Hagen Graf, Flickr</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Open Cloud Exchange: public and open cloud</p>
    <p>Massachusetts Open Cloud</p>
    <p>Po w er</p>
    <p>Co ol in g</p>
    <p>OpenStack MapReduce</p>
    <p>N et w or k</p>
    <p>See h3p://info.massopencloud.org/ for more details</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Where does Networking fit?</p>
    <p>Our goal: networking should be a first class service, not just basic infrastructure</p>
    <p>Providers should compete, all the way to the physical level, to provide networking!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can we make networking part of the marketplace?</p>
    <p>Vision:  Alice wants to provision 50 VMs in a compute pool,</p>
    <p>and 50 VMs in a GPU pool  Wants to connect these VMs in a single LAN  Gets offered two options to create this network:</p>
    <p>Standard, best effort network (free)  Dedicated 10Gbps network with RDMA (for $$)</p>
    <p>Selects the second option, and her traffic is automatically routed through the right switches, with the right queues configured</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Source: h3p://www.mtc.ca.gov/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Potential reasons</p>
    <p>Isolation  Physical (security)  Performance (BW/Latency)</p>
    <p>Control  E.g., DCTCP, PFabric, NetFPGA</p>
    <p>Special/Niche needs  100Gbps, Lossless Ethernet (RoCE, RDMA), 60GHz</p>
    <p>wireless,</p>
    <p>Enable innovation and market-driven competition for network services</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The NetEx Prototype</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GPUs Storage Compute Pod A Pod B Pod C</p>
    <p>Baseline Architecture</p>
    <p>Jointly administered machines w/ internal network</p>
    <p>Common Network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multi-Provider Inter-Pod Network</p>
    <p>Pod A Pod B Pod C</p>
    <p>Network Providers X Y Z</p>
    <p>EoP EoP EoP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multi-Provider Inter-Pod Network</p>
    <p>Pod A Pod B Pod C</p>
    <p>Network Exchange Marketplace</p>
    <p>Network Providers</p>
    <p>Network Users</p>
    <p>X Y Z</p>
    <p>NetEx Agent</p>
    <p>EoP EoP EoP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Configuring a Path</p>
    <p>User requests path properties between two or more pods, for specific traffic (flowspec)  E.g., I need 10usec latency for my port 445 RPC traffic</p>
    <p>NetEx forwards request to network providers  Network providers return bids:</p>
    <p>&lt;path segment, properties, price&gt;  User selects path option  NetEx brokers provisioning</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Configuring a Path</p>
    <p>Selected network provider provisions internal path segment, returns opaque handle</p>
    <p>NetEx configures pod switches: &lt;flowspec, provider, handle&gt;</p>
    <p>Requirement: packet matching flowspec arrives at the egress EoP provider port with the label handle</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Pod-level Design  Current prototype in Mininet</p>
    <p>Uses OpenFlow with nested MPLS labels  Divides responsibility between ToR and EoP</p>
    <p>EoP directs traffic to providers based on per-provider label</p>
    <p>ToR matches on flowspec and configures loose source route:</p>
    <p>source pod label &gt; provider label &gt; provider internal label &gt; dest</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>fwd(Aint)</p>
    <p>pop(Yint) pop(Xint)</p>
    <p>fwd(dst)</p>
    <p>fwd(dst)</p>
    <p>push(Aint, X|Y, Xint|Yint)</p>
    <p>Pod A Pod B</p>
    <p>Network Provider Y</p>
    <p>Network Provider X</p>
    <p>EoP Switch Server</p>
    <p>fwd(X|Y)</p>
    <p>pop(X)</p>
    <p>pop(Aint)</p>
    <p>pop(Y)</p>
    <p>fwd(dst)</p>
    <p>ToR Switch</p>
    <p>fwd(Yint)</p>
    <p>fwd(Xint)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alternatives  Other pod designs possible</p>
    <p>E.g., Vswitch does the tagging at the hypervisor (if present)</p>
    <p>EoP does more of the work  Not necessarily MPLS inside the pod</p>
    <p>Requirement: packet matching flowspec arrives at the egress EoP provider port with the label handle</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Next Steps</p>
    <p>Does this make sense? J  Moving to implementation on MOC  Our goal is to have an architecture that does not</p>
    <p>preclude a network marketplace in the cloud  Design client APIs, market mechanisms  Design challenges</p>
    <p>Accountability, enforcement, (price) transparency  Extend to the wide area</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>rfonseca@cs.brown.edu dyu@cs.brown.edu</p>
    <p>luo.mai11@imperial.ac.uk sarianfa@cisco.com</p>
    <p>okrieg@bu.edu oran@cisco.com</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
