<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Seven GDPR Sins of Personal-Data Processing Systems</p>
    <p>Supreeth Shastri, Melissa Wasserman, Vijay Chidambaram</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!3</p>
    <p>General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR)</p>
    <p>Hefty penalty Max penalty of 4% of global revenue or 20 million, whichever is greater</p>
    <p>Fundamental right Grants all European people a right to</p>
    <p>protection and privacy of personal data</p>
    <p>Personal data Any information relating to a natural person;</p>
    <p>Broad in scope unlike FERPA, HIPAA</p>
    <p>Covers entire lifecycle Collection, processing, protection, transfer</p>
    <p>and deletion; Regulated via 99 articles</p>
    <p>May 25, 2018 Adopted after 2 years of public debate. All but 2 EU countries have legislated.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!4</p>
    <p>send personal data for external processing</p>
    <p>store and process personal data internally</p>
    <p>provide personal</p>
    <p>data</p>
    <p>share personal data</p>
    <p>GDPR Entities</p>
    <p>Processor (e.g., Google cloud)</p>
    <p>Controller (e.g., Spotify)</p>
    <p>Other Controllers (e.g., SoundCloud)</p>
    <p>Data Subject (e.g., Spotify user)</p>
    <p>exercise GDPR rights</p>
    <p>allo w d</p>
    <p>ata sh</p>
    <p>arin g</p>
    <p>Personal data GDPR queriesGDPR queries</p>
    <p>Supervisory Authority</p>
    <p>report GDPR violations</p>
    <p>audit and investigatenot</p>
    <p>ify dat</p>
    <p>a b rea</p>
    <p>che s</p>
    <p>aud it a</p>
    <p>nd inv</p>
    <p>est iga</p>
    <p>te</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!5</p>
    <p>Adapted</p>
    <p>&lt;50% estimated compliance By the end of 2018 [Gartner 2018]</p>
    <p>Assumed compliance everyone else</p>
    <p>Advertised compliance BigTech</p>
    <p>Terminated</p>
    <p>GDPR in the Wild</p>
    <p>In the first 9 months of GDPR rollout</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!6</p>
    <p>The Seven GDPR Sins</p>
    <p>Internet-era systems have primarily focused on reliability, scalability, and affordability.</p>
    <p>Relegating security and privacy as afterthoughts has given rise to</p>
    <p>principles and practices that are at odds with GDPR. KEY</p>
    <p>OBSERVATION</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!7</p>
    <p>17: Right To Be Forgotten (1) The data subject shall have the right to obtain from the</p>
    <p>controller the erasure of personal data without undue delay [...]</p>
    <p>5(1)(E): Storage Limitation [...] kept for no longer than is necessary for the purposes</p>
    <p>for which the personal data are processed [...]</p>
    <p>AF TE</p>
    <p>R</p>
    <p>Time that Google cloud requires to guarantee that a requested personal</p>
    <p>data item is fully deleted</p>
    <p>B EF</p>
    <p>O R</p>
    <p>E</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!8</p>
    <p>21: Right To Object (1)The data subject shall have the right to object at any time to processing of personal data concerning</p>
    <p>him or her [...].</p>
    <p>5(1)(B): Purpose Limitation Personal data shall be collected for specified, explicit and legitimate purposes and not further processed in a manner that is incompatible with those purposes [...]</p>
    <p>AF TE</p>
    <p>R</p>
    <p>50m On Jan 21st 2019, the French DPA</p>
    <p>levied the largest GDPR fine yet on Google for purpose bundling</p>
    <p>B EF</p>
    <p>O R</p>
    <p>E Facebook is using your 2FA phone number to</p>
    <p>target ads at you</p>
    <p>Reported by GIZMODO on 9/26/2018</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!9</p>
    <p>Source: 2014 FTC report on 9 largest personal data brokers</p>
    <p>B EF</p>
    <p>O R</p>
    <p>E</p>
    <p>Unique data points per US consumer</p>
    <p>Many programmatic ad exchanges shut down</p>
    <p>AF TE</p>
    <p>R</p>
    <p>14: Information To Be Provided Where Personal Data Have Not Been Obtained</p>
    <p>From The Data Subject (1) (c) the purposes of the processing [...], (e) the recipients [...], (2) (a) the period for which the personal data will be stored [...],</p>
    <p>(f) from which source the personal data originate [...].</p>
    <p>20: Right to Data Portability (1) The data subject shall have the right to receive the personal data concerning him or her, which he or she has provided to a</p>
    <p>controller. (2) [...] the right to have the personal data transmitted directly from one controller to another.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!10</p>
    <p>36: Prior Consultation The controller shall consult the supervisory authority prior to processing where [...] it would result in a high risk in absence</p>
    <p>of measures taken by the controller to mitigate the risk.</p>
    <p>35: Data Protection Impact Assessment</p>
    <p>Where processing, in particular using new technologies, is likely to result in a high risk to the rights of natural persons,</p>
    <p>the controller shall, prior to the processing, carry out an assessment of the impact of the envisaged processing.</p>
    <p>B EF</p>
    <p>O R</p>
    <p>E AF</p>
    <p>TE R</p>
    <p>&gt;50m User accounts hacked in 2018,</p>
    <p>after Facebooks View-As feature was exploited.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!11</p>
    <p>33: Notification of A Personal Data Breach</p>
    <p>(1) the controller shall without undue delay and not later than 72 hours after having become aware of it,</p>
    <p>notify the supervisory authority. [] (3) The notification shall at least describe the nature of the personal breach, [...] likely consequences, and [...]</p>
    <p>measures taken to mitigate its adverse effects.</p>
    <p>Breaches in the real world</p>
    <p>Reported data breaches 6 months before and after GDPR</p>
    <p>(only Europe)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!12</p>
    <p>15: Right of Access (1) The data subject shall have the right to obtain from the</p>
    <p>controller [...] meaningful information about the logic involved, as well as the significance and the envisaged</p>
    <p>consequences of such processing.</p>
    <p>22: Automated Individual Decision-Making</p>
    <p>(1) The data subject shall have the right not to be subject to a decision based solely on automated processing [...]</p>
    <p>AF TE</p>
    <p>R</p>
    <p>Workshop on Explainable AI</p>
    <p>Workshop on Human Interpretability in ML</p>
    <p>B EF</p>
    <p>O R</p>
    <p>E</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!13</p>
    <p>25: Data Protection By Design and By Default</p>
    <p>(1) [...] design to implement data protection principles in an effective manner [...]</p>
    <p>Security in the real world</p>
    <p>ML-driven reactive security</p>
    <p>24: Responsibility of the Data Controller the controller shall [] be able to demonstrate that processing is</p>
    <p>performed in accordance with this Regulation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!14</p>
    <p>Concluding Remarks</p>
    <p>FUTURE DIRECTIONS</p>
    <p>GDPR-compliant Redis Exploring system-level tradeoff</p>
    <p>in achieving compliance</p>
    <p>Beyond GDPR Californias CCPA is going</p>
    <p>into effect 1/1/2020</p>
    <p>Cloud consolidation Could compliance be better</p>
    <p>tackled at cloud provider level?</p>
    <p>We want to hear from you! https://utsaslab.github.io/research/gdpr/</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
