<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Serverless Boom or Bust? An Analysis of Economic Incentives Xiayue Charles Lin, Joseph E. Gonzalez, Joseph M. Hellerstein UC Berkeley</p>
    <p>HotCloud 2020  Monday, July 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Economic Model for Serverless</p>
    <p>Serverless: pay for consumption instead of capacity  In broad strokes, when is serverless advantageous?</p>
    <p>Why an economic model?</p>
    <p>Serverless is exciting, but still in its relative infancy - provisioned servers are far from being replaced</p>
    <p>Inform research and build intuition:  Which parts of the design space are economically sensible?  Which directions have transformative potential?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions we want to reason about</p>
    <p>Gauging how compelling arbitrary improvements are  Suppose a new paper shows some technique can reduce straggler latency by 2x for serverless</p>
    <p>application Y  What does that mean? Is it game changing? Does this enable the previously infeasible?  What if cloud vendors change serverless prices in the future? Instead of redoing benchmarks,</p>
    <p>intuitively reason about whether serverless Y makes sense fundamentally or temporarily</p>
    <p>Informing design decisions  Autoscaling policies  Pricing Quality of Service</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Developing the model  The constraint: for any serverless product to be viable,</p>
    <p>both the provider and the customer must prefer it to a serverful option</p>
    <p>For the provider, we assume profit to be the most important  Serverless product should bring in at least as much revenue as if the resources were spent on a</p>
    <p>serverful product instead  We consider utilization ratio and price ratio (for any particular vendor and product)</p>
    <p>Resource underutilization from serverless must be compensated by higher product price</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Developing the model</p>
    <p>The customer also faces an analogous price-to-utilization tradeoff: the premium they pay for serverless must be worth the time they would waste if they provisioned a serverful product</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Developing the model</p>
    <p>Another decision factor: the customer may also find serverless less useful  Specialized hardware requirements?  Quality of service requirements?  Transition cost, operational concerns, lock-in concerns</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Developing the model</p>
    <p>Another decision factor: the customer may also find serverless less useful  Specialized hardware requirements?  Quality of service requirements?  Transition cost, operational concerns, lock-in concerns</p>
    <p>Can model this as a binary variable, but might as well make it continuous:</p>
    <p>(teal term represents relative usefulness of serverless product over serverful)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Developing the model</p>
    <p>Combining the provider and customer models:</p>
    <p>On the two ends: how much better providers are at using resources than individual customers, and how useful serverless products are</p>
    <p>Price ratio serves as a public bound for these otherwise opaque terms</p>
    <p>For brevity, we will denote the customer characteristics as</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Classifying customers</p>
    <p>Individual customers (and use cases) have different characteristics, and thus different levels of alpha. All levels of alpha fall into one of three categories:</p>
    <p>alpha &lt; 1  No amount of utilization or price improvements will help them; more useful serverless products</p>
    <p>are required</p>
    <p>1 &lt; alpha &lt; c-1  These customers prefer consumption-based versus capacity-based pricing if possible, but</p>
    <p>providers cannot profitably serve them yet</p>
    <p>alpha &gt; c-1  Providers can profitably provide</p>
    <p>serverless products to these customers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Examining Autoscaling</p>
    <p>Increasing granularity from customers to their individual provisioned resources (e.g. individual VMs)</p>
    <p>Simulation: A customer provisions for peak to serve a generic job queue</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Examining Autoscaling</p>
    <p>Oracle provisioning (1-minute windows) does not substantially change todays breakeven points for preferring serverless:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Examining quality of service</p>
    <p>Customer might not know peak, or deliberately underprovision anyway, which incurs queuing latency</p>
    <p>Alpha of last VM needed to reduce queuing latency below a p(xx) target</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Serverless systems that are price-competitive with serverful designs are to be expected, and we will inevitably see more of these - especially as specialized hardware enters serverless</p>
    <p>We should explore a mix of provisioned capacity and pay-for-consumption (hybrid serverless designs)</p>
    <p>We should think consciously about incentives and tradeoffs to consumers when designing policies for new serverless systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>Charles Lin  charles.lin@berkeley.edu Joseph Gonzalez  jegonzal@berkeley.edu Joseph Hellerstein  hellerstein@berkeley.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
