<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Completion Time Minimization and Robust</p>
    <p>Power Control in Wireless Packet Networks</p>
    <p>Chris T. K. Ng, Muriel Medard, Asuman Ozdaglar</p>
    <p>ICC, June 16, 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>In a wireless network, power control aims to allocate</p>
    <p>resources among users in the most efficient way.</p>
    <p>A users transmission becomes interference to the other users.</p>
    <p>Power control has a significant impact on the QoS on all users.</p>
    <p>Performance metrics: user rates</p>
    <p>Non-convex optimization. Good GP approximations at high SINRs</p>
    <p>(e.g., voice). Iterative approach to find local solutions at low SINRs.</p>
    <p>Data applications: send at arbitrarily low SINR (e.g., wireless</p>
    <p>sensor networks).</p>
    <p>Completion time:</p>
    <p>Convex optimization at all SINRs.</p>
    <p>Imperfect channel knowledge: robust power control with constraints</p>
    <p>on outage probability.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Model: Wireless Packet Network</p>
    <p>AWGN wireless packet network:</p>
    <p>M users in the network:</p>
    <p>Transmission from each user interferes with one another.</p>
    <p>Hijs: Constant or random variables.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Model: Performance Metrics</p>
    <p>Need to optimize power allocation among users.</p>
    <p>Transmit at maximum power is not necessarily optimal due to</p>
    <p>interference.</p>
    <p>Power constraint for each user:</p>
    <p>Interference is treated as noise.</p>
    <p>Signal to interference-plus-noise ratio (SINR) at receiver i :</p>
    <p>Completion time:</p>
    <p>Minimize a convex completion time cost function: J(T1,,TM).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perfect Channel Estimation</p>
    <p>Channels are known constants:</p>
    <p>Completion time minimization:</p>
    <p>Not a convex optimization problem as stated above.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Convex Reformulation</p>
    <p>Introduce new variable Si to represent the SINR:</p>
    <p>Similar to the change of variables in geometric</p>
    <p>programming (GP):</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Convex Optimization</p>
    <p>Assumes , otherwise valid for all ranges of SINRs.</p>
    <p>Solution efficiently computed by standard convex optimization</p>
    <p>techniques (e.g., interior point methods).</p>
    <p>May incorporate additional convex constraints on Ts and Ps. 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Convexity of the Feasibility Regions</p>
    <p>In a wireless network (when interference is treated as noise), the feasible rate</p>
    <p>region is not convex.</p>
    <p>However, the corresponding feasible completion time region is convex.</p>
    <p>Rate Region Completion Time Region</p>
    <p>Low SINR regime: P1 = P2 = 0 dB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relations to Rate Region</p>
    <p>Suppose J+(T) is convex and nondecreasing, then it is a</p>
    <p>special case of rate utility maximization:</p>
    <p>Some special cases of U(R) can be formulated as</p>
    <p>completion time minimization:</p>
    <p>Minimum potential delay fairness:</p>
    <p>Weighted harmonic mean:</p>
    <p>Minimum rate:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outage Probability Constraints</p>
    <p>Channel gains are modeled as random variables.</p>
    <p>Users know the joint distribution, but not the realizations.</p>
    <p>Based on channel distribution, each user chooses a target</p>
    <p>SINR (target encoding rate).</p>
    <p>Results in an outage if SINR realization falls below the target.</p>
    <p>Completion time minimization subject to outage probability</p>
    <p>constraints:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reliability Function</p>
    <p>Similar logarithmic change of variables as before:</p>
    <p>Outage probability constraint:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Robust Power Control</p>
    <p>Proof follows from applying the composition rules for log-concave</p>
    <p>functions.</p>
    <p>E.g., each user experiences independent fading distributed as: i)</p>
    <p>Rayleigh, ii) Nakagami, and iii) log-normal.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Wireless packet network:</p>
    <p>Each users transmission interferes with the others.</p>
    <p>Optimal power allocation to minimize completion time.</p>
    <p>Known channel gains:</p>
    <p>Logarithmic change of variables similar to GP.</p>
    <p>Convex optimization formulation at all ranges of SINRs.</p>
    <p>Completion time minimization is a special case of rate utility</p>
    <p>maximization.</p>
    <p>Fading channels:</p>
    <p>Constraints on the outage probability.</p>
    <p>Convex problems under Rayleigh, Nakagami, and log-normal</p>
    <p>fading.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
