<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Are FPGAs Suitable For Edge Computing?</p>
    <p>Saman Biookaghazadeh, Ming Zhao, Fengbo Ren Arizona State University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Future of Internet-of-Things (IoT) by 2020  IoT will connect 50 billion devices  It is expected to generate 400 Zetta Bytes of data</p>
    <p>annually  Cloud infrastructure is falling short!</p>
    <p>Cannot handle such large and distributed amount of data  Mainly designed for time-insensitive applications, end</p>
    <p>users, processing batches of data  Solution?</p>
    <p>A new paradigm called edge computing  Serve time-sensitive IoT applications, and support various</p>
    <p>streaming I/O channels</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations of Existing Solutions</p>
    <p>How about existing cloud and edge servers?  Simply a miniature version of cloud servers  Architectured for using CPUs and GPUs  For batches of data, power hungry, and unpredictable</p>
    <p>performance</p>
    <p>What do we need?  New hardware for the new paradigm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background of FPGA</p>
    <p>Reconfigurable Farm of logic  Opportunity to program using C, C++ and OpenCL  Inherently efficient for streaming applications  Suitable for a wide range of applications</p>
    <p>Spatial parallelism, parallelism in space  Temporal parallelism, parallelism in time</p>
    <p>Power Efficient  Improve thermal stability and reduce cooling cost</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivations for FPGA-based Edge Computing</p>
    <p>Edge computings most important requirements  Predictable performance for IoT service providers  Operational in locations with limited power supply  Accelerate a wide variety of service applications</p>
    <p>We study suitability of FPGAs with respect to:  Sensitivity of processing throughput to the workload size  Adaptiveness to algorithm concurrency and dependency  Energy efficiency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Testbench</p>
    <p>Nallatech 385A (Intel Arria A10)</p>
    <p>Intel Xeon E5-1275</p>
    <p>Tesla K40m</p>
    <p>Intel Xeon E5-2637</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sensitivity to Workload Size</p>
    <p>Two stage matrix multiplication (A x B x C) as a benchmark  Widely used in linear algebraic algorithms</p>
    <p>32 x 32 matrices, with single-precision floating-point random numbers</p>
    <p>Varying batch size between 2 to 2048</p>
    <p>GPU</p>
    <p>FPGA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sensitivity to Workload Size</p>
    <p>FPGA reads input from the Ethernet I/O  GPU reads input from the card main memory  Unlike GPU, FPGA can provide consistent throughput</p>
    <p>By jointly exploiting spatial and temporal parallelism</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adaptiveness</p>
    <p>How well FPGAs and GPUs adapt to algorithm characteristics?  Data Dependency: Dependency across different iterations of a</p>
    <p>loop  Conditional Dependency: Dependency on conditional</p>
    <p>statements with each iteration of the loop  Benchmark</p>
    <p>Simple iterative block (for-loop)  Each iteration performs certain number of operations  Generic enough to model large set of computationally</p>
    <p>intensive applications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Dependency  Introducing dependency among different iterations  Varying the data dependency degree</p>
    <p>Changing the size of the group  GPUs performance closely depends on available data parallelism  FPGAs can exploit pipelining and execute iterations, regardless of</p>
    <p>dependency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conditional Dependency  Adding if-else statements into the loop  Each branch contains half of the operations  Varying number of operations in each if and else block  Different devices show different behaviours:</p>
    <p>GPU is highly sensitive to conditional statement  FPGA can utilize a look-up table</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Energy Efficiency</p>
    <p>Collecting energy consumption on both devices  Nvidia-smi on the GPU  Nallatech MMD Layer API on FPGA.</p>
    <p>Varying workload input size</p>
    <p>Matrix Multiplication Data Dependency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions and Future Works</p>
    <p>FPGAs can handle unique edge requirements  FPGA can be considered as a core computational accelerator</p>
    <p>in the emerging edge systems  FPGAs can provide predictive throughput, Algorithm</p>
    <p>adaptiveness, and energy-efficiency</p>
    <p>Future Directions?  Studying edge workloads  Studying other algorithms characteristics and suitability of</p>
    <p>different hardware architectures  Scalability (Up &amp; Out) of FPGAs compared to GPUs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgement</p>
    <p>Sponsors  National Science Foundation (CNS-1629888)</p>
    <p>Intel FPGA university program</p>
    <p>VISA LAB: http://visa.lab.asu.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Question?</p>
    <p>Supported by NSF CNS-1629888 and Intel FPGA University Program</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
