<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Industrial Robot System Based on Edge Computing: An Early Experience</p>
    <p>Youdong Chen1, Qiangguo Feng1 and Weisong Shi2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>mechanical engineering, sensor, control theory and so on. It is widely used in automobile manufacturing, welding, assembly, spray painting, polishing, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Teaching programming: tedious and inefficient  Offline programming: large computation and no real</p>
    <p>time  Cloud robot: strong capability but heavy network</p>
    <p>traffics and long time-delay</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System architecture: Industrial robot system based on edge computing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud layer</p>
    <p>Service managementProvide all kinds of processes and algorithms to the</p>
    <p>robot in the form of service.</p>
    <p>Resource monitorMonitor the energy consumption, memory and network</p>
    <p>status of cloud and edge nodes.</p>
    <p>Craft database Robot process technology(assembly,welding,etc.)</p>
    <p>Motion databaseThe realization of services(simulation, data fitting,</p>
    <p>path planning, etc.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Edge layer</p>
    <p>Device interfaceIntegrated devices interfaces API.</p>
    <p>Data filterPre-processing raw data from the field.</p>
    <p>Workstation management Manage robotic workstation devices</p>
    <p>Why choose Edge?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Physical resource</p>
    <p>l Robot workstation</p>
    <p>Actuators: Robot, gantry frame, conveyors, AGV, etc</p>
    <p>Sensors: Industrial camera, laser sensor, smart meters, etc</p>
    <p>l Closed loop robot system</p>
    <p>Robot task is sent to workstation from the upper layer;</p>
    <p>Production process is measured via sensors and fed back to the upper layer.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Membrane water wall Membrane water wall is widely used in boiler industry. To fix and support</p>
    <p>refractory materials laid on membrane water wall, a large number of pins should be</p>
    <p>welded on the surface of membrane water wall.</p>
    <p>pin</p>
    <p>Steel tube</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current welding method: manual welding</p>
    <p>High labor intensity, eg: a 11m2m membrane water wall requires about 18000 pins</p>
    <p>Low efficiency</p>
    <p>Bad precision</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud: Alibaba Cloud</p>
    <p>Edge node: Local PC with 2 cores and 4G memories</p>
    <p>Workstation: LAN is set up to linking devices, each device is assigned a logical address</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AutoCAD drawing of the membrane water wall</p>
    <p>Parse the drawing and extract process information</p>
    <p>Read and parse the AutoCAD drawing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Welding technical requirements: Pins are welded vertically on the surface of the tube in a radial</p>
    <p>direction</p>
    <p>Robot path planning</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pose measurement: Deformations and warps may occur while the tube is being welded. We adopted a light section</p>
    <p>sensor to measure the profile of the steel tubes. And then we use the measurement results to compensate the errors.</p>
    <p>Pose measurement</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modeling: Robot modeling and kinematic analysis.</p>
    <p>Modeling and simulation</p>
    <p>Simulation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment: MH50II robot, LPS36HI light section sensor, membrane wall sample and a welding torch model</p>
    <p>Experiment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud-based approach: uploads all raw data to the cloud and executes all tasks on the cloud</p>
    <p>Cloud-edge hybrid approach: executes pose measurements on the edge node and executes the remaining tasks on the cloud</p>
    <p>Cloud-based Cloud-edge hybrid</p>
    <p>Path planning and simulation   Upload raw data</p>
    <p>Pose measurement   Upload filtered data -</p>
    <p>Transfer robot file back</p>
    <p>Table 1: The two approaches tasks</p>
    <p>We conducted four experiments. The number of times that sensors detected is 1, 5, 20, and 50, respectively. The sensor detected times are the identity of the data amount that the system deals with.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: All subtask execution time and total execution time. Red lines indicate the results of the cloud-based approach; blue lines indicate the results of the cloud-edge</p>
    <p>hybrid approach.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: cloud-edge hybrid approach saves network bandwidth by nearly three orders of magnitude in all four experiments.</p>
    <p>Number of times detected</p>
    <p>Bandwidth of cloudbased approach</p>
    <p>(Kb/s)</p>
    <p>Bandwidth of cloudedge hybrid</p>
    <p>approach (Kb/s)</p>
    <p>Saved bandwidth (Kb/s)</p>
    <p>Table 2: The two approaches occupied bandwidth.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Although the edge node data processing ability is inferior to the cloud server, the Cloud-edge hybrid approach has a better real-time performance than the cloud-based approach.</p>
    <p>Edge node pre-processing sensor data can save a lot of network bandwidth and significantly reduce data transmission time.</p>
    <p>Future work:</p>
    <p>Further expand and develop the system based on edge computing.</p>
    <p>Conduct more experiment in the robot workstation. Some progress has been made.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>THANKS</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
