<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>Mobile Edge Computing Platform Deployment in 4G LTE Networks: A Middlebox Approach</p>
    <p>Chi-Yu Li1, Hsueh-Yang Liu1, Po-Hao Huang1, Hsu-Tung Chien1, Guan-Hua Tu2, Pei-Yuan Hong1, Ying-Dar Lin1</p>
    <p>Taiwan</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l Introduction</p>
    <p>l Background and Related Work</p>
    <p>l Challenges and Design Ideas</p>
    <p>l Prototype and Evaluation</p>
    <p>l Conclusion</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l Emerging low-latency apps in cellular networks p E.g., C-V2X (Cellular Vehicle-to-Everything), Virtual Reality (VR), etc.</p>
    <p>l A key technology: Mobile Edge Computing (MEC) p Determined as a 5G feature by both ETSI and 3GPP p Providing a cloud computing platform at the network edge</p>
    <p>l MEC: shortening latency with two major merits p Short end-to-end distance</p>
    <p>n Small propagation delay n No bottleneck/congestion from the Internet</p>
    <p>p Offloading services from the cloud</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>C-V2X Apps</p>
    <p>VR Apps</p>
    <p>MEC Platform</p>
    <p>. . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l Control plane: UE  RAN  MME/HSS p Functions: mobility, security, resource allocation</p>
    <p>l User plane: UE  RAN  S-GW/P-GW p Routing data traffic between UE and Internet p Carried by GTP Tunnel</p>
    <p>n One tunnel is built for each UEs Internet traffic</p>
    <p>Background: 4G LTE Network</p>
    <p>S1 Interface</p>
    <p>UE (User Equipment)</p>
    <p>eNB (evolved Node B)</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>MME</p>
    <p>S-GW</p>
    <p>HSS</p>
    <p>P-GW</p>
    <p>Core Network</p>
    <p>GTP Tunnel</p>
    <p>Control plane</p>
    <p>User plane</p>
    <p>MME: Mobility Management Entity HSS: Home Subscriber Server S-GW: Serving Gateway P-GW: Packet Data Network Gateway GTP: GPRS Tunneling Protocol</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l ETSI standard[1]</p>
    <p>p Several options in LTE networks n Various components at the Edge</p>
    <p>p No concrete designs/implementations</p>
    <p>l Other research studies p Several Surveys [2] [3] [4] : No examination of the MEC deployment in 4G networks p Existing deployment solutions[5] [6]: Not standard-compliant</p>
    <p>n Modifications on the eNB or/and the core network</p>
    <p>Related Work: MEC Deployment</p>
    <p>UE eNB Internet</p>
    <p>Core Network</p>
    <p>MEC</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>S-GW MEC</p>
    <p>S-GW MECP-GW MME</p>
    <p>Our Solution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l Goal: low costs, high deployment incentives</p>
    <p>l Requirements p Standard-compliant</p>
    <p>p No modification requirements on eNB or/and core networks</p>
    <p>How to Deploy the MEC in LTE Networks?</p>
    <p>eNB Internet</p>
    <p>Core Network</p>
    <p>MEC</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>S-GW MEC</p>
    <p>S-GW MECP-GW MME</p>
    <p>UE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l MEC platform sits on the S1 interface p Some traffic is routed to the MEC</p>
    <p>p The others pass through the MEC to reach the Internet</p>
    <p>l A middlebox approach: transparent to the network architecture</p>
    <p>Key Idea: MEC Deployment as a Middlebox</p>
    <p>UE eNB Internet</p>
    <p>Core Network</p>
    <p>MEC</p>
    <p>S1 Interface</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l I. How to intercept and forward GTP packets? l II. How to redirect data traffic to the MEC? l III. How to enable MEC apps to serve GTP packets? l IV. How to identify the GTP tunnel associated with each packet?</p>
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>UE eNB Internet</p>
    <p>Core Network</p>
    <p>GTP TunnelGTP Packets</p>
    <p>MEC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l MEC divides S1 into two network segments l No ARP response: eNB/S-GW doesnt know where to send packets</p>
    <p>I. How to intercept and forward GTP packets?</p>
    <p>eNB 172.17.1.1</p>
    <p>S-GW 172.17.100.254</p>
    <p>No response No response</p>
    <p>MEC platform 172.17.1.2</p>
    <p>ARP request ARP request S1</p>
    <p>Target IP =172.17.1.1 Target MAC=?</p>
    <p>Target IP =172.17.100.254 Target MAC=?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l MEC replies ARP requests p To eNB: MECs MAC address  S-GWs IP p To S-GW: MECs MAC address  eNBs IP</p>
    <p>Solution: Proxy ARP</p>
    <p>eNB 172.17.1.1</p>
    <p>S-GW 172.17.100.254</p>
    <p>MEC platform 172.17.1.2</p>
    <p>ARP request ARP request S1</p>
    <p>Target IP =172.17.1.1 Target MAC=?</p>
    <p>Target IP =172.17.100.254 Target MAC=?</p>
    <p>Response:MAC+,- Response:MAC+,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l MEC needs to redirect UEs data packets to its app servers p Instead of forwarding them to the Internet</p>
    <p>l Keep both apps and their servers work as usual</p>
    <p>II. How to redirect data traffic to MEC?</p>
    <p>UE eNB Internet</p>
    <p>MEC platform</p>
    <p>APPs</p>
    <p>Core Network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l Intercept all DNS packets from UE l Return local IP addresses in response to apps domain names</p>
    <p>Solution: Traffic Redirection via DNS</p>
    <p>UE eNB Internet</p>
    <p>MEC platform</p>
    <p>APPs</p>
    <p>Core NetworkDNS server</p>
    <p>DNS query: www.youtube.com</p>
    <p>DNS response: 10.0.0.2</p>
    <p>IP: 10.0.0.2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>MEC platform</p>
    <p>APPs</p>
    <p>l IP packets are carried by GTP tunnels l App servers dont recognize GTP packets</p>
    <p>III. How to enable APPs to serve GTP packets?</p>
    <p>GTPHDR IPHDR</p>
    <p>UE</p>
    <p>Payload</p>
    <p>GTPHDR IPHDR Payload</p>
    <p>Unrecognized Format</p>
    <p>Discarded</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l Strip off GTP headers before redirecting l Maintain a dynamic table for each UEs tunnel l Encapsulate GTP headers back after app server respond</p>
    <p>Solution: GTP header repackaging</p>
    <p>MEC platform</p>
    <p>DNS server</p>
    <p>GTPHDR IPHDR</p>
    <p>Header Repackaging</p>
    <p>uplink</p>
    <p>IPHDR</p>
    <p>UE IP: E</p>
    <p>GTPHDR IPHDR</p>
    <p>downlinkTEID: PQ</p>
    <p>Uplink tunnel</p>
    <p>Downlink tunnel</p>
    <p>UE IP TEID A XY</p>
    <p>E PQ</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l GTP tunnels are dynamically built for each UE l Encapsulating requires the correct mapping between IP and tunnel ID</p>
    <p>IV. How to identify tunnels for each UE</p>
    <p>UE IP: A</p>
    <p>UE IP: B</p>
    <p>UE IP: E MEC platform</p>
    <p>DNS server</p>
    <p>Header Repackaging</p>
    <p>TEID: MN</p>
    <p>TEID: XY</p>
    <p>TEID: PQ</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>Stateful tracking module</p>
    <p>l UE info are maintained in the MME l Prevent changes to the CN: communication between MEC and MME</p>
    <p>is prohibited l Do stateful tracking when there is outgoing traffic instead</p>
    <p>Solution: Stateful tracking of GTP tunnels</p>
    <p>MME HSS</p>
    <p>SGW PGW</p>
    <p>UE IP: E eNB Core Network</p>
    <p>Interface?</p>
    <p>Maintain mapping between UE IP &amp; TEID</p>
    <p>TEID: PQ</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>UE IP TEID A XY   E PQ</p>
    <p>MEC platform</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>MEC Platform Architecture</p>
    <p>MEC Platform</p>
    <p>S1 Interface</p>
    <p>APP1 Server</p>
    <p>eNB Core</p>
    <p>APP2 Server</p>
    <p>DNS Server</p>
    <p>GTP Unpacking and Repackaging</p>
    <p>Platform Manager</p>
    <p>Stateful Tracking</p>
    <p>New Data Path</p>
    <p>Signaling Path</p>
    <p>APP Layer</p>
    <p>Packets Forwarding</p>
    <p>Default GTP Tunnels</p>
    <p>Proxy ARP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l Prototype with OpenAirInterface (OAI) cellular platform</p>
    <p>Prototype</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l Compare webpage response (CNN news) between cloned web server on MEC platform and on Internet p Results in different percentile(5%, 50%, 95%) p Overall latency vs. radio-link-omitted latency</p>
    <p>Evaluation  Experiment #1</p>
    <p>DNS query Webpage service</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l Video streaming from MEC and from Google Cloud Platform(GCP) p Using VLC media player</p>
    <p>l Experiment settings: p RTP protocol p Streaming settings</p>
    <p>n Video: H264 codec, 24fps, 720p quality n Audio: MPEG codec, 128K bitrate</p>
    <p>Evaluation - Experiment #2 (1/2)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l Results: pStream 1: 512K video bitrate; Stream 2: 1M video bitrate pPacket jitter in different percentile</p>
    <p>Evaluation - Experiment #2 (2/2)</p>
    <p>Video stream Audio stream</p>
    <p>Stream1 Stream2 Stream1 Stream2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l Scalability Challenges p Computing power demand for GTP packets p Context management for different eNBs</p>
    <p>l Security and Billing p Third party content provider could imply malicious applications p Traffic does not travel through CN so billing and access control is necessary</p>
    <p>l Mobility Management pMigrate application states and UE context during handover</p>
    <p>Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>Enabled MEC with a middlebox approach in Cellular Networks  A Standard compliant solution</p>
    <p>Effectiveness of latency reduction  Can be a reference design of the 5G MEC</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l A middlebox approach of MEC deployment in Cellular Networks p Standard-compliant, low costs, high deployment incentives</p>
    <p>l Open issues p Scalability challenges</p>
    <p>p Multiple MEC apps and their state transfers</p>
    <p>p Mobility management</p>
    <p>p Security and billing</p>
    <p>p Fault tolerance</p>
    <p>l Limitation: S1 interface cannot be confidentially protected p 3GPP standard: this confidentiality protection is vendor-specific p It is usually disabled by default</p>
    <p>Concluding Remarks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>Thank you for your attention Questions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>l Enabling confidentiality protection on S1 interface is based on the operators choice</p>
    <p>l In practice, S-GW and eNB are usually placed in physically secured environment l If ciphering function is enabled, operators need to allow MEC to acquire the</p>
    <p>security context of the S1 interface</p>
    <p>What if confidentiality protection is enabled on S1 interface?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX HotEdge 2018</p>
    <p>[1] ETSI white paper 24: MEC deployment in 4G, 5G networks [2] AHMED, A., AND AHMED, E. A Survey on Mobile Edge Computing. In International Conference on Intelligent Systems and Control (ISCO) (2016), IEEE. [3] TALEB, T., SAMDANIS, K., AND MADA, B. On Multi-Access Edge Computing: A Survey of the Emerging 5G Network Edge Cloud Architecture and Orchestration. IEEE Communications Surveys and Tutorials 19, 3 (2017), 16571681. [4] MACH, P.,AND BECVAR, Z. Mobile Edge Computing: A Survey on Architecture and Computation Offloading. IEEE Communications Surveys and Tutorials 19, 3 (2017), 16281656. [5] CHANG, C.-Y., ALEXANDRIS, K., NIKAEIN, N., KATSALIS, K., AND SPYROPOULOS, T. MEC Architectural Implications for LTE/LTE-A Networks. In Proceedings of the Workshop on Mobility in the Evolving Internet Architecture(MobiArch)(2016), ACM. [6] HUANG, S.-C., CHEN, B.-L., LUO, Y.-C., CHUNG, Y.-C., AND CHOU, J. Application-aware Traffic Redirection: A Mobile Edge Computing Implementation toward Future 5G Networks. In International Symposium on Cloud and Service Computing(SC2) (2017), IEEE.</p>
    <p>Reference</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
