<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
    <p>A Privacy-Preserving Deep Learning</p>
    <p>Approach for Face Recognition with</p>
    <p>Edge Computing Yunlong Mao1, Shanhe Yi2, Qun Li2, Jinghao Feng1, Fengyuan Xu1, Sheng Zhong1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline1 Face Recognition with Deep LearningIntroduction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
    <p>Face Recognition</p>
    <p>with Deep Learning</p>
    <p>Introduction 01</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
    <p>Smart devices with multiple sensors have improved peoples daily life significantly,</p>
    <p>such as Smart Phone, Smart Glasses and Smart Watch.</p>
    <p>Deep neural networks are applied to various fields. Many successful deep neural</p>
    <p>networks are changing our life. Such as YOLO [1], VGGFace [2] and Cancer</p>
    <p>Detection [8].</p>
    <p>Plentiful sensor data has changed users role from data consumer to data producer.</p>
    <p>How can smart device users benefit from deep learning based face recognition</p>
    <p>with their massive private data?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
    <p>Solution #1</p>
    <p>Any user who has interests in deep learning based face</p>
    <p>recognition should upload all private data to a central</p>
    <p>server (or cluster) which has enough computing power to</p>
    <p>train a deep neural network based classification model.</p>
    <p>Solution #2</p>
    <p>Any user who has interests in deep learning based face</p>
    <p>recognition should perform collaborative training with a</p>
    <p>parameter server in charge of parameters aggregation.</p>
    <p>Many attentions have been attracted by this solution, e.g. [1-3].</p>
    <p>ACM SIGSAC Conference on Computer and Communications Security. ACM, 2017</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
    <p>Motivation:</p>
    <p>Existing solutions have serious privacy and resource issues. Users private data will be violated seriously if the central</p>
    <p>server is untrusted.</p>
    <p>Smart device users are holding plentiful data which is very valuable for deep learning models.</p>
    <p>Users should outsource heavy computing task to an edge server to avoid intensive computing.</p>
    <p>However, the edge server could be untrusted, users privacy may be violated.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
    <p>Privacy Threat Model</p>
    <p>System Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
    <p>VGG-Face Network [1]</p>
    <p>Edge Server</p>
    <p>Client-server Model</p>
    <p>Client</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
    <p>Privacy Leakage Threat</p>
    <p>The edge server is assumed to be honest-but-curious.</p>
    <p>The edge server can peek at clients training data.</p>
    <p>The adversary we deal against will be untrusted edge server.</p>
    <p>The adversary can launch membership inference attack based on models parameters [1-2].</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
    <p>Our DP-A Algorithm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
    <p>To prevent the adversary from peeking at training data, we partition original DNN into two parts.</p>
    <p>The first part contains a small portion of the network, which pre-processes raw input data.</p>
    <p>The second part containing the rest of the network will be deployed on the edge server.</p>
    <p>To defend against inference attack based on parameters, differential privacy will be applied.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
    <p>output activations.</p>
    <p>privacy loss budget.</p>
    <p>construct differentially private activations.</p>
    <p>DP-A Algorithm</p>
    <p>We have proved that parameters will be differentially</p>
    <p>private if activations in each iteration received from the</p>
    <p>client are differentially private.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
    <p>We use VGG-Face network and Labeled Faces in the Wild (LFW) dataset.</p>
    <p>The network is partitioned at the first convolutional layer.</p>
    <p>Training results of accuracy and loss with regards to different privacy budget are shown in the figures.</p>
    <p>The smaller epsilon is, the more privacy will be preserved.</p>
    <p>Mobile client: Huawei Nexus 6P phone (2GHz Qualcomm Snapdragon 810 processor)</p>
    <p>Edge server: AWS based edge server.</p>
    <p>A batch of training samples from LFW can be loaded on the phone under 0.4s when batch size is 8.</p>
    <p>Forward pass for the batch will be done under 0.6s. Backward pass will cost less than 0.2s per sample.</p>
    <p>The allocated mobile memory usage will be under 500MB for processing a batch of samples. When the mobile phone is</p>
    <p>processing the first convolutional layer, battery will be consumed under 3.5mAh per minute for the batch.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>i) what kind of</p>
    <p>feedback you are</p>
    <p>looking to receive</p>
    <p>Any helpful idea.</p>
    <p>Which part should be</p>
    <p>improved.</p>
    <p>ii) the controversial</p>
    <p>points of the paper</p>
    <p>Resource consumption</p>
    <p>for device user is high.</p>
    <p>iii) the open issues</p>
    <p>the paper does not</p>
    <p>address</p>
    <p>How to select the</p>
    <p>optimal partitioning</p>
    <p>layer.</p>
    <p>Whether our method is</p>
    <p>capable of training</p>
    <p>other deep neural</p>
    <p>networks.</p>
    <p>iv) under what</p>
    <p>circumstances the</p>
    <p>whole idea might</p>
    <p>fall apart.</p>
    <p>Unknown for now.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing 2018</p>
    <p>THANK YOU</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
