<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Toward Optimal Performance with Network Assisted TCP at Mobile Edge</p>
    <p>Soheil Abbasloo, Yang Xu, H. Jonathon Chao, Hang Shi, Ulas C. Kozat, Yinghua Ye</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Statement</p>
    <p>TCP performs poorly in cellular networks mainly because of two fundamental issues:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TCP: Jack of all trades, master of none!</p>
    <p>Cellular networks differ significantly from their general wired counterparts, which impacts the performance of a TCP designed as a general solution:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distributed Measurement Paradox</p>
    <p>It is impossible to create a distributed algorithm that converges to the point where (any form of)  = '()*+,(-+.</p>
    <p>/0123 is maximized (Jaffe. 1981).</p>
    <p>Intuition:  A Measurement Paradox!  Minimum delay is visible in Area 1  But maximum bandwidth is visible in Area 2!</p>
    <p>In-Flight packetsBDP D</p>
    <p>el ay</p>
    <p>D el</p>
    <p>iv er</p>
    <p>y Ra</p>
    <p>te</p>
    <p>Problem becomes even worse when link bandwidth is not a flat and stable one!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of the solution</p>
    <p>control  Servers are located very close to the RAN  Single authority manages the network and servers,</p>
    <p>The wireless scheduler (at BTS) knows per-user quality of channel, queue occupancy, etc. in a fine-grain timescale (1ms timeframes)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network-Assisted TCP</p>
    <p>UE</p>
    <p>NetAssist 1 Per-User Info.</p>
    <p>Measurement</p>
    <p>E-GW</p>
    <p>MEC</p>
    <p>Edge Server</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two versions: a clean-slate &amp; a backward-compatible</p>
    <p>NATCP:  A clean-slate design replacing the TCP at end-hosts  Periodically, receives feedback information (avg.  and ):</p>
    <p>=   )2.0 =</p>
    <p>NACubic:  A backward compatible design  Underlying TCP still calculates the   The feedback from NetAssist is used to cap the values of</p>
    <p>H2I =    = (H2I,)  )2.0 =  7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overall results (averaged over more than 15 cellular traces)</p>
    <p>{ =</p>
    <p>}</p>
    <p>Better Scheme</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  The controversial points of the paper  Exploring new design space and philosophy for designing TCP for MobileEdge</p>
    <p>What kind of feedback you are looking to receive  Any feedback on the implementation of NATCP!</p>
    <p>Under what circumstances the whole idea might fall apart  If components dealing with the measurements are providing wrong feedback</p>
    <p>The open issues the paper does not address  How to provide security for communications among different entities?  The standardized/detailed protocols for communication among various</p>
    <p>component 9</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BKP Slides</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NATCP: Fairness</p>
    <p>In a general network number of competing flows is not known, but this is not the case in cellular networks!  Per-User buffers at BTS:  Number of competing flows</p>
    <p>is known by client!  Inter-Fairness  Wireless scheduler handles it</p>
    <p>Intra-Fairness  The client sends fairness info.</p>
    <p>to the server</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Do we really need the delay feedback?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In-Band vs. Out-of-Band Signaling</p>
    <p>Comparison between In-Band (IB) and Out-of-Band (OoB) signaling when feedback only consists of Bw and the time it has both Bw &amp; delay (NATCP):</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
