<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Home, SafeHome: Ensuring a Safe and Reliable Home Using</p>
    <p>the Edge Shegufta Ahsan*, Rui Yang*, Shadi Noghabi**,</p>
    <p>Indranil (Indy) Gupta*</p>
    <p>Usenix HotEdge 2019</p>
    <p>http://dprg.cs.uiuc.edu/ :: http://indy.cs.illinois.edu</p>
    <p>(* Univ. of Illinois Urbana-Champaign, ** Microsoft Research)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Smart Homes  All media are extensions of some human faculty -- psychic or physical.</p>
    <p>-- Marshall McLuhan.</p>
    <p>Not true in smart homes/buildings today!</p>
    <p>correctness issues</p>
    <p>House LOCKED =&gt; Security cameras ON</p>
    <p>ATMOST (1)(South Lawn Sprinklers, North Lawn Sprinklers)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The State Today</p>
    <p>Routines (sequences of commands) that are concurrent can conflict with each other, creating inconsistent outcomes and unsafe states  Humans cannot reason about concurrency at millisecond-level</p>
    <p>Erroneous routines may violate Safety Properties  Switch OFF Exhaust Fan; Switch ON Stove;</p>
    <p>Failures of devices have unintended consequences and result in inconsistent outcomes and unsafe states</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two Concurrent Routines</p>
    <p>Routines R1 and R2 run on (X-axis) TP-Link HS105 smart plugs. R1 turns on all lights, then R2 turns off all lights. Times above (ms) show time gap from R1 start to R2 start.</p>
    <p>SafeHomes goal: Bring all lines down to horizontal axisR2 starts soon after R1</p>
    <p>More final states are inconsistent Worse with longer routines</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SafeHome</p>
    <p>A software-defined management approach for smart home management.</p>
    <p>Features:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ASID Challenges</p>
    <p>A: SafeHome-Atomicity. Execution of a routine is atomic and exactly-once.  When a routine finishes, either: a) all its commands have been executed successfully, or b)</p>
    <p>none of its commands have had an effect on the smart home.  Challenges: a) catching conflicts, b) aborting routines, c) undo-ing routines.</p>
    <p>S: SafeHome-Safety. User-specific Safety properties are satisfied at runtime.  Challenges: a) Safety properties span multiple devices, b) catching these at run-time.</p>
    <p>I: SafeHome-Isolation. Concurrent routines are isolated from interfering with each other at devices.  Challenges: If routines interfere, SafeHome must ensure the execution is serially equivalent.</p>
    <p>D: SafeHome-Durability. A routine that completes successfully cannot be undone (except by another subsequent routine).  Challenges: No undo after commit point of routine.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Safety Properties: SafeHomes Grammar</p>
    <p>This is a first-cut grammar. Surprisingly, captures a wide swathe of safety specifications.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Undesirable State Desirable Safety Property</p>
    <p>Routine R1 turns on both stove and exhaust-fan, but then Routine R2 turns off exhaust-fan.</p>
    <p>IF (stove==ON) THEN (exhaust-fan==ON)</p>
    <p>Routine R1 opens a window, Routine R2 turns on airconditioner.</p>
    <p>IF (air-cond==ON) THEN (windows==CLOSED)</p>
    <p>Power overload due to multiple heavy devices. IF (dishwasher==on) THEN ATMOST(1) (washingmachine==ON, dryer==ON)</p>
    <p>Turning on all sprinklers around the house leads to insufficient water pressure.</p>
    <p>ATMOST(1) (Northeast-sprinkler=ON,</p>
    <p>Northwest-sprinkler=ON,</p>
    <p>Southeast-sprinkler=ON)</p>
    <p>User accidentally leaves garage-door open overnight. IF (garage-door.OPEN &gt; `n' hours) THEN (garage-door==CLOSE)</p>
    <p>Safety Specifications: Examples</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Failures and Safety</p>
    <p>Safety properties are impossible to guarantee always  Stove and Exhaust fan are both ON  Exhaust fan fails</p>
    <p>SafeHome ensures safety properties are invalid for at most a tolerance window (after a failure)  Could be set by user or physical constraints (e.g., reboot time)</p>
    <p>SafeHome uses tolerance window to set timeout in its failure detector algorithm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Where it Really Gets Interesting (1/2) I. ASID@IoT Mechanisms can borrow heavily from ACID@Database mechanisms. But key differences:</p>
    <p>ASID@IoT optimizes latency and abort rate, while ACID@DB optimizes throughput and abort rate.</p>
    <p>Intermediate states in ASID@IoT are almost always visible to user (may not be in ACID)  Undo of routine needs to have consolidated action across affected devices</p>
    <p>Long-running routines exist in ASID@IoT (rarer in ACID)  Run North Sprinklers for 15 minutes; Run South Sprinklers for 20 minutes;</p>
    <p>Challenges: a) Interaction between long-running and short-running (instant) routines; b) Interaction among long-running routines.</p>
    <p>Human Interrupts, Exceptions, Pauses</p>
    <p>Concurrency Control: Optimistic vs. Pessmistic Approaches 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Where it Really Gets Interesting (2/2) II. Safety Checking can borrow from Static and Dynamic Type Checking in Compilers/Programming Languages. But:</p>
    <p>Dynamic checking need to deal with a) concurrent routines, b) failed devices that may or may not recover (optimistic abort vs. pessimistic abort)</p>
    <p>III. Interesting dilemmas  Goto Dilemma: Should the default state (after-failure reboot) for garage door</p>
    <p>be OPEN or CLOSED?  OPEN = Hello, Burglars!</p>
    <p>CLOSED = Door closes on a car underneath it.</p>
    <p>Also occur in self-driving cars (Tesla Model S fatality May 2016, Ohio)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Feedback/Controversial/Open Qs/Fall Apart  Latency</p>
    <p>Biggest need, and main reason for system to fall apart: its too slow!  DB ACID consistency literature: useful? How deep? (our focus: Latency)</p>
    <p>User involvement  UI: Need an easy UI for specifying safety properties, and for programming routines.  Is ASID behavior (esp. abort and undo) cumbersome to user?  Cannot (always) require human intervention. E.g., deadlocks, safety violations.</p>
    <p>Device Resources: SafeHome assumes no extra capability or memory on devices. With more capable devices:  More capable devices can be used for failure recovery when edge is down,</p>
    <p>eliminating cloud reliance.  Such smart devices can serve as failover for edge device (run SafeHome logic).</p>
    <p>ACID: Downsides?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SafeHome</p>
    <p>A software-defined management approach for smart home management.</p>
    <p>Features:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Backup Slides</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SafeHome Architecture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Term Definition</p>
    <p>device a smart home device with a set of potential states</p>
    <p>command a user/program triggered instruction that changes the state of an individual device</p>
    <p>routine a sequence of commands</p>
    <p>Safety properties guaranteed device behaviors that user expects from the smart home</p>
    <p>Definitions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A. Future of Health</p>
    <p>B. Future of Relationships</p>
    <p>C. Future of Employment (job finding, task matching, team making)</p>
    <p>J. Future of Programming</p>
    <p>D. Future of Transportation</p>
    <p>I. Future of Data Analytics</p>
    <p>K. Future of Research</p>
    <p>F. Future of Agriculture</p>
    <p>Future of PeoplePeople: Needs &amp; Wants</p>
    <p>Intelligent Infrastructures</p>
    <p>X. Internet &amp; Telecom</p>
    <p>I. Social Media</p>
    <p>III. IoT Smart cities, Smart vehicles, Smart*</p>
    <p>XI. Datacenters &amp; Clouds</p>
    <p>IV. Finance V. Energy Oil, Gas, Nuclear</p>
    <p>VII. Materials &amp; Manufacturing</p>
    <p>VI. Utilities</p>
    <p>VIII. Healthcare</p>
    <p>IX. Supply-Chain</p>
    <p>E. Future of News</p>
    <p>H. Future of Markets</p>
    <p>II. Intelligent Web</p>
    <p>L. Future of Peace</p>
    <p>XII. Defense</p>
    <p>G. Future of Communities</p>
    <p>Systems Researchers Need to do this more!</p>
    <p>Systems Researchers Do These Very well!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
