<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SMC: Smart Media Compression for Edge Storage Offloading</p>
    <p>Ali Elgazar Mohammad Aazam Khaled A. Harras</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem description (Files are too large)</p>
    <p>Rising media technologies and online</p>
    <p>presence results in large media files</p>
    <p>occupying large amounts of space on</p>
    <p>our device.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem description (Storage is too expensive)</p>
    <p>Device storage is limited and higher</p>
    <p>storage capacity devices end up costing</p>
    <p>the user significantly more than what</p>
    <p>they would otherwise have to pay!</p>
    <p>Or the user can rent storage on a cloud</p>
    <p>for 9.99$ a month!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem description (Cloud is compromised)</p>
    <p>Recent hackings of different cloud</p>
    <p>storage solutions lead to growing</p>
    <p>concerns over privacy and cloud</p>
    <p>security.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem description (Network infrastructure)</p>
    <p>With low bandwidths/intermittent</p>
    <p>connections, offloading large quantities</p>
    <p>of files to centralized clouds becomes</p>
    <p>infeasible.</p>
    <p>Distributed Edge Clouds (DECs),</p>
    <p>however, rely on their distributed nature</p>
    <p>to combat privacy/security concerns,</p>
    <p>and are typically equipped for areas with</p>
    <p>challenged networks. But...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem description (Energy use in compression)</p>
    <p>DECs lack optimizations based on</p>
    <p>compression. Compression is energy</p>
    <p>intensive on user mobile devices, as</p>
    <p>such, services tend to avoid</p>
    <p>compressing large volumes of media</p>
    <p>files, when offloading data.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SMC is an energy efficient compression and offloading mechanism, which</p>
    <p>is integratable with any DEC. SMC determines the relevance of files to the</p>
    <p>user by examining the users file access patterns. SMC utilizes said</p>
    <p>relevance to automate offloading and compressing the users files.</p>
    <p>Proposed solution (Smart Media Compression SMC)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>By examining the users access patterns and classifying their files</p>
    <p>relevance, SMC provides three key benefits:</p>
    <p>Automating storage offload procedures.</p>
    <p>Reducing offloaded files through compression.</p>
    <p>Saving energy by selectively compressing only when</p>
    <p>necessary.</p>
    <p>Proposed solution (SMC benefits)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SMC operates over several steps:</p>
    <p>Classifying file relevance.</p>
    <p>Determining necessity of compression.</p>
    <p>Determining compression ratios.</p>
    <p>Solution Implementation (SMC operation)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SMC classifies files into three categories based on their</p>
    <p>relevance to the user:</p>
    <p>Unpopular.</p>
    <p>Popular.</p>
    <p>Semi-Popular.</p>
    <p>Solution Implementation (Classifying file relevance)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SMC augments a binary (popular/unpopular) algorithm called Pattern Based</p>
    <p>Popularity Assessment (PBPA). APBPA operates over several steps:</p>
    <p>Files not accessed recently (within a variable parameter) are considered</p>
    <p>stale and unpopular.</p>
    <p>The rest of the files are considered active files and the top accessed</p>
    <p>portions of said files are considered popular.</p>
    <p>Based on metrics established by PBPA, active files whose access</p>
    <p>patterns match the access patterns of popular files.</p>
    <p>The remaining active files are classified as semi-popular, based on</p>
    <p>temporal locality.</p>
    <p>Solution Implementation (Classifying file relevance)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Compression is only really required if there is</p>
    <p>a need to hold more files on the users</p>
    <p>device.</p>
    <p>This only occurs if the user requests an</p>
    <p>amount of storage offloaded that is greater</p>
    <p>than the amount of unpopular files.</p>
    <p>Solution Implementation (Determining necessity of compression)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The file compression ratio determines how much a media file will be</p>
    <p>compressed, and utilizes the following formulae.</p>
    <p>Solution Implementation (Determining compression ratios)</p>
    <p>Ratio if compressing only semi-popular.</p>
    <p>Ratio if compressing both popular and semi-popular</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We attach SMC to a recently developed DEC, EdgeStore (ES)[1].</p>
    <p>We evaluate SMC+ES vs ES using a simulated environment</p>
    <p>running on the One simulator.</p>
    <p>We utilize a set of real life mobile device file access traces to</p>
    <p>simulate file accesses, and offloading[2].</p>
    <p>Evaluation (Setup)</p>
    <p>[1] A. Elgazar, M. Aazam, and K. Harras, Edgestore: Leveraging edge devices for mobile storage offloading, (CloudCom) IEEE, 2018,</p>
    <p>pp. 5661.</p>
    <p>[2] R. Friedman and D. Sainz, File system usage in android mobile phones, in 9th SSC. ACM, 2016, p. 16</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Amount of storage offloaded: 20%, 50%, and 90%</p>
    <p>The platform used for offloading: EdgeStore Vs</p>
    <p>SMC+EdgeStore</p>
    <p>The environment in which the user resides: Metropolitan, Urban,</p>
    <p>Rural</p>
    <p>Evaluation (Parameter)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Delay on accessing files: The amount of time from when a user</p>
    <p>accesses a file, to when it opens up on their UI.</p>
    <p>Battery consumption: The average hourly battery consumption</p>
    <p>of each platform during the simulation.</p>
    <p>Evaluation (Metrics)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>On average, the user had 62%, 37%, and 4% unpopular, semi-popular, and popular files.</p>
    <p>Note that when we offload 50% or less of the users files, ES and SMC perform the same, as</p>
    <p>no compression takes place due to the compression checks implemented.</p>
    <p>In the metropolitan, urban, and rural environments, the average delay drops from 312ms to</p>
    <p>improvement in delays.</p>
    <p>Evaluation (results)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>When SMC checks are removed, we can see that theres almost no improvement in file</p>
    <p>access delays in the rural environment.</p>
    <p>Evaluation (Removing the SMC checks)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The average hourly energy consumption in all simulations for ES, SMC, and USMC is1415,</p>
    <p>Devices running ES, SMC, and USMC ran out of battery every 33, 28, and 19 hours</p>
    <p>respectively on average.</p>
    <p>While SMC costs an additional 14%of energy consumption, it prevents an additional 43%</p>
    <p>energy consumption through its smart checks.</p>
    <p>Evaluation (Impact on battery)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Compressing the users media files can be utilized to not just lower</p>
    <p>network traffic, but also to dramatically enhance the average access</p>
    <p>time by retaining more files on the users device.</p>
    <p>We can determine and predict the relevance of files to the user in</p>
    <p>order to leverage such compression systems appropriately.</p>
    <p>Areas with challenged networks benefit the most from such</p>
    <p>systems.</p>
    <p>Large scale compression can be energy efficient when done</p>
    <p>selectively based on the users needs and access patterns.</p>
    <p>Conclusion (Overall message)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Wed like some feedback on our choice of attaching SMC to DECs instead of</p>
    <p>centralized clouds.</p>
    <p>A controversial point in this paper is that while we are providing a solution that</p>
    <p>reduces the potential energy consumption of compression, our solution still</p>
    <p>requires more energy consumption overall from any system it is attached to.</p>
    <p>In this paper, we dont examine or account for the networking conditions</p>
    <p>themselves when compressing files, this might lead to more optimal delays on</p>
    <p>accessing files depending on the environment.</p>
    <p>Our compression algorithm relies on accurate classification of the users file</p>
    <p>relevance. If such classification was inaccurate for any reason, not only would</p>
    <p>the idea fall apart, but it would completely backfire.</p>
    <p>Conclusion (Discussion topics)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We are here at the Carnegie Mellon Qatar Networking and Systems Lab</p>
    <p>have many interesting and ongoing projects! Check us out using the</p>
    <p>following code!</p>
    <p>Q&amp;A time! Thank you!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
