<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Impact of Linguistic Analysis on the Semantic Impact of Linguistic Analysis on the Semantic Graph Coverage and Learning of Document Graph Coverage and Learning of Document ExtractsExtracts</p>
    <p>Jurij LeskovecJurij Leskovec Carnegie Mellon Univ.Carnegie Mellon Univ. Pittsburgh, PAPittsburgh, PA</p>
    <p>Document SummarizationDocument Summarization</p>
    <p>AAAI ConferenceAAAI Conference, , PittsburghPittsburgh July 11, 2005July 11, 2005</p>
    <p>Marko GrobelnikMarko Grobelnik Jozef Stefan InstituteJozef Stefan Institute Ljubljana, Slovenia Ljubljana, Slovenia</p>
    <p>Natasa Milic-Natasa MilicFraylingFrayling Microsoft ResearchMicrosoft Research Cambridge, UKCambridge, UK</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem definitionProblem definition</p>
    <p>Produce a shorter version of the Produce a shorter version of the original document by original document by selecting selecting sentencessentences from the text from the text</p>
    <p>HypothesisHypothesis::</p>
    <p>Extracted summaries should capture prominent Extracted summaries should capture prominent concepts and relations in the text.concepts and relations in the text.</p>
    <p>Structure of the semantic graph of a document Structure of the semantic graph of a document could help identify the key concepts and could help identify the key concepts and relations for summarization.relations for summarization.</p>
    <p>Cracks Appear in U.N. Trade Embargo Against Iraq.</p>
    <p>Cracks appeared Tuesday in the U.N. trade embargo against Iraq as Saddam Hussein sought to circumvent the economic noose around his country. Japan, meanwhile, announced it would increase its aid to countries hardest hit by enforcing the sanctions. Hoping to defuse criticism that it is not doing its share to oppose Baghdad, Japan said up to $2 billion in aid may be sent to nations most affected by the U.N. embargo on Iraq. President Bush on Tuesday night promised a joint session of Congress and a nationwide radio and television audience that ``Saddam Hussein will fail'' to make his conquest of Kuwait permanent. ``America must stand up to aggression, and we will,'' said Bush, who added that the U.S. military may remain in the Saudi Arabian desert indefinitely. ``I cannot predict just how long it will take to convince Iraq to withdraw from Kuwait,'' Bush said. More than 150,000 U.S. troops have been sent to the Persian Gulf region to deter a possible Iraqi invasion of Saudi Arabia. Bush's aides said the president would follow his address to Congress with a televised message for the Iraqi people, declaring the world is united against their government's invasion of Kuwait. Saddam had offered Bush time on Iraqi TV. The Philippines and Namibia, the first of the developing nations to respond to an offer Monday by Saddam of free oil _ in exchange for sending their own tankers to get it _ said no to the Iraqi leader. Saddam's offer was seen as a none-too-subtle attempt to bypass the U.N. embargo, in effect since four days after Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait, by getting poor countries to dock their tankers in Iraq. But according to a State Department survey, Cuba and Romania have struck oil deals with Iraq and companies elsewhere are trying to continue trade with Baghdad, all in defiance of U.N. sanctions. Romania denies the allegation. The report, made available to The Associated Press, said some Eastern European countries also are trying to maintain their military sales to Iraq. A well-informed source in Tehran told The Associated Press that Iran has agreed to an Iraqi request to exchange food and medicine for up to 200,000 barrels of refined oil a day and cash payments. There was no official comment from Tehran or Baghdad on the reported food-for-oil deal. But the source, who requested anonymity, said the deal was struck during Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz's visit Sunday to Tehran, the first by a senior Iraqi official since the 1980-88 gulf war. After the visit, the two countries announced they would resume diplomatic relations. Well-informed oil industry sources in the region, contacted by The AP, said that although Iran is a major oil exporter itself, it currently has to import about 150,000 barrels of refined oil a day for domestic use because of damages to refineries in the gulf war. Along similar lines, ABC News reported that following Aziz's visit, Iraq is apparently prepared to give Iran all the oil it wants to make up for the damage Iraq inflicted on Iran during their conflict. Secretary of State James A. Baker III, meanwhile, met in Moscow with Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze, two days after the U.S.-Soviet summit that produced a joint demand that Iraq withdraw from Kuwait. During the summit, Bush encouraged Mikhail Gorbachev to withdraw 190 Soviet military specialists from Iraq, where they remain to fulfill contracts. Shevardnadze told the Soviet parliament Tuesday the specialists had not reneged on those contracts for fear it would jeopardize the 5,800,</p>
    <p>Cracks appeared in the U.N. trade embargo against Iraq.</p>
    <p>The State Department reports that Cuba and Romania have struck oil deals with Iraq as others attempt to trade with Baghdad in defiance of the sanctions.</p>
    <p>Iran has agreed to exchange food and medicine for Iraqi oil.</p>
    <p>Saddam has offered developing nations free oil if they send their tankers to pick it up.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ApproachApproach</p>
    <p>Create a graph that represents a Create a graph that represents a semantic structure of the semantic structure of the documentdocument</p>
    <p>Train a Train a machine learning modelmachine learning model for for selecting sentences which includes selecting sentences which includes the properties of the semantic the properties of the semantic graph.graph.</p>
    <p>Cracks Appear in U.N. Trade Embargo Against Iraq.</p>
    <p>Cracks appeared Tuesday in the U.N. trade embargo against Iraq as Saddam Hussein sought to circumvent the economic noose around his country. Japan, meanwhile, announced it would increase its aid to countries hardest hit by enforcing the sanctions. Hoping to defuse criticism that it is not doing its share to oppose Baghdad, Japan said up to $2 billion in aid may be sent to nations most affected by the U.N. embargo on Iraq. President Bush on Tuesday night promised a joint session of Congress and a nationwide radio and television audience that ``Saddam Hussein will fail'' to make his conquest of Kuwait permanent. ``America must stand up to aggression, and we will,'' said Bush, who added that the U.S. military may remain in the Saudi Arabian desert indefinitely. ``I cannot predict just how long it will take to convince Iraq to withdraw from Kuwait,'' Bush said. More than 150,000 U.S. troops have been sent to the Persian Gulf region to deter a possible Iraqi invasion of Saudi Arabia. Bush's aides said the president would follow his address to Congress with a televised message for the Iraqi people, declaring the world is united against their government's invasion of Kuwait. Saddam had offered Bush time on Iraqi TV. The Philippines and Namibia, the first of the developing nations to respond to an offer Monday by Saddam of free oil _ in exchange for sending their own tankers to get it _ said no to the Iraqi leader. Saddam's offer was seen as a none-too-subtle attempt to bypass the U.N. embargo, in effect since four days after Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait, by getting poor countries to dock their tankers in Iraq. But according to a State Department survey, Cuba and Romania have struck oil deals with Iraq and companies elsewhere are trying to continue trade with Baghdad, all in defiance of U.N. sanctions. Romania denies the allegation. The report, made available to The Associated Press, said some Eastern European countries also are trying to maintain their military sales to Iraq. A well-informed source in Tehran told The Associated Press that Iran has agreed to an Iraqi request to exchange food and medicine for up to 200,000 barrels of refined oil a day and cash payments. There was no official comment from Tehran or Baghdad on the reported food-for-oil deal. But the source, who requested anonymity, said the deal was struck during Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz's visit Sunday to Tehran, the first by a senior Iraqi official since the 1980-88 gulf war. After the visit, the two countries announced they would resume diplomatic relations. Well-informed oil industry sources in the region, contacted by The AP, said that although Iran is a major oil exporter itself, it currently has to import about 150,000 barrels of refined oil a day for domestic use because of damages to refineries in the gulf war. Along similar lines, ABC News reported that following Aziz's visit, Iraq is apparently prepared to give Iran all the oil it wants to make up for the damage Iraq inflicted on Iran during their conflict. Secretary of State James A. Baker III, meanwhile, met in Moscow with Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze, two days after the U.S.-Soviet summit that produced a joint demand that Iraq withdraw from Kuwait. During the summit, Bush encouraged Mikhail Gorbachev to withdraw 190 Soviet military specialists from Iraq, where they remain to fulfill contracts. Shevardnadze told the Soviet parliament Tuesday the specialists had not reneged on those contracts for fear it would jeopardize the 5,800,</p>
    <p>Cracks appeared in the U.N. trade embargo against Iraq.</p>
    <p>The State Department reports that Cuba and Romania have struck oil deals with Iraq as others attempt to trade with Baghdad in defiance of the sanctions.</p>
    <p>Iran has agreed to exchange food and medicine for Iraqi oil.</p>
    <p>Saddam has offered developing nations free oil if they send their tankers to pick it up.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Linguistic processing</p>
    <p>and construction</p>
    <p>of the semantic</p>
    <p>graph</p>
    <p>Sub-graph that characterizes extracted summaries</p>
    <p>Sentence extraction based on the extracted sub- graph</p>
    <p>Automatically generated document summary</p>
    <p>Cracks Appear in U.N. Trade Embargo Against Iraq.</p>
    <p>Cracks appeared Tuesday in the U.N. trade embargo against Iraq as Saddam Hussein sought to circumvent the economic noose around his country. Japan, meanwhile, announced it would increase its aid to countries hardest hit by enforcing the sanctions. Hoping to defuse criticism that it is not doing its share to oppose Baghdad, Japan said up to $2 billion in aid may be sent to nations most affected by the U.N. embargo on Iraq. President Bush on Tuesday night promised a joint session of Congress and a nationwide radio and television audience that ``Saddam Hussein will fail'' to make his conquest of Kuwait permanent. ``America must stand up to aggression, and we will,'' said Bush, who added that the U.S. military may remain in the Saudi Arabian desert indefinitely. ``I cannot predict just how long it will take to convince Iraq to withdraw from Kuwait,'' Bush said. More than 150,000 U.S. troops have been sent to the Persian Gulf region to deter a possible Iraqi invasion of Saudi Arabia. Bush's aides said the president would follow his address to Congress with a televised message for the Iraqi people, declaring the world is united against their government's invasion of Kuwait. Saddam had offered Bush time on Iraqi TV. The Philippines and Namibia, the first of the developing nations to respond to an offer Monday by Saddam of free oil _ in exchange for sending their own tankers to get it _ said no to the Iraqi leader. Saddam's offer was seen as a none-too-subtle attempt to bypass the U.N. embargo, in effect since four days after Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait, by getting poor countries to dock their tankers in Iraq. But according to a State Department survey, Cuba and Romania have struck oil deals with Iraq and companies elsewhere are trying to continue trade with Baghdad, all in defiance of U.N. sanctions. Romania denies the allegation. The report, made available to The Associated Press, said some Eastern European countries also are trying to maintain their military sales to Iraq. A well-informed source in Tehran told The Associated Press that Iran has agreed to an Iraqi request to exchange food and medicine for up to 200,000 barrels of refined oil a day and cash payments. There was no official comment from Tehran or Baghdad on the reported food-for-oil deal. But the source, who requested anonymity, said the deal was struck during Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz's visit Sunday to Tehran, the first by a senior Iraqi official since the 1980-88 gulf war. After the visit, the two countries announced they would resume diplomatic relations. Well-informed oil industry sources in the region, contacted by The AP, said that although Iran is a major oil exporter itself, it currently has to import about 150,000 barrels of refined oil a day for domestic use because of damages to refineries in the gulf war. Along similar lines, ABC News reported that following Aziz's visit, Iraq is apparently prepared to give Iran all the oil it wants to make up for the damage Iraq inflicted on Iran during their conflict. Secretary of State James A. Baker III, meanwhile, met in Moscow with Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze, two days after the U.S.-Soviet summit that produced a joint demand that Iraq withdraw from Kuwait. During the summit, Bush encouraged Mikhail Gorbachev to withdraw 190 Soviet military specialists from Iraq, where they remain to fulfill contracts. Shevardnadze told the Soviet parliament Tuesday the specialists had not reneged on those contracts for fear it would jeopardize the 5,800,</p>
    <p>Original document</p>
    <p>Cracks appeared in the U.N. trade embargo against Iraq.</p>
    <p>The State Department reports that Cuba and Romania have struck oil deals with Iraq as others attempt to trade with Baghdad in defiance of the sanctions.</p>
    <p>Iran has agreed to exchange food and medicine for Iraqi oil.</p>
    <p>Saddam has offered developing nations free oil if they send their tankers to pick it up.</p>
    <p>Semantic graph of the</p>
    <p>original document</p>
    <p>Learn the sub-graph selection model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research QuestionsResearch Questions</p>
    <p>How do the properties of the semantic How do the properties of the semantic graph influence summarization? graph influence summarization?</p>
    <p>What are the important attributes for What are the important attributes for learning?learning?</p>
    <p>What role does linguistic analysis play What role does linguistic analysis play in the summarization procedure?in the summarization procedure?</p>
    <p>Can we relax the complexity of Can we relax the complexity of linguistic analysis?linguistic analysis?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summarization Summarization Procedure Procedure</p>
    <p>George Bush linked with George Bush linked with Bush and PresidentBush and President</p>
    <p>Replace pronoun references Replace pronoun references to the objects by their to the objects by their name (for he, she, they, ) name (for he, she, they, )</p>
    <p>Tom went to town. In a bookstore he bought a large book.</p>
    <p>Tom went to town. In a bookstore he [Tom] bought a large book.</p>
    <p>Tom  go  town Tom  buy  book</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summarization Summarization Procedure Procedure</p>
    <p>George Bush linked with George Bush linked with Bush and PresidentBush and President</p>
    <p>Replace pronoun references Replace pronoun references to the objects by their to the objects by their name (for he, she, they, ) name (for he, she, they, )</p>
    <p>Tom went to town. In a bookstore he bought a large book.</p>
    <p>Tom went to town. In a bookstore he [Tom] bought a large book.</p>
    <p>Tom  go  town Tom  buy  book</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Syntactic parse trees are used Syntactic parse trees are used to generate different linguistic to generate different linguistic representations sentencesrepresentations sentences</p>
    <p>From Simple to Complex From Simple to Complex Linguistic AnalysisLinguistic Analysis</p>
    <p>Parse tree</p>
    <p>Logical form</p>
    <p>ANVANV: adjectives, nouns and verbs: adjectives, nouns and verbs  NPVNPV: head nouns and verbs: head nouns and verbs</p>
    <p>LFLF: logical form triples with syntactic and semantic : logical form triples with syntactic and semantic tagstags</p>
    <p>Example: Jure sent Marko a letter</p>
    <p>Triples: Jure  sent Marko Jure  sent  letter</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NodesNodes representation: representation:  Each element is a node. Each element is a node.  Links connect elements Links connect elements</p>
    <p>from the same triplefrom the same triple</p>
    <p>Creation of the Semantic Creation of the Semantic GraphsGraphs</p>
    <p>NamedLink NamedLink representation:representation:  Link is labeled with a verbLink is labeled with a verb</p>
    <p>Thoma s</p>
    <p>stand take</p>
    <p>Thoma s</p>
    <p>standtake</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Text coverage by the graphText coverage by the graph</p>
    <p>Relaxing linguistic processing increases the coverageRelaxing linguistic processing increases the coverage</p>
    <p>Semantic GraphSemantic Graph StructureStructure</p>
    <p>Covered Covered SummarySummary</p>
    <p>sentences [%]sentences [%]</p>
    <p>Covered non-Covered nonsummarysummary</p>
    <p>sentences [%]sentences [%] ANV with TriplesANV with Triples 93.493.4 86.686.6</p>
    <p>ANV with Triples + PairsANV with Triples + Pairs 98.698.6 94.694.6</p>
    <p>NPV with TriplesNPV with Triples 73.473.4 63.663.6</p>
    <p>NPV with Triples + PairsNPV with Triples + Pairs 94.094.0 83.383.3</p>
    <p>LF with TriplesLF with Triples 80.080.0 69.869.8</p>
    <p>LF with Triples + PairsLF with Triples + Pairs 90.690.6 87.487.4</p>
    <p>QUESTIONQUESTION</p>
    <p>What is the impact of the document representation and What is the impact of the document representation and coverage on summarization performance?coverage on summarization performance?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Learning sub-structure of the Learning sub-structure of the graphgraph</p>
    <p>LEARNING PROBLEM:LEARNING PROBLEM:</p>
    <p>Given a semantic graph, learn to Given a semantic graph, learn to select parts that describe the select parts that describe the document summary.document summary.</p>
    <p>Binary classification problem:Binary classification problem:  Positive examples are triples Positive examples are triples</p>
    <p>from the human selected from the human selected sentences sentences</p>
    <p>Negative examples are all other Negative examples are all other triplestriples</p>
    <p>Train the linear Support Vector Train the linear Support Vector classifier to detect positive triplesclassifier to detect positive triples</p>
    <p>To each triple from a document To each triple from a document graph the classifier assigns a graph the classifier assigns a confidence score that the triple confidence score that the triple belongs to a summary sentence. belongs to a summary sentence.</p>
    <p>Label nodes and links that correspond to the summary sentences</p>
    <p>Cracks Appear in U.N. Trade Embargo Against Iraq.</p>
    <p>Cracks appeared Tuesday in the U.N. trade embargo against Iraq as Saddam Hussein sought to circumvent the economic noose around his country. Japan, meanwhile, announced it would increase its aid to countries hardest hit by enforcing the sanctions. Hoping to defuse criticism that it is not doing its share to oppose Baghdad, Japan said up to $2 billion in aid may be sent to nations most affected by the U.N. embargo on Iraq. President Bush on Tuesday night promised a joint session of Congress and a nationwide radio and television audience that ``Saddam Hussein will fail'' to make his conquest of Kuwait permanent. ``America must stand up to aggression, and we will,'' said Bush, who added that the U.S. military may remain in the Saudi Arabian desert indefinitely. ``I cannot predict just how long it will take to convince Iraq to withdraw from Kuwait,'' Bush said. More than 150,000 U.S. troops have been sent to the Persian Gulf region to deter a possible Iraqi invasion of Saudi Arabia. Bush's aides said the president would follow his address to Congress with a televised message for the Iraqi people, declaring the world is united against their government's invasion of Kuwait. Saddam had offered Bush time on Iraqi TV. The Philippines and Namibia, the first of the developing nations to respond to an offer Monday by Saddam of free oil _ in exchange for sending their own tankers to get it _ said no to the Iraqi leader. Saddam's offer was seen as a none-too-subtle attempt to bypass the U.N. embargo, in effect since four days after Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait, by getting poor countries to dock their tankers in Iraq. But according to a State Department survey, Cuba and Romania have struck oil deals with Iraq and companies elsewhere are trying to continue trade with Baghdad, all in defiance of U.N. sanctions. Romania denies the allegation. The report, made available to The Associated Press, said some Eastern European countries also are trying to maintain their military sales to Iraq. A well-informed source in Tehran told The Associated Press that Iran has agreed to an Iraqi request to exchange food and medicine for up to 200,000 barrels of refined oil a day and cash payments. There was no official comment from Tehran or Baghdad on the reported food-for-oil deal. But the source, who requested anonymity, said the deal was struck during Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz's visit Sunday to Tehran, the first by a senior Iraqi official since the 1980-88 gulf war. After the visit, the two countries announced they would resume diplomatic relations. Well-informed oil industry sources in the region, contacted by The AP, said that although Iran is a major oil exporter itself, it currently has to import about 150,000 barrels of refined oil a day for domestic use because of damages to refineries in the gulf war. Along similar lines, ABC News reported that following Aziz's visit, Iraq is apparently prepared to give Iran all the oil it wants to make up for the damage Iraq inflicted on Iran during their conflict. Secretary of State James A. Baker III, meanwhile, met in Moscow with Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze, two days after the U.S.-Soviet summit that produced a joint demand that Iraq withdraw from Kuwait. During the summit, Bush encouraged Mikhail Gorbachev to withdraw 190 Soviet military specialists from Iraq, where they remain to fulfill contracts. Shevardnadze told the Soviet parliament Tuesday the specialists had not reneged on those contracts for fear it would jeopardize the 5,800,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Learned summary graph (1):Learned summary graph (1): War in KuwaitWar in Kuwait</p>
    <p>Nodes like Saddam Hussein, President Bush, gulf force are central in the graph</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Learned summary graph (2)Learned summary graph (2) Russian presidential electionRussian presidential election</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Learned summary graph (3):Learned summary graph (3): Bill Clinton giving a talkBill Clinton giving a talk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attributes of triples used in Attributes of triples used in learning learning  Positional informationPositional information</p>
    <p>Of the sentence from which the triple Of the sentence from which the triple was derived relative to the document was derived relative to the document texttext</p>
    <p>Of the triple relative to the beginning of Of the triple relative to the beginning of the sentencethe sentence</p>
    <p>NLPWin NLPWin linguistic attributeslinguistic attributes of the of the nodes in the triple:nodes in the triple:  18 syntactic attributes18 syntactic attributes</p>
    <p>100 semantic attributes100 semantic attributes</p>
    <p>14 14 graph attributesgraph attributes: PageRank, In/Out : PageRank, In/Out Degree, reachable neighbours, etc. Degree, reachable neighbours, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extract and evaluate Extract and evaluate summariessummaries</p>
    <p>SUMMARY EXTRACTION:SUMMARY EXTRACTION:  Score each sentence in the Score each sentence in the</p>
    <p>document as a sum of confidence document as a sum of confidence scores associated with triples from scores associated with triples from the sub-graph the sub-graph</p>
    <p>Include into the summary a pre-Include into the summary a predefined number of high scoring defined number of high scoring sentences from the documentsentences from the document</p>
    <p>EVALUATE SUMMARIESEVALUATE SUMMARIES  Report microaveraged precision, Report microaveraged precision,</p>
    <p>recall, and F1 on the sentence recall, and F1 on the sentence levellevel</p>
    <p>Calculate ROUGE score to Calculate ROUGE score to measure the coverage of conceptsmeasure the coverage of concepts</p>
    <p>Use node confidence</p>
    <p>scores to select sentences</p>
    <p>Cracks appeared in the U.N. trade embargo against Iraq.</p>
    <p>The State Department reports that Cuba and Romania have struck oil deals with Iraq as others attempt to trade with Baghdad in defiance of the sanctions.</p>
    <p>Iran has agreed to exchange food and medicine for Iraqi oil.</p>
    <p>Saddam has offered developing nations free oil if they send their tankers to pick it up.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DUC2002  Document Understanding DUC2002  Document Understanding ConferenceConference  300300 newspaper articles newspaper articles on on 30 30 different topics: different topics:</p>
    <p>people, natural disasters, events,  people, natural disasters, events,   Each topic has about 10 articlesEach topic has about 10 articles  147 of these articles have document extracts147 of these articles have document extracts</p>
    <p>CAST DataCAST Data  Subset of 89 documents with marked by a Subset of 89 documents with marked by a</p>
    <p>single annotatorsingle annotator  2 levels of granularity:2 levels of granularity:</p>
    <p>CAST-15%: 6 sentences marked as essentialCAST-15%: 6 sentences marked as essential  CAST-30%: additional 6 sentences marked as CAST-30%: additional 6 sentences marked as</p>
    <p>importantimportant</p>
    <p>DatasetsDatasets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Influence of Linguistic Influence of Linguistic AnalysisAnalysis</p>
    <p>The Logical Form The Logical Form representation representation yields highest F1 yields highest F1 of extracted of extracted sentencessentences</p>
    <p>Generally, SVM Generally, SVM learns well from all learns well from all levels of linguistic levels of linguistic processingprocessing</p>
    <p>By ROUGE the By ROUGE the simplest linguistic simplest linguistic analysis, with analysis, with highest coverage, highest coverage, performs bestperforms best</p>
    <p>DUC 2002DUC 2002</p>
    <p>Linguistic UnitsLinguistic Units Prec.Prec. RecallRecall F1F1 RougeRouge</p>
    <p>ANVANV 0.390.39 0.400.40 0.400.40 0.670.67 NPVNPV 0.370.37 0.390.39 0.380.38 0.650.65 LFLF 0.400.40 0.400.40 0.400.40 0.640.64</p>
    <p>CAST-30%CAST-30%</p>
    <p>Linguistic UnitsLinguistic Units Prec.Prec. RecallRecall F1F1 RougeRouge</p>
    <p>ANVANV 0.430.43 0.570.57 0.490.49 0.670.67 NPVNPV 0.410.41 0.660.66 0.500.50 0.630.63 LFLF 0.420.42 0.670.67 0.520.52 0.660.66</p>
    <p>Experiment set up:Experiment set up: Graph created using triples and pairs. Graph created using triples and pairs.</p>
    <p>Learning based on all the attributesLearning based on all the attributes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Semantic Graph Semantic Graph representationrepresentation</p>
    <p>Increasing the coverage of sentences by including node Increasing the coverage of sentences by including node pairs does not hurt the performancepairs does not hurt the performance</p>
    <p>The ROUGE score slightly improvesThe ROUGE score slightly improves</p>
    <p>DUC 2002DUC 2002</p>
    <p>Semantic StructureSemantic Structure Prec.Prec. RecallRecall F1F1 RougeRouge</p>
    <p>ANV with TriplesANV with Triples 0.310.31 0.620.62 0.410.41 0.670.67</p>
    <p>ANV with Triples+PairsANV with Triples+Pairs 0.300.30 0.630.63 0.410.41 0.660.66</p>
    <p>NPV with TriplesNPV with Triples 0.290.29 0.620.62 0.400.40 0.650.65</p>
    <p>NPV with Triples+PairsNPV with Triples+Pairs 0.300.30 0.640.64 0.410.41 0.670.67</p>
    <p>LF with TriplesLF with Triples 0.390.39 0.390.39 0.390.39 0.640.64</p>
    <p>LF with Triples+PairsLF with Triples+Pairs 0.380.38 0.390.39 0.380.38 0.650.65</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Influence of the attribute Influence of the attribute setssets  For all levels of linguistic processing, the performance For all levels of linguistic processing, the performance</p>
    <p>increases when we include graph attributesincreases when we include graph attributes</p>
    <p>Node AttributesNode Attributes Prec.Prec. RecallRecall F1F1 RougeRouge</p>
    <p>ANV: Pos + LingANV: Pos + Ling 0.270.27 0.580.58 0.370.37 0.650.65</p>
    <p>ANV: Pos + Ling + ANV: Pos + Ling + GraphGraph</p>
    <p>NPV: Pos + LingNPV: Pos + Ling 0.370.37 0.350.35 0.360.36 0.620.62</p>
    <p>NPV: Pos + Ling + NPV: Pos + Ling + GraphGraph</p>
    <p>LF: Pos + LingLF: Pos + Ling 0.260.26 0.610.61 0.360.36 0.620.62</p>
    <p>LF: Pos + Ling + GraphLF: Pos + Ling + Graph 0.400.40 0.400.40 0.400.40 0.640.64</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ConclusionConclusion</p>
    <p>We investigated the impact of the We investigated the impact of the level of level of linguistic analyseslinguistic analyses and and attributes of the attributes of the semantic graphsemantic graph on the SVM classifier for on the SVM classifier for summary extractionsummary extraction</p>
    <p>Relaxing the structure of individual Relaxing the structure of individual sentence representation yields a wider sentence representation yields a wider text coveragetext coverage</p>
    <p>Using graph attributes yields better Using graph attributes yields better summary performancesummary performance</p>
    <p>Wider text coverage yields higher ROUGE Wider text coverage yields higher ROUGE scoresscores</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
