<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The University of Minnesota Internet of Things Lab, part of the Distributed Computing Systems Group</p>
    <p>An Edge-based Abstraction for Enabling Cooperation in Internet of Things</p>
    <p>Applications Zach Leidall, Abhishek Chandra, Jon Weissman</p>
    <p>University of Minnesota, Twin Cities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The IoT is the merging of the physical and the digital.</p>
    <p>Connected roads/transit</p>
    <p>Smart homes/buildings</p>
    <p>Environmental monitoring</p>
    <p>Personal health improvement</p>
    <p>IoT and The Edge</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The edge provides numerous benefits over the cloud  Latency</p>
    <p>Privacy</p>
    <p>Security</p>
    <p>Why The Edge?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Industry Edge/Cloud Solutions</p>
    <p>Pros Cons  Writing applications is often</p>
    <p>much easier, especially if you utilize their sensors and actuators.</p>
    <p>Lack of interoperability</p>
    <p>Few standards</p>
    <p>Systems just call functions,</p>
    <p>little (or no) understanding</p>
    <p>of context.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Applications sharing the same physical space are likely to interfere  Cooperation</p>
    <p>E.g., using the same sensor can enable reuse</p>
    <p>Conflicts  E.g., setting the same light(s) to different intensity</p>
    <p>Conflicts or Cooperation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A single person wants to control their environment</p>
    <p>Motivating Example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Many stakeholders seeking control of many devices</p>
    <p>Motivating Example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Edge-based OS-like abstraction for managing access to underlying IoT resources.</p>
    <p>Our Solution: Constellation</p>
    <p>Device Drivers</p>
    <p>Semantic Runtime System</p>
    <p>CQL Engine</p>
    <p>Applications</p>
    <p>Devices</p>
    <p>Constellation Node</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FIND DEVICES WITH Temperature geoLoc=(12.345, 11.111) AS TEMPS</p>
    <p>FIND DEVICES WITH furnaceOn geoLoc=(12.345, 11.111) AS FURNACE</p>
    <p>SENSE Temperature FROM TEMPS PERIOD 30 SEC</p>
    <p>ACTUATE furnaceOn ON FURNACE PARAMS intensity=40</p>
    <p>EVENT maintainTemp</p>
    <p>ACTUATE furnaceOn ON FURNACE PARAMS intensity=40</p>
    <p>WHEN (SENSE Temperature FROM TEMPS PERIOD 30 SEC) &lt; 70</p>
    <p>CQL Examples</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FIND DEVICES WITH toggleLight geoLoc=(12.345, 11.111) AS LIGHTS</p>
    <p>The Device Set (DevSet)</p>
    <p>DevSets are sets of functionally equivalent devices.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Semantic Runtime schedules what device to use when  Based on metric to be optimized (latency, accuracy, energy, etc.)</p>
    <p>Example strategies for energy consumption:  Round-robin  Greedy  Dispersion</p>
    <p>DevSet Choice</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Preliminary Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Devices may be deemed functionally equivalent if they have similar effects, e.g., increasing light.</p>
    <p>DevSets and Conflict Resolution</p>
    <p>Compromise</p>
    <p>Utilizing Alternatives</p>
    <p>Prioritization</p>
    <p>User Intervention</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Internet of Things requires systems which can account for the semantic richness of the physical world.</p>
    <p>Constellation provides many examples and optimizations based on such semantics.</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Desired feedback  Thoughts on potential use cases  Thoughts on the practicality or difficulties involved in putting such a system into</p>
    <p>practice</p>
    <p>Controversial Points  Assumption of interoperability  Privacy concerns</p>
    <p>Open Problems  Security  Extending for wider areas</p>
    <p>Depreciating Circumstances  Moores Law, Next-Gen Networking, Heterogeneity/Interoperability</p>
    <p>Questions/Discussion</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
