<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Publish-Pay-Subscribe Protocol for Payment-driven</p>
    <p>Edge Computing Gowri Ramachandran, Sharon L.G. Contreras, and</p>
    <p>Bhaskar Krishnamachari USC Viterbi School of Engineering, University of Southern California.</p>
    <p>HotEdge, 9-July-2019</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sources: https://www.cpomagazine.com/data-privacy/the-california-digital-dividend-plan-can-data-monetizati on-revenue-sharing-work/, https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-02-12/california-governor-proposes-digital-dividen d-targeting-big-tech</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An IoT Community Marketplace for Smart Cities</p>
    <p>For more details, please visit</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Publish-Subscribe Communication Pattern  Messaging framework operate in</p>
    <p>client-server architecture  Benefits</p>
    <p>Isolation between data producers (publishers) and data consumers (subscribers)</p>
    <p>One-to-many message distribution</p>
    <p>Broker</p>
    <p>Publishers Subscribers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Need for Payment Integration to Pub-Sub</p>
    <p>Data is the new oil  Monetizing publishers to</p>
    <p>share their data</p>
    <p>Flexible platform for Data and Service providers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Towards a Marketplace for Edge Computing  Publishers sell data or trigger</p>
    <p>remote service  Subscribers buy data and could</p>
    <p>also resell processed data to other subscribers</p>
    <p>Value chain creation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introducing Pub-Pay-Subscribe Protocol 1. Publishers Connect to Broker 2. Register Payment Information 3. Publish Data 4. Register Topic at the Broker 5. Subscriber Connect to Broker 6. Subscribe to a Topic and Agrees to</p>
    <p>Pay the Price Set by the Publisher 7. Metering and Payment to Transfer</p>
    <p>the Fee from Subscribers Account to Publishers Account</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation: Cryptocurrency as a Payment Platform  Prominent cryptocurrency platforms charge transaction fee</p>
    <p>Ethereum: $0.214  BitCoin: $1.56 USD  Stripe charge 2.9% plus $0.30 USD per transaction</p>
    <p>For example, 10 messages cost = $2.14 (10 * $0.214)  We introduce K-parameter to reduce the transaction fees</p>
    <p>Initiate payment for every Kth message  For example, assuming K=10 -&gt; Message Cost = $0.214</p>
    <p>Transaction time is another issue  Payment handler is not on the critical path</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion [1/2] - Open Issues</p>
    <p>Payment processing overhead  Payment handler is triggered whenever a data flows from a publisher to a</p>
    <p>subscriber</p>
    <p>Pricing of data is critical for the platform to be usable  Who decides the price for the data?  Need to support Auction?</p>
    <p>Rating and Reputation System to Track the Publishers and Subscribers  Prevent financially motivated attacks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion [2/2]  Feedback</p>
    <p>Use Cases</p>
    <p>Controversial Points  Trust issues  Data quality - Is my data improving the quality/accuracy of the model?  Should you preserve the isolation between the publisher and the subscriber when handling</p>
    <p>payments?  What happens when a publisher wants to know who subscribed to the data?</p>
    <p>Threats  Cost of Privacy?  Financially motivated attacks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  Emerging data economy require protocols with built-in payment support</p>
    <p>Pub-Pay-Sub enable IoT/edge devices and users to sell their data to applications and service</p>
    <p>Existing pub-sub systems can buy data or earn incentive without significant changes</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
