<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Open Infrastructure for Edge: A Distributed Ledger Outlook</p>
    <p>A. Zavodovski, N. Mohan, W. Wong and J. Kangasharju</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How Will Edge Get Deployed?</p>
    <p>Edge = edge for shared or general purpose computing  Private edge deployments for specific purposes not relevant for us</p>
    <p>Spectrum of edge deployments</p>
    <p>Small number of large providers (like cloud today)</p>
    <p>Large number of small providers (our focus)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation: An Open Infrastructure for Edge</p>
    <p>Where will the edge servers come from?  Anyone should be able to become an edge provider  Set of common standards and practices for edge providers is required  Solution for handling agreement and financial transactions  Large number of independent providers  Large number of clients/users</p>
    <p>Is a distributed ledger a possible choice? (our focus in this paper)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Distributed Ledgers for Edge?</p>
    <p>Widely used and popular, despite known issues  In principle, they provide decentralized trust and transactions  Very interesting and useful for open edge</p>
    <p>Two key building blocks:  Smart contracts: Executable code  Ricardian contracts: Legal agreement in machine-readable tamper-proof form</p>
    <p>Ricardian triple: &lt;prose, parameters, code&gt;  Prose = Ricardian contract  Code = Smart contract  Parameters: This particular instance of the agreement</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Requirements for Agreements in Open Edge</p>
    <p>Fast and cheap transactions  Appropriate level of privacy and accountability  Protection from volatility of crypto assets  Conflict resolution and escrow service  Legislation for digital agreement  Environmentally sustainable operation  True decentralization, no central authority</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sustainability, Transaction Cost, Volatility</p>
    <p>Energy consumption of Bitcoin and Ethereum, similar levels to Colombia or Portugal</p>
    <p>Sources: https://digiconomist.net /bitcoin-energy-consumption, https://etherscan.io/charts, https://www.buybitcoinworldwide.com /volatility-index/</p>
    <p>Ethereums transaction costs peak at ICOs.</p>
    <p>Volatility of Ether, Bitcoin, and gold.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Smart Contract Platforms</p>
    <p>Ethereum has been the leader so far  Cons: high energy consumption (proof-of-work), low performance, high costs  Pros: truly distributed, backing community is largest (7000-20000 nodes)  Transition to greener proof-of-stake Casper protocol is expected</p>
    <p>Second generation of platforms  EOS, Stellar, Cardano, etc  Many use delegated proof-of-stake (DPoS), greener and faster  Some charge zero fee</p>
    <p>Decentralization vs. efficiency  DPoS is efficient, but its decentralization is often questioned (e.g., EOS)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other Considerations</p>
    <p>Volatility protection  Stable coins, e.g., Tether, USD Coin, TrueUSD, backed by some institution  Buyer of the coin must trust the institution, no decentralization  Allegations, e.g., no real money backing Tether, no way to check</p>
    <p>Privacy  Blockchain is open by design  For business considerations, edge providers might want to conceal their prices  Systems like Zcash use zero knowledge proofs to store private data while</p>
    <p>keeping blockchain public  No smart contract system supporting privacy in convenient way so far</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Takeaways</p>
    <p>No distributed ledger exists that would support everything that open infrastructure for edge ideally requires  Common tradeoffs</p>
    <p>Accountability vs. privacy  Efficiency and low costs vs. true decentralization  Volatility vs. Trusting a non-regulated institution</p>
    <p>Legal status of digital agreement will always be out of technical scope  Energy wasteful PoW and low transaction throughput are likely to be</p>
    <p>tackled as proof-of-stake family of protocols take hold  Interledgers unite diverse systems enabling interactions between</p>
    <p>participants using different ledgers  Current developments are leading into a positive direction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Open Questions? Issues? Problems?</p>
    <p>Will there ever be a general-purpose edge?  What form will it take?  Based on current cloud operators?  Based on independent edge providers?</p>
    <p>This paper: Thought experiment + requirement analysis for open edge  Main conclusion: Feasible, although needs more work</p>
    <p>Shared edge looks very likely  Shared = One application, many providers  Need: Standardized APIs, discovery, agreements</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you! jussi.kangasharju@helsinki.fi</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
