<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trustless IoT: A Logic Driven Architecture for</p>
    <p>IoT Hubs Soumya Basu Emin Gn Sirer</p>
    <p>HotEdge June 26, 2020</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Internet of Things  5.8 billion IoT devices by the end of 2020</p>
    <p>20% increase from 2019</p>
    <p>Affects many major sectors of the economy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Centralized hubs are the dominant emerging architecture</p>
    <p>Small number of hubs effectively control 5.8 B devices</p>
    <p>Why hubs are here to stay:</p>
    <p>Simplicity of administration and control</p>
    <p>Limited vendors due to economies of scale</p>
    <p>Limited communication modalities on devices</p>
    <p>Emerging Architecture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What about security?  The state of IoT security is poor (the s is for security)</p>
    <p>Device security</p>
    <p>Hub security</p>
    <p>Many examples of unauthorized access to devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What about security?  The state of IoT security is poor (the s is for security)</p>
    <p>Device security</p>
    <p>Hub security</p>
    <p>Many examples of unauthorized access to devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What about security?  The state of IoT security is poor (the s is for security)</p>
    <p>Device security</p>
    <p>Hub security</p>
    <p>Many examples of unauthorized access to devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why is security poor?  Root cause: Implicit full trust in the hub</p>
    <p>Hubs are:</p>
    <p>In the TCB of every device</p>
    <p>Always on and internet connected</p>
    <p>Can commandeer any action on any actuator</p>
    <p>Hub compromise can hurt national security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OrbanHub Proposal  A modified IoT architecture where hubs cannot</p>
    <p>misbehave</p>
    <p>Byzantine hub is constrained in its actions</p>
    <p>Safety: No command executed by any device unless authorized by user policy</p>
    <p>Liveness: All commands that should be executed will eventually execute</p>
    <p>Lightweight, incrementally deployable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Guaranteeing Safety  Proof carrying statements (PCS) ensure safety</p>
    <p>Actions sent from the hub to actuators must be accompanied by a proof that they were authorized by the users policy</p>
    <p>Sensors upload cryptographically signed statements that serve as inputs to proofs</p>
    <p>Hubs are tasked with creating PCS and cannot engage in actions unjustified by a policy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sample Proof  User policy: If door is open, lights turn</p>
    <p>on ( )</p>
    <p>Door sensor: Door is open. ( )</p>
    <p>User inference ( ):</p>
    <p>Door sensor says User says</p>
    <p>User infers: (lights turn on)</p>
    <p>Light actuator then turns on due to user inference</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Control Flow</p>
    <p>Hub</p>
    <p>Door Lock Lights 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Guaranteeing Liveness  All statements are logged using a hash chain</p>
    <p>Hashchains constrain hub to deleting tail of log</p>
    <p>All devices are required to send periodic updates</p>
    <p>Prevents hub from withholding update forever</p>
    <p>If a device is quiet, then failure alert is generated</p>
    <p>Range of potential fallback mechanisms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>New Way Forward  IoT is becoming more ubiquitous</p>
    <p>Attacks become more lucrative</p>
    <p>Security is a first class concern</p>
    <p>OrbanHub is a new, trustless IoT model</p>
    <p>Works with existing architecture</p>
    <p>Limited overhead on devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Contact: soumya@cs.cornell.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
