<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scale-out Edge Storage Systems with Embedded Storage Nodes to Get Better Availability and</p>
    <p>Cost-Efficiency At the Same Time (aka Embedded Storage at the Edge Paper)</p>
    <p>Jianshen Liu*, Matthew Leon Curry, Carlos Maltzahn*, Philip Kufeldt</p>
    <p>*UC Santa Cruz, Sandia National Laboratories, Seagate Technology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges of Data Availability at the Edge</p>
    <p>Edge Deployments</p>
    <p>Truck rolls are expensive!</p>
    <p>Failure</p>
    <p>Environmental Limitations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Embedded Storage</p>
    <p>Ethernet-attached storage devices integrated with computing resources</p>
    <p>Computational storage devices</p>
    <p>General-purpose (GP) Servers</p>
    <p>Embedded Storage Devices</p>
    <p>An Ethernet SSD with NVMe-oF Interface *</p>
    <p>* https://www.servethehome.com/marvell-88ss5000-nvmeof-ssd-controller-shown-with-toshiba-bics/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Failure Domains and Data Availability</p>
    <p>The more independent failure domains a failover mechanism spans, the more available the data becomes.</p>
    <p>Each GP servers contains multiple storage devices</p>
    <p>Embedded Storage Devices</p>
    <p>Embedded Storage enables more nodes under the same cost/space/power restrictions.</p>
    <p>Simpler</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Analytical Model</p>
    <p>Server-based Storage System</p>
    <p>Embedded Storage System</p>
    <p>Determine availability of embedded storage relative to traditional servers.</p>
    <p>Pdata-loss(server-based storage system)</p>
    <p>Pdata-loss(embedded storage system) Relative Benefit = Relative Benefit &gt; 1 embedded storage is better</p>
    <p>Goal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Analytical Model  Assumptions of System Configurations</p>
    <p>The units of deployment are homogeneous.</p>
    <p>Both systems have the same level of network redundancy and power redundancy for all nodes.</p>
    <p>Both systems use 3-way replication for data protection.</p>
    <p>Both systems use the copyset replication scheme instead of the random replication scheme.</p>
    <p>Independence of servers and storage devices. Therefore, we can use Poisson distribution* to model the possibilities of hardware failures.</p>
    <p>Cidon, Asaf, et al. &quot;Copysets: Reducing the frequency of data loss in cloud storage.&quot; Presented as part of the 2013 {USENIX} Annual Technical Conference ({USENIX}{ATC} 13). 2013. * Wikipedia contributors. &quot;Poisson distribution.&quot; Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia. Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia, 10 Mar. 2020. Web. 31 Mar. 2020.</p>
    <p>It's not our work, but we apply this scheme to our model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Copyset Replication vs. Random Replication</p>
    <p>Relationships of Nodes with Random Replication Relationships of Nodes with Copyset Replication</p>
    <p>With a sufficient number of data chunks stored, data loss is nearly guaranteed</p>
    <p>if any combination of r nodes fail simultaneously.</p>
    <p>: a node can store copies of the data in the other node</p>
    <p>Replication Factor r = 3</p>
    <p>A node has replica set relationships with 5 nodes A node has replica set relationships with &lt;=2 nodes</p>
    <p>Reducing the number of replica sets can reduce the likelihood of data loss</p>
    <p>under a correlated failure.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Analytical Model  Assumptions of Model Parameters</p>
    <p>and</p>
    <p>, where For hard drives, f could be greater than 2, while for SSDs, f could be less than 1. (We call the ratio of failure rates)</p>
    <p>, where (We call the ratio of computing performance)</p>
    <p>(We call the ratio of storage performance)</p>
    <p>(3-way replication)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>and</p>
    <p>Failure Rate of non-storage components</p>
    <p>Our Analytical Model  Assumptions of Model Parameters</p>
    <p>In</p>
    <p>Failure Rate of non-storage components</p>
    <p>In</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>and</p>
    <p>Failure Rate of the storage component</p>
    <p>Failure Rate of a storage device</p>
    <p>Our Analytical Model  Assumptions of Model Parameters</p>
    <p>In In</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>, where For hard drives, f could be greater than 2, while for SSDs, f could be less than 1. (We call the ratio of failure rates)</p>
    <p>Our Analytical Model  Assumptions of Model Parameters</p>
    <p>Failure Rate of non-storage components</p>
    <p>In</p>
    <p>Failure Rate of a storage device</p>
    <p>In</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We need units of to get the</p>
    <p>same performance of a single</p>
    <p>Our Analytical Model  Assumptions of Model Parameters</p>
    <p>, where (We call the ratio of computing performance)</p>
    <p># of</p>
    <p># of</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Analytical Model  Assumptions of Model Parameters</p>
    <p>(We call the ratio of storage performance)</p>
    <p>is the number of storage devices ( 2) in a server.</p>
    <p>...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Analytical Model  Assumptions of Model Parameters</p>
    <p>(3-way replication)</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>need at least 3 servers for 3-way replication</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Analytical Model  Assumptions of Model Parameters</p>
    <p>and</p>
    <p>, where For hard drives, f could be greater than 2, while for SSDs, f could be less than 1. (We call the ratio of failure rates)</p>
    <p>, where (We call the ratio of computing performance)</p>
    <p>(We call the ratio of storage performance)</p>
    <p>(3-way replication)</p>
    <p>How sensitive is the Relative Benefit to these parameters?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>and</p>
    <p>As an example, we evaluate the Relative Benefit of embedded storage regarding the data unavailability caused by failures of exactly three components.</p>
    <p>A component can be:</p>
    <p>A server  An embedded storage device  A storage component in a failure domain</p>
    <p>(the failure rate of the storage component over the failure rate of the non-storage components)  (the number of nodes that have a replica set relationship with a node)  (# of GP servers)  (# of storage devices in a server)  (# of embedded storage device / # of servers)</p>
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>Pdata-loss(server-based storage system)</p>
    <p>Pdata-loss(embedded storage system) Relative Benefit =</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Impact of Compute Aggregation on the Relative Benefit</p>
    <p>The Impact of Storage Aggregation on the Relative Benefit</p>
    <p>Evaluation  Spinning Media as Storage</p>
    <p>The failure rate of a storage device is 2x of that of the non-storage components of a server (f = 2)</p>
    <p>The number of nodes that have a replica set relationship with a node is 4 (w = 4) [Vishwanath, et al. &quot;Characterizing cloud computing hardware reliability.&quot; 2010]</p>
    <p>the server-based system has (m=) 10 servers  each server has (n=) 4 storage devices  relative benefit is 7.1</p>
    <p>the server-based system has (m=) 10 servers  the embedded storage system has (17x10=) 170 devices  relative benefit is 114.3</p>
    <p>c = n = 4  the embedded storage system has (10x4=) 40 devices</p>
    <p>each server has 12 storage devices</p>
    <p>Higher Storag</p>
    <p>e Aggr egatio</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>Hig he</p>
    <p>r C om</p>
    <p>pu te</p>
    <p>Ag gre</p>
    <p>gat ion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The failure rate of a storage device is 0.06x of that of the non-storage components of a server (f = 0.06)</p>
    <p>The number of nodes that have a replica set relationship with a node is 4 (w = 4)</p>
    <p>Evaluation  Solid-state Drives as Storage</p>
    <p>[Xu, Erci, et al. &quot;Lessons and actions: What we learned from 10k ssd-related storage system failures.&quot; 2019]</p>
    <p>the server-based system has (m=) 10 servers  each server has (n=) 4 storage devices  relative benefit is 20.7</p>
    <p>The Impact of Storage Aggregation on the Relative Benefit</p>
    <p>The Impact of Compute Aggregation on the Relative Benefit</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Insights (part 1/5)</p>
    <p>Server-based Storage System</p>
    <p>Embedded Storage System</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Insights (part 2/5)</p>
    <p>Server-based Storage System</p>
    <p>Embedded Storage System</p>
    <p>The total # of storage devices of the two systems are the same.</p>
    <p>m servers have 4 storage devices each, resulting in m failure domains.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Insights (part 3/5)</p>
    <p>Server-based Storage System</p>
    <p>Embedded Storage System</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Insights (part 4/5)</p>
    <p>Server-based Storage System</p>
    <p>Embedded Storage System</p>
    <p>units of can provide the same</p>
    <p>storage performance of a single</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Insights (part 5/5)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Embedded storage devices are simpler, making it is possible to have more independent failure domains.</p>
    <p>Storage systems with more independent failure domains can improve data availability.</p>
    <p>A great design point, but many unsolved challenges! (e.g., explore the balance between availability and storage performance)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you! Questions?</p>
    <p>Jianshen Liu jliu120@ucsc.edu</p>
    <p>https://cross.ucsc.edu (Eusocial Storage Devices)</p>
    <p>This work was supported in part by NSF grants OAC-1836650, CNS-1764102, and CNS-1705021, and by the Center for Research in Open Source Software (cross.ucsc.edu). Sandia National Laboratories is a multimission laboratory managed and operated by National Technology and Engineering Solutions of Sandia, LLC, a wholly owned subsidiary of Honeywell International, Inc., for the U.S. Department of Energy's National Nuclear Security Administration under contract DE-NA0003525.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Example of Copyset Replication</p>
    <p>A copyset is a set of nodes that stores all of the copies of a data chunk.</p>
    <p>Scatter width is the number of nodes the data of a node can be replicated to.</p>
    <p>Example:</p>
    <p>Copysets:</p>
    <p>Each permutation increases the scatter width of a node by</p>
    <p>The number of copysets is</p>
    <p># of nodes (m) replication factor (r) scatter width (w)</p>
    <p>{1,2,3}, {4,5,6}, {7,8,9} {1,4,7}, {2,5,8}, {3,6,9}</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Copyset Replication vs. Random Replication</p>
    <p>Number of copysets (3-way replication):</p>
    <p>With a sufficient number of data chunks stored, random replication creates a failure domain for any combination of r nodes (r is the replication factor).</p>
    <p>Copyset Replication (CR)</p>
    <p>Random Replication (RR)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Analytical Model  Modeling the Two Systems</p>
    <p>where where</p>
    <p>The possibility of data loss of server-based storage systems</p>
    <p>The possibility of data loss of embedded storage systems</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
