<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tao Lu Marvell Technology Group Wen Xia, Xiangyu Zou Harbin Institute of Technology Qianbin Xia Marvell Technology Group</p>
    <p>Adaptively Compressing IoT Data on the Resource-constrained Edge</p>
    <p>This research was conducted using publicly accessible academic resources. It does not reflect viewpoints of Marvell Technology Group.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview  Background  ZipMate Adaptive Compression Design  Preliminary Evaluation  Conclusion and Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Big Data Concerns in IoT Environments  IDC Predicts</p>
    <p>By 2025  41.6 billion connected IoT devices or things  Generating more than 79 zettabytes (ZB) of data</p>
    <p>NSF Data Storage Research Report Identifies  IoT brings an explosion of data collection, storage, and processing demands</p>
    <p>It is important to identify and reduce IoT data in a timely fashion  It is important to balance among storage, preprocessing, and communication between IoT devices and cloud</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Application Scenario: Edge-Cloud Data Transfer</p>
    <p>Wide-area network bottleneck</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Compression-based Data Transfer</p>
    <p>Read Data</p>
    <p>Compression on the Edge</p>
    <p>Network Transfer</p>
    <p>Read Data</p>
    <p>Compression on the Edge</p>
    <p>Network Transfer</p>
    <p>Read Data</p>
    <p>Compression on the Edge</p>
    <p>Network Transfer</p>
    <p>Read Data</p>
    <p>Compression on the Edge</p>
    <p>Read Data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Challenge of Compression-based Data Transfer: Compressor Selection</p>
    <p>Data Pool Compressor Pool</p>
    <p>BZIP2GZIP</p>
    <p>LZMA ZSTD</p>
    <p>SZ Webp</p>
    <p>Floating point Integer</p>
    <p>Image Video</p>
    <p>Key-value Text</p>
    <p>A challenge: which compressor to use for a specific dataset?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ZipMate Application Scenarios  Scenario 1: Computation offloading</p>
    <p>To accelerate the data transfer so that analysis of IoT data in cloud can be launched as soon as possible</p>
    <p>Scenario 2: Storage offloading  To reduce data volume as much as possible, maximizing cloud storage cost savings.</p>
    <p>Accelerate data analysis</p>
    <p>Minimize cloud storage costs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimal Compressor Selection A simplified model for Scenario 1 : Data transfer throughput (in uncompressed size) = min (Compression Throughput, Network Bandwidth  Compression Ratio) In Scenario 1: The optimal compressor is the one that can deliver maximal data transfer throughput. In Scenario 2: The optimal compressor is simply the one that can achieve maximal compression ratio. Predicting the compression ratios of a dataset with different compressors is the key.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IoT Datasets for Evaluation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observation 3: The resource-aware adaptive compressor selection scheme consistently outperforms unitary or random solutions in achieving the shortest edge-to-cloud transfer time.</p>
    <p>Preliminary Evaluation for Scenario 1 (Target Shortest Edge to Cloud Transfer Time)</p>
    <p>Observation 1: Network bandwidth and computing power both have obvious impact on data transfer time, but the bandwidth dominates the impact.</p>
    <p>Observation 2: There is no single compressor which performs best in all or even most cases.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Preliminary Evaluation for Scenario 2 (Target Highest Compression Ratio)</p>
    <p>Same as Observation 2 in Scenario 1: There is no single compressor which performs best in all or even most cases.</p>
    <p>Similar to Observation 3 in Scenario 1: The resource-aware adaptive compressor selection scheme consistently outperforms unitary or random solutions in achieving the highest compression ratio.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  For a dataset, different compressors show different performance.</p>
    <p>In resource limitation conditions, data transfer is limited by various runtime resource bottlenecks including available CPU resources and WAN bandwidth.</p>
    <p>Resource-aware adaptive compressor selection can considerably accelerate edge to cloud data transfer or improve data compression ratio.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work  To build and enhance compression ratio prediction models for various compressors.</p>
    <p>To run representative edge analytics workloads to measure the performance degradation of other edge applications caused by compression.</p>
    <p>To investigate the security challenges in IoT, edge, and cloud environments to enforce proper data security policies in our middleware.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks &amp; Questions</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
