<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Making a Case for Proactive</p>
    <p>Flow Control in Optical</p>
    <p>Circuit-switched Networks</p>
    <p>M. Kumar, V. Chaube, P. Balaji, W. Feng and H.-W. Jin</p>
    <p>Department of Computer Science, Virginia Tech Mathematics and Computer Science, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>Department of Computer Science and Engg., Konkuk University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lambda Grids: Trends and Promises</p>
    <p>Lambda Grids  A new paradigm in distributed computing  High-bandwidth optical networks allowing for globally</p>
    <p>distributed compute, storage and visualization systems to work together as one large planetary-scale supercomputer</p>
    <p>Realizing the lambda grid comprises of two parts:  Creating an environment to enable Lambda Grids, i.e.,</p>
    <p>several globally distributed nodes bundled together with fast optical networks  this is mostly a reality today !</p>
    <p>Networking capability to utilize the Lambda Grid, i.e., networking protocols that allow us to harness its potential</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protocols for the Lambda Grid</p>
    <p>TCP/IP on the Lambda Grid  High overhead of congestion control and flow-control  Not the best protocol for networks with zero congestion</p>
    <p>UDP-based approaches offer better performance  Light weight  Additions such as flow-control can be added on-demand</p>
    <p>Rate controlled reliable UDP variants widely accepted  Basic idea: sender sends at a pre-negotiated rate  Examples: RBUDP, RAPID, RBUDP+, RAPID+, UDT</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Issues with Rate-controlled UDP protocols  While the basic idea of rate-controlled UDP protocols is</p>
    <p>good, the current implementations are nave  Problems:</p>
    <p>Coarse-grained control  Most rate-controlled protocols are not adaptive, i.e., rate not</p>
    <p>varied through the life time of the data transfer  Others vary at a very coarse-grained level</p>
    <p>E.g., after each round of data transfer</p>
    <p>Reactive approach to packet drops  Rate is varied after the packet drop has occurred  Understanding receiver host behavior to proactively predict</p>
    <p>packet drops is not trivial !</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach</p>
    <p>We take a two-phase approach  Design a fine-grained rate-control approach with an</p>
    <p>asynchronous feedback mechanism  Analyze the issues related to reactive rate control as</p>
    <p>compared to proactive rate control</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation Overview</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Asynchronous Fine-grained Rate Control</p>
    <p>A Case for Proactive Rate Control</p>
    <p>Concluding Remarks</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problems with Fine-grained Rate Control</p>
    <p>Why is fine-grained rate control difficult?  Rate-controlled UDP protocols send data one packet at a</p>
    <p>time (i.e., 1500 bytes)  Data sent over a UDP channel and rate-adaptation feedback</p>
    <p>received over a TCP control channel  For fine-grained rate control, both the UDP and TCP</p>
    <p>channels have to be continuously monitored  Additional system call for every 1500 bytes of data transfer  Can cause performance degradation</p>
    <p>Common Solution: Perform coarse-grained rate control  Monitor the TCP channel after a large amount of data is sent</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ASYNCH: Basic Idea  ASYNCH: Asynchronous, fine-grained reactive rate control</p>
    <p>Rate-adaption feedback is infrequent as compared to the data transfer  continuous monitoring is wasted system calls !</p>
    <p>Our approach:  Allow a separate thread to wait on the TCP/IP control channel</p>
    <p>while the main thread sends data out at the negotiated rate  When a rate adaptation feedback arrives, the control thread</p>
    <p>sends a signal to the main thread  Main thread adapts its rate on receiving this signal</p>
    <p>Advantages:  All the benefits of coarse-grained rate control</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Understanding</p>
    <p>We evaluate ASYNCH and RAPID+ for various receiver end-host conditions</p>
    <p>Test-bed: Attempt to emulate a real-world dedicated circuit switched network</p>
    <p>3 node sender receiver setup; middle node emulating a WAN</p>
    <p>File size: 1GB, RTT: 56ms</p>
    <p>Dual-core AMD Opteron 2218; with 1MB cache, 4 GB RAM</p>
    <p>Myrinet 10GB adapter</p>
    <p>Linux kernel: 2.6.18</p>
    <p>We bind receive process to same core</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Performance Comparison</p>
    <p>Sharp rise in packet loss rate beyond 5.5Gbps  ASYNCHs fine-grained feedback mechanism helps adapt to packet loss quickly;</p>
    <p>resulting in 50% better throughput</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Impact of Socket Buffers and RTT</p>
    <p>Data at receiver is stored in socket buffers</p>
    <p>ASYNCH shows much smaller loss rate</p>
    <p>compared to RAPID+ for all buffer sizes</p>
    <p>Both ASYNCH and RAPID+ use a TCP</p>
    <p>control channel for reliability (RTT</p>
    <p>sensitive)</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation Overview</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Asynchronous Fine-grained Rate Control</p>
    <p>A Case for Proactive Rate Control</p>
    <p>Concluding Remarks</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Case for Proactive Rate Control</p>
    <p>Can proactive rate control help?</p>
    <p>Why does packet loss occur?</p>
    <p>Can this loss be predicted?</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Effect of Load on Receiver End-host</p>
    <p>Figures 4 and 5</p>
    <p>On an average, ASYNCH shows lower drop in throughout as compared to</p>
    <p>RAPID+, for increasing number of various loads</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Loss Patterns</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet Loss vs. Process Scheduling</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
    <p>Packet loss concentrated around the region where the network process has no access to the CPU</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation Overview</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Asynchronous Fine-grained Rate Control</p>
    <p>A Case for Proactive Rate Control</p>
    <p>Concluding Remarks</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Concluding Remarks</p>
    <p>This paper presented ASYNCH  an asynchronous, feedback-based, reactive, rate-control protocol</p>
    <p>Protocol effectively solves problems faced by current ratebased protocols  Provides improved and more accurate rate adaptation  Higher throughput</p>
    <p>We also highlight the need and the feasibility of implementing a proactive protocol  Case solidified based on analysis and observations of end</p>
    <p>host behavior in dynamic environments</p>
    <p>Pavan Balaji, Argonne National Laboratory</p>
    <p>(HiPC: 12/20/2008)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!</p>
    <p>Contacts:</p>
    <p>M. Kumar: mithil@cs.vt.edu</p>
    <p>V. Chaube: vineetac@cs.vt.edu</p>
    <p>P. Balaji: balaji@mcs.anl.gov</p>
    <p>W. Feng: feng@cs.vt.edu</p>
    <p>H.-W. Jin: jinh@konkuk.ac.kr</p>
    <p>Web links:</p>
    <p>http://www.mcs.anl.gov/~balaji</p>
    <p>http://synergy.cs.vt.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
