<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FERRET: Fall-back to LTE Microservices for Low Latency Data Access</p>
    <p>Presenter: Muhammad Taqi Raza, Ph.D. The University of Arizona</p>
    <p>June 25, 2020</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background - LTE</p>
    <p>LTE Evolved Packet Core (EPC) functionality is divided into control-plane and user-plane.  Control plane logic performs device registration/deregistration, mobility, location update, paging, and many more.  User plane forwards traffic to the next hop along the path to the selected destination network according to control</p>
    <p>plane logic.</p>
    <p>Control-Plane</p>
    <p>S1-AP MME HSS</p>
    <p>ServingGateway</p>
    <p>PDN-Gateway</p>
    <p>User-Plane</p>
    <p>LTE Core Network</p>
    <p>Device Radio Network Internet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background  IP Multimedia Subsystem (IMS)  Our Use Case Example</p>
    <p>SGW PGW</p>
    <p>LTE EPCRadio Network</p>
    <p>IMS Core</p>
    <p>Serving</p>
    <p>Server</p>
    <p>Media</p>
    <p>Server</p>
    <p>IMS Signaling (SIP)</p>
    <p>IMS Service (RTP/RTCP)</p>
    <p>Data Service</p>
    <p>Telephony Network</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>IMS supports real-time multimedia services.</p>
    <p>Voice call request (control plane)  Voice call speech packets flow (user plane)</p>
    <p>Regular user data traffic (user plane)</p>
    <p>IMS Client</p>
    <p>Proxy</p>
    <p>Server</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Existing IMS over LTE  Purpose-built hardware platforms, such as Ericssons Blade Systems (EBS), Alcatel-Lucents Element Management</p>
    <p>System (EMS), etc.</p>
    <p>Coupling between software and hardware, such as Ericssons ERLANG, Alcatel-Lucents NVP, etc.  Dedicated network resources for each user.</p>
    <p>Device Radio Network</p>
    <p>IMS</p>
    <p>EPC</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LTE-NFV Architecture</p>
    <p>LTE NFV virtualizes LTE core network functions over off-the-shelf boxes.  This reduces CAPEX and OPEX for operators.</p>
    <p>Device Radio Network</p>
    <p>Operator Network</p>
    <p>vEPC Data Center</p>
    <p>Internet Radio</p>
    <p>Network Mang.</p>
    <p>vEPC Network</p>
    <p>Mang.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why LTE-NFV Architecture is bad for IMS?</p>
    <p>Control plane signaling messages are executed on the cloud  Good: Different vNFs coordinate with each other to facilitate an event (e.g. mobility)</p>
    <p>User plane traffic is forwarded to Internet through vEPC Gateways (i.e. Serving Gateway, PDN Gateway, IMS NFs).  Bad: Voice traffic unnecessarily goes through the data center.</p>
    <p>Device Radio Network</p>
    <p>Operator Network</p>
    <p>vEPC Data Center</p>
    <p>Internet Radio</p>
    <p>Network Mang.</p>
    <p>vEPC Network</p>
    <p>Mang.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Forwarding through Mobile Edge Compute NF</p>
    <p>Lets decouple control-plane and user-plane  Control-plane traffic still goes to vEPC and vIMS  User-plane traffic is routed through mobile edge compute NFs.</p>
    <p>Device Radio Network</p>
    <p>Operator Network Internet</p>
    <p>Radio Network</p>
    <p>Mang.</p>
    <p>vEPC Network</p>
    <p>Mang.</p>
    <p>Mobile Edge Compute</p>
    <p>We decompose SGW and PGW user plane functionalities and install them at the edge  We also install MGW of IMS at the edge.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Considerations</p>
    <p>Decouple LTE and IMS CP and UP and install them at core and edge, respectively.</p>
    <p>PGW  U Resource management</p>
    <p>IP address and TEID assignment</p>
    <p>Packet forwarding</p>
    <p>Forwarding of buffered packet</p>
    <p>Accounting for Charging</p>
    <p>Transport level packet marking</p>
    <p>SGW  U Resource management</p>
    <p>IP address and TEID assignment</p>
    <p>Packet forwarding</p>
    <p>Transport level packet marking</p>
    <p>UL/DL APN-AMBR enforcement</p>
    <p>UL/DL bearer MBR enforcement</p>
    <p>UL and DL service level gating</p>
    <p>UL and DL service level MBR</p>
    <p>PGW - C</p>
    <p>IP address allocation</p>
    <p>DHCPv4 / DHCPv6 client</p>
    <p>Router advertisement</p>
    <p>Mobility b/w 3GPP and non-3GPP</p>
    <p>PGW pause of charging</p>
    <p>Change of target GTP-U endpoint</p>
    <p>SGW  C</p>
    <p>Change of target GTP-U endpoint</p>
    <p>Delay Downlink Data Notification</p>
    <p>PGW pause of charging</p>
    <p>Accounting for Charging</p>
    <p>Bearer binding</p>
    <p>Event reporting</p>
    <p>Redirection</p>
    <p>Mobile Edge</p>
    <p>Forwarding of buffered packet</p>
    <p>EPC and IMS CP</p>
    <p>Proxy Server (of IMS)</p>
    <p>Serving Server (of IMS)</p>
    <p>Media Gateway (of IMS)</p>
    <p>MEC Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Considerations: Pure UP and CP Separation</p>
    <p>All UP functions are moved to edge, whereas all CP functions (including PCRF, LCS and others) are placed at the core.</p>
    <p>Issue:  The UP traffic will steer to CP for charging. This adds latencies and bandwidth wastage for voice call operation.</p>
    <p>Device Radio Network</p>
    <p>Operator Network vEPC Data Center</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>Radio Network</p>
    <p>Mang.</p>
    <p>vEPC Network</p>
    <p>Mang.</p>
    <p>Charging</p>
    <p>Provide copy of all common CP NFs at the edge</p>
    <p>MEC Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Considerations: Share Common Functions between CP and UP</p>
    <p>Those functions (e.g. PCRF or charging function) which both CP and UP rely should be shared (i.e. copied).  Let the CP, being central entity, handle the NF allocation. Issue:  Creates race conditions. Example, SGW-U requests SGW-C for relocating SGW-U, while the TAU procedure is ongoing at the core, e.g.</p>
    <p>MME performs SGW relocation by sending same request to SGW-C.</p>
    <p>MMEDevice SGW-U</p>
    <p>Relocation Req. (part of TAU)</p>
    <p>SGW-C</p>
    <p>Tracking Area Update Req.</p>
    <p>Overload</p>
    <p>Relocation Req.</p>
    <p>Race Condition</p>
    <p>Let UP manage its own resources based on policy provided by CP</p>
    <p>MEC Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Considerations: Share Common Functions between CP and UP</p>
    <p>Those functions (e.g. PCRF or charging function) which both CP and UP rely should be shared (i.e. copied).</p>
    <p>Issue:  Creates deadlocks. Example, when ModifyBearer request at CP and UP locks their respective PCRF copies.</p>
    <p>Tracking Area Update</p>
    <p>Overload Modify Bearer Req.</p>
    <p>Session Modification</p>
    <p>LockModify Bearer Req.</p>
    <p>Session Modification</p>
    <p>Lock</p>
    <p>Device PGW-U PCRF-U PGW-C PCRF-CMME</p>
    <p>Reflect update to PCRF-C</p>
    <p>Reflect update to PCRF-U</p>
    <p>Deadlock</p>
    <p>Use blocking mode operations</p>
    <p>MEC Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Realizing IMS Application over MEC through FERRET</p>
    <p>FERRET Key Idea</p>
    <p>Let the CP perform all control-plane operations at the core.</p>
    <p>Once all operations are performed at CP, then replay them at the edge.</p>
    <p>Only transmit VoLTE call control plane packets once the call is established (before user-plane traffic starts).</p>
    <p>VoLTE call requires: (1) Call establishment phase (control plane), and</p>
    <p>(2) Speech data packets flow (user plane).</p>
    <p>Core</p>
    <p>NF1 NF2 M1</p>
    <p>M2</p>
    <p>NF2</p>
    <p>NF1</p>
    <p>M1 M2</p>
    <p>End</p>
    <p>Edge</p>
    <p>IMS Application over MEC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reducing User Plane Latencies through FERRET</p>
    <p>VoLTE call packets are forwarded to the Internet without going to the core.  Baseline results represent operational VoLTE network latencies.  This includes eNodeB &lt;-&gt; vEPC &lt;-&gt; IMS latencies for both caller and callee</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>MEC is part of 5G agenda that requires important network components to be installed at the edge.</p>
    <p>Through IMS, we demonstrate MEC architecture that reduces upto 6X user-plane latencies.</p>
    <p>In the future work, we will measure MEC design from different system and networking aspects.  Bandwidth, Latency, Call Rate, Mobility and more.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
