<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DAPA: Diagnosing Applica/on Performance Anomalies for Virtualized Infrastructures</p>
    <p>Hui Kang, Stony Brook University Xiaoyun Zhu, VMware</p>
    <p>Jennifer Wong, Stony Brook University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance management in cloud compu/ng</p>
    <p>AcAons taken by the system administrator</p>
    <p>Cloud user</p>
    <p>Cloud service provider Service level</p>
    <p>agreement (SLA)</p>
    <p>Localize the faulty applicaAon or system components  Find the root cause  Bring the system back to normal status</p>
    <p>Localize the faulty applicaAon or system components  Find the root cause  Bring the system back to normal status</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exis/ng solu/ons</p>
    <p>Domain knowledge in specific applicaAon/plaNorms and associated performance best pracAces, e.g., [B2007] (labor intensive, non-scalable)</p>
    <p>Dependency model approach , e.g, [B2003, K2005]  heavy instrumenta4on  packet trace on each node</p>
    <p>ML techniques modeling the relaAonship in distributed systems, [C2004] (complexity high, unfit for online analysis)</p>
    <p>AnalyAc performance models for adapAve resource provisioning of VMs, e.g., [P2009] (model inputs determined by human experts, redundant and non-scalable)</p>
    <p>Mostly designed in the Absence of Virtualiza/on 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Characteris/cs of virtualized infrastructures</p>
    <p>Performance loss caused by resource contenAon between VMs in the same host</p>
    <p>Fine-grained, system-level performance counters</p>
    <p>VM migraAon</p>
    <p>Strong dependency between VMs and their hosts =&gt; strong correlated metrics  negaAve modeling accuracy  wasAng compuAng Ame</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DAPA  Diagnosis And Performance Analysis</p>
    <p>Metric pre-selecAon</p>
    <p>Model pre-construcAon</p>
    <p>Model clustering</p>
    <p>Modeling</p>
    <p>Diagnosis</p>
    <p>ApplicaAon response Ame</p>
    <p>System metrics</p>
    <p>Model reconciliaAon</p>
    <p>Suspicious metrics from VMs or hosts</p>
    <p>Model series construcAon</p>
    <p>SLA viola/on detected</p>
    <p>within a /me window!</p>
    <p>Metric collecAon Monitoring</p>
    <p>SLA monitor</p>
    <p>Poten/al SLA viola/on detected!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DAPA typical deployment</p>
    <p>Cloud User</p>
    <p>Cloud Infrastructure</p>
    <p>VirtualizaAon Layer</p>
    <p>Anomalous VM &amp; host aHributes</p>
    <p>DAPA Analysis Engine</p>
    <p>Diagnosis</p>
    <p>Cloud Provider</p>
    <p>System Administrator</p>
    <p>Modeling</p>
    <p>SLA Monitor</p>
    <p>Metric Collector</p>
    <p>DAPA Monitoring</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Online monitoring</p>
    <p>Metric pre-selecAon</p>
    <p>Model pre-construcAon</p>
    <p>Model clustering</p>
    <p>Modeling</p>
    <p>Diagnosis</p>
    <p>ApplicaAon response Ame</p>
    <p>System metrics</p>
    <p>Model reconciliaAon</p>
    <p>Suspicious metrics from VMs or hosts</p>
    <p>Model series construcAon</p>
    <p>SLA viola/on detected</p>
    <p>within a /me window!</p>
    <p>Metric collecAon Monitoring</p>
    <p>SLA monitor</p>
    <p>Poten/al SLA viola/on detected!</p>
    <p>CollecAon applicaAon performance and system metrics periodically  TransacAon response Ame  cpu uAlizaAon, memory usage, etc</p>
    <p>Raise an alarm on a poten4al SLA violaAon 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Poten/al SLA viola/on</p>
    <p>A more stringent condiAon than true SLA violaAon  Always occurs prior to a true SLA violaAon  Trigger of the modeling phase</p>
    <p>Example  SLA violaAon: more than 10% of the response 4me for a certain</p>
    <p>type of transac4on within one minute are greater than one second.</p>
    <p>PotenAal SLA violaAon: At least 5% are greater than one second</p>
    <p>Benefits  capturing the characterisAcs of the system in both normal and abnormal status</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modeling</p>
    <p>Metric pre-selecAon</p>
    <p>Model pre-construcAon</p>
    <p>Model clustering</p>
    <p>Modeling</p>
    <p>Diagnosis</p>
    <p>ApplicaAon response Ame</p>
    <p>System metrics</p>
    <p>Model reconciliaAon</p>
    <p>Suspicious metrics from VMs or hosts</p>
    <p>Model series construcAon</p>
    <p>SLA viola/on detected</p>
    <p>within a /me window!</p>
    <p>Metric collecAon Monitoring</p>
    <p>SLA monitor</p>
    <p>Poten/al SLA viola/on detected!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Problems:  Lots of metrics and redundancy due to virtualizaAon  SensiAvity of the models to data variaAons  Model overtuned</p>
    <p>Approach: need an appropriate modeling technique</p>
    <p>VM cpu %</p>
    <p>cpu % from host Disk block</p>
    <p>read</p>
    <p>More than hundreds of correla4on pairs Brute force calculaAon is infeasible</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sta/s/cs</p>
    <p>Least angle regression (LARS) [E2004]</p>
    <p>L1 penalty RSS</p>
    <p>Prof. Bradley Efron (Main inventor of LARS) 11</p>
    <p>Input: X1, X2,  Xm  predicator variables and Y  response variable. All are n-dim vectors</p>
    <p>Output: A set of vector of regression coefficients  that minimize the RSS, subject to a constraint on the sum of .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LARS regression</p>
    <p>Example  [E2004]</p>
    <p>LARS</p>
    <p>t Coefficients become non- zero one at a Ame</p>
    <p>All coefficients become non- zero at the same Ame</p>
    <p>LARS Ridge regression</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LARS in DAPA</p>
    <p>Data collected by DAPA  System metrics as the predictor variables, e.g, CPU %, disk I/O</p>
    <p>ApplicaAon performance as the response variable, e.g., response Ame of a search request</p>
    <p>At each step, one metric is included into the learned model, i.e., its coefficient becomes non-zero</p>
    <p>Determine the stop condiAon such that an appropriate subset of metrics are included in the model (Metric pre-selec4on)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Metric pre-selec/on  A preliminary step before potenAal SLA violaAon  Cp,i: the risk of including a metric in the model</p>
    <p>Output the most important metrics for modeling the system 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DAPA - Diagnosis</p>
    <p>Metric pre-selecAon</p>
    <p>Model pre-construcAon</p>
    <p>Modeling</p>
    <p>ApplicaAon response Ame</p>
    <p>System metrics</p>
    <p>Model series construcAon</p>
    <p>Metric collecAon Monitoring</p>
    <p>SLA monitor</p>
    <p>Poten/al SLA viola/on detected!</p>
    <p>Model clustering</p>
    <p>Diagnosis</p>
    <p>Model reconciliaAon</p>
    <p>Suspicious metrics from VMs or hosts</p>
    <p>SLA viola/on detected</p>
    <p>within a /me window!</p>
    <p>Build a series of models using pre-selected metrics  A true SLA violaAon triggers the diagnosis phase</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model clustering and reconcilia/on</p>
    <p>k-means clustering (k=2) classifies models into two clusters: SLA compliance and violaAon</p>
    <p>Clustering models</p>
    <p>Aggregate the data samples of the SLA violaAon cluster and create a new LARS model  Metrics ordered by their impacts to the SLA violaAon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment setup</p>
    <p>Deploy DAPA prototype in the virtualized environment</p>
    <p>Inject several syntheAc faults into the system, causing SLA violaAons</p>
    <p>Metric pre-selecAon is crucial  Localize the resource boqleneck in a component related to the SLA violaAon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System architecture</p>
    <p>Xen 4.0 hypervisor and all VM Fedora 13  Olio  a mulA-Aer social network applicaAon  Trace driven workloads [A2000]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data collec/on</p>
    <p>ApplicaAon performance  CriAcal system metrics</p>
    <p>CPU, memory, disk, network, OS  Runs in 5 second interval</p>
    <p>Collected metrics  Applica/on performance</p>
    <p>metrics is the tag search transac/on response /me</p>
    <p>SLA viola/on   &gt; 10% of the response /me within one minute are greater than one second</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Synthe/c faults injected</p>
    <p>Inject one single fault at a Ame  I/O intensive processes in an app-Aer VM  Ballooning down the available memory of a DB VM  Add CPU-intensive VM to contend with an app-Aer VM</p>
    <p>Each LARS model built on 120 data samples  10 models (100 minutes run) for each fault</p>
    <p>Re sp on</p>
    <p>se A m e (s ec on</p>
    <p>d)</p>
    <p>Time (x 5 second)</p>
    <p>t1 t0 tf Applica/on response /me of tag search transac/ons under I/O fault case</p>
    <p>Fault injected</p>
    <p>Poten/al SLA viola/on</p>
    <p>SLA viola/on</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results  metrics pre-selec/on</p>
    <p>Reduce number of metrics by 1/3, from 54 to 32  Eliminate highly correlated metrics  The scales of Y-axis are different</p>
    <p>Correlated metrics, Bi increase rapidly</p>
    <p>LARS on original metrics LARS on pre-selected metrics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results  selected metrics</p>
    <p>Injected faults</p>
    <p>Top three metrics from DAPA</p>
    <p>Descrip/on</p>
    <p>Disk io waitvm1, bovm1, cxtvm3 IO wait, block out, and cxt switch selected; intensive I/O acAviAes on vm1 and vm3 affected</p>
    <p>Memory actvm4, sovm4, sivm4, AcAve memory, swap out/in selected; vm4 short of memory</p>
    <p>CPU hcvm1, hcvm2, htxvm1, Host CPU resource contenAon between vm1 and vm2;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>DAPA: a model-based performance diagnosis framework  Consider metric variaAons and scalability  Customized modeling techniques  Output ranked metrics related to performance loss</p>
    <p>Deploy with a mulA-Aer web applicaAon in a virtualized infrastructure</p>
    <p>Localize several boqlenecks causing the SLA violaAons</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future work</p>
    <p>Incorporate internal knowledge from various system layers of the virtualizaAon plaNorm  Gray-box approach  DifferenAate root causes between misconfiguraAon of VM and interference from other VMs</p>
    <p>Global knowledge e.g., network topology</p>
    <p>AutomaAcally finding the causal relaAonship between VM instances in the hosted applicaAon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References</p>
    <p>[A2000] ARLITT, M., AND JIN, T. A workload characterizaAon of study of the 1998 world cup web site. In IEEE Networks (May/June 2000), pp. 3037.</p>
    <p>[B2003] BARHAM, P., ISAACS, R., MORTIER, R., AND NARAYANAN, D. Magpie: Online modeling and performance-aware systems. In HotOS IX (2003), pp. 85  90.</p>
    <p>[B2007] BAHL, P., CHANDRA, R., GREENBERG, A., KANDULA, S., MALTZ, D. A., AND ZHANG, M. Towards highly reliable enterprise network services via inference of mulA- level dependencies. In Sigcomm (2007), pp. 1324.</p>
    <p>[C2004] COHEN, I., CHASE, J. S., GOLDSZMIDT, M., KELLY, T., AND SYMONS, J. CorrelaAng instrumentaAon data to system states: a building block for automated diagnosis and control. In OSDI (2004), pp. 231244.</p>
    <p>[E2004] EFRON, B., HASTIE, T., JOHNSTONE, I., AND TIBSHIRANI, R. Least angle regression. The Annals of Sta4s4cs 32 (2004), 407499.</p>
    <p>[K2005] KOMPELLA, R. R., YATES, J., GREENBERG, A., AND SNOEREN, A. C. Ip fault localizaAon via risk modeling. In NSDI (2005), pp. 387390.</p>
    <p>[P2009] PADALA, P., HOU, K.-Y., SHIN, K., ZHU, X., AND UYSAL, M. Auto- mated control of mulAple virtualized resources. In Eurosys (2009), pp. 13 26.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Backup</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results  metrics ranking (I/O fault case)</p>
    <p>Re sp on</p>
    <p>se A m e (s ec on</p>
    <p>d)</p>
    <p>waitvm1(%)</p>
    <p>SLA compliance SLA violaAon</p>
    <p>RS S</p>
    <p>Number of metrics</p>
    <p>Top three selected</p>
    <p>CPU usage of the faulty VM</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
