<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TRIPLE MODULAR REDUNDANCY WITH STANDBY (TMRSB)</p>
    <p>SUPPORTING DYNAMIC RESOURCE RECONFIGURATION</p>
    <p>K. Zhang, Guy BedetteK. Zhang, Guy Bedette and R. F. DeMaraand R. F. DeMara School of Elec. Engr. and Comp. Sci.School of Elec. Engr. and Comp. Sci.</p>
    <p>University of Central FloridaUniversity of Central Florida</p>
    <p>K. Zhang, Guy BedetteK. Zhang, Guy Bedette and R. F. DeMaraand R. F. DeMara School of Elec. Engr. and Comp. Sci.School of Elec. Engr. and Comp. Sci.</p>
    <p>University of Central FloridaUniversity of Central Florida</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NMR/TMR System</p>
    <p>N Modular Redundancy (NMR)  Approach: N identical functional modules, N=2m-1 for integer m&gt;1  Output: obtain a fault-free result from a majority voter in N identical</p>
    <p>parallel outputs when m &lt; N/2</p>
    <p>Triple Modular Redundancy (TMR)  Most popular NMR configuration  Let N=3, modules M1, M2, and M3 operate in parallel  Outputs converge at the majority voter to obtain the validated</p>
    <p>output</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Types of Standby Systems</p>
    <p>Hot Standby  Keeps primary and backup components running</p>
    <p>simultaneously with the backup tracking the primary system in real time</p>
    <p>Cold Standby  A secondary component is only called upon when</p>
    <p>the primary component fails  Warm Standby</p>
    <p>Periodically mirrors the primary component which means that there are times when both components do not contain the exact same data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparison of TMR vs. Standby Systems</p>
    <p>TMR</p>
    <p>no</p>
    <p>single fault</p>
    <p>detection and voting</p>
    <p>delay</p>
    <p>voter</p>
    <p>yes</p>
    <p>Standby</p>
    <p>yes</p>
    <p>multiple faults</p>
    <p>detection and switch delay</p>
    <p>switch and backup storage</p>
    <p>no</p>
    <p>Spare Utilization Capacity ability to use backup components</p>
    <p>Fault Coverage capacity # of fault handled</p>
    <p>Fault-Resolution Overhead &amp; Latency degradation factors on performance</p>
    <p>System Vulnerability vulnerability of critical component</p>
    <p>Autonomous Detection detection fault without outside intervention</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Characteristics of Embedded Reconfiguration Fault Tolerance</p>
    <p>Multi-million gate-equivalent devices  Can realize extensive functionality in a single chip  Simple glue logic through processor cores</p>
    <p>Unlimited reconfiguration ability  Provides switching capability for fault handling  Partial reconfiguration possible: reconfigure only fa</p>
    <p>ulty functional unit while others remain in service</p>
    <p>Small-sized configuration bitstreams  Allows switching with low overhead and delay</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Embedded Reconfigurable Devices (FPGAs)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Previous TMR-based Fault Tolerance Techniques for FPGAs</p>
    <p>TMR + Bitstream scrubbing  The voting mechanism identifies the faulty config</p>
    <p>uration based and reconfigures (scrubs) the devi ce with an alternative bitstream</p>
    <p>Single failure assumption</p>
    <p>Triple Module Redundancy Design Techni ques for Virtex FPGAs  Different types of data structures such as Throug</p>
    <p>hput Logic, State-Machine Logic and I/O Logic ar e illustrated in terms of a TMR technique</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Reliability Analysis: Standby System Configuration</p>
    <p>System Definition  Only one active component Ci where i=0, 1, 2m designates t</p>
    <p>he feasible set of one active and m standby components  An exponential distribution given by the parameter  for the co</p>
    <p>mponent reliability  Assume ideal switch and fault recovery capacity</p>
    <p>Life time Z follows a two-stage Erlang distribution f or the m=1 case and m-stage Erlang distribution in general  The reliability function for m&gt;1 is</p>
    <p>First term represents the reliability of the initially-selected active component</p>
    <p>Subsequent summation term represents the probability that ea ch standby component will provide a viable alternative</p>
    <p>kmte k</p>
    <p>t etR</p>
    <p>m</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>t k</p>
    <p>t dbyS ,2,1,0,0,</p>
    <p>!1 tan</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System with Unknown Configuration Status</p>
    <p>Two assumptions for simplify analysis 1. Faults in an active configuration will simultaneously disable that</p>
    <p>configuration and initiate a single configuration switch operation.</p>
    <p>The reliability of Standby System with unknown status configurations is given by:</p>
    <p>,2,1,,0,0</p>
    <p>, !</p>
    <p>)1( 1</p>
    <p>tan</p>
    <p>mmvt</p>
    <p>e k</p>
    <p>t petR</p>
    <p>m</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>t k</p>
    <p>vt dbyS</p>
    <p>System Reliability Analysis: Standby System Configuration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>x 10 4</p>
    <p>time</p>
    <p>R e lia</p>
    <p>b ili</p>
    <p>ty</p>
    <p>Unknown Status Standby Configurations System</p>
    <p>m=1 m=2 m=4 m=10 m=15</p>
    <p>System Reliability Analysis: Standby System Configuration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Reliability Analysis: NMR/TMR System</p>
    <p>Model of NMR with a perfect voter system is based on binomial distribution:</p>
    <p>If each component follows an exponential distribution:</p>
    <p>then Reliability of TMR system is given by (k=2,n=3):</p>
    <p>ini n</p>
    <p>ki NMR pp</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>n R</p>
    <p>1</p>
    <p>intti n</p>
    <p>ki NMR ee</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>n R</p>
    <p>1</p>
    <p>tt TMR eeR</p>
    <p>32 23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hybrid TMR &amp; Standby System</p>
    <p>tantan</p>
    <p>! 1</p>
    <p>m</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>t k</p>
    <p>vt dbyS</p>
    <p>in dbyS</p>
    <p>i dbyS</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>ki TMRSB</p>
    <p>e k</p>
    <p>t petR</p>
    <p>RR i</p>
    <p>n R</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TMR vs. Standby vs. TMRSB system Reliability Comparison</p>
    <p>Parameters selected: p=0.9, v=0.1, m=4 and =0.001</p>
    <p>Time</p>
    <p>R e</p>
    <p>lia b</p>
    <p>ili ty</p>
    <p>o f</p>
    <p>R e</p>
    <p>d u</p>
    <p>n d</p>
    <p>a n</p>
    <p>t S</p>
    <p>ys te</p>
    <p>m</p>
    <p>TMR System Standby System TMRSB system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation Result of Standby System and TMRSB system</p>
    <p>Parameters selected: p=0.9, v=0.1, m=4 and =0.001 in BlockSim 6.0 software</p>
    <p>time(hours)</p>
    <p>R e</p>
    <p>lia b</p>
    <p>ili ty</p>
    <p>o f</p>
    <p>R e</p>
    <p>d u</p>
    <p>n d</p>
    <p>a n</p>
    <p>cy S</p>
    <p>ys te</p>
    <p>m StandBy System TMRStandBy System m=4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation Result: M=2 and M=4 TMRSB System</p>
    <p>Parameters selected: p=0.9, v=0.1 and =0.001 with m=2 and m=4 respectively in BlockSim 6.0 software</p>
    <p>x 10 4</p>
    <p>time(hours)</p>
    <p>R e</p>
    <p>lia b</p>
    <p>ili ty</p>
    <p>o f</p>
    <p>R e</p>
    <p>d u</p>
    <p>n d</p>
    <p>a n</p>
    <p>cy S</p>
    <p>ys te</p>
    <p>m</p>
    <p>m=2 m=4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>TMRSB Model:  New system model interpretation  Standby configurations do not require distinct physical</p>
    <p>resources  Provides an interesting resource cost vs. reliability</p>
    <p>tradeoff</p>
    <p>Reliability of Standby-Based systems:  May not increase linearly in terms of the number of</p>
    <p>standby configurations  Reliability of the configurations which are both active and</p>
    <p>standby becomes an essential factor determining overall system reliability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks</p>
    <p>Question?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Erlang Distribution</p>
    <p>Probability density function The probability density function of the Erla ng distribution is</p>
    <p>where e is the base of the natural logarithm and ! is the factorial function. The parameter k is calle d the shape parameter and the parameter  is called the rate parameter.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Binomial Distribution</p>
    <p>In general, if the random variable X follows the binomial dis tribution with parameters n and p, we write X ~ B(n, p). The probability of getting exactly k successes is given by the probability mass function:</p>
    <p>for and where</p>
    <p>is the binomial coefficient &quot;n choose k&quot; (also denoted C(n, k) or nCk), hence the name of the distribution. The formula can be understood as follows: we want k successes (pk) an d n  k failures ((1  p)n  k). However, the k successes can occur anywhere among the n trials, and there are C(n, k) dif ferent ways of distributing k successes in a sequence of n t rials.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
