<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Automatic Extraction of Parallel Speech Corpora from Dubbed Movies Alp ktem, Mireia Farrs, Leo Wanner Presented by: Simon Mille</p>
    <p>{alp.oktem|mireia.farrus|leo.wanner|simon.mille}@upf.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contents</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Parallel Speech Corpora</p>
    <p>Spoken parallel corpora are useful in building speech-to-speech applications.</p>
    <p>Costly: Laborious with respect to translation and interpretation</p>
    <p>Available corpora:</p>
    <p>Contain unexpressive speech (e.g. interpreted)  Do not capture spontaneous spoken language traits</p>
    <p>(e.g. read)  Lack one-to-one alignment between words/sentences</p>
    <p>(e.g. constrained conversations)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dubbed movies as a resource</p>
    <p>Popular movies, documentaries, TV shows are dubbed in many countries*.</p>
    <p>A good resource for obtaining bilingual data:</p>
    <p>(1) Available parallel audio data in dubbed movies. (2) Transcripts available with time information in subtitles.</p>
    <p>Expressive</p>
    <p>Speech!</p>
    <p>Movie still from The Man Who Knew Too Much (1956)  Universal Pictures</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Dubbing in European Countries</p>
    <p>Image source: Wikipedia - Dubbing (filmmaking)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proposed Method</p>
    <p>Automatic extraction of segmented parallel sentences with prosodic parameters</p>
    <p>Input: Bilingual audio and subtitles pair  Output: Aligned bilingual sentences annotated with prosodic features</p>
    <p>Key points:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology Overview</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Stage 1: Sentence Segmentation</p>
    <p>Use subtitle time-information to find script location in audio</p>
    <p>SRT subtitle file</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Stage 1: Sentence Segmentation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Stage 2: Prosodic Parameter Extraction</p>
    <p>ProsodyPro1 library used for prosodic feature extraction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Stage 3: Parallel Sentence Alignment</p>
    <p>Goal: Given sentence s1 in lang. 1 find corresponding sentence s2 in lang.2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Applying the Methodology</p>
    <p>Three movies processed:</p>
    <p>The Man Who Knew Too Much (1956)  Slow West (2015)  The Perfect Guy (2015)</p>
    <p>Films originally in English, dubbed to Spanish.</p>
    <p>Audio extracted from DVD using Libav1</p>
    <p>English and Spanish subtitles obtained from opensubtitles2.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Currently obtained corpus</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Shortcomings</p>
    <p>Copyright restrictions for distributing the corpus.</p>
    <p>Main bottlenecks in capturing data:</p>
    <p>Hinders audio-text alignment</p>
    <p>Processing The Man Who Knew Too Much</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sub-dub differences Extracted English (Sub + audio) Spanish Sub Spanish Dub</p>
    <p>yes Daddy , you're sure I've never been to Africa before ?</p>
    <p>Pap , ests seguro de que nunca estuve antes en frica ?</p>
    <p>Papa, ests seguro que no habamos estado ya en frica?</p>
    <p>no It looks familiar. Me parece conocido. Todo esto ya lo conozco.</p>
    <p>yes You saw the same scenery last summer driving to Las Vegas .</p>
    <p>Viste el mismo panorama el verano pasado cuando manejamos a Las Vegas .</p>
    <p>Vimos un paisaje muy parecido cuando fuimos a Las Vegas</p>
    <p>yes Where Daddy lost all that money at the crap ...</p>
    <p>Claro , donde pap perdi todo ese dinero en la mesa</p>
    <p>Ah claro, donde pap perdi toda el dinero en la mesa de juego?</p>
    <p>no Hey, look! Miren! Hey mirad!</p>
    <p>no A Camel. Un camello! Un camello!</p>
    <p>yes Of course this isn't really Africa, honey. Y esto no es realmente frica . Realmente esto no es frica, cario.</p>
    <p>yes It's the French Morocco . Es el Marruecos francs . Es el Marruecos Francs.</p>
    <p>yes Well , it's northern Africa . Es frica del Norte. Bueno, es frica del Norte.</p>
    <p>yes Still seems like Las Vegas . An se parece a Las Vegas . Pues, sigue parecindose a Las Vegas.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Automatic building of multimodal bilingual corpora from dubbed media</p>
    <p>Speech, text, prosody</p>
    <p>Conversational speech  Useful for speech-to-speech translation applications</p>
    <p>Works on any language pair (with trained acoustic model)</p>
    <p>No further training needed</p>
    <p>Code available at http://www.github.com/TalnUPF/movie2parallelDB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>E.g. p2fa (based on CMU Sphinx ASR system)</p>
    <p>Instead of directory structure only</p>
    <p>Identifying the speaker of each sentence</p>
    <p>Depending on agreement with Copyright holders</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions? Suggestions?</p>
    <p>Directly to author: alp.oktem@upf.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Appendix A: State of the Art Corpora</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Appendix B: ProsodyPro Files</p>
    <p>Some of the files generated by ProsodyPro</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
