<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 1</p>
    <p>Minimizing Energy and Maximizing Network Lifetime Multicasting in Wireless Ad Hoc Networks</p>
    <p>Weifa Liang</p>
    <p>Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>Australian National University</p>
    <p>Canberra, ACT 0200, Australia</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 3</p>
    <p>Most mobile nodes in a wireless ad hoc network are powered by energy</p>
    <p>limited batteries, the limited battery lifetime imposes a constraint on the</p>
    <p>network performance. Therefore, energy efficiency is paramount of im</p>
    <p>portance in the design of routing protocols for the applications in such a</p>
    <p>network to enhance the network lifetime.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 4</p>
    <p>Given a wireless ad hoc network M = (N, A), a source node s, and a desti</p>
    <p>nation set D ( N), the minimizing energy and maximizing network lifetime</p>
    <p>multicast problem is to construct a multicast tree rooted at the source and</p>
    <p>spanning the nodes in D such that the minimum residual battery energy</p>
    <p>among the nodes is maximized and at the same time the sum of transmis</p>
    <p>sion energies at non-leaf nodes is minimized.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 5</p>
    <p>Given a constant 0 &lt;   1, we aim to find such a multicast tree that the</p>
    <p>total transmission energy consumption is minimized under the constraint</p>
    <p>that the minimum residual battery energy among the nodes is no less than</p>
    <p>times of the optimum.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 6</p>
    <p>An approximation algorithm with an approximation ratio of 4 ln K, if the</p>
    <p>network is symmetric</p>
    <p>An approximation algorithm with an approximation ratio of O(K ) oth</p>
    <p>erwise</p>
    <p>where K is the number of destination nodes,  is constant with 0 &lt;   1.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 7</p>
    <p>Consider source-initiated multicast sessions. The wireless ad hoc network</p>
    <p>is modeled by a graph M = (N, A), where N is the set of nodes with |N| =</p>
    <p>n, a directed edge u, v  A if node v is within the transmission range of</p>
    <p>u. Assume the nodes in M are stationary, and each node is equipped with</p>
    <p>omnidirectional antennas.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 8</p>
    <p>In this model each node has a number of power levels. For a transmission</p>
    <p>from node u to node v, separated by a distance du,v, to guarantee that v</p>
    <p>is within the transmission range of u, the transmission power at node u is</p>
    <p>modeled to be proportional to d u,v, where  is a parameter that typically</p>
    <p>takes on a value between 2 and 4.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 9</p>
    <p>A wireless ad hoc network is symmetric if there is always a corresponding</p>
    <p>power level with the same amount of power for two neighboring nodes u and</p>
    <p>v, i.e., there is a power level with power d u,v at u and v respectively if u and v</p>
    <p>are the neighbors.</p>
    <p>Otherwise, the network is asymmetric.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 10</p>
    <p>Most existing studies focused on either prolonging the network lifetime or</p>
    <p>minimizing the total energy consumption of a multicst (broadcast) tree.</p>
    <p>A few studies have taken into account the above two conflicting objectives</p>
    <p>by proposing heuristics.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 11</p>
    <p>The problem is to construct a multicast tree such that the network lifetime</p>
    <p>is maximized. We show that the maximizing network lifetime broadcast</p>
    <p>problem (MNLB for short), a special case of the maximizing network lifetime</p>
    <p>multicast problem (MNLM for short), is polynomially solvable, So is MNLM.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 12</p>
    <p>Symmetric case: An auxiliary, node-weighted, undirected graph G = (V, E, )</p>
    <p>is constructed as follows.</p>
    <p>For each node vi  N, let wi,1, wi,2 . . . , wi,li be adjustable power at its li power</p>
    <p>levels.</p>
    <p>w i,1</p>
    <p>w i,2</p>
    <p>w</p>
    <p>w</p>
    <p>i,2</p>
    <p>i,1</p>
    <p>i s 0</p>
    <p>u</p>
    <p>u</p>
    <p>u</p>
    <p>u</p>
    <p>i,l1 ii,l1</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>i,li,l i i</p>
    <p>Mobile vertex</p>
    <p>Power vertex</p>
    <p>Figure 1: The widget Gi = (Vi, Ei) for node vi</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 13</p>
    <p>Algorithm for symmetric networks. It consists of two steps.</p>
    <p>Find an approximate, minimum node-Steiner stree in G</p>
    <p>Transform the found tree into a multicast routing tree in M.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 14</p>
    <p>Asymmetric case: An auxiliary, edge-weighted, directed graph G = (V, E, 1)</p>
    <p>is constructed. A widget Gi = (Vi, Ei) for each node vi  N is built, where</p>
    <p>Vi = {si, vi,1, vi,2, . . . , vi,li} and Ei = {si, vi,l | 1  l  li},</p>
    <p>i,k1 w</p>
    <p>i,k w</p>
    <p>i,2 w</p>
    <p>w i,1</p>
    <p>v</p>
    <p>v i,1</p>
    <p>v i,k1</p>
    <p>v i,k</p>
    <p>i,2</p>
    <p>i s</p>
    <p>Figure 2: The widget Gi = (Vi, Ei) for node vi</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 15</p>
    <p>Algorithm for asymmetric networks, it consists of</p>
    <p>Find an approximate, minimum directed Steiner tree in G</p>
    <p>Transform the rooted directed tree into a multicast routing tree.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 16</p>
    <p>The algorithm for symmetric networks consists of two stages.</p>
    <p>Stage 1 is to remove those potential links from G that result in the net</p>
    <p>work lifetime less than  times of the optimum if they are used to trans</p>
    <p>form the multicast message.</p>
    <p>Stage 2 is to find an approximate, minimum-energy multicast tree in the</p>
    <p>subnetwork.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 17</p>
    <p>Algorithm Balan Symm Multicast Tree (N, s, D, )</p>
    <p>Step 1. Find No pt(M) using the auxiliary directed graph G = (N, A, w).</p>
    <p>Step 2. Construct a node-weighted, auxiliary graph G = (V, E, ), where</p>
    <p>(v) = rc(u)  du,v for each power vertex v derived from a mobile vertex u,.</p>
    <p>Step 3. An auxiliary graph G1 = (V, E, ) is induced from G by removing</p>
    <p>those power vertices v and the edges incident to them if (v) &lt; No pt(M).</p>
    <p>Step 4. Another graph G2 = (V, E, ) is constructed, and each power</p>
    <p>vertex v  V in G2 derived from u is assigned (v) = rc(u)  (v) = du,v.</p>
    <p>Step 5. Find an approximate, minimum node-Steiner tree Ta p p in G2.</p>
    <p>Step 6. Transform Ta p p into a valid multicast tree.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 18</p>
    <p>Theorem 1 Given a symmetric wireless ad hoc network M = (N, A), a source,</p>
    <p>a destination set D, and a given constant  with 0 &lt;   1, there is an approxi</p>
    <p>mation algorithm for the minimizing energy and maximizing network lifetime</p>
    <p>multicast problem, which delivers such a solution that the total energy con</p>
    <p>sumption in the tree is within 4 ln K times of the optimum, while the minimum</p>
    <p>residual battery energy among the nodes in M is no less than  times of the</p>
    <p>optimum.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 19</p>
    <p>The minimizing energy and maximizing network lifetime multicast prob</p>
    <p>lem in asymmetric networks can be dealt similarly. Instead of working in a</p>
    <p>node-weighted, undirected auxiliary graph G, an edge-weighted, directed aux</p>
    <p>iliary graph G will be used, and each directed edge from a mobile vertex u</p>
    <p>to its power vertex v is assigned a weight (u, v) = rc(u)  du,v.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 20</p>
    <p>Algorithm Balan Asymm Multicast Tree (N, s, D, )</p>
    <p>Step 1. Find No pt(M) using G = (N, A, w);</p>
    <p>Step 2. Construct an edge-weighted, directed auxiliary graph G = (V, E, ),</p>
    <p>where (u, v) = rc(u)  du,v for each directed edge v, u derived from a mo</p>
    <p>bile vertex u.</p>
    <p>Step 3. G1 = (V, E, ) is induced from G by removing those directed edges</p>
    <p>u, v if (u, v) &lt; No pt(M).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 21</p>
    <p>Algorithm Balan Asymm Multicast Tree (N, s, D, )</p>
    <p>Step 4. Another auxiliary graph G2 = (V, E, ) whose topology is identi</p>
    <p>cal to G1 is constructed. Assign each directed edge u, v in G2 a new weight</p>
    <p>(u, v) = du,v.</p>
    <p>Step 5. Find an approximate, minimum directed Steiner tree Ta p p in G2</p>
    <p>rooted at the source.</p>
    <p>Step 6. Transform Ta p p into a valid multicast tree.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 22</p>
    <p>Theorem 2 Given an asymmetric ad hoc wireless network M(N, A), a destina</p>
    <p>tion set D, and a constant  with 0 &lt;   1, there is an approximation algo</p>
    <p>rithm for finding a directed multicast tree rooted at the source and spanning</p>
    <p>the nodes in D. The solution delivered is O(|D|) times of the optimum un</p>
    <p>der the constraint that the minimum residual battery energy energy among</p>
    <p>the nodes is no less than  times of the optimum, where  is constant with</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China Tour 23</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
