<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Write Amplification Reduction in FlashBased SSDs Through Extent-Based</p>
    <p>Temperature Identification</p>
    <p>Mansour Shafaei Peter Desnoyers Jim Fitzpatrick</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Background  Related Work  Extent-Based Temperature Identification</p>
    <p>Evaluations  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background  Performance of flash-based storage dominated</p>
    <p>by  Cleaning costs (Write Amplification)</p>
    <p>The number of internal copies required before erasing blocks</p>
    <p>WA reduction  Selection (Non-predictive)</p>
    <p>Cost-Benefit based block selection  Placement (Predictive)</p>
    <p>Hot/Cold data segregation  High performance  Requires write frequency/recency tracking</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Temperature Identification Schemes  Implicit</p>
    <p>Length heuristic  Short host writes  shorter-lived data</p>
    <p>Inaccuracy issues</p>
    <p>Explicit  Per LBA data access tracking</p>
    <p>EWMA  Requiring excessive resources</p>
    <p>Approximated  E.g., Multiple Hash Functions (MHF) (Hsieh et al.) and</p>
    <p>Multiple Bloom Filters (MBFs) (Park et al.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Density-based clustering  Data temperature identification can be</p>
    <p>considered as a density-based stream clustering problem  Well-studied subject in the AI domain</p>
    <p>Definition  Finding arbitrary shape clusters based on the</p>
    <p>density of data in a given address space  Forming dense clusters separated by sparse areas</p>
    <p>Types</p>
    <p>Grid-Based MicroCluster -Based</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Applicability of Density-Based Clustering to Storage Workloads  Running trace driven test to measure:</p>
    <p>Number of extents needed for accurate identification</p>
    <p>Accuracy loss by merging hot extents separated by small amounts of cold data</p>
    <p>Required extents Accuracy Loss</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extent-Based Temperature Identification (ETI)  Beginning with a single extent covering the entire</p>
    <p>address space</p>
    <p>Extent and counter updates based on incoming writes  If boundaries of corresponding extent match incoming</p>
    <p>writes offset and length:  Increments the counter</p>
    <p>Otherwise, if # of extents &lt; max. # of allowed extents:  Creates new extents accordingly and increments the counter values</p>
    <p>Else:  Increments the extent counters fully or partially(&gt;%) overwritten</p>
    <p>by the write</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ETI (cont.)  Periodic aging</p>
    <p>Divide all counters by two and round off  Merge all adjacent hot extents with equal counter</p>
    <p>values  Merge all adjacent cold (counter &lt; ) extents</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ETI Overhead  More complex</p>
    <p>Requiring an ordered search structure vs. Bloom filter</p>
    <p>Per write operation execution  Vs. existing schemes per block operations  Up to 96% reduction among available traces</p>
    <p>Optimized search by taking advantage of spatial locality  Beginning each search at the location of latest</p>
    <p>accessed extent</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Setup  Environment</p>
    <p>FTLSim  A high-level SSD simulator written in C and Python</p>
    <p>Page-map FTL  32K of 128-page blocks ~ 16 GB  7% spare factor  A global greedy cleaning algorithm with hot and cold</p>
    <p>data segregation</p>
    <p>Metric  Write Amplification</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Setup (Cont.)  Schemes</p>
    <p>ETI (max. # of extents=2048)  MHF (table size=2048, CRC HFs)  MBF (BF size=2048, CRC HFs)</p>
    <p>Workload  Selected MSR traces  A series of traces provided by an industrial partner</p>
    <p>One RAID-0 and two RAID-6 variants  Two backup applications, a database, a Hadoop HDFS</p>
    <p>cluster, and an unspecified software application</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Comparison  Using ETI</p>
    <p>Up to 21% WA reduction  Never worse than MHF  Only 4% worse in one single trace compared to</p>
    <p>MBF</p>
    <p>MHF MBF ETI</p>
    <p>W ri</p>
    <p>te</p>
    <p>A m</p>
    <p>p li fi c a ti</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>Trace</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Comparison (cont.)  Dedicating more memory resources to the</p>
    <p>implemented hash-based schemes for a more fair comparison  MBFs with twice and 4 times larger BF sizes  Modest improvements in four traces</p>
    <p>Significantly less than what achieved by ETI</p>
    <p>Almost no improvement in two other traces!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  We propose Extent-based Temperature</p>
    <p>Identification (ETI) as a one-dimensional densitybased clustering scheme to get used combined with a dual frontier, page-mapped Greedy translation layer.</p>
    <p>We measure by write amplification reduction unlike previous work which used identification accuracy.</p>
    <p>Results show by up to 21% WA reductions over both Multiple Hash Functions and Multiple Bloom Filters schemes.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
