<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AN OFFLINE CAPTURE THE FLAG-STYLE VIRTUAL MACHINE FOR CYBER SECURITY EDUCATION</p>
    <p>Tom Chothia Chris Novakovic University of Birmingham</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction  A VM to support cyber security education.</p>
    <p>The VM creates unique flags, which the students get if they solve the exercise.</p>
    <p>Flags submitted by students online and used to support marking.</p>
    <p>Comparison of flag only marking vs. traditional continuous assessment marking.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Capture the Flag Competitions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flag We Have Known:  Flag:'a012c434d1ec6db911fda4884de14fdd</p>
    <p>31c3_a5bb3ead8fbc6617374ea3f57f0563d2</p>
    <p>the_snozberries_taste_like_snozberries</p>
    <p>'this is a key</p>
    <p>SECCON{TeaBreakAtWork}</p>
    <p>FLAG(CYBERCONTROLCYBERDATACYBERCOR PORATION)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problems with using CTFs in Education</p>
    <p>Everyone gets the same flag and same infrastructure.</p>
    <p>Short lived intense competitions  We dont want students to win or loose the course.  Not compatible with an 11 week module.</p>
    <p>Live, online competitions use complex infrastructure and need a lot of support.</p>
    <p>IT Services do not support large amounts of hostile attack</p>
    <p>traffic on their network.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Solution</p>
    <p>Web Server</p>
    <p>User space</p>
    <p>SQL Database</p>
    <p>KM Course key Start Up Script</p>
    <p>VM_id</p>
    <p>Alice</p>
    <p>Bob</p>
    <p>VM</p>
    <p>Source code 1</p>
    <p>Source code 2</p>
    <p>{Ex_2:VM_id}KM</p>
    <p>{Ex_4:VM_id}KM</p>
    <p>{Ex_5:VM_id}KM</p>
    <p>Weak Service 1</p>
    <p>Weak Service 2 {Ex_6:VM_id}KM</p>
    <p>{Ex_7:VM_id}KM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exercises  Encryption</p>
    <p>Students need to write code to decrypt RSA &amp; AES: ECB, CBC, CTR, CCM mode encryption.</p>
    <p>Flags are inside the encrypted messages.  Perform known plaintext bit flipping attacks.</p>
    <p>Access control  Start up script writes flags to files and sets access permissions.  Subtle errors in the access control allow access to these flags and</p>
    <p>the shadow file  E.g. chained confused deputy using setuid.</p>
    <p>Cracking the passwords gives access to account with flag  Root &amp; some other passwords cannot be cracked.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Examples: Protocol Questions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Student Feedback  Each time taught it has been the most popular course in the school</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Assessment  We used the existence of flags to aid human marking of</p>
    <p>written answers and code.</p>
    <p>Flags were required and gave the marker confidence that code worked and that written answers were correct.  But we gave no marks for just the flags</p>
    <p>Would fully automated marking based only on flags have worked?  Full marking of exercises lets us test this.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flag marking  Difference between a 1st and a very high 1st was showing</p>
    <p>a full and complete understanding. E.g.  Protocols, low 1st: correct, but inefficient attacks and fixes  Protocols, high 1st: most efficient attacks and fixes possible  Reverse engineering, low 1st: right answer found by lots of trial and</p>
    <p>error.  Reverse engineering, high 1st: complete understanding of the</p>
    <p>assembly.</p>
    <p>Fully automated flag only marking would be fine for broad classifications, but would not recognize the best students.</p>
    <p>Better than no assessed course work.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Using Flags to Assess Ability</p>
    <p>Could better flag exercises accurately assess ability?  As exercises become harder, luck plays more of a part.  Too many exercises make them a race against time.</p>
    <p>IMHO: Flags are a great way to make CTFs fun, but can</p>
    <p>only play a small part in academic assessment.</p>
    <p>Side note: the best CTF teams will write up their CTF results.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Plagiarism  Plagiarism is an issue with all coursework.</p>
    <p>4 cases of plagiarism on 3 iterations of the course.  Four submitted the same flags &amp; almost the same answers.  Two students submitted different flags &amp; almost the same answers.  Two students submitted the same flags.  Another two students submitted the same flags.</p>
    <p>Roughly half the rate of plagiarism as before flags.</p>
    <p>Questioned informally, students said they didnt plagiarise flags because they had to do written answers and vice versa.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other issues</p>
    <p>Other problems with flag only marking:  Value of written solutions and feedback  Written work stops flag plagiarism</p>
    <p>Online monitoring of token submissions.  Very useful.</p>
    <p>Students can bypass system</p>
    <p>Good students that finish exercises early, encouraged to do this  Designed to be harder to bypass exercises than solve correctly.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary  Design for offline CTF-style, cyber security education VM.</p>
    <p>Each students VM contains unique flags.  Very popular with students but still difficult exercises.  Publically available, no restrictions on use  http://www.cs.bham.ac.uk/~tpc/SecEduVM/</p>
    <p>Flags support human marking and discourage plagiarism.</p>
    <p>Marking based only on flags would not have accurately assessed good students.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
