<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>On the Hardness of Being Truthful</p>
    <p>Michael Schapira Yale University and UC Berkeley</p>
    <p>Joint work with Christos Papadimitriou and Yaron Singer (2008),</p>
    <p>and with Elchanan Mossel, Christos Papadimitriou and Yaron Singer</p>
    <p>(2009)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>On the Agenda</p>
    <p>Algorithmic mechanism design</p>
    <p>An impossibility result: Truthfulness and computation can clash!</p>
    <p>Extending our results to combinatorial auctions</p>
    <p>Open questions and directions for future research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Designing Algorithms for Environments With Selfish</p>
    <p>Agents  Computational concerns:</p>
    <p>bounded computational resources optimization</p>
    <p>Economic concerns: truthful behaviour fairness</p>
    <p>computatio nal</p>
    <p>efficiency</p>
    <p>incentivecompatibilit</p>
    <p>y</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithmic Mechanism Design</p>
    <p>Can these different desiderata coexist?</p>
    <p>The central problem in Algorithmic Mechanism Design [Nisan-Ronen]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Paradigmatic Problem: Combinatorial Auctions</p>
    <p>A set of m items on sale {1,m}.</p>
    <p>n bidders {1,,n}. Each bidder i has valuation function vi : 2[m]  R0.</p>
    <p>Goal: find a partition of the items between the bidders S1,,Sn such that social welfare i vi(Si) is maximized</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Do We Want?</p>
    <p>Quality of the solution: As close to the optimum as possible.</p>
    <p>Computationally tractable: Polynomial running time (in n and m).</p>
    <p>Truthful: Motivate (via payments) bidders to report their true values.  The utility of each agent is ui = vi(S)  pi  Solution concepts: dominant strategies, ex-post</p>
    <p>Nash.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can Truth and Computation Coexist?</p>
    <p>easy + easy = easy? ]canonically hard problems  Feigenbaum-Shenker[</p>
    <p>NO! ]Papadimitriou-S-Singer[</p>
    <p>Hard (Clique)</p>
    <p>Easy (in APX, e.g.,</p>
    <p>matching)</p>
    <p>Easy (social</p>
    <p>welfare max. in auctions) Hard</p>
    <p>(max-min fairness in auctions)</p>
    <p>Computatio n</p>
    <p>Incentive s</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Combinatorial Public Project Problem (CPPP)</p>
    <p>Motivation: Find the best overlay network.</p>
    <p>source nodes</p>
    <p>destination nodespotential overlay nodes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Combinatorial Public Projects</p>
    <p>Set of n agents; Set of m resources;</p>
    <p>Each agent i has a valuation function: vi : 2[m]  R0</p>
    <p>Objective: Given a parameter k, choose a set of resources S* of size k which maximizes the social welfare:</p>
    <p>S* = argmaxi i vi(S) S [m], |S|=k</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Assumptions Regarding Each Valuation Function</p>
    <p>Normalized: v() = 0</p>
    <p>Non-decreasing: v(S)  v(T) S T</p>
    <p>Submodular: v(S{j})  v(S)  v(T{j})  v(T) S T</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Special Cases</p>
    <p>Elections for a committee: The agents are voters, resources are potential candidates.</p>
    <p>Overlay networks: The agents are source nodes, resources are potential overlay nodes.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Are Combinatorial Public Projects Easy?</p>
    <p>Computational Perspective: A 1-1/e approximation ratio is achievable (not truthful!)  A tight lower bound exists [Feige].</p>
    <p>Strategic Perspective: A truthful solution is achievable via VCG payments (but NP-hard to obtain)</p>
    <p>What about achieving both simultaneously?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theorem (Informal): [Papadimitriou-SSinger]</p>
    <p>Any algorithm for CPPP that is both truthful and computationally-efficient does not have an approximation ratio better than 1/m  Even for n=2.  Tight! [S-Singer].</p>
    <p>Two models:  Communication complexity.  Computational complexity.</p>
    <p>Truth and Computation Dont Mix</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Combinatorial Public Projects: The Proof</p>
    <p>Complexit y theory</p>
    <p>mechanis m design</p>
    <p>combinator ics</p>
    <p>(the hardness of truthful</p>
    <p>algorithms)</p>
    <p>(what do truthful algorithms look</p>
    <p>like?)</p>
    <p>(the combinatorial properties of</p>
    <p>truthful algorithms)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theorem: Any truthful algorithm for CPPP that approximates better than 1/m requires exponential communication.</p>
    <p>Communication Complexity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proving the Lower Bound</p>
    <p>Lemma 1: Any maximal-in-range (MIR) algorithm for CPPP that approximates better than 1/m requires exponential communication in m.</p>
    <p>Lemma 2 (!): An algorithm for the combinatorial public project problem is truthful iff it is MIR;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>all sets of resources of size k</p>
    <p>Maximal-In-Range Algorithms (= VCG-Based)</p>
    <p>Definition:</p>
    <p>A is MIR if there is some</p>
    <p>RA {|S | = k| S [m]}</p>
    <p>s.t. A(v1,v2) = argmax S in R v1(S) + v2(S)</p>
    <p>* we shall refer to RA as As range. RA</p>
    <p>A</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lower Bound For MIR</p>
    <p>Inapproximability Lemma: Any MIR algorithm for CPPP that approximates better than 1/m requires exponential communication in m.</p>
    <p>Proof in two steps: [Dobzinski-Nisan]</p>
    <p>Proposition 1: In order to get an approximation better than 1/m, the range must be exponentially large (in m).</p>
    <p>Even for n=1. Simple (succinctly described) valuations.</p>
    <p>Proposition 2: Maximizing over a range RA requires communicating |RA| bits.</p>
    <p>Even for n=2. We use the fact that valuations can be exponentially long.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Characterization Lemma</p>
    <p>Characterization Lemma: An algorithm for CPPP is truthful iff it is MIR</p>
    <p>Theorem (Roberts 79): For unrestricted valuation functions any truthful algorithm is MIR.  Actually, affine maximizer</p>
    <p>We use machinery from simplified proofs of Roberts Theorem [Lavi-Mualem-Nisan].  But our domain is severely restricted!  But our domain isnt open!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Characterizing Truthfulness (cntd)</p>
    <p>unrestricted valuations single-parameter</p>
    <p>domains</p>
    <p>Only MIR (Roberts 1979)</p>
    <p>Many non-MIR algorithms</p>
    <p>(truthfulness is well-understood)</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>combinatorial auctions, combinatorial pubic projects,</p>
    <p>Not always MIR ]auction environments: Lavi-Mualem-Nisan, Bartal-Gonen-Nisan[</p>
    <p>Truthful = MIR for CPPP!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>To prove our results we had to assume that the ``input can be exponential in m. Realistic?</p>
    <p>If users have succinctly described valuations then computationalcomplexity techniques are required. No such impossibility results are known.</p>
    <p>Computational Hardness of Truthfulness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Proof Revisited</p>
    <p>Characterization Lemma: an algorithm is truthful if it is an affine-maximizer. Observation: The proof only requires succinctly</p>
    <p>described valuations.</p>
    <p>Inapproximability Lemma: Any affine maximizer which approximates better than m requires exponential communication. Proposition 1: In order to get an</p>
    <p>approximation better than m, the range must be exponential.</p>
    <p>Proposition 2: Maximizing over a range RA requires communicating |RA| bits.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>New Proof</p>
    <p>Characterization Lemma: an algorithm is truthful if it is an affine-maximizer.</p>
    <p>Inapproximability Lemma: No affine maximizer can approximate better than m unless [computational assumption] is false.</p>
    <p>Proposition 1: In order to get an approximation better than m, the range must be exponential.</p>
    <p>New Challenge: Maximizing over an exponential-size range in polynomial time implies that [computational assumption] is false. New technique.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All sets of resources of size k</p>
    <p>Computational Complexity Hardness</p>
    <p>For many families of succinctly described valuations CPPP is NP-hard. Special case: MAX-K-COVER [Feige]</p>
    <p>So, optimizing over the set of all possible solutions is hard.</p>
    <p>What about optimizing over a set of solutions of exponential size? Intuition - also hard!</p>
    <p>RA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analogous Problem: SATL</p>
    <p>You are given a language L {0,1}n s.t. L is exponentially dense, i.e., |L|  2n (for some constant 0&lt;1)</p>
    <p>SATL: Given a CNF boolean formula determine whether or not it has a satisfying assignment in L.</p>
    <p>Conjecture: SATL is NP-hard for every exponentially dense L.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Intuition</p>
    <p>Let L = {s| s is of the form 000xxx}</p>
    <p>For this L, SATL is obviously NP-hard.</p>
    <p>General approach: Find a smaller SAT hiding in SATL. Not too small!</p>
    <p>n/2 n/2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The VC Dimension</p>
    <p>universe</p>
    <p>x x x 4 x</p>
    <p>collection of subsets</p>
    <p>R</p>
    <p>shattered set</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lower Bounding the VC Dimension</p>
    <p>The Sauer-Shelah Lemma: Let R be a collection of subsets of a universe U. Then, there exists a subset E of U such that:</p>
    <p>E is shattered by R.</p>
    <p>|E|  ( log(|R|)/log(|U|) ).</p>
    <p>Think of L as a collection of subsets of the universe of variables.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sauer-Shelah Lemma (for SATL)</p>
    <p>Let L be some exponentially dense language.</p>
    <p>Then, there exists a set N of n variables (for some constant 0&lt;1) s.t. all assignments for these variables are in L.</p>
    <p>Are we done? Did we prove that SATL is NP-hard?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>No!  We do not know how to find (approximate)</p>
    <p>N in polynomial time. Hard! [Papadimitriou-Yannakakis, Schaefer, Mossel-Umans]</p>
    <p>Theorem: If SATL is in P then SAT has polynomial-sized circuits.</p>
    <p>What about a probabilistic reduction from SAT? A nave approach fails. Ajtais probabilistic version of the SauerShelah Lemma helps in our case!</p>
    <p>What about SATL? (CIRCUIT-SATL is different)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>So</p>
    <p>Truthulness and computation can clash! In two complexity models.</p>
    <p>APX is not preserved under truthfulness (unlike P and NP).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Back to Combinatorial Auctions</p>
    <p>A set of m items on sale {1,m}.</p>
    <p>n bidders {1,,n}. Each bidder i has valuation function vi : 2[m]  R0.</p>
    <p>Goal: find a partition of the items between the bidders S1,,Sn such that social welfare i vi(Si) is maximized</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sounds Familiar?</p>
    <p>Easy from an economic perspective.  VCG!</p>
    <p>Easy to solve computationally in many intersting cases.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Huge Gaps!</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>non-truthful:</p>
    <p>constant approximation</p>
    <p>ratios (subadditive, submodular)</p>
    <p>truthful:</p>
    <p>non-constant approximations</p>
    <p>are known (subadditive, submodular)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What About Combinatorial Auctions?</p>
    <p>Complexit y theory</p>
    <p>mechanis m design</p>
    <p>combinator ics</p>
    <p>(the embedding of NP-hard problems)</p>
    <p>(Characterization of truthful algorithms,</p>
    <p>based on Roberts Theorem)</p>
    <p>(VC dimension)</p>
    <p>consider a specific class of algorithms</p>
    <p>(MIR = VCG based).</p>
    <p>generalize the VC dimension to</p>
    <p>handle partitions of a universe.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Case of 2 Bidders</p>
    <p>Not trivial even for n=2!</p>
    <p>Not trivial even for if bidders valuation functions are of a very restricted form.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simple 2-bidder Combinatorial Auctions</p>
    <p>A set of m items for sale {1,m}.</p>
    <p>2 bidders. Each bidder i has an additive valuation with a spending constraint vi.  per-item values ai1,,aim  maximum spending value bi  For every bundle S, vi(S)=min {j in S aij , bi},</p>
    <p>Goal: find a partition of the items between the 2 bidders (S1,S2) such that social welfare v1(S1)+v2(S2) is maximized</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Truthful vs. Unrestricted Algortihms</p>
    <p>A non-truthful FPTAS exists [AndelmanMansour]</p>
    <p>A simple MIR algorithm obtains a approximation ratio.  Simply bundle all items together.  The best truthful appx. for this problem</p>
    <p>to date.</p>
    <p>Is this the best we can do?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Yes! (Sort Of)</p>
    <p>Theorem [Mossel-Papadimitriou-S-Singer]: No computationally-efficient MIR mechanism M obtains an appx-ratio of + in the allocate-all-items case.  unless NP has polynomial size circuits.</p>
    <p>Techniques similar to those used in the proof for CPPP.</p>
    <p>Removing the allocate-all-items assumption is not trivial!  If we just allocate unallocated items arbitrarily we</p>
    <p>might lose the MIR property!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Intuition</p>
    <p>MIR algorithm A</p>
    <p>RA</p>
    <p>M is (implicitly) optimally solving a 2-item auction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Intuition</p>
    <p>We wish to prove the existence of a subset of items E that is shattered by As range (RA).  Embed a small NP-hard auction in E.  Not too small! (|E|  m)</p>
    <p>VC dimension  We need to bound the VC dimension of</p>
    <p>collections of partitions!  Of independent interest.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VC Dimension of Partitions</p>
    <p>We want to prove an analogue of the Sauer-Shelah Lemma for the case of partitions of a universe.  That do not necessarily cover the</p>
    <p>universe.</p>
    <p>Problem: The size of the collection of partitions does not tell us much.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Analogue of the SauerShelah Lemma [Mossel</p>
    <p>Papadimitriou-S-Singer]</p>
    <p>Definition: A partition of a universe is a pair of disjoint subsets of the universe.  Does not necessarily exhaust the universe!  We refer to a partition that does exhaust</p>
    <p>the universe as a covering partition.</p>
    <p>Definition: Two partitions, (T1,T2) and (T1,T2) , are said to be b-far (or at distance b) if |T1 U T2| + |T1 U T2|  b.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Analogue of the SauerShelah Lemma [Mossel-Papadimitriou</p>
    <p>S-Singer]</p>
    <p>Lemma: Let &gt; 0 be some constant. Let R be a collection of partitions of a universe U, such that every two partitions in R are |U|far.</p>
    <p>Then, there exists a subset E of U such that:</p>
    <p>Rs projection on E contains all covering partitions of E.</p>
    <p>|E|  ( log(|R|)/log(|U|) ).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Directions for Future Research</p>
    <p>Relaxing the computational assumptions.</p>
    <p>Characterizing truthful algorithms for combinatorial auctions.</p>
    <p>Lower bounds for MIR algorithms for combinatorial auctions.  Recent results by Buchfuhrer and Umans</p>
    <p>obtained using our techniques and new ones.</p>
    <p>Many intriguing questions regarding the VC dimension of partitions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank YouThank You</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
