<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TClouds No. 257243 Trustworthy Clouds - Privacy and Resilience for Internet-scale Critical Infrastructure</p>
    <p>Challenges for Provenance in Cloud Compu5ng Imad Abbadi and John Lyle</p>
    <p>Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>University of Oxford</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud compu5ng is a model for enabling convenient, on- demand network access to a shared pool of configurable compu6ng resources (e.g., networks, servers, storage, applica5ons, and services) that can be rapidly provisioned and released with minimal management effort or service provider interac5on.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why cloud compu5ng?</p>
    <p>Popular  Low barrier to entry  Cost effec5ve  Incredibly scalable  Resilient and reliable (in theory)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>hWp://geekandpoke.typepad.com/geekandpoke/2009/03/let-the-clouds-make-your-life-easier.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why provenance?</p>
    <p>Clouds hide complexity  Some5mes the complexity maWers.  Common request: In which country is my computa5on happening?</p>
    <p>Forensics, billing, security  Clouds go wrong  Errors can be very difficult to track down without provenance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How are clouds structured?</p>
    <p>User Properties</p>
    <p>Infrastructure proper6es</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges  Building a logical sequence of events  Involves data from every layer, at mul5ple 5me intervals</p>
    <p>Combining this data currently very difficult, oaen ad- hoc.</p>
    <p>Not just storage, but all levels of the cloud.  Requires common data structures and seman5cs at all layers</p>
    <p>Need to trust the cloud providers  Protec5ng log data  Not losing the usability benefits</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example scenario</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TClouds Project</p>
    <p>Building trustworthy, resilient cloud systems  Two example cases  Healthcare  Public ligh5ng</p>
    <p>Provenance opportunity  Top-down approach (design phase)  BoWom-up approach (pragma5c)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Clouds are really dynamic, and hide a lot of complexity</p>
    <p>Errors, security incidents and privacy requirements require this complexity to be revealed</p>
    <p>Oaen data and execu5on provenance doesnt exist, or could be false</p>
    <p>What is the best approach for providing provenance in the cloud?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Collec5ng context data in webinos  Cross-device applica5on environment</p>
    <p>Mobile, Car, Set-top-box, PC  Think Java but for web applica5ons</p>
    <p>Use &amp; crea5on of contextual data  Loca5on, social graph, proximity sensors, etc  Shared between devices in a big, synchronised database</p>
    <p>Used for:  BeWer user interface &amp; experience  Analy5cs and adver5sing  Making access control decisions</p>
    <p>Privacy and reliability concerns!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>App</p>
    <p>Policy enforcement</p>
    <p>Smartphone Car Smart TV PC</p>
    <p>Context Store</p>
    <p>App makes context query</p>
    <p>App running on Smartphone</p>
    <p>Make query for context data</p>
    <p>Policy query: access control</p>
    <p>Sensor data, loca5on, user data, social network data,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Real conclusion</p>
    <p>I have two projects which would benefit from introducing provenance  Webinos  TClouds</p>
    <p>Can this audience provide any sugges5ons or warnings?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you.</p>
    <p>Any ques5ons?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
