<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VC v. VCG: Inapproximability of Combinatorial</p>
    <p>Auctions via Generalizations of the VC Dimension</p>
    <p>Michael Schapira Yale University and UC Berkeley</p>
    <p>Joint work with Christos Papadimitriou and Yaron Singer (2008) and</p>
    <p>Elchanan Mossel, Christos Papadimitriou and Yaron Singer</p>
    <p>(2009)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Auctions: Different Concerns</p>
    <p>Computational concerns: bounded computational resources optimization</p>
    <p>Economic concerns: truthful behaviour fairness</p>
    <p>computatio nal</p>
    <p>efficiency</p>
    <p>incentivecompatibilit</p>
    <p>y</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithmic Mechanism Design</p>
    <p>Can these different desiderata coexist?</p>
    <p>The central problem in Algorithmic Mechanism Design [Nisan-Ronen]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Illustration: Restricted Combinatorial Auctions</p>
    <p>A set of m items for sale {1,m}.</p>
    <p>n bidders {1,,n}. Each bidder i has an additive valuation with a spending constraint vi.  per-item values ai1,,aim  maximum spending value bi  For every bundle S, vi(S)=min {j in S aij , bi},</p>
    <p>Goal: find a partition of the items between the bidders S1,,Sn such that social welfare i vi(Si) is maximized</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Do We Want?</p>
    <p>Quality of the solution: As close to the optimum as possible.</p>
    <p>Computationally tractable: Polynomial running time (in n and m).</p>
    <p>Truthful: Motivate (via payments) agents to report their true values.  The utility of each user is ui = vi(S)  pi  Solution concepts: dominant strategies, ex-post</p>
    <p>Nash.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>State of the Art</p>
    <p>Easy from an economic perspective.  VCG!</p>
    <p>Easy to solve computationally.  NP-hard (even for n=2) [Lehmann-Lehmann-Nisan] but  We can get arbitrarily close to the optimum for</p>
    <p>any constant n (PTAS)! [Andelman-Mansour]</p>
    <p>Can both be achieved simultaneously?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Huge Gap!</p>
    <p>? non-truthful: get arbitrarily close to opt.</p>
    <p>truthful: 1/n-appx mechanism</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Truthfulness and Computation Clash: Combinatorial Public Projects Problem</p>
    <p>(CPPP)</p>
    <p>Orthogonal to combinatorial auctions (elections, overlay networks).</p>
    <p>Easy from a purely economic perspective (VCG), and from a purely computational perspective (in APX).</p>
    <p>Theorem (Informal) [Papadimitriou-S-Singer]:</p>
    <p>No truthful and computationally-efficient mechanism for CPPP obtains a constant approximation ratio.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Combinatorial Public Projects: The Proof</p>
    <p>Complexit y theory</p>
    <p>mechanis m design</p>
    <p>combinator ics</p>
    <p>(the embedding of NP-hard problems)</p>
    <p>(Characterization of truthful</p>
    <p>mechanisms, based on Roberts</p>
    <p>Theorem)</p>
    <p>(VC dimension)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What About Combinatorial Auctions?</p>
    <p>Complexit y theory</p>
    <p>mechanis m design</p>
    <p>combinator ics</p>
    <p>(the embedding of NP-hard problems)</p>
    <p>(Characterization of truthful</p>
    <p>mechanisms, based on Roberts</p>
    <p>Theorem)</p>
    <p>(VC dimension)</p>
    <p>consider a specific class of</p>
    <p>mechanisms (VCG-based).</p>
    <p>generalize the VC dimension to</p>
    <p>handle partitions of a universe.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VCG-Based Mechanisms</p>
    <p>VCG-based = Maximal-In-Range (MIR).</p>
    <p>MIR mechanisms provide the best known (deterministic) approximations for a large variety of problems:  Combinatorial auctions (general, subadditive,</p>
    <p>submodular).  Multi-unit auctions.  Unrelated machine scheduling.</p>
    <p>In fact, sometimes MIR is all you can do. [Roberts, Lavi-Mualem-Nisan, Dobzinski-Sundararajan, Papadimitriou-SSinger]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Maximal-In-Range Mechanisms</p>
    <p>A mechanism M is MIR (= VCG-based) if:</p>
    <p>Theres a fixed subset RM of the possible outcomes (allocations of the m items between the n bidders) = Ms range.</p>
    <p>For every valuation profile (v1,vn) M outputs the optimal partition in RM.</p>
    <p>Example: The trivial (1/n-appx.) mechanism  Bundle all items together.  Allocated them to the highest bidder.</p>
    <p>Fact: MIR mechanisms are truthful (VCG).</p>
    <p>RM</p>
    <p>all partitions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can We Do Better Than the Trivial MIR Mechanism?</p>
    <p>Can we choose RM such that</p>
    <p>the optimum in RM always provides a constant approximation to the global optimum.</p>
    <p>optimizing over RM can be done in a computationallyefficient manner.</p>
    <p>Not for the more general class of submodular valuations! [Dobzinski-Nisan]</p>
    <p>But the input there is assumed to be exponentially large! (exp. communication)  What about succinctly-described valuations?  No computational-complexity results are known!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Case of 2 Bidders</p>
    <p>Not trivial even for n=2!  We shall focus on this case.</p>
    <p>Let us first consider the (more easy) allocate-all-items case.  all outcomes in RM do not leave any item</p>
    <p>unallocated.</p>
    <p>Theorem: No computationally-efficient MIR mechanism M obtains an appx-ratio of + in the allocate-all-items case.  unless NP has polynomial size circuits.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proof</p>
    <p>Let M be a MIR mechanism for the 2bidder case.</p>
    <p>Assume, by contradiction, that M obtains an appx-ratio of (1/2+).</p>
    <p>We shall prove that optimizing over RM implicitly means solving an NPhard problem.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proof (intuition)</p>
    <p>items</p>
    <p>Mechanism M</p>
    <p>RM</p>
    <p>M is (implicitly) optimally solving a 2-item auction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proof</p>
    <p>So, we wish to prove the existence of a subset of items E that is shattered by Ms range (RM).</p>
    <p>Embed a smaller auction in E.</p>
    <p>Not too small! (|E|  m)</p>
    <p>VC dimension!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proof</p>
    <p>Lemma: If a MIR mechanism M obtains an appx-ratio of + in the allocate-all-items case then |RM|  2m (for some constant &gt;0).</p>
    <p>Proof by probabilistic construction.</p>
    <p>Corollary: Bidder 1 can be assigned at least 2m different subsets of items by M.  Denote this collection of subsets by RM,1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proof</p>
    <p>The Sauer-Shelah Lemma: Let R be a collection of subsets of a universe U. Then, there exists a subset E of U such that:</p>
    <p>Rs projection on E is 2E.</p>
    <p>|E|  ( log(|R|)/log(|U|) ).</p>
    <p>Corollary (set R=RM,1): There is a subset of items E, |E|  m, s.t. bidder 1 can be assigned all subsets of E in M.</p>
    <p>Corollary: All partitions of E are induced by RM.  Because all items are allocated.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proof</p>
    <p>We can now conclude that if M optimizes over its range then it is optimally solving an identical auction with m items.  An NP-hard task.</p>
    <p>A non-uniform reduction.  We do not know how to find E in polynomial</p>
    <p>time.</p>
    <p>So No computationally-efficient MIR mechanism M obtains an appx-ratio of + in the allocate-all-items case (unless NP has polynomial size circuits). QED</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Getting Rid of the Allocate-AllItems Assumption</p>
    <p>Not trivial!  If we just allocate unallocated items</p>
    <p>arbitrarily we might lose the MIR property!</p>
    <p>Our approach: Generalizing the VC dimension.  Of independent interest.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Analogue of the SauerShelah Lemma</p>
    <p>Definition: A partition of a universe is a pair of disjoint subsets of the universe.  Does not necessarily exhaust the universe!</p>
    <p>Definition: Two partitions, (T1,T2) and (T1,T2) , are said to be b-far (or at distance b) if |T1 U T2| + |T1 U T2|  b.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Analogue of the SauerShelah Lemma</p>
    <p>Lemma: Let &gt; 0 be some constant. Let R be a collection of partitions of a universe U, such that every two partitions in R are |U|-far. Then, there exists a subset E of U such that:</p>
    <p>Rs projection on E is all partitions of E.</p>
    <p>|E|  ( log(|R|)/log(|U|) ).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Lower Bound</p>
    <p>Theorem: For any MIR mechanism M that obtains an appx-ratio of  + , there exists some R  RM such that</p>
    <p>R is exponential in m.</p>
    <p>Every two partitions in R are m-far (for some constant &gt;0)</p>
    <p>Theorem: No computationally-efficient MIR mechanism M obtains an appx-ratio of +  unless NP has polynomial size circuits.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Directions for Future Research</p>
    <p>A recent result [Buchfuhrer-Umans]: For any constant n, no MIR mechanism M obtains an appx-ratio of 1/n+ (unless NP has polynomial size circuits).  Tight for all constant ns.  Non-constant ns?</p>
    <p>Other classes of valuation functions.</p>
    <p>Characterizing truthful mechanisms for combinatorial auctions.</p>
    <p>Relaxing the computational assumption.</p>
    <p>Many intriguing questions regarding the VC dimension of partitions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank YouThank You</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
