<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ultra-Low Latency SSDs Impact on Overall Energy Efficiency Bryan Harris and Nihat Altiparmak</p>
    <p>Computer Science &amp; Eng. Department University of Louisville</p>
    <p>HotStorage 20</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is Ultra-Low Latency (ULL) data access?</p>
    <p>Device Latency Performance Gap</p>
    <p>(relative to DRAM)</p>
    <p>HDD  10 ms 100,000</p>
    <p>Traditional SSD  100 s 1000</p>
    <p>Ultra-Low Latency SSD  10 s 100</p>
    <p>DRAM  100 ns 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is Optane SSD?</p>
    <p>Based on 3D Xpoint technology by Intel and Micron, using phase</p>
    <p>change memory (PCM)</p>
    <p>Also available as byte addressable DIMM</p>
    <p>Ideal for applications that require low latency access</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation Energy characterization</p>
    <p>Existing studies of Optane SSDs primarily focuses on performance  Energy studies look at only individual device or CPU usage</p>
    <p>Impact on overall system software</p>
    <p>ULL disk IO puts increased pressure on system software  How does this affect power consumption?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HotStorage 20</p>
    <p>Energy Characterization &amp; Impact</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test devices</p>
    <p>Technology Interface Model Capacity</p>
    <p>Magnetic SATA 3.1 WD Black 7200 rpm 4 TB</p>
    <p>Flash SATA 3.1 Samsung 850 EVO 1 TB</p>
    <p>Flash PCIe 3 Samsung 960 EVO 500 GB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental setup</p>
    <p>HOBO plug meter logs power, current, joules, etc., every second.</p>
    <p>fio (Flexible IO tester) generates storage IO workloads</p>
    <p>Image from ONSET online catalog https://www.onsetcomp.com/products/data-loggers/ux120-018/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Storage IO workloads</p>
    <p>Larger data</p>
    <p>requests</p>
    <p>More simultaneous requests</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HotStorage 20</p>
    <p>Observations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observation 1</p>
    <p>At idle, Optane uses more power than Flash SSDs</p>
    <p>Idle vs. active power consumption</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Idle vs. active power consumption</p>
    <p>Observation 2</p>
    <p>Active power increases with lower latency devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Read vs. write power consumption</p>
    <p>HDD (SATA) Flash (SATA) Flash (NVMe) Optane (NVMe)</p>
    <p>Observation 3</p>
    <p>Newer storage generations have greater differences in power consumption between reads and writes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Energy proportionality</p>
    <p>System power Power normalized to peak power observed</p>
    <p>Storage performance utilization IOPS normalized to peak IOPS for each device</p>
    <p>Consuming energy in proportion to the amount of work performed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Energy proportionality</p>
    <p>Reads Writes</p>
    <p>Observation 4</p>
    <p>Newer advancements lead to better energy proportionality</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observation 5</p>
    <p>As latency decreases, pressure on the system software increases, resulting in more overall energy consumption.</p>
    <p>Impact on system software</p>
    <p>Reads Writes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Impact on system software</p>
    <p>Effect on CPU Effect on Power</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overall energy efficiency metrics</p>
    <p>Performance per unit energy</p>
    <p>Bandwidth: Bytes/second</p>
    <p>= Bytes per joule watt (joule/second)</p>
    <p>Throughput: IOPS</p>
    <p>= IOs per joule watt (joule/second)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observation 6</p>
    <p>Energy efficiency as bytes per joule increases as request size increases.</p>
    <p>Impact on overall energy efficiency</p>
    <p>HDD (SATA) Flash (SATA) Flash (NVMe) Optane (NVMe)</p>
    <p>Bytes transferred per joule</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observation 7</p>
    <p>Energy efficiency as IOs per joule is coupled to internal parallelism.</p>
    <p>Impact on overall energy efficiency</p>
    <p>Flash NVMe Optane SSD</p>
    <p>IOs per joule</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Optane SSD has the greatest energy proportionality since its power consumption scales better than previous storage generations based on its range of throughput. Although Optanes peak power consumption is higher, it yields better energy efficiency as measured in bytes per joule and IOs per joule.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion and future research</p>
    <p>Rethink system software for energy efficiency:</p>
    <p>Polling vs. interrupts?  New IO interfaces: io_uring, SPDK, etc.?  Simpler mechanisms for blk-mq and NVMe?  IO scheduling?  Merging, prefetching, buffering, log structuring?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion and future research</p>
    <p>Investigate R/W asymmetry:</p>
    <p>Why do writes use more CPU but fewer interrupts?  Do existing design choices get in the way of 3D XPoint?  Strategies for hybrid drives for energy efficiency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion and future research</p>
    <p>Energy as a whole:</p>
    <p>Do performance optimizations lose sight of energy efficiency?  Compared to CPU and memory, is the impact of the storage subsystem</p>
    <p>underestimated?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HotStorage 20</p>
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>Questions? Please contact us:</p>
    <p>Bryan Harris bryan.harris.1@louisville.edu</p>
    <p>Nihat Altiparmak nihat.altiparmak@louisville.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References</p>
    <p>[1] Luiz Andr Barroso and Urs Hlzle. The case for energy-proportional computing. Computer, 40(12):3337, 2007. https://doi.org/10.1109/MC.2007.443.</p>
    <p>[2] Kan Wu, Andrea Arpaci-Dusseau, and Remzi Arpaci-Dusseau. Towards an unwritten contract of Intel Optane SSD. In 11th USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Storage and File Systems (HotStorage 19), Renton, WA, July 2019. USENIX Association. https://www.usenix.org/conference/hotstorage19/presentation/wu-kan</p>
    <p>[3] Sehgal, Priya, Vasily Tarasov, and Erez Zadok. &quot;Evaluating Performance and Energy in File System Server Workloads.&quot; FAST 2010.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
