<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consensus-based EvaluationConsensus-based Evaluation for for Fault Isolation Fault Isolation and On-line Evolutionary Regenerationand On-line Evolutionary Regeneration</p>
    <p>K. Zhang, R. F. DeMara, and C. A. SharmaK. Zhang, R. F. DeMara, and C. A. Sharma University of Central FloridaUniversity of Central Florida</p>
    <p>K. Zhang, R. F. DeMara, and C. A. SharmaK. Zhang, R. F. DeMara, and C. A. Sharma University of Central FloridaUniversity of Central Florida</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technical Objective: Autonomous FPGA Regeneration</p>
    <p>Redundancy</p>
    <p>increases with amount of spare capacity</p>
    <p>restricted at design-time</p>
    <p>based on time required to select spare resource</p>
    <p>determined by adequacy of spares available (?)</p>
    <p>yes</p>
    <p>Regeneration</p>
    <p>weakly-related to number</p>
    <p>recovery capacity</p>
    <p>variable at recovery-time</p>
    <p>based on time required to find suitable recovery</p>
    <p>affected by multiple characteristics (+ or -)</p>
    <p>yes</p>
    <p>Overhead from Unutilized Spares weight, size, power</p>
    <p>Granularity of Fault Coverage resolution where fault handled</p>
    <p>Fault-Resolution Latency availability via downtime required to handle fault</p>
    <p>Quality of Repair likelihood and completeness</p>
    <p>Autonomous Operation recover without outside intervention</p>
    <p>Increased availability without pre-configured spares</p>
    <p>everyday example spare tire can of fix-a-flat</p>
    <p>NASA Moon, Mars, and Beyond:</p>
    <p>Realize 10s years service life ???</p>
    <p>Stardust: 110 FPGAs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fault Recovery Characteristics of Selected ApproachesFault Recovery Characteristics of Selected Approaches</p>
    <p>Previous Work on Fault Recovery</p>
    <p>Normalized Power Consumption (Energy per Operation):</p>
    <p>n-plex solution using n redundant devices</p>
    <p>Reconfiguration cost r</p>
    <p>Gate-Level redundancy g</p>
    <p>Updated with scan rate s</p>
    <p>on c CLBs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exploiting Population Information</p>
    <p>Population contains more robust information than individualsPopulation contains more robust information than individuals  Utilize this information for robust fault detection, faster Utilize this information for robust fault detection, faster</p>
    <p>regeneration, increased diversity for adaptationregeneration, increased diversity for adaptation  Detect Failure and Isolate Faulty ResourcesDetect Failure and Isolate Faulty Resources</p>
    <p>Detect by inconsistencies among the populationDetect by inconsistencies among the population  Isolate faults using outlier identification and agingIsolate faults using outlier identification and aging</p>
    <p>Realize RegenerationRealize Regeneration  Recovery Complexity &lt;&lt; Design ComplexityRecovery Complexity &lt;&lt; Design Complexity</p>
    <p>utilize diverse raw material during regeneration vs. isolated re-designutilize diverse raw material during regeneration vs. isolated re-design</p>
    <p>Temporal consensus directs searchTemporal consensus directs search  Adaptable Performance based on Online InputsAdaptable Performance based on Online Inputs</p>
    <p>The population evolves to changing physical environment, input The population evolves to changing physical environment, input vectors, and target application while increasing availabilityvectors, and target application while increasing availability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Procedural Flow under Consensus-Based Evaluation</p>
    <p>Initialization Population partitioned into</p>
    <p>functionally-identical yet physically-distinct half-configurations</p>
    <p>Fitness Adjustment</p>
    <p>update fitness of only L and R based on detection results</p>
    <p>either L's or R's fitness &lt; Repair</p>
    <p>Threshold?</p>
    <p>Selection choose</p>
    <p>FPGA configuration(s) labeled L and R</p>
    <p>Detection apply functional inputs</p>
    <p>to compute FPGA outputs using L, R</p>
    <p>Adjust Controls detection mode, overlap interval, ...</p>
    <p>invoke</p>
    <p>Genetic Operators only once</p>
    <p>and only on L or R</p>
    <p>L=R</p>
    <p>L=R</p>
    <p>PRIMARY LOOP</p>
    <p>discrepancy free</p>
    <p>L, R results</p>
    <p>NO</p>
    <p>YES</p>
    <p>is</p>
    <p>InitializationInitialization Partition P into sub-populations of size |P|/2 to designate</p>
    <p>physical FPGA left-half or right-half resource utilization</p>
    <p>Consensus Based EvaluationConsensus Based Evaluation Discrepancy Operator: CL  CR Four Fitness States : Pristine Suspect Under Repair Refurbished</p>
    <p>RegenerationRegeneration Genetic Operators recover based on Reintroduction Rate  Operators only applied once then offspring returned to service without concern about increasing fitness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consensus-Based Evaluation (CBE) Overview</p>
    <p>Uses a Relative Fitness MeasureUses a Relative Fitness Measure  Pairwise discrepancy checking yields relative fitness measurePairwise discrepancy checking yields relative fitness measure  Broad temporal consensus in the population used to determine Broad temporal consensus in the population used to determine</p>
    <p>fitness metricfitness metric  Transition between Transition between Fitness States Fitness States occurs in the populationoccurs in the population  Provides graceful degradation in presence of changing Provides graceful degradation in presence of changing</p>
    <p>environments, applications and inputs, since this is a moving environments, applications and inputs, since this is a moving measuremeasure</p>
    <p>Test Inputs = Normal Inputs for Data ThroughputTest Inputs = Normal Inputs for Data Throughput  CBE does not utilizes additional functional nor resource test CBE does not utilizes additional functional nor resource test</p>
    <p>vectorsvectors  Potential for higher availability as regeneration is integrated Potential for higher availability as regeneration is integrated</p>
    <p>with normal operationwith normal operation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>pristine</p>
    <p>suspec t</p>
    <p>refurbished</p>
    <p>under repair</p>
    <p>partial repair</p>
    <p>L R</p>
    <p>L = R</p>
    <p>complete repair</p>
    <p>primordial</p>
    <p>L = R</p>
    <p>L R</p>
    <p>L R</p>
    <p>L = R</p>
    <p>L = R</p>
    <p>LR</p>
    <p>fi fOT :</p>
    <p>L = R</p>
    <p>: fi fOT</p>
    <p>fi &lt; fRT</p>
    <p>L R :</p>
    <p>fi &lt; fRT</p>
    <p>L R :</p>
    <p>integral w ith</p>
    <p>: fi fRT</p>
    <p>: fi &lt; fOT</p>
    <p>C O M P E T I T I O N</p>
    <p>C O M P E T I T I O N</p>
    <p>E V O L U T I O N</p>
    <p>States Transitions during lifetime of States Transitions during lifetime of</p>
    <p>iithth Half-Configuration Half-Configuration</p>
    <p>Configuration Health States</p>
    <p>Discrepancy OperatorDiscrepancy Operator  Baseline Discrepancy Operator  is dyadic operator with binary output:</p>
    <p>Z(Ci) is FPGA data throughput output of configuration Ci</p>
    <p>Othewise</p>
    <p>CZCZ CC</p>
    <p>R i</p>
    <p>L iR</p>
    <p>i L i</p>
    <p>)()(</p>
    <p>R ji</p>
    <p>L jii CEORC ,,j  =RS:</p>
    <p>(Hamming Distance)</p>
    <p>R ji</p>
    <p>L jii CEORC ,,j ^ =WTA:</p>
    <p>(Equivalence)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Selection and Repair Process</p>
    <p>Maintain AvailabilityMaintain Availability  Choose Pristine, Suspect, Refurbished individuals in that orderChoose Pristine, Suspect, Refurbished individuals in that order</p>
    <p>Enable RegenerationEnable Regeneration</p>
    <p>Choose Under-Repair individuals subject to Re-introduction rate (Choose Under-Repair individuals subject to Re-introduction rate (RR))</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fitness State Adjustment / Repair</p>
    <p>Discrepancy?</p>
    <p>Increase L's &amp; R 's DV</p>
    <p>Is the individual</p>
    <p>Pristine?</p>
    <p>Mark individual as Suspect</p>
    <p>Is its fi &gt; DVR?</p>
    <p>YES</p>
    <p>NO</p>
    <p>NO</p>
    <p>YES</p>
    <p>Mark individual as Under Repair</p>
    <p>Invoke Genetic Operators only once and only on L or R</p>
    <p>Mark individual as Refurbished</p>
    <p>Is individual Under</p>
    <p>Repair?</p>
    <p>Is its fi &lt; DVO?</p>
    <p>YES</p>
    <p>adjust controls &amp; goto Selection process</p>
    <p>NO</p>
    <p>Evaluation Occurence</p>
    <p>&gt; EW?</p>
    <p>YES</p>
    <p>YES</p>
    <p>Is individual Refurbished?</p>
    <p>NO</p>
    <p>YES YES</p>
    <p>Is individual Suspect?</p>
    <p>NO</p>
    <p>NO</p>
    <p>NO</p>
    <p>YES</p>
    <p>NO</p>
    <p>Calculate the DVo,DVR for this EW and isolate faulty individuals over the Sliding</p>
    <p>Window samples by three Std Dev</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Individuals Fitness: Evaluation Window</p>
    <p>Number of Selections with ReplacementP ro</p>
    <p>b a</p>
    <p>b ili</p>
    <p>ty o</p>
    <p>f S</p>
    <p>e le</p>
    <p>ct io</p>
    <p>n C</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>ta in</p>
    <p>in g a</p>
    <p>ll K</p>
    <p>it e</p>
    <p>m s</p>
    <p>Each individual subjected to sufficient random operational inputs for accurately assessmentEach individual subjected to sufficient random operational inputs for accurately assessment  For combinational logic, EFor combinational logic, EWW is determined on the basis of input word width is determined on the basis of input word width  Genetic operators invoked once every EGenetic operators invoked once every EW W iterations on Under-Repair individuals to avoid iterations on Under-Repair individuals to avoid</p>
    <p>unnecessary modificationsunnecessary modifications  EW = 600 Random run-time inputs provide a 99.5% certainty of the test being exhaustive and EW = 600 Random run-time inputs provide a 99.5% certainty of the test being exhaustive and</p>
    <p>conclusiveconclusive</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Population Comparison: Fitness Indices</p>
    <p>Population Consensus Sliding WindowPopulation Consensus Sliding Window  Population behavior is periodically sampled to determine Population behavior is periodically sampled to determine</p>
    <p>current oracle value for global fitness metriccurrent oracle value for global fitness metric  Thresholds need to be current but not updated more Thresholds need to be current but not updated more</p>
    <p>frequently than necessaryfrequently than necessary  Updating thresholds occurs after 25% ofUpdating thresholds occurs after 25% of individuals individuals</p>
    <p>completed Ecompleted EWW</p>
    <p>Ensures aEnsures a fast-moving fast-moving relativerelative measure for adaptability measure for adaptability  Case study: Case study:</p>
    <p>|C|=20 individuals  |CL|=|CR |= |C|/2  Sliding Window = 5 EEWW  5/20 = 25% individuals evaluated == sufficient</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Integer Multiplier Case Study</p>
    <p>Automated Creation of a Population of Multipliers:Automated Creation of a Population of Multipliers:  Building blocks Building blocks</p>
    <p>Half-Adder: 18 templates createdHalf-Adder: 18 templates created  Full-Adder: 24 templatesFull-Adder: 24 templates  Parallel-And : 1 template createdParallel-And : 1 template created</p>
    <p>OR, AND, XOR, NOR, NAND and NOT functions can be OR, AND, XOR, NOR, NAND and NOT functions can be assigned to a LUTassigned to a LUT</p>
    <p>Randomly select templates for instantiation in modulesRandomly select templates for instantiation in modules</p>
    <p>Strict Feed-Forward flow enforced Strict Feed-Forward flow enforced</p>
    <p>XOR function excluded from initial designs to increase design XOR function excluded from initial designs to increase design spacespace</p>
    <p>Average of 21 CLBs utilized for a 3bit x 3bit MultiplierAverage of 21 CLBs utilized for a 3bit x 3bit Multiplier</p>
    <p>Configurations divided into two groups, each subset using Configurations divided into two groups, each subset using exclusive resourcesexclusive resources</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GA Parameters &amp; Experiments</p>
    <p>SpeciationSpeciation  Two-point crossover between individuals from same sub-groupTwo-point crossover between individuals from same sub-group  Crossover points chosen to prevent intra-CLB crossoverCrossover points chosen to prevent intra-CLB crossover  Breeding occurs exclusively among members of sub-populationsBreeding occurs exclusively among members of sub-populations  Maintains non-interfering resource use among Maintains non-interfering resource use among L, RL, R</p>
    <p>GA operatorsGA operators External-Module-CrossoverExternal-Module-Crossover Internal-Module-Crossover Internal-Module-Crossover Internal-Module-MutationInternal-Module-Mutation</p>
    <p>GA parametersGA parameters Population size : 20 individuals Population size : 20 individuals Crossover rate : 5% Crossover rate : 5% Mutation rate : up to 80% per bitMutation rate : up to 80% per bit</p>
    <p>Fault Isolation CharacteristicsFault Isolation Characteristics  Regenerative ExperimentsRegenerative Experiments</p>
    <p>Demonstrate Demonstrate   Objective fitness function replaced Objective fitness function replaced</p>
    <p>by the Consensus-based Evaluation by the Consensus-based Evaluation Approach and Relative FitnessApproach and Relative Fitness</p>
    <p>Elimination of additional test vectorsElimination of additional test vectors</p>
    <p>Experiments Experiments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Isolation of a single faulty individual with 1-out-of-64 impact</p>
    <p>Outliers are identified after EW iterations have elapsed  Expected D.V. = (1/64)*600 = 9.375 from individual impacted by fault  Isolated faulty individuals DV differs from the average DV by 33 after 1 or more observation intervals of length</p>
    <p>EW</p>
    <p>instantaneous DV (point</p>
    <p>values) for a sample</p>
    <p>individual in population</p>
    <p>and</p>
    <p>population oracles (solid</p>
    <p>lines)</p>
    <p>Sliding Window</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Isolation of a single faulty L individual with 10-out-of-64 impact</p>
    <p>Compare with 1-out-of-64 fault impactCompare with 1-out-of-64 fault impact  Expected DV of (10/64)*600 = 93.75 for faulty configuration  One isolation will be complete approx. once in every 93.75/5 = 19 Sliding Windows  Fault Isolation achieved is 100%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Isolation of 8 faulty individuals L4&amp;R4 with 1-out-of-64 impact</p>
    <p>Expected isolations do not occur approx. 40% of the timeExpected isolations do not occur approx. 40% of the time  Average discrepancy value of the population is higher  Outlier isolation difficult  Multiple faulty individual, Discrepancies scattered</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Regeneration PerformanceRegeneration Performance</p>
    <p>Difference (vs. Hamming Distance) Evaluation Window, Ew = 600 Suspect Threshold: DVS = 1-6/600=99% Repair Threshold: DVR = 1-4/600 = 99.3% Re-introduction rate: r = 0.1</p>
    <p>ParametersParameters:</p>
    <p>Repairs evolvedRepairs evolved in-situ, in real-time, without additional test in-situ, in real-time, without additional test vectors, vectors, while allowing device to remainwhile allowing device to remain partially online. partially online.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Repair ComplexityRepair Complexity  should be more tractable that Design Complexity, given should be more tractable that Design Complexity, given</p>
    <p>diverse spare designsdiverse spare designs</p>
    <p>Population-Centric AssessmentPopulation-Centric Assessment  Provides adaptability and self-calibrating autonomy with a Provides adaptability and self-calibrating autonomy with a</p>
    <p>relative assessment methodrelative assessment method</p>
    <p>Run-time Fault ManagementRun-time Fault Management  Can be realized using consensus-driven assessment Can be realized using consensus-driven assessment</p>
    <p>methods, and using information contained in the populationmethods, and using information contained in the population  Integrate Detection, Isolation, Repair under a single Integrate Detection, Isolation, Repair under a single</p>
    <p>Population-based techniquePopulation-based technique</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
