<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Discriminative Model for Semantics-to-String Translation</p>
    <p>Ales Tamchyna1 and Chris Quirk2 and Michel Galley2</p>
    <p>July 30, 2015</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 1 / 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>State-of-the-art MT models still use a simplistic view of the data I words typically treated as independent, unrelated units I relations between words only captured through linear context</p>
    <p>Unified semantic representations, such as Abstract Meaning Representation (AMR, Banarescu et al. 2013), (re)gaining popularity</p>
    <p>Abstraction from surface words, semantic relations made explicit, related words brought together (possibly distant in the surface realization)</p>
    <p>Possible uses:</p>
    <p>I Richer models of source context  our work I Target-side (or joint) models to capture semantic coherence I Semantic transfer followed by target-side generation</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 2 / 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Semantic Representation Logical Form transformed into an AMR-style representation (Vanderwende et al., 2015) Labeled directed graph, not necessarily acyclic (e.g. coreference) Nodes  content words, edges  semantic relations Function words (mostly) not represented as nodes Bits capture various linguistic properties</p>
    <p>Figure 1 : Logical Form (computed tree) for the sentence: I would like to give you a sandwich taken from the fridge.</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 3 / 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Graph-to-String Translation</p>
    <p>Translation = generation of target-side surface words in order, conditioned on source semantic nodes and previously generated words.</p>
    <p>Start in the (virtual) root</p>
    <p>At each step, transition to a semantic node and emit a target word</p>
    <p>A single node can be visited multiple times</p>
    <p>One transition can move anywhere in the LF</p>
    <p>Source-side semantic graph: G = (V ,E ), V = {n1, ...,nS}, E  V V Target string E = (e1, ...,eT ), alignment A = (a1, ...,aT ), ai  0...S.</p>
    <p>P(A,E|G ) = T i=1</p>
    <p>P(ai|ai11 ,e i1 1 ,G )P(ei|a</p>
    <p>i 1,e</p>
    <p>i1 1 ,G )</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 4 / 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Translation Example</p>
    <p>Ich mchte dir ...</p>
    <p>I like you ... &quot;Dsub^-1&quot; &quot;Dobj-&gt;Dind&quot;</p>
    <p>einen</p>
    <p>sandwich &quot;Dind^-1-&gt;Dobj&quot;</p>
    <p>Sandwich</p>
    <p>&quot;&quot;</p>
    <p>sandwich</p>
    <p>Figure 2 : An example of the translation process illustrating several first steps of translating the sentence into German (Ich mochte dir einen Sandwich...). Labels in italics correspond to the shortest undirected paths between the nodes.</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 5 / 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alignment of Graph Nodes</p>
    <p>How do we align source-side semantic nodes to target-side words?</p>
    <p>Evaluated approaches:</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 6 / 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alignment of Graph Nodes  Gibbs Sampling Alignment ( transition) distribution P(ai|   ) modeled as a categorical distribution:</p>
    <p>P(ai|ai1,G )  c(label(ai1,ai ))</p>
    <p>Translation ( emission) distribution modeled as a set of categorical distributions, one for each source semantic node:</p>
    <p>P(ei|nai )  c(lemma(nai )  ei )</p>
    <p>Sample from the following distribution:</p>
    <p>P(t|ni )  c(lemma(ni )  t) +</p>
    <p>c(lemma(ni )) + L</p>
    <p>c(label(ni,ni1)) +</p>
    <p>T + P</p>
    <p>c(label(ni+1,ni )) +</p>
    <p>T + P</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 7 / 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alignment of Graph Nodes  Evaluation</p>
    <p>Parser-provided alignment  GIZA++</p>
    <p>I Source-target word alignment  GIZA++</p>
    <p>Manual inspection of alignments</p>
    <p>Alignment composition clearly superior</p>
    <p>Not much difference between GIZA++ and parser alignments</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 8 / 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discriminative Translation Model</p>
    <p>A maximum-entropy classifier</p>
    <p>P(ei|nai ,nai1,G,e i1 ik+1) =</p>
    <p>exp ( ~w ~f (ei,nai ,nai1,G,e</p>
    <p>i1 ik+1)</p>
    <p>) Z</p>
    <p>Z =</p>
    <p>eGEN(nai )</p>
    <p>exp(~w ~f (e,nai ,nai1,G,e i1 ik+1))</p>
    <p>Possible classes: top 50 translations observed with given lemma</p>
    <p>Online learning with stochastic gradient descent</p>
    <p>Learning rate 0.05, cumulative L1 regularization with weight 1, batch size 1, 22 hash bits</p>
    <p>Early stopping when held-out perplexity increases</p>
    <p>Parallelized (multi-threading) and distributed learning for tractability</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 9 / 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Feature Set</p>
    <p>Ich mchte dir ...</p>
    <p>I like you ... &quot;Dsub^-1&quot; &quot;Dobj-&gt;Dind&quot;</p>
    <p>einen</p>
    <p>sandwich &quot;Dind^-1-&gt;Dobj&quot;</p>
    <p>Sandwich</p>
    <p>&quot;&quot;</p>
    <p>sandwich</p>
    <p>Current node, previous node, parent node  lemma, POS, bits Path from previous node  path length, path description Bag of lemmas  capture overall topic of the sentence Graph context  features from nodes close in the graph (limited by the length of shortest undirected path) Generated tokens  fertility; some nodes should generate a function word first (e.g. an article) and then the content word Previous tokens  target-side context</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 10 / 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Evaluated in a n-best re-ranking experiment I Generate 1000-best translations of devset sentences I Add scores from our model I Re-run MERT on the enriched n-best lists</p>
    <p>Basic phrase-based system, FrenchEnglish 1 million parallel training sentences</p>
    <p>Obtained small but consistent improvements</p>
    <p>Differences would most likely be larger after integration in decoding</p>
    <p>Dataset Baseline +Semantics</p>
    <p>WMT 2009 = devset 17.44 17.55 WMT 2010 17.59 17.64 WMT 2013 17.41 17.55</p>
    <p>Table 1 : BLEU scores of n-best reranking in FrenchEnglish translation.</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 11 / 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Initial attempt at including semantic features in statistical MT</p>
    <p>Feature set comprising morphological, syntactic and semantic properties</p>
    <p>Small but consistent improvement of BLEU</p>
    <p>Future work:</p>
    <p>Integrate directly in the decoder</p>
    <p>Parser accuracy limited  use multiple analyses</p>
    <p>Explore other ways of integration I Target-side models of semantic plausibility I Semantic transfer and generation</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 12 / 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 13 / 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References</p>
    <p>Laura Banarescu, Claire Bonial, Shu Cai, Madalina Georgescu, Kira Griffitt, Ulf Hermjakob, Kevin Knight, Philipp Koehn, Martha Palmer, and Nathan Schneider. Abstract meaning representation for sembanking. In Proceedings of the 7th Linguistic Annotation Workshop and Interoperability with Discourse, pages 178186, Sofia, Bulgaria, August 2013. Association for Computational Linguistics. URL http://www.aclweb.org/anthology/W13-2322.</p>
    <p>Lucy Vanderwende, Arul Menezes, and Chris Quirk. An AMR parser for English, French, German, Spanish and Japanese and new AMR-annotated corpus. In Proceedings of the 2015 NAACL HLT Demonstration Session, Denver, Colorado, June 2015. Association for Computational Linguistics.</p>
    <p>Tamchyna, Quirk, Galley Semantics-to-String Translation July 30, 2015 14 / 14</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
