<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A First Look at Colocation Demand Response</p>
    <p>Shaolei Ren and M. A. Islam</p>
    <p>Florida International University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demand response program</p>
    <p>Market-based program</p>
    <p>Reduce peak energy usage</p>
    <p>Lo a</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>Time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demand response program</p>
    <p>Market-based program</p>
    <p>Reduce peak energy usage</p>
    <p>Increase adoption of renewables</p>
    <p>e.g., encourage customers to reduce energy during low renewables</p>
    <p>Data centers are promising participants in demand reponse</p>
    <p>Large yet flexible energy demands!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multi-tenant colocation data center</p>
    <p>Multiple tenants house their own servers in one shared space and manage their equipment independently</p>
    <p>Data center operator is only responsible for facility management (e.g., power distribution, cooling)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why colocation demand response?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In reality</p>
    <p>Most large data centers are built to host servers from multiple companies (often called colocation data centers, or &quot;colos&quot;).</p>
    <p>--- The Datacenter as a Computer, a study by Google Research in 2013</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Colocation is growing</p>
    <p>Therere over 1,000 colocation data centers in the U.S.</p>
    <p>Projected to grow to US$ 43 billion by 2018</p>
    <p>Annual compound growth rate of 11%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Who are using colocations, and why?</p>
    <p>Small and medium businesses</p>
    <p>Building self-owned data centers is out of the question</p>
    <p>Public cloud is not a one-size-fits-all solution</p>
    <p>But, theyre not really small</p>
    <p>Wikipedia, Twitter, etc.</p>
    <p>62% of Facebooks servers were housed in colocations as of 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Who are using colocations, and why?</p>
    <p>Small and medium businesses</p>
    <p>Building self-owned data centers is out of the question</p>
    <p>Public cloud is not a one-size-fits-all solution</p>
    <p>But, theyre not really small</p>
    <p>Wikipedia, Twitter, etc.</p>
    <p>62% of Facebooks servers were housed in colocations as of 2012</p>
    <p>Are colocations competing with cloud?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Many clouds live in colocations!  Medium-scale cloud operators</p>
    <p>Even the largest ones</p>
    <p>e.g., Microsoft and Amazon have many edge centers to realize global footprints</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Colocation is ideal for demand response</p>
    <p>Most large data centers are colocations</p>
    <p>Colocations are mostly in metropolitan areas</p>
    <p>Downtown Los Angeles, New York, Silicon Valley, etc.</p>
    <p>This is where demand response is mostly wanted!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Its not easy to enable colocation demand response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why colocation demand response is challenging?</p>
    <p>A commonly used pricing model is based on Power Subscriptions</p>
    <p>http://www.terremark.com/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why colocation demand response is challenging?</p>
    <p>A commonly used pricing model is based on Power Subscriptions</p>
    <p>Split incentive</p>
    <p>Colocation operator desires demand response but has no control over tenants servers</p>
    <p>Tenants manage servers but have no incentive for demand response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We need to incentivize tenants for colocation demand response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>iCODE</p>
    <p>Incentive mechanism based on negotiation</p>
    <p>Step 1: Each participating tenant decides its bid, including planned energy reduction and desired payment</p>
    <p>Step 2: Colocation operator chooses winning bids</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model</p>
    <p>Tenant</p>
    <p>: energy reduction (by turning off unused servers)</p>
    <p>: requested payment is a non-decreasing function of energy reduction</p>
    <p>Switching cost + delay cost</p>
    <p>Colocation operator</p>
    <p>: incentive rate provided by load serving entity for each unit energy reduction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Decide winning bids to maximize energy reduction subject to no profit loss constraint</p>
    <p>LSE benefits from peak energy reduction</p>
    <p>Colocation operator reduces energy at no additional cost</p>
    <p>Tenants receives financial compensation without affecting application performance</p>
    <p>maximize bids</p>
    <p>s.t.</p>
    <p>Problem formulation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case study</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to evaluate iCODE?</p>
    <p>Consider a real-life trace simulation</p>
    <p>Three different tenants  A multi-tenant colocation data center in New York, NY,</p>
    <p>with a PUE of 1.6</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Colocation demand response</p>
    <p>iCODE can reduce over 4 MWh when requested by utility  Equivalent to completely shutting electricity for</p>
    <p>thousands of households 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Three messages</p>
    <p>Multi-tenant colocation data center supports our Internet and is the physical home of many clouds</p>
    <p>Most large data centers are colocations</p>
    <p>Colocation has a huge potential for demand response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
