<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Couture: Tailoring STT-MRAM for Persistent Main Memory</p>
    <p>Mustafa M Shihab Jie Zhang</p>
    <p>Shuwen Gao Joseph Callenes-Sloan</p>
    <p>Myoungsoo Jung</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Executive Summary</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 2</p>
    <p>Motivation: DRAM plays an instrumental role in modern computers, serving as the exclusive main memory technology. But process scaling has exposed it to high leakage and refresh power consumption. STT-MRAM can be an excellent replacement for DRAM, given its high endurance and near-zero leakage.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Executive Summary</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 3</p>
    <p>Motivation: DRAM plays an instrumental role in modern computers, serving as the exclusive main memory technology. But process scaling has exposed it to high leakage and refresh power consumption. STT-MRAM can be an excellent replacement for DRAM, given its high endurance and near-zero leakage.</p>
    <p>Challenge: Conventional STT-MRAM cannot directly substitute DRAM, because of</p>
    <p>- Large cell area - High write energy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Executive Summary</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 4</p>
    <p>Motivation: DRAM plays an instrumental role in modern computers, serving as the exclusive main memory technology. But process scaling has exposed it to high leakage and refresh power consumption. STT-MRAM can be an excellent replacement for DRAM, given its high endurance and near-zero leakage. Challenge: Conventional STT-MRAM cannot directly substitute DRAM, because of</p>
    <p>- Large cell area - High write energy</p>
    <p>Solution: We propose, Couture, a tailored STT-MRAM based memory that offers</p>
    <p>- DRAM-comparable storage density - High performance with low write energy - Intelligent data scrubbing (iScrub) to ensure data integrity</p>
    <p>with minimum overhead</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Executive Summary</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 5</p>
    <p>Motivation: DRAM plays an instrumental role in modern computers, serving as the exclusive main memory technology. But process scaling has exposed it to high leakage and refresh power consumption. STT-MRAM can be an excellent replacement for DRAM, given its high endurance and nearzero leakage. Challenge: Conventional STT-MRAM cannot directly substitute DRAM, because of</p>
    <p>- Large cell area - High write energy</p>
    <p>Solution: We propose, Couture, a tailored STT-MRAM based memory that offers</p>
    <p>- DRAM-comparable storage density - High performance with low write energy - Intelligent data scrubbing method (iScrub) to ensure data integrity with</p>
    <p>minimum overhead</p>
    <p>Results: Compared to a contemporary DRAM, our proposed Couture can</p>
    <p>- Achieve up to 23% performance improvement - Consume 18% less energy, on average</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main Memory  DRAM</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 6</p>
    <p>Applications are getting increasingly data-intensive, demanding larger memory. So, DRAM has to scale-down to process technologies that can hurt its performance</p>
    <p>Cache: Fastest Most Expensive Smallest</p>
    <p>Storage: Slowest</p>
    <p>Least Expensive Largest</p>
    <p>Main Memory</p>
    <p>Main memory ensures optimal performance-cost balance by bridging the gap between on-chip</p>
    <p>cache and storage</p>
    <p>DRAM has been the ubiquitous choice for main memory - most often incarnated as DIMMs</p>
    <p>Scaling down DRAM cells increases off-state leakage</p>
    <p>Leakage results in frequent refresh operations that burden DRAM with extra latency and power overhead. Particularly</p>
    <p>critical for HPCs and data-centers with TBs of memory</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>STT-MRAM: Opportunity and Challenges</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 7</p>
    <p>Spin Transfer Torque Magnetoresistive RAM (STT-MRAM) stores data in a magnetic tunnel</p>
    <p>junction (MTJ) core</p>
    <p>Physical configuration of the MTJ determines data type i.e., 0 or 1 . Data can only be written by driving current to change MTJ configuration.</p>
    <p>This is both good and bad!</p>
    <p>In absence of write current there is no switching.</p>
    <p>This means there is no scope for off-state leakage</p>
    <p>X Physical switching of the MTJ requires a large current.</p>
    <p>This makes the write energy high</p>
    <p>X Large write current requires a large access transistor to drive it, increasing the cell area. A typical STTMRAM cell (40F2) is roughly</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tailored STT-MRAM: Critical Design Parameters</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 8</p>
    <p>Couture proposes to reduce the STT-MRAM cell area and write energy by exploiting the design parameters for the MTJ core</p>
    <p>Critical current (IC): Minimum current for switching the polarity of MTJs free layer</p>
    <p>and  = fitting constants that represent the operational environment</p>
    <p>Thermal Stability Factor (): Refers to the stability of an MTJs magnetic orientations</p>
    <p>Eb = energy barrier, T = temperature, HK = anisotropic field, MS = saturation magnetization, kB = Boltzmann constant, and V = MTJs volume</p>
    <p>Retention time (TRetention): The expected time before a random bit-flip occurs</p>
    <p>f0 is the operating frequency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Access Transistor Optimization</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 9</p>
    <p>STT-MRAM cell area is dominated by the access transistor, as MTJ is comparatively smaller in size</p>
    <p>The transistor size is mainly determined by the current driven by it. So, to make the transistor smaller, we need to reduce the critical current</p>
    <p>We reduce the MTJ thickness to lower the thermal stability factor, which in turn lowers the critical current</p>
    <p>As we lowered the thermal stability factor from 40.29 to 28.91 by reducing MTJ volume, the cell area is reduced from 36 F2 to 10 F2</p>
    <p>Unfortunately, lowering the thermal stability factor also shortens the retention time of our tailored STT-MRAM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Write Energy Optimization</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 10</p>
    <p>Lowering the critical current allows us to lower the STT-MRAM write current.</p>
    <p>This in turn can reduce the write power by 50%</p>
    <p>The lowered write current results in a marginally increased the write latency</p>
    <p>But, reducing the write current can improve overall write energy by 33%</p>
    <p>Lowering the thermal stability factor from its default value of 40.3 to 28.9, STT-MRAMs write energy decreases from 0.66 pJ to 0.44 pJ</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Couture Memory Module</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 11</p>
    <p>For a smooth transition from DRAM, our proposed Couture fits in the existing main memory DIMM packaging</p>
    <p>2 Ranks in the Module &gt;&gt; 8 memory Chips (+1 ECC Chip) per Rank</p>
    <p>8 logical Banks per Rank &gt;&gt; Each Bank is divided into subarrays of Cells</p>
    <p>Each Cell contains an Access Transistor and an MTJ, connected via a bit-line (BL),</p>
    <p>a source-line (SL), and a word-line (WL)</p>
    <p>Chip ECCR a</p>
    <p>n k</p>
    <p>R a</p>
    <p>n k</p>
    <p>Global Address Bus Global Data Bus On-Chip Control Logic</p>
    <p>DDR Channel</p>
    <p>Couture</p>
    <p>G lo</p>
    <p>b a</p>
    <p>l A</p>
    <p>d d</p>
    <p>re ss</p>
    <p>D e</p>
    <p>co d</p>
    <p>e r</p>
    <p>Subarray1 Local Row Buffer</p>
    <p>Local Row Buffer</p>
    <p>Subarrayn Local Row Buffer</p>
    <p>Lo ca</p>
    <p>l A</p>
    <p>d rs</p>
    <p>D e</p>
    <p>c</p>
    <p>Global Row Buffer</p>
    <p>Lo ca</p>
    <p>l A</p>
    <p>d rs</p>
    <p>D e</p>
    <p>c</p>
    <p>Banks</p>
    <p>WL</p>
    <p>Row Buffer</p>
    <p>Sensing Circuit</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dual Write Driver and Sensing Circuit</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 12</p>
    <p>STT-MRAM requires opposing current paths for writing 0 and 1, as the MTJ needs to be switched from anti-parallel to parallel configuration Couture connects the cells to two write-input drivers - W0_En and W1_En</p>
    <p>Coutures sensing circuit detects the content of a cell by comparing it with a reference cell that has an MTJ that is set at a resistance level exactly in the</p>
    <p>middle of the resistance spectrum: +</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Intelligent Data Scrub (iScrub)</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 13</p>
    <p>Cell-level optimization reduces the data retention time in tailored STT-MRAM  But, data retention in STT-MRAM is actually probabilistic in nature</p>
    <p>Even with a fixed retention time, some of the cells can retain data for a longer time, while others can lose it before the set period</p>
    <p>Reinforcement learning: learns and improve with experience  Interacts with its environment over time and senses the current state (S) of</p>
    <p>its environment and executes an action (A) that produces a reward (R)  Goal is to maximize the cumulative reward by learning an optimal policy for</p>
    <p>mapping states to actions and gradually update a state-action-reward table</p>
    <p>iScrub  a reinforcement learning based scrub scheduler that can exploit such probabilistic behavior and ensure data integrity with minimum overhead</p>
    <p>Couture Memory</p>
    <p>iScrub Scheduler</p>
    <p>Rewards R(t): Immediate: Maintain BER</p>
    <p>Long-term: Minimize Scrubbing</p>
    <p>States S(t): Scrub freq, BER, Time</p>
    <p>Actions A(t+1): Read, Write, Scrub</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>iScrub: Scheduling Algorithm</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 14</p>
    <p>Select page for scrubbing</p>
    <p>Access corresponding bank</p>
    <p>Perform scrub operation</p>
    <p>More pages to scrub in bank?</p>
    <p>No</p>
    <p>I/O scheduled for bank?</p>
    <p>Yes</p>
    <p>A cc</p>
    <p>e ss</p>
    <p>n e</p>
    <p>xt p</p>
    <p>a g</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>fo r</p>
    <p>sc ru</p>
    <p>b b</p>
    <p>in g</p>
    <p>No</p>
    <p>Release bank for one I/O Yes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation Setup</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 15</p>
    <p>Simulated configurations:</p>
    <p>DDR3 DRAM: DRAM memory with periodic refresh operations</p>
    <p>STT-MRAM: Main memory design with conventional STTMRAM (10yr retention)</p>
    <p>Couture: Proposed Couture design without iScrub scheduler</p>
    <p>Couture-i: Optimal configuration for our Couture design with iScrub scheme</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Analysis - IPC</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 16</p>
    <p>Instructions per cycle (IPC) for the 4 memory configurations, normalized to that of the DDR3 DRAM baseline</p>
    <p>STT-MRAM eliminated refresh but average IPC fell below the baseline by 17%  Because of the long write latency</p>
    <p>Lowering the write latency, Couture improved IPC by 8%, on average</p>
    <p>With iScrub, Couture-i improved the average IPC by 16% over DDR3 DRAM, peaking at 23% for the bzip2 and hmmer benchmarks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Analysis - Throughput</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 17</p>
    <p>Second performance comparison in terms of I/O throughput</p>
    <p>STT-MRAM fell short of the baseline DDR3 DRAM by 5%, on average</p>
    <p>Couture exceeded the baselines throughput by 8%, on average</p>
    <p>Couture-i performed best with an average improvement of 13% over the DDR3</p>
    <p>DRAM baseline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Energy Improvement</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 18</p>
    <p>Energy consumption results:  Normalized to the DDR3 DRAM baseline  5 components: standby, activation, read, write, and refresh</p>
    <p>DRAM consumed a significant energy for standby (leakage) and refresh  STT-MRAM eliminated refresh and reduced standby energy, but the high write</p>
    <p>energy increases the overall consumption by 9.5%  Couture, with optimized write current, shows an average improvement of 14%  Couture-i reduced scrub energy with iScrub and further lowered total energy</p>
    <p>Peak reduction: 20% (for bzip2), Average reduction: 18%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Backup Slides</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>iScrub Algorithm</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation Process</p>
    <p>Couture  USENIX Inflow 2016 22</p>
    <p>We build Couture latency model by considering cell-level and peripheral circuit latency</p>
    <p>We calibrated CACTI to get reasonable peripheral latency of main memory.</p>
    <p>For STT-MRAMs subarray access latency, we collect the data by modifying NVSim</p>
    <p>For system-level evaluation, we integrate Couture latency model in the gem5</p>
    <p>We verify the performance of our Couture with ten workload applications from the</p>
    <p>SPEC2006 benchmark suite.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
