<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>On the Impact of Garbage Collection on flash-based SSD endurance</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt</p>
    <p>Dept. Mathematics and Computer Science University of Antwerp Antwerp, Belgium</p>
    <p>INFLOW 16</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 1/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>SSD basics</p>
    <p>Prior work</p>
    <p>System description</p>
    <p>GC algorithms Workloads GC mechanism</p>
    <p>Performance measures</p>
    <p>Model framework</p>
    <p>Findings</p>
    <p>Future work</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 2/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flash-based SSD</p>
    <p>SSD Structure (plane level)</p>
    <p>Data is organized in N blocks</p>
    <p>Fixed number of b pages per block (e.g., b = 32)</p>
    <p>Unit of data exchange is a page</p>
    <p>Page has 3 possible states: erase, valid or invalid.</p>
    <p>Operations</p>
    <p>Data can only be written on pages in erase state</p>
    <p>Erase operations can be performed on entire blocks only</p>
    <p>Each block tolerates Wmax program-erase (PE) cycles before wearing out</p>
    <p>Out-of-place writes are supported (old data becomes invalid)</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 3/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flash-based SSD</p>
    <p>Internal operation (internal log structure)</p>
    <p>New data is sequentially written to one or more special blocks called write frontiers (WFs)</p>
    <p>When a WF is full, a new WF is selected by the garbage collection (GC) algorithm</p>
    <p>Write Amplification (WA)</p>
    <p>Valid pages in the victim block are temporarily copied to perform erase</p>
    <p>Assume j valid pages on a victim block with probability pj , write amplification A equals</p>
    <p>A = b</p>
    <p>b  b</p>
    <p>j=0 jpj</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 4/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Write Amplification</p>
    <p>Importance</p>
    <p>Affects IOPS and life span of the drive</p>
    <p>Over-provisioning</p>
    <p>Physical storage capacity exceeds the user-visible (logical) capacity</p>
    <p>Measure is spare factor Sf = 1 :</p>
    <p>= the user-visible capacity</p>
    <p>total storage capacity</p>
    <p>fraction Sf of the pages is guaranteed to be in erase/invalid state</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 5/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prior work</p>
    <p>Analytical models</p>
    <p>Mostly under uniform random writes and Rosenblum (hot/cold) workloads</p>
    <p>Exact (closed-form) results for WA as N tends to infinity</p>
    <p>Random GC FIFO/LRU GC (Menon, Robinson, Desnoyers) Greedy GC (Bux, Iliadis, Desnoyers) d-choices GC (Van Houdt, Li et al.) Windowed GC (Hu et al., Iliadis) etc.</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 6/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prior work</p>
    <p>Main observations w.r.t. Write Amplification</p>
    <p>Greedy is optimal under uniform random writes, d-choices close to optimal (for d as small as 10)</p>
    <p>Increasing hotness worsens WA in case of single WF (as no hot/cold data separation takes place)</p>
    <p>Double WF (separates writes triggered by host and GC): WA decreases as hotness increases (as partial hot/cold data separation takes place)</p>
    <p>Greedy is no longer optimal with hot/cold data: there exists optimal d for d-choices</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 7/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Class C of GC algorithms modeled</p>
    <p>Definition</p>
    <p>Let ~m(t) = (m0(t), . . . ,mb(t)), where mi (t) is the fraction of blocks containing i valid pages at time t</p>
    <p>A GC algorithm belongs to C if 1 A block containing j valid pages is selected by the GC</p>
    <p>algorithm with probability pj (~m(t)) 2 The probabilities pj (~m(t)) are smooth in ~m(t) (can be slightly</p>
    <p>relaxed)</p>
    <p>It is possible to further extend this class when hot/cold data identification techniques are in place</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 8/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Class C of GC algorithms modeled</p>
    <p>Examples</p>
    <p>random and erases a block containing the smallest number of valid pages among the d selected blocks:</p>
    <p>pj (~m) =</p>
    <p>b</p>
    <p>`=j</p>
    <p>m`</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>b</p>
    <p>`=j+1</p>
    <p>m`</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 9/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workload model</p>
    <p>Rosenblum model</p>
    <p>A fraction f of the data is termed hot</p>
    <p>Hot pages are updated at rate r  f , cold pages at rate 1  r Reducing f or increasing r makes hot data hotter</p>
    <p>Special case: Uniform random writes (r = f )</p>
    <p>Every (logical) page on the device is updated with the same probability</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 10/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System description</p>
    <p>GC mechanism: Double Write Frontier (DWF)</p>
    <p>Uses 2 write frontiers:</p>
    <p>WFE: External WF for externally issued writes (by host) WFI: Internal WF used during GC</p>
    <p>Separates data without hot/cold data identification techniques</p>
    <p>Garbage collection with DWF</p>
    <p>GC algorithm invoked when WFE becomes full, chooses victim containing j valid pages</p>
    <p>Assume WFI contains b  j pages in erase state j  b  j: j valid pages copied to WFI,</p>
    <p>victim becomes new WFE j &gt; b  j: j valid pages copied to WFI,</p>
    <p>victim becomes new WFI, reinvoke GC</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 11/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance measures</p>
    <p>PE fairness</p>
    <p>Mean number of PE cycles performed on blocks before any block reaches Wmax PE cycles, divided by Wmax</p>
    <p>Describes how fairly the PE cycles are distributed among blocks</p>
    <p>SSD endurance</p>
    <p>Expected number of external writes before any block reaches Wmax PE cycles</p>
    <p>Expresses the life span of the device in full drive writes (FDW)</p>
    <p>Main questions</p>
    <p>How much can wear leveling mechanisms improve performance?</p>
    <p>Which of the proposed measures dominates w.r.t. performance and what role does the GCA play?</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 12/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model framework</p>
    <p>Background on mean field models</p>
    <p>Stochastic system of N interacting blocks (N-dimensional Markov chain)</p>
    <p>Problem: impractical to compute steady state for large N</p>
    <p>Solution: consider the limit of N tending to infinity</p>
    <p>Limit is a deterministic system, its evolution captured by the trajectories of a set of ODEs (called drift equations)</p>
    <p>Drift corresponds to studying the behavior of one (type of) block, averaging the effects of other blocks</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 13/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model framework</p>
    <p>Drift equations and fixed point (for uniform random writes)</p>
    <p>Let fi,w (~m) represent the expected change in the fraction of blocks containing i valid pages with w PE cycles</p>
    <p>Determine fixed point ~m? where</p>
    <p>b i=0</p>
    <p>fi,w (~m ?) = 0</p>
    <p>WA, PE fairness and SSD endurance based on fixed point</p>
    <p>Gives exact results for N tending to infinity (provided that limits are exchangeable)</p>
    <p>Model extension for Rosenblum workload</p>
    <p>Can be extended for hot/cold workload, but numerical solution is computation intensive</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 14/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main findings: Uniform random writes</p>
    <p>Maximum number of PE cycles</p>
    <p>P E</p>
    <p>f a ir n e s s</p>
    <p>d = 100 d = 10 d = 6 d = 3 d = 2 d = 1</p>
    <p>Figure: PE fairness under uniform random writes with b = 32 and Sf = 0.1.</p>
    <p>Increasing b, d or Sf results in increased PE fairness. Narrow margin for improving by implementing wear leveling mechanisms.</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 15/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main findings: Uniform random writes</p>
    <p>Maximum number of PE cycles</p>
    <p>S S</p>
    <p>D E</p>
    <p>n d u ra</p>
    <p>n c e</p>
    <p>b = 64 b = 32 b = 16 b = 8 b = 4 b = 2</p>
    <p>Figure: SSD endurance under uniform random writes with Sf = 0.1 and d = 10.</p>
    <p>Smaller block sizes b result in higher endurance due to lower WA.</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 16/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main findings: Hot/cold data</p>
    <p>Maximum number of PE cycles</p>
    <p>P E</p>
    <p>f a</p>
    <p>ir n</p>
    <p>e s s</p>
    <p>d =100</p>
    <p>d = 30</p>
    <p>d = 10</p>
    <p>d = 6</p>
    <p>d = 3</p>
    <p>d = 2</p>
    <p>d = 1</p>
    <p>Figure: PE fairness under hot/cold data (DWF) with b = 32, Sf = 0.1, f = 0.2 and r = 0.8.</p>
    <p>In contrast with uniform random writes, smaller d and Sf values result in better fairness. The GCA then more likely chooses victims containing primarily cold data, which have a lower number of PE cycles.</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 17/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main findings: Hot/cold data</p>
    <p>Maximum number of PE cycles</p>
    <p>S S</p>
    <p>D E</p>
    <p>n d</p>
    <p>u ra</p>
    <p>n c e</p>
    <p>d =100</p>
    <p>d = 30</p>
    <p>d = 10</p>
    <p>d = 6</p>
    <p>d = 3</p>
    <p>d = 2</p>
    <p>d = 1</p>
    <p>Figure: SSD endurance under hot/cold data (DWF) with b = 32, Sf = 0.1, f = 0.2 and r = 0.8.</p>
    <p>There exists a finite d value optimizing SSD endurance. Smaller d have higher WA, outweighing benefits of better PE fairness.</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 18/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main findings: Hot/cold data</p>
    <p>Maximum number of PE cycles</p>
    <p>S S</p>
    <p>D E</p>
    <p>n d u ra</p>
    <p>n c e</p>
    <p>f =0.01</p>
    <p>f =0.05</p>
    <p>f =0.10</p>
    <p>f =0.20</p>
    <p>f =0.40</p>
    <p>Figure: SSD endurance under hot/cold data (DWF) with b = 32, Sf = 0.1 and d = 10.</p>
    <p>PE fairness reduces with hotness, but lower WA of hotter data results in better endurance.</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 19/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main findings: Hot/cold data</p>
    <p>r f dMIN WA dMAX End dMAX Fair 0.90 0.80 0.20 13 13 2 0.90 0.95 0.05 10 8 1 0.90 0.99 0.01 27 24 1 0.85 0.80 0.20 11 9 2 0.90 0.80 0.20 13 13 2 0.95 0.80 0.20 22 21 2</p>
    <p>Table: Comparison of d values optimizing WA, SSD endurance and PE fairness for several parameter settings in a system of N = 10, 000 blocks of size b = 32 with Wmax = 5000 (10 runs).</p>
    <p>Minimizing WA is more beneficial for endurance than maximizing fairness.</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 20/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main takeaway</p>
    <p>Uniform random writes</p>
    <p>Greedy (or d large) GC delivers near optimal fairness and endurance</p>
    <p>Large blocksizes can result in shorter life span (high WA outweighs fairness)</p>
    <p>Hot/cold data (DWF)</p>
    <p>Increasing data hotness leads to lower PE fairness</p>
    <p>Lowering PE fairness may lead to higher SSD endurance</p>
    <p>d values maximizing endurance are relatively small, but closer to those minimizing WA than those maximizing PE fairness</p>
    <p>When increasing hotness, minimizing WA outweighs achieving roughly equal wear</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 21/22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Possible extensions and ongoing work</p>
    <p>Possible extensions</p>
    <p>GC algorithms depending on wear of blocks</p>
    <p>Impact of wear leveling mechanism on SSD endurance</p>
    <p>Ongoing and future work</p>
    <p>Fairness and endurance of trace-based workloads</p>
    <p>Impact of data separation techniques on device lifespan</p>
    <p>Robin Verschoren and Benny Van Houdt Impact of Garbage Collection on SSD endurance 22/22</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
