<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Analysis of Long Lines in Richland County, South</p>
    <p>Carolina</p>
    <p>Duncan A. Buell</p>
    <p>University of South Carolina</p>
    <p>USENIX EVT/WOTE 2013, Washington DC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Weve got to fix that.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Weve got to fix that.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Weve got to fix that.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Weve got to fix that.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Richland County</p>
    <p>Home of Columbia, SC, the state capital, and home of the University of South Carolina</p>
    <p>~550 DREs operating at 7am on Nov 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All election data ordered by a judge to be counted by SC Law Enf Division (11/08/2012); data sent to SLED</p>
    <p>Judge overruled (11/09/2012); data returned to county</p>
    <p>State Supreme Court orders counting 11/13/2012 Results announced 11/15/2012</p>
    <p>Legislative delegation hearing 11/26/2012 Uncounted votes discovered 11/27/2012, 11/29/2012</p>
    <p>Conspiracy theories about a sales tax referendum Lawsuit to throw out the entire election not settled</p>
    <p>(against) until 3/22/2013</p>
    <p>(and yes, theres morelots more)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Disclaimer</p>
    <p>Steve Hamm actually paid me (personally) for 36 hours worked specifically on his behalf.</p>
    <p>I was paid at the official hourly rate of my</p>
    <p>university salary (as would be charged to NSF or other external funding).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Long Lines and Policy</p>
    <p>No evidence (none at all!) of intent, fraud, malfeasance, etc., etc., etc.</p>
    <p>Conspiracy theories had the affluent voters disenfranchised (sales tax related)</p>
    <p>Early voting doesnt exist in SC Absentee voting was substantial (and largely</p>
    <p>by African-American voters?)</p>
    <p>This was just a colossal screw-up</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Late Votes</p>
    <p>How long did voters actually wait? Why are Richland and Greenville so different?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Late Votes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Doing the Analysis</p>
    <p>SC votes entirely on ES&amp;S iVotronic DREs One advantage of the DREs is that there is</p>
    <p>actual data</p>
    <p>And the data is public record We can work the data to find out how bad it</p>
    <p>really was</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lots of Issues with the Data</p>
    <p>EL155 cast vote record EL152 event log</p>
    <p>EL30A, EL45A results files</p>
    <p>Timestamps are not always correct</p>
    <p>Event messages not always precise or complete We dont get an I am a dead computer message</p>
    <p>We dont get actual time-to-vote (endtime-starttime)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Nonetheless,</p>
    <p>We compute time between cast vote messages</p>
    <p>(looks log normal) We can histogram votes collected</p>
    <p>If a pct is collecting votes, but a terminal is</p>
    <p>not, AND the terminal has thrown error messages, then maybe its not being used</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Time-to-Vote (logs of)</p>
    <p>Of late votes, after excluding some (dubious) times</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We Simulate the Election</p>
    <p>Percents of total voters/pct in each hour (10, 10, 10, 5, 5, 5, 10, 10, 5, 5, 5, 10 10)</p>
    <p>Poisson interarrivals in each hour Log normal time-to-vote</p>
    <p>(we have stats before closing, county-wide, and stats after closing for pcts with many late votes)</p>
    <p>Choose 14 worst pcts in Richland, random 14 best, and all of Greenville County</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Capacity</p>
    <p>SC permits three minutes for voting 12 hours * 60 mins / 3 (mins/vote) =240 votes/DRE</p>
    <p>Queueing theory says dont go over  this capacity (i.e., 120 votes/DRE)</p>
    <p>Richland had 192/DRE, Greenville had 200</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Estimated Effective Terminal Count</p>
    <p>Look at open times and close times, and prorate hours Look at histograms of votes collected</p>
    <p>Look at EL152 for anomalies, errors, etc. Use first hand information (pcts 340, 378)</p>
    <p>There were reports of broken terminals all over the county. Some of this can be substantiated and quantified by manual examination of the data.</p>
    <p>Manual, subjective,  yes, we admit that</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Validating the Simulation</p>
    <p>Simulate with various numbers of terminals to include actual count and estimated effective count</p>
    <p>Simulate with before 7pm and after 7pm time-to-vote</p>
    <p>Match up the number of late votes (simulated vs. real) to get a terminal count as per the simulation</p>
    <p>We consider the simulation and model validated, because the terminal count as per the simulation is very close to the independently estimated effective terminal count</p>
    <p>We can then look at the wait times from simulation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results, Richland Late Votes</p>
    <p>Only 1 is truly anomalous</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results, Richland Late Votes</p>
    <p>x</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results, Richland Late Votes</p>
    <p>x</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results, Richland No Late Votes</p>
    <p>x</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results, Greenville County</p>
    <p>the 3 above)</p>
    <p>Even with few late votes, still 36,000 voters in line for more than one hour</p>
    <p>But simulation has no wait times more than two hours</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Wait Times, Richland County</p>
    <p>Conservatively: &gt;53,000 voters (44%) more than one hour</p>
    <p>&gt;20,000 voters (17%) more than two hours</p>
    <p>Even in sampled good pcts,  of voters &gt;one hour</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ballot Complexity</p>
    <p>Richland</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Capacity Redux</p>
    <p>Richland: 121,206 votes * 190 secs = 533 DREs for 12 hours</p>
    <p>Never more than 578 collecting votes</p>
    <p>Greenville: 171,146 votes * 190 secs = 752 DREs for 12 hours</p>
    <p>Table II (if nothing else) shows the sharp sensitivity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The End</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
