<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to Build an Undervoting Machine: Lessons from an Alternative Ballot Design</p>
    <p>Kristen K. Greene* Michael D. Byrne Stephen N. Goggin Rice University Houston, TX http://chil.rice.edu/</p>
    <p>*Now at NIST Now at UC Berkeley</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>National Science Foundation  ACCURATE center</p>
    <p>Local election officials  Brazoria County, TX  Victoria County, TX</p>
    <p>Acknowledgements</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>Research Aims Prior Research Method Results Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Electronic Voting Machines?</p>
    <p>Despite security concerns, there are several compelling reasons why DREs (direct recording electronic voting machines) remain an important research area  Potential for accessibility accommodations that traditional</p>
    <p>paper-based systems cannot offer  Opportunity to present ballots to voters in novel ways + This space has not been systematically explored + Need baseline data against which to evaluate emerging and</p>
    <p>future voting methods</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Aims</p>
    <p>Widen the space of DRE design inquiry  How does changing the ballot navigation model impact</p>
    <p>usability? Explore the relationship between residual votes and true error rates through experimental work  Prior work (Campbell &amp; Byrne, 2009a) found that while the</p>
    <p>overall average residual vote and true error rates may be similar, the variability in one is not mirrored by the other</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prior Research</p>
    <p>Our previous work is the only work we know of that directly assessed usability of older voting systems Key results from prior research:  Methods comparable in terms of efficiency  Bubble style paper ballots superior subjective usability</p>
    <p>relative to lever machines and punch cards  Error rates ranging from 1.5% to 5% per race</p>
    <p>Need research that directly compares typical DREs and older methods  Furthermore, how do novel design features (like navigation) of</p>
    <p>DREs affect performanceor do they?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Research Compared four voting systems:  DREs: sequential vs. direct access navigation  Paper ballots  Punch cards  Lever machines</p>
    <p>Used metrics from International Organization for Standardization (ISO):  Efficiency (time to cast ballot)  Effectiveness (errors)  Satisfaction (SUS, a subjective usability questionnaire)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>Participants  64 paid volunteers (30 male, 34 female) from Houston area  Ages 18-77 years, mean age of 50.3 (SD = 14.8)  Diverse in terms of education, ethnicity, and income</p>
    <p>Primary independent variable: DRE navigation style  Half of participants voted with direct access DRE  Half of participants voted with sequential DRE  Each participant voted twice on assigned DRE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DRE Voting Method: VoteBox, Sequential Navigation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>Non-DRE voting method  In addition to voting twice on a DRE, each subject voted</p>
    <p>on one of three other non-DRE methods: paper ballots, punch cards, or lever machines</p>
    <p>Information condition  Undirected: users given a guide and allowed to vote as they</p>
    <p>pleased  Directed: users given a sheet, told who to vote for + Directed with no roll-off, directed with moderate roll-off, directed</p>
    <p>with additional roll-off</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Non-DRE Voting Methods</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ballots</p>
    <p>Same ballot on all voting methods Entirely fictional candidates 21 offices  Choose one candidate per office</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Error Measures</p>
    <p>Extra vote error  A voter makes a selection for a race s/he had originally</p>
    <p>intended to skip Omission (undervote) error  A voter fails to choose a candidate for a race in which s/he</p>
    <p>had intended to vote Wrong choice error  A voter makes a selection other than the one intended</p>
    <p>Overvote error  A voter makes more than the allowed number of choices</p>
    <p>(paper or punchcard only)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extra vote Omission Wrong choice</p>
    <p>Total error</p>
    <p>Sequential DRE</p>
    <p>Direct DRE</p>
    <p>Bubble ballot</p>
    <p>Lever machine</p>
    <p>Punch card</p>
    <p>Error Rates</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Omission Errors</p>
    <p>Direct access DRE omission error rate significantly greater than sequential DRE  8 of 32 people (25%) cast vote prematurely with direct access</p>
    <p>DRE  0 of 32 did so with sequential DRE</p>
    <p>Postcompletion errors: Fleeing voter problem  4 of 32 people (12.5%) failed to cast vote with direct access</p>
    <p>DRE  2 of 32 people (6.3%) did so with sequential DRE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Intentional Abstentions</p>
    <p>Undirected information condition only People using the direct access DRE voted in far fewer races  With direct access DRE, voters abstained from nearly half of</p>
    <p>all races: intentional abstention rate of 45.4%  With sequential DRE, voters almost never abstained from a</p>
    <p>race: intentional abstention rate of .7%  Those using the direct access DRE were therefore</p>
    <p>significantly faster + Difference in overall ballot completion time only; per-race voting</p>
    <p>times similar between navigation types</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Residual Vote in Political Science</p>
    <p>The residual vote rate reflects the total number of votes for any given race that cannot be counted Historically used in Political Science field studies as an indirect measure of accuracy Comprised of overvote errors, omission errors, and intentional abstentions No information on wrong choice errors No differentiation between omission errors and intentional abstentions Requirements to report number of unrecorded votes vary by state</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How Accurate is the Residual Vote as a Measure of Voter Error?</p>
    <p>Must know voter intent to answer this question Design of our experiment explicitly tracked this, providing a direct measure of accuracy How well does the true error rate correlate with what would have been reported as the residual vote?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Top-Ballot (Presidential) Residual Votes vs. True Error Rates</p>
    <p>Sequential DRE Direct Access DRE 0.00</p>
    <p>M ea</p>
    <p>n R</p>
    <p>ep or</p>
    <p>te d</p>
    <p>R at</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>E M</p>
    <p>Navigation Type</p>
    <p>True Error Rate</p>
    <p>Residual Vote Rate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Down-Ballot Residual Votes vs. True Error Rates</p>
    <p>Sequential DRE Direct Access DRE 0.00</p>
    <p>M ea</p>
    <p>n R</p>
    <p>ep or</p>
    <p>te d</p>
    <p>R at</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>E M</p>
    <p>Navigation Type</p>
    <p>True Error Rate</p>
    <p>Residual Vote Rate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sequential navigation:  correlation between residual vote and true error rate was not</p>
    <p>significant, r(6) = -.14, p = .74,  nor was the difference in means, t(7) = 0.00, p = 1.00</p>
    <p>Direct access navigation:  correlation between residual vote and true error rate was not</p>
    <p>significant, r(6) = .41, p = .32,  nor was the difference in means, t(7) = 1.00, p = .35</p>
    <p>Top-Ballot (Presidential) Residual Votes vs. True Error Rates</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Down-Ballot Residual Votes vs. True Error Rates</p>
    <p>Sequential navigation:  correlation between residual vote and true error rate was not</p>
    <p>significant, r(6) = .22, p = .60  nor was the difference in means, t(7) = .43, p = .68</p>
    <p>Direct access navigation:  correlation between residual vote and true error rate was not</p>
    <p>significant, r(6) = .16, p = .70  nor was the difference in means, t(7) = 1.64, p = .15</p>
    <p>Non-significant correlations suggest the residual vote may not be as tightly coupled to the true error rate as has often been assumed.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ballot Completion Times</p>
    <p>Sequential DRE Direct Access DRE</p>
    <p>M ea</p>
    <p>n B</p>
    <p>al lo</p>
    <p>t C om</p>
    <p>pl et</p>
    <p>io n</p>
    <p>Ti m</p>
    <p>e (s</p>
    <p>ec )</p>
    <p>E M</p>
    <p>Navigation Style</p>
    <p>Undirected</p>
    <p>Directed: no roll-off</p>
    <p>Directed: moderate roll-off</p>
    <p>Directed: additional roll-off</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Satisfaction</p>
    <p>Sequential DRE Direct Access DRE 0</p>
    <p>M ea</p>
    <p>n S</p>
    <p>U S</p>
    <p>s co</p>
    <p>re</p>
    <p>E M</p>
    <p>Navigation Type</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>DREs were no better than traditional methods in terms of efficiency and effectiveness Manipulation of single design feature (navigation style) significantly impacted both subjective and objective usability  Best subjective usability ratings with sequential DRE  Direct access DRE faster and more error-prone than</p>
    <p>sequential DRE  Rate of intentional abstention much higher for direct DRE  New type of error seen with direct access DRE: voters cast</p>
    <p>ballot prematurely  Voters also failed to cast ballot entirely (fleeing voter)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>Consistent with (Campbell &amp; Byrne, 2009a), our data indicate that residual vote rate may not be as tightly coupled to true error rate as has traditionally been assumed Mean error rate generated by both measures approximately the same As a tool to detect large-scale problems across many voters, residual vote rate is likely still a good tool Near-zero correlation at the ballot level warrants further research  Impossible to address during real elections, but feasible in</p>
    <p>laboratory environments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
