<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tes$ng Voters Understanding of a Security Mechanism used in</p>
    <p>Verifiable Vo$ng</p>
    <p>Morgan Llewellyn, Steve Schneider, Zhe Xia, Chris Culnane James Heather, Peter Y.A. Ryan, Sriramkrishnan Srinivasan</p>
    <p>IMT Lucca; University of Surrey; Luxembourg</p>
    <p>EVT/WOTE 2013 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Structure of talk</p>
    <p>Introduc*on/Mo*va*on  The Prt  Voter voter-verifiable system  Users understanding  Experiment Design  Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduc$on</p>
    <p>Voter-verifiable vo*ng systems introduce security mechanisms or procedures such as receipts or challenges to provide verifiability</p>
    <p>Voter understanding of these may impact on their interac*on with the system, e.g. verifying the ballot</p>
    <p>How can we inves*gate voters understanding?  Here we explore voters understanding of the Prt  Voter</p>
    <p>split ballot mechanism for providing vote secrecy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Mo$va$on</p>
    <p>2010: Focus group discussions around usability of Prt  Voter prototype, with its principles explained, to try out scenarios.</p>
    <p>Revealed some lack of understanding/awareness that the receipt does not expose the vote (despite par*cipants claims)</p>
    <p>Why? we can speculate: - receipt terminology: expecta*on that receipt will show vote? - poor explana*ons provided to par*cipants? - genuine difficulty in understanding the principle?</p>
    <p>Reference: Focus Group Views on Prt  Voter 1.0 Schneider, Llewellyn, Culnane, Heather, Srinivasan, Xia Requirements Engineering for Electronic Vo3ng Systems 2011</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduc*on  The Prt  Voter voter-verifiable system  Users understanding  Experiment Design  Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prt  Voter</p>
    <p>A voter-verifiable vo*ng system, invented by Peter Ryan  Verifiability: voters and independent checkers can verify</p>
    <p>stages of the elec*on</p>
    <p>Integrity (uncondi*onal): checkable evidence is provided that the result is correct</p>
    <p>Privacy: have to trust some elements of the system, but aim to minimize this</p>
    <p>A Polling place scheme (not Internet). All procedures in a controlled environment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Candidates in random order</p>
    <p>Prt  Voter Ballot Forms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Candidates in random order</p>
    <p>Prt  Voter Ballot Forms</p>
    <p>Different ballot forms have different orders.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Candidates in random order</p>
    <p>Prt  Voter Ballot Forms</p>
    <p>Different ballot forms have different orders.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Candidates in random order</p>
    <p>Prt  Voter Ballot Forms</p>
    <p>Different ballot forms have different orders.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Candidates in random order</p>
    <p>Prt  Voter Ballot Forms</p>
    <p>Different ballot forms have different orders.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Place X or preferences against desired candidate. (candidates in random order)</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Place X or preferences against desired candidate. (candidates in random order)</p>
    <p>Separate lea hand side.</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Place X or preferences against desired candidate. (candidates in random order)</p>
    <p>Separate lea hand side.  Destroy lea hand side.</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Place X or preferences against desired candidate. (candidates in random order)</p>
    <p>Separate lea hand side.  Destroy lea hand side.</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Place X or preferences against desired candidate. (candidates in random order)</p>
    <p>Separate lea hand side.  Destroy lea hand side.</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Place X or preferences against desired candidate. (candidates in random order)</p>
    <p>Separate lea hand side.  Destroy lea hand side.  Cast (scan) vote.</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Place X or preferences against desired candidate. (candidates in random order)</p>
    <p>Separate lea hand side.  Destroy lea hand side.  Cast (scan) vote.</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Place X or preferences against desired candidate. (candidates in random order)</p>
    <p>Separate lea hand side.  Destroy lea hand side.  Cast (scan) vote.  Take receipt home.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>X</p>
    <p>Doesnt the receipt show how you voted?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>X</p>
    <p>Crystal</p>
    <p>Doesnt the receipt show how you voted?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>X</p>
    <p>Diane</p>
    <p>Doesnt the receipt show how you voted?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>X</p>
    <p>Doesnt the receipt show how you voted?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>X</p>
    <p>Elaine</p>
    <p>Doesnt the receipt show how you voted?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voters can choose to confirm the ballot form instead To check the printed list of candidates matches the ciphertext</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voters can choose to confirm the ballot form instead To check the printed list of candidates matches the ciphertext</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Public bulle*n board of votes cast.</p>
    <p>ifde</p>
    <p>w8u</p>
    <p>jt1e</p>
    <p>Voters receipt</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voters confirm inclusion of their untampered vote</p>
    <p>Public bulle*n board of votes cast.</p>
    <p>ifde</p>
    <p>w8u</p>
    <p>jt1e</p>
    <p>Voters receipt</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tallying</p>
    <p>When the votes are cast:</p>
    <p>Publish the votes cast (newspaper, or web bulle*n board)  these should match the receipts, and voters can check.</p>
    <p>Mix up the votes (see next slide), so resul*ng votes are not linked to input votes (which correspond to receipts):</p>
    <p>Decrypt the mixed votes  Publish the resul*ng votes.  Count the votes.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Server 1 Server 2 Server 3 Server 4</p>
    <p>Re-encryp$on mixnets</p>
    <p>Re-encryp*on mixing: {c,r1}  {c,r2} are different encryp*ons of c</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tellers provide `proofs of shuffles: that the set of encrypted values is not changed from one stage to the next.</p>
    <p>These proofs can be independently checked.</p>
    <p>Server 1 Server 2 Server 3 Server 4</p>
    <p>proof1 proof 2 proof 3 proof 4</p>
    <p>Re-encryp$on mixnets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voters Encrypted Votes</p>
    <p>Encrypted Votes Results</p>
    <p>Ballot Cas*ng</p>
    <p>Ballot Shuffling</p>
    <p>by mixnet</p>
    <p>Decrypt and Count</p>
    <p>Verify by receipts</p>
    <p>Verify by checking proofs</p>
    <p>Verify by public</p>
    <p>informa*on</p>
    <p>End-to-end verifiability</p>
    <p>End-to-end Verifiability for Prt  Voter</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduc*on  The Prt  Voter voter-verifiable system  Users understanding  Experiment Design  Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why is it important whether voters understand?</p>
    <p>If voters think the receipt gives away informa*on about how they voted, or if they are unsure...</p>
    <p>they may destroy the receipt instead of retaining it to check its presence on the web bulle*n board</p>
    <p>if they dont intend to check the WBB themselves, they are less likely to give it to someone to check on their behalf</p>
    <p>they could be suscep*ble to bluff coercion (I want you to vote for my candidate - give me the receipt so I can check)</p>
    <p>they might decide not to vote at all as the safest op*on 17</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inves$ga$ng understanding</p>
    <p>Want to inves*gate understanding of the principle of the split ballot: do people `get it ?</p>
    <p>Design an economics-style game where par*cipants will make choices and obtain a financial reward</p>
    <p>Underlying assump*ons:  Par*cipants want to maximise their return  Par*cipants will make choices that they perceive to be in</p>
    <p>their own best interest</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Linking behaviour and understanding</p>
    <p>Want to link par*cipant behaviour (observable) to understanding (not directly observable, and harder to elicit)</p>
    <p>Game design:  If they believe the receipt gives nothing away, they will</p>
    <p>make a par*cular choice</p>
    <p>If they believe the receipt may give informa*on away (about their vote), they will make the other choice</p>
    <p>If unsure, they may vary between the two choices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Notes</p>
    <p>Not intended to be a simula*on of an actual elec*on  We emphasise to par*cipants that it is an economics style</p>
    <p>game, i.e. there is no decep*on: they are told what is actually going on. We are interested in their strategies given the rules of the game.</p>
    <p>Care with terminology taken not to bias their understanding. In par*cular the word guess was avoided for their selec*ons.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduc*on  The Prt  Voter voter-verifiable system  Users understanding  Experiment Design  Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Audience par$cipa$on</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Each par*cipant is given a PaV ballot form and casts a vote: - marks an X - separates the two halves - shreds the names - submits the remaining half (receipt)</p>
    <p>They also decide, before submission, if their receipt will be made public to the other par*cipants: they mark Post or Not post.</p>
    <p>Step 1</p>
    <p>Ali</p>
    <p>Dawn</p>
    <p>Eliot</p>
    <p>Cathy</p>
    <p>Ben</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Submission of a vote (for Cathy)</p>
    <p>or</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Step 2</p>
    <p>For each vote cast, par*cipants select who they think that vote was for. If the receipt for that vote is `posted, then they get to see it when making their selec*on.</p>
    <p>Par*cipants do not know which of them cast the vote. They have nothing to go on, except (possibly) the posted receipt.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Step 2: ballot 101</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>selections collected from all participants</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Step 2: ballot 102</p>
    <p>no post</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Step 2: ballot 103</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>etc</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Payoff</p>
    <p>Pos*ng: 1.00 if you post, nothing if you dont.  Making a correct selec*on: 0.50 for each correct selec*on of</p>
    <p>a vote cast.</p>
    <p>Having a correct selec*on made against your vote: -0.50.</p>
    <p>e.g. Terry chooses to post his receipt, correctly selects 2 and has 3 correct selec*ons against him. Payoff: 0.50</p>
    <p>e.g. Sharon chooses not to post her receipt, correctly selects 2 and has 1 correct selec*on against her. Payoff: 0.50</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>To post or not to post? linking behaviour to understanding  Other par*cipants will guess at your choice irrespec3ve of</p>
    <p>whether you post</p>
    <p>The only difference is that if you post then they can see your receipt when they make their selec*on</p>
    <p>If you think that will help (some of) them make a correct selec*on then you will expect to lose money for correct selec*ons being made against you, outweighing the 1 gained for pos*ng. So you will not post.</p>
    <p>If you think it will make no difference then you will post and take the 1 for pos*ng</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Calibra$on</p>
    <p>The expected payoff for a round is 1 if you post, and 0 if you dont post. Large enough (especially over several rounds) not to throw away.</p>
    <p>Value of a correct guess is selected to be large enough that several correct guesses against a par*cipant will outweigh the gain from pos*ng, so an uncertain par*cipant will be incen*vised not to post</p>
    <p>Also large enough to allow for fluctua*ons from the guessing to give anomalous feedback and worry uncertain par*cipants. [This happened on one occasion, but not enough to draw conclusions.]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Several Rounds</p>
    <p>The game runs for several rounds (5 or 6)  The first couple of *mes allow for par*cipants getng to</p>
    <p>understand the rules of the game and the payoffs</p>
    <p>Also allows for par*cipants to develop their strategy as they develop their understanding</p>
    <p>Expect stabilisa*on aaer ~6 rounds</p>
    <p>Ini*al stake: 10. Final payoff between 10 and 20 (for 90 minutes par*cipa*on)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Feedback between rounds: op$ons</p>
    <p>No feedback  Payoff of each par*cipant  Payoff of each par*cipant and whether or not they posted  Average payoff for posGng group and for non-posGng group</p>
    <p>e.g. In this round, - pos*ng group average payoff 0.83 - non-pos*ng group average payoff 0.50</p>
    <p>Almost all rounds had the pos*ng group average payoff higher than the non-pos*ng group average</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Par$cipants</p>
    <p>Obtained mostly by email adver*sing  Mostly postgrad students (across subjects), some university</p>
    <p>staff</p>
    <p>Told to expect a payoff of 10-20 for 90 minutes par*cipa*on</p>
    <p>12 per session</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduc*on  The Prt  Voter voter-verifiable system  Users understanding  Experiment Design  Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>5 sessions  60 par*cipants  29 rounds</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ballot pos$ng by round</p>
    <p>No sta*s*cally significant trend. High pos*ng rate throughout.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Majority seemed to get it straight away, even without any explana*on of the split ballot principle</p>
    <p>Most of the rest appeared to comprehend, but with less certainty... ... or did they `follow the money without understanding?</p>
    <p>Anecdotally: user trials in Victoria have found that voters either get it or arent worried about it.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Further possible experiments</p>
    <p>Adjus*ng the experiment to use different feedback - individual payoffs per round (much more fluctua*ng, but par*cipants may s*ll be following the money) - no feedback at all (only change between rounds will be increased understanding of the game and the rules)</p>
    <p>Giving an explana*on of the split ballot before the game  Interviewing par*cipants aaer the game about their reasons</p>
    <p>for making their choices</p>
    <p>Wider cross-sec*on of popula*on, different demographics  Understanding of other elements of the system?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
