<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Classifica(on of UDP Traffic for DDoS Detec(on</p>
    <p>Alexandru G. Bardas, Loai Zomlot, Sathya Chandran, Xinming Ou</p>
    <p>Kansas State University</p>
    <p>{bardasag, xou, lzomlot, sathya}@ksu.edu</p>
    <p>S. Raj Rajagopalan, Marc R. Eisenbarth</p>
    <p>HP Labs, HP TippingPoint</p>
    <p>{raj.rajagopalan, marc.r.eisenbarth}@hp.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why UDP based DoS/DDoS?</p>
    <p>Reportedly a significant part of the recent effecWve DDoS aXack traffic was based on UDP</p>
    <p>Our work is focused on detecWng DoS/DDoS flooding a&lt;acks leveraging UDP packets</p>
    <p>Free tools that perform flooding aXacks: Low Orbit Ion Canon (LOIC), Stacheldraht, Trin00 etc.</p>
    <p>Despite past research, we sWll lack pracWcal soluWons to deal with UDP DoS/DDoS aXacks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Datagram Protocol</p>
    <p>UDP is a transport protocol that offers minimal transport service</p>
    <p>UDP Packet:</p>
    <p>UDP does NOT provide reliability, datagram ordering and data integrity</p>
    <p>Source Port (opWonal) DesWnaWon Port</p>
    <p>Length Checksum (opWonal)</p>
    <p>Payload</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UDP DoS/DDoS CharacterisWcs</p>
    <p>Usual UDP flooding packets properWes:  Every packet has the same payload</p>
    <p>The source IP address may or may NOT be spoofed (more effecWve if its not randomized)</p>
    <p>In case of a flooding a&lt;ack there is a one-way flood of packets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UDP DoS/DDoS DetecWon Challenges</p>
    <p>Unique payloads can be generated for every single UDP packet</p>
    <p>Replay a&lt;acks  aXackers may send previously recorded benign UDP traffic</p>
    <p>UDP is stateless  DoS/DDoS prevenWon methods based on connecWon state are not applicable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The ProporWonal Packet Rate AssumpWon</p>
    <p>During normal operaWon, the packet rate of traffic going to an address is proporWonal to the packet rate of traffic going from that address</p>
    <p>[T.M. Gil, M. PoleXo, MULTOPS: a data-structure for bandwidth a:ack detec&lt;on, 2001]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-RaWo IntuiWon</p>
    <p>Hypotheses:</p>
    <p>Under normal operaWon the raWo will be less than a predefined allowed maximum threshold value</p>
    <p>RaWo can be used to separate benign traffic from aXack traffic</p>
    <p>Source Des(na(on</p>
    <p>For every n data packets</p>
    <p>ConfirmaWon packet</p>
    <p>ApplicaWon Layer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Using the ProporWonal Packet Rate AssumpWon in a Classifier</p>
    <p>DoS/DDoS flooding aXacks can be detected early at the vicWms side by calculaWng the raWos for every single sender</p>
    <p>We developed a classifier based on the proporWonality assumpWon</p>
    <p>Classifier monitors an enterprise network to detect possible DDoS flooding aXacks targeted at it</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Classifier  Basic Approach</p>
    <p>if ra)o1  threshold-value</p>
    <p>ALERT!</p>
    <p>Its fine !</p>
    <p>True</p>
    <p>False</p>
    <p>ra)ox=</p>
    <p># IN pktsx</p>
    <p># IN pktsx</p>
    <p># OUT pktsx , # OUT pktsx  0</p>
    <p>, # OUT pktsx= 0 # IN pkts2 # OUT pkts2</p>
    <p>expired bucket TTL</p>
    <p>valid bucket TTL</p>
    <p># IN pktsN # OUT pktsN</p>
    <p>valid bucket TTL</p>
    <p>src_IP_addr1 # IN pkts1 # OUT pkts1</p>
    <p>src_IP_addrN</p>
    <p>src_IP_addr2</p>
    <p>Monitored DesWnaWon</p>
    <p>calculate ra)oN</p>
    <p>calculate ra)o1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ExperimentaWon</p>
    <p>Hypotheses:  Under normal operaWon the raWo will be less than a predefined</p>
    <p>allowed maximum threshold value</p>
    <p>RaWo can be used to separate benign traffic from aXack traffic  Measured the raWo for benign and aXack traffic on:</p>
    <p>Synthe(c Data:  Own testbed at Kansas State (Argus CyberSecurity Lab)  DeterLab</p>
    <p>Produc(on Networks:  Our departmental network (CIS - CompuWng and InformaWon Sciences)</p>
    <p>Non-DNS UDP packet captures from twelve dis(nct networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DeterLab Setup</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CIS Departmental Network Setup</p>
    <p>Campus Network (Internet access)</p>
    <p>CIS Internal Network Span link</p>
    <p>CIS Core Router</p>
    <p>Machine running the DoS/DDoS detecWon tool</p>
    <p>Reports DoS/DDoS suspicious source</p>
    <p>addresses 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Twelve DisWnct Networks</p>
    <p>Data from a large number of producWon networks including:  Large corporaWons (edge and core)  ISPs  UniversiWes  Financial insWtuWons</p>
    <p>For privacy reason DNS traffic was removed and names cannot be revealed</p>
    <p>Data was captured between 2002 and 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Benign UDP-Traffic RaWos VariaWons</p>
    <p>BTTL in sec</p>
    <p>Argus Testbed</p>
    <p>DeterLab Data from Produc(on Networks</p>
    <p>CIS D+ G ISP O+ S T C0</p>
    <p>. . .</p>
    <p>Legend:</p>
    <p>Symbol Meaning</p>
    <p>+ contains one-way protocols</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AXack Traffic RaWos Time into the A&lt;ack</p>
    <p>(sec)</p>
    <p>Ra(o  ArgusTestBed (w/ LOIC traffic)</p>
    <p>Ra(o  DeterLab (w/ LOIC traffic)</p>
    <p>Highest Speed Lowest Speed Highest Speed Lowest Speed</p>
    <p>A&lt;ack Traffic is present and BTTL = 3 sec</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Analysis (1/2)</p>
    <p>Benign applicaWons use UDP packets in different ways:  Constant communica(on between sender and receiver</p>
    <p>Examples: NFS, video streaming applicaWons (Sopcast)</p>
    <p>Ini(al communica(on and then a one-way burst of UDP packets  Examples: SIP (Session IniWaWon Protocol), T.38 protocol (fax)</p>
    <p>One-way burst of packets (by protocol design no response message is necessary)  Examples: Syslog over UDP, Newlow (older versions)</p>
    <p>Hypotheses hold if the cutoff pair values (threshold value - BTTL) are appropriately chosen</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Analysis (2/2)</p>
    <p>DDoS aXempt discovered in the ISP dataset  Benign RaWo was approx. 85</p>
    <p>Discovered using a sequence of classifiers (with different cutoff pair values) to monitor the same target</p>
    <p>Dura(on (sec)</p>
    <p>Ra(o 21  39  45  64  84  99  100  218  349  373</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LimitaWons &amp; Future Work</p>
    <p>Spoofed (especially randomized) IP addresses and Network Address TranslaWon setups can cause problems for the classifier</p>
    <p>Inline version of the classifier is under development</p>
    <p>Interacts with the source by blocking the incoming packets for a very short Wme (NACK feature)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Designed a UDP traffic classificaWon algorithm based on the proporWonal-packet rate assumpWon</p>
    <p>ProporWonality assumpWon examined through experimentaWon on a large number of data sets from producWon networks and various testbeds</p>
    <p>ExperimentaWon results provide key observaWons for DoS/DDoS detecWon</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
