<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Understanding the Emerging Threat of DDoS-as-a-Service</p>
    <p>Mohammad Karami and Damon McCoy George Mason University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What this Talk is About</p>
    <p>Booter services are commoditizing DDoS</p>
    <p>DDoS as subscription based service  Tiered pricing (Payment via PayPal)  Easy to use website interface  Ability to DDoS medium-end webservers</p>
    <p>Use leaked backend data from TWBooter to</p>
    <p>gain insight</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to Setup Booter Service</p>
    <p>Step 1: Website code  Asylumbooter source code is available at:</p>
    <p>http://softwaretopic.informer.com/asylum-bootersource/</p>
    <p>Step 2: Attack Infrastructure  Rent or use compromised servers</p>
    <p>Step 3: Establish payment via PayPal  Step 4: Advertise on Hackforums and Gamer sites  Step 5: Profit $$$</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dataset</p>
    <p>Publicly post backend data from TWBooter2</p>
    <p>Includes information on all attacks  IP/Domain targeted, type, duration, client  Confirmed details of attacks with one victim</p>
    <p>Provides insight into infrastructure, users, and victims</p>
    <p>Duration Users Victims Attacks</p>
    <p>Jan. 2013 - Mar. 2013 312 11,174 48,844</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Used to Target Bloggers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TWBooter Details</p>
    <p>People  Askaa (Money)  DaL33t (Developer)  Both non-US citizens</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack Infrastructure</p>
    <p>15 servers total servers  3 active the entire two months  Most hosted at a Netherlands ISP  9 active at the time of data leak</p>
    <p>Offered SYN flood, UDP flood and amplification attacks, HTTP-based attacks including HTTP POST/GET/HEAD and RUDY (RU-Dead-Yet)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack Capacity</p>
    <p>Subscribed to service to measure capacity.</p>
    <p>SYN Floods spoof IP  UDP Flood uses DNS amplification</p>
    <p>HTTP used 26,296 proxy servers over 5 mins  Some of these leaked original attack servers IPs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Growth Rate</p>
    <p>After initial burst growth rate of 3.2 Users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Subscriptions</p>
    <p>Categorized users based on subscription type  Gamers &lt;= 10 Min attacks (65%)  Website &gt;= 1 hour attacks (32%)  Privileged unlimited attacks (3%)</p>
    <p>TwBooter earned $7,727/month based on subscription type</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Attacks</p>
    <p>6 users are responsible for half (28,154 hours) of the attack time.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Victims</p>
    <p>10,485 unique IP addresses attacked</p>
    <p>689 identified as websites  Most are either game servers or game forums  Other booters and bloggers also targeted</p>
    <p>Two users attacked government sites for 142 hours  Two Indian government  Los Angles police department</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other Booter Services</p>
    <p>Leaks backend for Asylumbooter  Shows 5,622 subscribers  almost half a million attacks over 16 months</p>
    <p>More backends can be found on pastebin  Show evidence of compromised servers used as</p>
    <p>attack infrastructure  Hacked into by vigilante groups, such as</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Booters focused on low cost ($10-$200) and usability</p>
    <p>Integrating features such as anti-cloudflare and Skype tracking</p>
    <p>Uses effective DNS amplification attacks</p>
    <p>TWBooter earned around $7,500/month</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
