<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Devil is Phishing: Rethinking Web Single SignOn Systems Security</p>
    <p>Chuan Yue USENIX Workshop on LargeScale Exploits</p>
    <p>and Emergent Threats (LEET 2013)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Web Single SignOn (SSO) systems</p>
    <p>Sign in multiple relying party (RP) websites using one single identity provider (IdP) account.</p>
    <p>Users are relieved from the huge burden of registering many online accounts and remembering many passwords.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rapid Adoption of Web SSO systems</p>
    <p>Open Web SSO standards OpenID and OAuth.  one billion OpenID enabled user accounts and over 50,000 RP websites (http://openid.net/getan openid/whatisopenid/).</p>
    <p>leading IT companies including Google, Facebook, Microsoft, and Yahoo are OpenID IdPs.</p>
    <p>OAuth 2.0 authorization framework has also been widely supported by IdPs and adopted by a large number of RP websites (http://oauth.net/about/).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security of Web SSO systems</p>
    <p>Formal security analysis of some Web SSO protocols [1, 2]  Logic flaws and implementation vulnerabilities of many deployed Web SSO systems [9, 11]</p>
    <p>Phishing attacks [10, 14, 17, 18] 4</p>
    <p>This figure comes from Reference [10] Figure 1 (a): OpenID login flow</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Example of Previous Web SSO Phishing Study</p>
    <p>This figure comes from Reference [10] page 20 (the original OpenID phishing demo website http://idtheft.fun.de is not available now).</p>
    <p>About 50% success rate in this particular case</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Main Argument and Contributions</p>
    <p>Argument  largescale threat from phishing attacks to realworld Web SSO systems has been significantly underestimated and insufficiently analyzed.</p>
    <p>Contributions  pinpoint what are really unique in Web SSO phishing  provide one example to illustrate how the IdPs of Web SSO systems can be spoofed with ease and precision</p>
    <p>present a preliminary user study to demonstrate the high effectiveness of Web SSO phishing attacks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What are Really Unique in Web SSO phishing</p>
    <p>The value of IdP accounts is highly concentrated.  The attack surface area is highly enlarged.  The difficulty of phishing detection (either by algorithms or</p>
    <p>by users) is highly increased.</p>
    <p>These characteristics make Web SSO phishing more profitable and insidious, and very challenging to defend against.</p>
    <p>Phishers have greater incentives to attack users IdP accounts.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Highly Concentrated Value of IdP Accounts</p>
    <p>A few major IdPs such as Google, Facebook, and Microsoft.</p>
    <p>IdP accounts are already highly valuable by themselves.</p>
    <p>A compromised IdP account also allows attackers to impersonate the victim on a large number of RP websites.</p>
    <p>Phishing IdP accounts becomes more profitable than before.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Highly Enlarged Attack Surface Area</p>
    <p>Traditionally, phishers mainly use spoofed emails.  a spoofed email provides the firstlevel context (asking for account</p>
    <p>verification or update) to entice users to click a phishing URL  the spoofed phishing website further provides the secondlevel context (e.g.,</p>
    <p>with look and feel similar to a targeted real website)</p>
    <p>In terms of this firstlevel context, the success of traditional phishing is limited by two main constraints:  phishing emails are suspicious, users would not visit phishing sites [3, 5]  a large number of phishing emails are captured by spam filters [12]</p>
    <p>In Web SSO, clicking a button that represents an IdP (e.g., Google or Facebook) to visit the IdPs login webpage is a common practice. Phishers are freed from these two constraints  they can host their own legitimate RP websites or webpages and post URLs everywhere (e.g., Web forums, blogs, and advertisements).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Highly Increased Phishing Detection Difficulty</p>
    <p>The clickandpopup user interaction style is the root cause of the difficulty.  a popup IdP login window, although displaying the EVSSL (Extended Validation SSL)</p>
    <p>icon and an HTTPs URL address, can be spoofed with ease and precision.  a spoofed popup login window does not need to correspond to a real URL address, thus</p>
    <p>can make the results of a large number of URLheuristicsbased automatic phishing detection algorithms (e.g., [4, 6, 7, 12, 13]) either inaccurate or incorrect.</p>
    <p>the look and feel of a spoofed popup login window can also deceive many users.</p>
    <p>JavaScript window.open() method</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spoofing IdPs with Ease and Precision</p>
    <p>We use HTML, CSS (Cascading Style Sheets), and JavaScript.  the essential trick is that such a spoofed login webpage is not contained in a real</p>
    <p>popup browser window  it is indeed contained in an HTML &lt;div&gt; (i.e., division) element, which is supported in all major browsers.</p>
    <p>the EVSSL icon and the HTTPs URL address in the &lt;div&gt; element are spoofed by copying a complete snapshot of the icon and the URL address from a real IdP login window.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Preliminary User Study</p>
    <p>Participants and Procedure  28 (offers a reasonably tight confidence</p>
    <p>interval [19]) adults, 14 females and 14 males, participated in our study.</p>
    <p>each participant logs into our shopping website using either a Google or a Facebook test account, and using one of the three browsers (i.e., Google Chrome, Firefox, and IE).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Study Results and Analysis</p>
    <p>Preprocedure Questionnaire  by looking at the Web SSO example webpage of one RP website (sears.com),</p>
    <p>Postprocedure  Q1: Is that Gmail or Facebook login page a genuine one?  Q2: Have you heard about phishing attacks?.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Study Results and Analysis</p>
    <p>Preprocedure Questionnaire  by looking at the Web SSO example webpage of one RP website (sears.com),</p>
    <p>Postprocedure  Q1: Is that Gmail or Facebook login page a genuine one?  Q2: Have you heard about phishing attacks?.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion and Conclusion</p>
    <p>Web SSO phishing is more profitable and insidious than traditional phishing, and is very challenging to defend against.</p>
    <p>The clickandpopup user interaction style is the root cause of the highly increased phishing detection difficulty for algorithms and users. We are exploring some smooth Web content and context switching techniques to address this root cause.</p>
    <p>IdPs should further improve their phishing protection capabilities. For example, they may need to actively adopt twofactor authentication techniques and incentivize users.</p>
    <p>Users should be educated and trained to understand and identify Web SSO phishing.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
