<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimizing a News Website for Speed and</p>
    <p>Stability</p>
    <p>Julian Dunn SecondMarket, Inc.</p>
    <p>Blake Crosby Canadian Broadcasting Corp.</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>- Who has worked for a news website - Who has configured a CDN - familiar with a CDN?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Whats This Talk About?</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12 Whats This Talk About?</p>
    <p>- How to build &amp; operate a large media website</p>
    <p>without spending millions of $</p>
    <p>without having it go down every 5 minutes</p>
    <p>Some technical things, but set the stage with non-technical things</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to build and operate a large media website...</p>
    <p>... without spending millions of dollars Friday, December 14, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>... and without your site going down every 5 minutes.</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Who Am I?</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>Systems engineer, worked for CBC as digital operations team lead for many years Now working for alternative markets startup in New York City doing cloud infrastructure &amp; web operations.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>CBC - Canadas National Public Broadcaster</p>
    <p>- Similar to NPR + PBS - combined radio and television station</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>cbc.ca</p>
    <p>- Most popular news website in Canada - 1 million unique visitors per day - News, sports, radio &amp; TV streaming (live and on demand), regional news, arts &amp; entertainment, etc. etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>Very first YouTube video was posted in 2005. Jawed Karim co-founder right here in San Diego at the zoo. (which I highly recommend -- its $44 but worth the money. one of the best zoos)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>We put up this website -- unbelievably its still up. I can also talk about data retention issues on a news website but thats a whole other talk.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>Polls closed at 9 p.m. Pacific Time</p>
    <p>Shortly after the site was down for over two hours</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(300 origin req/sec over 6 servers) WTF, right? Why?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bad Assumptions Friday, December 14, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Make the news stories appear as fast as possible</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>Journalists say, I want the stories to be as fresh as possible - were a news site after all</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>Developers say, ok thats great, well put all the stories in an Oracle database</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>+</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>And well render them using a J2EE web application.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Architecture was wrong Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>But this is actually not a great architecture for a news website.</p>
    <p>To understand why this is a bad idea, you have to look at news site access patterns</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>News of Whitney Houstons death Feb 11, 2012</p>
    <p>From &lt; 1 Gbps to 13 Gbps virtually instantaneously</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Number of Story Updates Per Hour</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>Story is updated very infrequently, though. Only about 5-6 times per hour even when news is breaking, and over a storys lifetime perhaps one or two dozen times.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>+</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>Senseless to use J2EE application to render stories.</p>
    <p>Wastes a lot of CPU doing the same thing over and over.</p>
    <p>Can even read about this in the outage post-mortem report from BC Votes 2005.</p>
    <p>Election news stories were not cached on disk.</p>
    <p>All stories were generated dynamically which requires more computer processing, hence resulting in more load on the servers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Real, Conflicting Requirements</p>
    <p>Stability and reliability  Content freshness  System complexity  Cost</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Site Architecture: SSI</p>
    <p>Primitive, but fast/secure  Audit trail  Easy to turn off site features  Details of wrapper mechanism in paper</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>Cache cache cache -- we took this to the extreme and made the backend as close to a cache as possible.</p>
    <p>News portion: no dynamic features outside SSI</p>
    <p>SSI is primitive, but fast/secure</p>
    <p>Audit trail - nothing gets into production w/o going through CMS</p>
    <p>Turn off features easily by modifying wrappers to discard site elements</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Delivery Parameters</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Set Global Site TTL</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>Originally all kinds of TTL rules for different types of content, path names, etc. Too complicated; journalists constantly calling helpdesk to purge things from cache</p>
    <p>If you have to purge things from cache youre doing it wrong.</p>
    <p>Setting a global site TTL (of 20 seconds) covers most cases and is fresh enough (ran some experiments with journalists and they seem not to notice that publishing is not actually instant)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>If-Modified-Since:</p>
    <p>GET /news/world/story/2012/02/11/whitneyhouston-dies.html HTTP/1.1</p>
    <p>HTTP/1.1 200 OK Content-Type: text/html</p>
    <p>CDN Origin</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>This is the regular HTTP transaction that we all know and love.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>If-Modified-Since:</p>
    <p>GET /news/world/story/2012/02/11/whitneyhouston-dies.html HTTP/1.1</p>
    <p>If-Modified-Since: Wed, 19 Oct 2005 10:50:00 GMT</p>
    <p>HTTP/1.1 304 Not Modified</p>
    <p>CDN Origin</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>If IMS is configured properly and the CDN has the object in cache, this is what the interaction looks like. Very small origin response, no need to send content body in most cases.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>Most cases actually turns out to be a lot... over two thirds of requests can be served out of CDN cache</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Organize filesystem by desired TTL</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>Allows you to override TTLs by path, e.g. long-lived objects can go in one top-level directory, medium-lived objects go in another, and so on. (examples: /favicon.ico, global site JS and CSS, etc.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Last mile acceleration, origin compression</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>origin compression - make sure to talk gzip to the CDN LMA - enable CDN to pass along the same gzipped content to the end-user</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Persistent connections Appropriate timeouts</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>* Set pconns with the CDN * Origin KeepAliveTimeout value synchronized with CDN (CDN, max 300s for pconn, origin KeepAliveTimeout 301s) so that origin doesnt kill the pconn before the CDN does</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General Lessons Learned</p>
    <p>Keep cache rules simple</p>
    <p>Keep tuning knobs at origin if you can</p>
    <p>Organize &amp; categorize content</p>
    <p>Understand meaning of TTL</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>TTL is not like a DNS TTL. It just means the time after which the CDN will check the origin for object freshness. If still fresh, then itll keep serving the object out of cache.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outcomes</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outcomes</p>
    <p>2003-2010 - no need to grow origin  2010-today - 9 origin webservers</p>
    <p>Average 40% CPU utilization</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>Entire origin farm to deliver content costs around $15K to buy, astonishing for a large news website.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>Another set of graphs showing that the strategy pays off; CDN serves 80-90% of traffic (both bandwidth &amp; requests)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>@julian_dunn jdunn@aquezada.com www.juliandunn.net</p>
    <p>ICQ: 1326831 (thats what was cool in 2005)</p>
    <p>Friday, December 14, 12</p>
    <p>My wifes ICQ # is 1290758 so she brags that shes cooler than me because her number is lower.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
