<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N IS</p>
    <p>T D</p>
    <p>N S</p>
    <p>S E</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>DNSSEC Deployment in the .gov TLD</p>
    <p>Scott Rose, NIST scott.rose@nist.gov</p>
    <p>LISA 2012, San Diego CA Dec. 14, 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N IS</p>
    <p>T D</p>
    <p>N S</p>
    <p>S E</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>What This Talk Will Cover  DNSSEC deployment drivers in the US Federal</p>
    <p>government  How did deployment progress?</p>
    <p>SPOILER ALERT: It wasnt speedy  Addressing poor deployment progress  Errors in deployment  What lessons were learned?</p>
    <p>i.e. If we could start over, what would I do different?</p>
    <p>This talk will not be about how DNSSEC works</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N IS</p>
    <p>T D</p>
    <p>N S</p>
    <p>S E</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>Drivers of DNSSEC Deployment  Black Hat 2008  Kaminsky Bug presented.  Same month: OMB-08-23 issued</p>
    <p>.gov to be signed Jan 2009  Rest of Federal (Executive Branch) zones by Dec 2009</p>
    <p>DNSSEC added to Federal Information Security Measurement Act (FISMA) controls  All Federal information systems fall under this</p>
    <p>regulation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N IS</p>
    <p>T D</p>
    <p>N S</p>
    <p>S E</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>So How Did We Do?  At first: Not good.</p>
    <p>The .gov TLD signed Feb 2009  Less than 30% of child zones met their deadline</p>
    <p>Error rates high  10% plus of (signed) zones had errors on a given day</p>
    <p>Very few caught by operators or noticed by clients (validation rarely seen)</p>
    <p>Some lingered in error state for weeks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N IS</p>
    <p>T D</p>
    <p>N S</p>
    <p>S E</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>Deployment Challenges</p>
    <p>Time is now a factor  Regular care and feeding required (i.e. resigning) even if DNS</p>
    <p>zone data has not changed.</p>
    <p>Increased Parent-Child Interaction  Child zones upload key material to Parent zone</p>
    <p>New operations require time, training to learn  Or (sometimes) new equipment or service change</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N IS</p>
    <p>T D</p>
    <p>N S</p>
    <p>S E</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>DNSSEC Operational Flow</p>
    <p>Data</p>
    <p>ZSK</p>
    <p>KSK</p>
    <p>Data</p>
    <p>ZSK</p>
    <p>KSK</p>
    <p>DS</p>
    <p>ZSK</p>
    <p>KSK</p>
    <p>DS</p>
    <p>ZSK</p>
    <p>KSK</p>
    <p>Data</p>
    <p>ZSK</p>
    <p>KSK</p>
    <p>DS</p>
    <p>DS</p>
    <p>Island, no DS in parent zone.</p>
    <p>.  DNS root.</p>
    <p>gov.</p>
    <p>opm.gov. nist.gov.</p>
    <p>Signer</p>
    <p>Zone Data</p>
    <p>nist.gov. Internal Operations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N IS</p>
    <p>T D</p>
    <p>N S</p>
    <p>S E</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>DNSSEC Tiger Team  Formed in April 2011 to address lagging</p>
    <p>deployment in .gov and failed security audits  Chartered by the Federal CIO Council and composed</p>
    <p>of volunteers from various agencies.  Held monthly meetings to discuss progress, issues</p>
    <p>and roadblocks to deployment.  Helped produce training material, monitoring</p>
    <p>tools and discussion forums for USG admins.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N IS</p>
    <p>T D</p>
    <p>N S</p>
    <p>S E</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>Impact of Tiger Team Activity</p>
    <p>Tiger Team Formed</p>
    <p>Table taken from the NIST IPv6 and IPv6 monitor showing total number of zones instead of number of agencies.</p>
    <p>However, the trend is the same.</p>
    <p>We got a better list of .gov domains</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N IS</p>
    <p>T D</p>
    <p>N S</p>
    <p>S E</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>What the Numbers Mean  Signed and Valid: We see DNSSEC signatures</p>
    <p>and a secure link from the .gov TLD  Unsigned: No DNSSEC  Error or Island: DNSSEC signatures are found</p>
    <p>over data, but we couldnt validate it.  Error in deployment  No link from .gov (very common part of deployment</p>
    <p>progress: sign zone first, link from .gov second).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N IS</p>
    <p>T D</p>
    <p>N S</p>
    <p>S E</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>Errors Seen in .gov Number of Daily Errors Obtained via Scanning Zone List at data.gov</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N IS</p>
    <p>T D</p>
    <p>N S</p>
    <p>S E</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>Definition of Errors Seen  No Sig: Zone was signed and DS in .gov, but signatures</p>
    <p>or keys missing.  Expired Sigs: RRSIG RRs expiration time has passed</p>
    <p>(no longer valid)  Sigs prior to inception: RRSIG inception time in the</p>
    <p>future.  Bad KSK rollover: Key mismatch between .gov and zone  DS points to pre-published key: DS in .gov points to KSK</p>
    <p>not in use in zone  Other: Some non-DNSSEC error e.g. server down, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N IS</p>
    <p>T D</p>
    <p>N S</p>
    <p>S E</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>Response to Errors Errors Seen</p>
    <p>April 2011 April 2012</p>
    <p>Number Errs.</p>
    <p>Avg. Days to Resolution</p>
    <p>Number Errs</p>
    <p>Avg Days to Resolution</p>
    <p>NoSigs 41 2 6 1 ExpiredSigs 21 6 4 2 SigsPriortoInception</p>
    <p>BadKeyRollover 3 14 2 12 DSPointsToPrePublishedKeys</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N IS</p>
    <p>T D</p>
    <p>N S</p>
    <p>S E</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>Lessons Learned  Set up a monitoring regime to report errors.  Insure each organization provides up to date</p>
    <p>POC for zone and/or security operations.  Who to contact when things go wrong.</p>
    <p>Encourage automation for applicable DNSSEC operations (e.g. resigning).</p>
    <p>Foster an internal community for admins to discuss issues, ask questions, etc.  Closed membership, if necessary</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
