<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Training and Professional Development in an IT</p>
    <p>Community George William Herbert</p>
    <p>Taos, Inc. gherbert@taos.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Studies show  that the worst thing a presenter can do is have</p>
    <p>the same words theyre saying on the slide theyre showing.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why is Professional Development important?</p>
    <p>For you:  Career advancement  Intellectual challenge</p>
    <p>For your employers:  More capable employees  ...who will stay longer</p>
    <p>For the field as a whole:  Adoption rate of new technologies gated by you  Invention rate of new technologies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>This is a Practice and Experience Report</p>
    <p>Not enough numbers, yet.</p>
    <p>Problem:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Telling you a story  Its about people, not computers</p>
    <p>Want you to tell a story later</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Who: The Community  Consulting / Contracting IT workers</p>
    <p>Hundreds of technical staff</p>
    <p>One major geographical region (SF Bay Area)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>When and What  Three major time periods:</p>
    <p>1980s-2004  2004-2008  2008 and on</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>First 15 years  Going back to late 1980s, through 2004ish</p>
    <p>A lot of: Professional Development Reimbursement (PDR), Expert Presentations  Some: Peer Mentoring, Self-paced training between</p>
    <p>assignments, Staff Management, Internal informal technical escalation support network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results  Peer mentoring: zzz</p>
    <p>Self-paced training: zzz</p>
    <p>Staff management: !</p>
    <p>Escalation support: !</p>
    <p>PDR: !</p>
    <p>Expert Presentations: !</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Office Hours  1-day 1-topic talks, internal or external experts or round tables, weekly</p>
    <p>Longer training classes (2-12 class sessions over weeks)</p>
    <p>Annual technical reviews standardized  Our interview process re-applied to existing</p>
    <p>employees</p>
    <p>Secret sauce involved</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Industry and economy-wide ouch  Consultants ancedotally wanted more training / PD</p>
    <p>Economy down  in 2009:  PDR temporarily suspended  Training temporarily suspended  Office hours continued, along with informal PD  Company moved further from major freeway</p>
    <p>Attempt at video distribution of training  Safari accounts for all</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>get to HQ</p>
    <p>Video distribution didnt work.  Shoulda used WebEx or YouTube.</p>
    <p>Internal website needed refresh, didnt get it</p>
    <p>2012: Attendance at office hours down, we changed to shorter more structured classes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some data  Data analysis of 2009 to mid-2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Number of events</p>
    <p>Fig. 1 Training and Office Hours Events</p>
    <p>Office Hours</p>
    <p>Training Classes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Office Hours attendance</p>
    <p>Fraction of total consultant base</p>
    <p>attending each event</p>
    <p>Fig. 2 Office Hours Attendence</p>
    <p>High % off hrs</p>
    <p>Low % off hrs</p>
    <p>Avg % off hrs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Training class attendance</p>
    <p>Fraction of total consultant base</p>
    <p>attending each event</p>
    <p>Fig. 3 Training Event Attendence</p>
    <p>High % training</p>
    <p>Low % training</p>
    <p>Avg % training</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PD Spending</p>
    <p>$0.00</p>
    <p>$50.00</p>
    <p>$100.00</p>
    <p>$150.00</p>
    <p>$200.00</p>
    <p>$250.00</p>
    <p>$300.00</p>
    <p>$350.00</p>
    <p>$400.00</p>
    <p>Fig. 4 Total per-consultant PD costs</p>
    <p>Quarterly PD and training costs/ consultant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Additional attendance statistics</p>
    <p>Approximately half of the consultants showed up at least once over 14 quarters</p>
    <p>Total attendance over 14 quarters was 7 times headcount</p>
    <p>137 total events (103 office hours, 34 training classes) with 1142 attendees (837 office hours, 305 training classes).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results and Benefits  A lot of people are engaged with the training and</p>
    <p>office hours and other professional development</p>
    <p>Those people seem to stay longer and advance faster professionally</p>
    <p>Those people cite the PD as a reason to come to the company and stay with it</p>
    <p>Wish we had better numbers. This is anecdotal. Macro to micro is a data gap.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participation  Some people show up a lot, are very motivated</p>
    <p>They probably self-train if you dont train them</p>
    <p>Some people show up a little, are somewhat motivated  They probably dont self-train that much if you dont</p>
    <p>Some people can be badgered into showing up  They dont self-train that much</p>
    <p>Some people dont show up  Not training themselves much at all</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Things that work  Annual technical reviews</p>
    <p>Weekly or biweekly staff-led office hours</p>
    <p>Longer staff-led training courses</p>
    <p>Escalation support structure</p>
    <p>Videotaping and COTS distribution</p>
    <p>Professional development reimbursements</p>
    <p>Safari accounts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons Learned  Track attendance by a better method than scrawled</p>
    <p>signatures. As you go along, on a computer.</p>
    <p>People arent using all their PDR, even highly selfmotivated learners.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Research  Attendance back to 2004, perhaps 2000 or earlier</p>
    <p>We have the data, just need to dig it up</p>
    <p>Individual attendance records  We have the data, but need to decipher it</p>
    <p>Correlating attendance with performance  How effective?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Strategy that works  Do events regularly.</p>
    <p>Keep trying new things. Some old things stop working, some new things dont work. But many do.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>And a challenge  We did this. Were not supermen. We used our</p>
    <p>smartest people to think about it and lead it, but you have smart people too</p>
    <p>If youre at LISA youre a smart leader. So</p>
    <p>So, go start a local training / professional development program!</p>
    <p>Stick with it</p>
    <p>Track the results. Talk about them.</p>
    <p>You win! We all win!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
