<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theia: Visual Signatures for Problem Diagnosis in Large Hadoop Clusters</p>
    <p>Elmer Garduno, Soila P. Kavulya, Jiaqi Tan, Rajeev Gandhi, Priya Narasimhan</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  Hadoop: Open-source MapReduce framework</p>
    <p>MapReduce is popular for data-intensive computing  100+ companies powered by Hadoop</p>
    <p>Yahoo, Facebook, Hulu,</p>
    <p>Problem diagnosis in Hadoop is challenging  Overwhelming volume of monitoring data  Complex component interactions obscure root-cause</p>
    <p>Goal: Generate visualizations that aid diagnosis</p>
    <p>Soila P. Kavulya  Dec12&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background: Hadoop MapReduce</p>
    <p>JobTracker Job Status</p>
    <p>Map</p>
    <p>Map</p>
    <p>Reduce</p>
    <p>Input splits</p>
    <p>Output file</p>
    <p>Assigns tasks</p>
    <p>Soila P. Kavulya  Dec12&quot;</p>
    <p>TaskTrackers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OpenCloud Cluster</p>
    <p>OpenCloud: Cluster for data-intensive research  64-nodes worker nodes  Each node has 8 cores, 16 GB DRAM,</p>
    <p>Run diverse kinds of real workloads  Graph mining, natural language processing,</p>
    <p>Tools available for diagnosis  Hadoop web console and Ganglia  Sysadmins also use Nagios to receive alerts</p>
    <p>Soila P. Kavulya  Dec12&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Shortcomings of Current Tools</p>
    <p>Ganglia</p>
    <p>Large number of monitoring panels can overwhelm user</p>
    <p>Hadoop Web Console</p>
    <p>Large number of tasks/jobs --- need to click through multiple screens to troubleshoot problem</p>
    <p>hdfs://node1:9000/hadoophome/mapred/system/job_0001/job.xmlhdfs://node1:9000/hadoophome/mapred/system/job_0001/job.xml</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Do Users Want? Users want to distinguish between*:</p>
    <p>*Results from user study published in CHIMIT 2011</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theia: Visualization Tool  Visualizes anomalies in Hadoop clusters</p>
    <p>Maps anomalies observed to broad problem classes  i,e., hardware failures, application issue, data skew</p>
    <p>Interactive interface supports data exploration  Users drill-down from cluster- to job-level displays  Hovering over the visualization gives more context</p>
    <p>Compact representation for scalability  Can support clusters with 100s of nodes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theia Implementation</p>
    <p>TASK_TYPE=&quot;REDUCE&quot; TASKID=X TASK_STATUS=&quot;SUCCESS&quot; HOSTNAME=node32 COUNTERS= [(FILE_BYTES_READ)(229524)] .</p>
    <p>Log Parsers</p>
    <p>Database Anomaly Detection</p>
    <p>Soila P. Kavulya  Dec12&quot;</p>
    <p>Job History Logs (100-300MB/day)</p>
    <p>Web UI</p>
    <p>~30 seconds</p>
    <p>~1-2 seconds</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quantifying Anomalies  Hadoop balances load across nodes in cluster</p>
    <p>Typically, tasks in a job perform similarly  Significant deviations may signal problems</p>
    <p>Indicators of anomalous behavior used by Theia  Large task duration  Large deviations in data processed (data skew)  Large task failure rates</p>
    <p>Quantify anomalies using z-score  Deviation of each observation from the mean  Normalized by standard deviation</p>
    <p>z = x</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Heuristics for Visual Signatures</p>
    <p>Application Problem</p>
    <p>Infrastructural Problem</p>
    <p>Time Single user/job over time</p>
    <p>Multiple users/jobs over time</p>
    <p>Space Span multiple nodes</p>
    <p>Affects single node, but correlated failures also occur</p>
    <p>Value Slow/failed tasks,</p>
    <p>or data skew</p>
    <p>Slow/failed tasks</p>
    <p>Mapping anomalies to problem classes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Types of Visualizations in Theia  Anomaly heatmap</p>
    <p>Visualizes cluster-level anomalies  High density overview of nodes in the cluster</p>
    <p>Job execution stream  Visualizes job-level anomalies  Compact view of aggregate job performance</p>
    <p>Job execution detail  Visualizes job-level anomalies  Detailed view of job progress over time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anomaly Heatmap  High density overview of cluster performance</p>
    <p>Summarizes job performance across nodes  Uses color variations to visualize anomalies</p>
    <p>Compact representation supports scale  Uses 2x2 pixels to represent job/node  Fits 1200 jobs x 700 nodes on a 27-inch display</p>
    <p>Best-suited for visualizing  Infrastructural problems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Heatmap of Hardware Problem N</p>
    <p>od e</p>
    <p>ID</p>
    <p>Job ID (sorted by start time)</p>
    <p>Performance degradation due to failing disk 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Heatmap of Application Problem N</p>
    <p>od e</p>
    <p>ID 1</p>
    <p>Job ID (sorted by start time)</p>
    <p>Resource contention due to buggy job</p>
    <p>Blacklisted node</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Job Execution Stream  Visualizes per-job performance across nodes</p>
    <p>Scrollable stream of jobs sorted by start time  Displays performance of Map and Reduce phases  Uses color variations to visualize anomalies</p>
    <p>Shows job execution trace in context  Job name, duration, and status  Task failure rates  Task duration anomalies</p>
    <p>Best-suited for detecting application problems  Software bugs, data skew</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Job Execution Stream</p>
    <p>Job_9438/HALFCAMS_kmeans_iteration_0  SUCCESS 21:54:47 / 0h 5m 44s / Oct 10</p>
    <p>Darker colored squares indicate anomalous task durations</p>
    <p>Red borders indicate failed tasks</p>
    <p>Yellow borders indicate speculative tasks were killed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Visualizing Application Problems</p>
    <p>job_9035 / depParseFeatExtract -- FAILED</p>
    <p>job_9146 / DocPerLineSentenceExtractor -- SUCCESS</p>
    <p>Soila P. Kavulya  Dec12&quot;</p>
    <p>Bug in reduce phase indicated by failed tasks</p>
    <p>Performance degradation due to data skew</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Job Execution Detail  Detailed view of task execution</p>
    <p>Less compact than job execution stream  Displays progress of job (using color variation)  Displays volume of I/O (using size variation)</p>
    <p>Best-suited for detecting application problems  Software bugs, data skew</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Job Execution Detail</p>
    <p>Maps Reduces</p>
    <p>job_9036 / depParseFeatExtract -- SUCCESS 09:06:48 / 0h 1m 32s / Oct -10</p>
    <p>Anomaly</p>
    <p>Time</p>
    <p>I/O %</p>
    <p>Status (Killed task ratio due to speculative execution)</p>
    <p>Larger size indicates larger I/O</p>
    <p>Divided in 5 equal timeslots</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Skew in Job job_9146 / DocPerLineSentenceExtractor -- SUCCESS 20:25:39 / 0h 17m 36s / Oct -07</p>
    <p>Imbalanced workload due to data skew</p>
    <p>Maps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bad NIC Degrades Performance</p>
    <p>Node: nodeX Successful Tasks: 6 Failed Tasks: 6 Failure Ratio: 0.5 Total I/0: 490 MB Total Time: 0h 23m 28s</p>
    <p>job_9627 / RandomShu!e -- KILLED 06:28:29 / 0h 20m 57s / Oct -09 Maps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of Tool  Analyzed one-month of data on OpenCloud</p>
    <p>1,373 jobs comprising of ~1.83 million tasks  Manually identified 157 application problems</p>
    <p>and 2 data skews  45 hardware failures identified by sysadmins</p>
    <p>42 disk controller failures  2 full hard drive failures  1 network interface controller (NIC) failure</p>
    <p>Evaluated performance by manually verifying that visualizations matched our heuristics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance of Visualizations</p>
    <p>Type Total Heatmap Job Execution Stream</p>
    <p>Application problem 157 0 157</p>
    <p>Infrastructural problem 45 33 10</p>
    <p>Data skew 2 2 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  Theia: Visualizations for Hadoop</p>
    <p>Compact, interactive visualizations of job behavior  Distinguishes h/w failures, s/w bugs, and data skew  Evaluated on real incidents in Hadoop cluster</p>
    <p>Next steps  Deploy on production cluster  User study</p>
    <p>Evaluate the effectiveness of our UI for diagnosis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Problem Diagnosis Website http://www.ece.cmu.edu/~fingerpointing/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work  [Mochi2009] J. Tan, X. Pan, S. Kavulya, R. Gandhi, and P.</p>
    <p>Narasimhan, Mochi: visual log-analysis based tools for debugging Hadoop, Proceedings of the 2009 conference on Hot topics in cloud computing, ser. HotCloud09, 2009</p>
    <p>[CHIMIT2011] J. D. Campbell, A. B. Ganesan, B. Gotow, S. P. Kavulya, J. Mulholland, P. Narasimhan, S. Ramasubramanian, M. Shuster, and J. Tan, Understanding and improving the diagnostic workflow of MapReduce users, ACM Symposium on Computer Human Interaction for Management of Information Technology (CHIMIT), 2011</p>
    <p>[Tufte2001] E. R. Tufte, The Visual Display of Quantitative Information, 2nd ed. Graphics Pr., May 2001</p>
    <p>[Bostock2011] M. Bostock, V. Ogievetsky, and J. Heer, D3: DataDriven documents, IEEE Trans. Visualization &amp; Comp. Graphics (Proc. InfoVis), 2011.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
