<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluating Text Coherence Based on Semantic Similarity Graph</p>
    <p>Jan Wira Gotama Putra and Takenobu Tokunaga Tokyo Institute of Technology, Japan wiragotama.github.io | gotama.w.aa@m.titech.ac.jp</p>
    <p>Semantic Similarity Graph | wiragotama.github.io 1TextGraph-11, ACL 2017</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Modeling coherence in linguistics theory into computational task (Barzilay &amp; Lapata, 2008; Guinaudeau &amp; Strube, 2013; Feng et al., 2014; Li and Hovy, 2014; Petersen et al., 2015, Nguyen and Joty, 2017)</p>
    <p>Approaches  Supervised  mostly</p>
    <p>Unsupervised  infrequent</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Coherence</p>
    <p>Coherent text is integrated as a whole, rather than a series of independent sentences (Bamberg, 1983; Garing, 2014)</p>
    <p>Every sentence in a coherent text has relation(s) to each other (Halliday and Hasan, 1976; Mann and Thompson, 1988; Grosz et al., 1995; Wolf and Gibson, 2005)</p>
    <p>Lexical and semantic (meaning) continuity are indispensable for coherent text (Feng et al., 2014)</p>
    <p>Graph structure</p>
    <p>Evaluate coherence through cohesion</p>
    <p>Semantic similarity</p>
    <p>TextGraph-11, ACL 2017Semantic Similarity Graph | wiragotama.github.io</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work: Entity Graph (1)</p>
    <p>Entity graph was introduced by Guinaudeau &amp; Strube (2013)</p>
    <p>Text -&gt; Bipartite Graph -&gt; Projection Graphs  Coherence is achieved by cohesion: considers</p>
    <p>repeated mention of entities and their syntactical role (weight)</p>
    <p>TextGraph-11, ACL 2017Semantic Similarity Graph | wiragotama.github.io</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Graph data structure can represent the structure of text and relations among sentences</p>
    <p>Coherence is achieved through lexical cohesion: repeated mention of entities.  Disadvantage: cannot capture the relation between related-yet-not identical entities (Li and Hovy,</p>
    <p>Relation between vertices in projection graph has to satisfy surface sequential ordering  Proposal: allows two directions (omit the constraint)</p>
    <p>Related Work: Entity Graph (2)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Formally, text is a graph  , , where   is a set of vertices, &amp; represents i-th sentence.   is a set of edges, &amp;( represents relation (cohesion) from i-th to j-th sentence (weighted &amp;</p>
    <p>directed).  Evaluate the coherence through cohesion</p>
    <p>Sentences are encoded into their meaning form Average of summation of word vectors (distributed representation of words)</p>
    <p>An edge represents cohesion among sentences Establishment of edge is decided as the operation of vectors representation of sentences</p>
    <p>Proposed Method (1)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proposed Method (2)</p>
    <p>Preceding Adjacent Vertex (PAV)</p>
    <p>Single Similar Vertex (SSV)</p>
    <p>Multiple Similar Vertex (MSV)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p># outgoing edges of vertex vi</p>
    <p>An edge is established from the sentence vertex in question to the other vertex with the weight calculated by</p>
    <p>Text coherence measure (higher is better) is calculated by averaging the averaged weight of outgoing edges from every vertex in the graph as</p>
    <p>Semantic Similarity Graph 8</p>
    <p>Proposed Method (3)</p>
    <p>normalization</p>
    <p># vertices TextGraph-11, ACL 2017Semantic Similarity Graph | wiragotama.github.io</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Task 1: Discrimination (Barzilay and Lapata, 2008)  Task 2: Insertion (Eisner and Charniak, 2011)</p>
    <p>Both tasks evaluate how well the methods in comparing coherence between texts</p>
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>TextGraph-11, ACL 2017Semantic Similarity Graph | wiragotama.github.io</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>S4 The goal is to compare original vs. permutated text</p>
    <p>Program is considered successful when giving greater score to the more coherent (original) text</p>
    <p>Dataset: 683 WSJ (LDC) texts, 13586 permutations (avg. 24 sentences, 521 tokens)</p>
    <p>Evaluation: Discrimination Task</p>
    <p>S1</p>
    <p>S2</p>
    <p>S3</p>
    <p>S4</p>
    <p>S1</p>
    <p>S2</p>
    <p>S3</p>
    <p>original permutated</p>
    <p>Semantic Similarity Graph | wiragotama.github.io</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Difference of performance is statistically significant at p &lt; 0.05</p>
    <p>PAV &gt; MSV &gt; Entity Graph Cohesion is not only about repeating mention of entities</p>
    <p>PAV  MSV pair shares 88.3% same judgement (largest).</p>
    <p>Local (adjacent) cohesion is possibly more important than long-distance cohesion</p>
    <p>Result: Discrimination Task</p>
    <p>Method Accuracy</p>
    <p>PAV 0.774 SSV 0.676 MSV 0.741 Entity Graph 0.725</p>
    <p>TextGraph-11, ACL 2017Semantic Similarity Graph | wiragotama.github.io</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Insertion task is more important than discrimination task</p>
    <p>It was proposed by Eisner and Charniak (2011):  Given a text, take out a sentence (randomly), then place it into other positions  Program is considered successful if it prefers to insert take-out-sentence at its original position</p>
    <p>rather than arbitrary (distorted) positions</p>
    <p>Our Proposal: use TOEFL iBT insertion-type questions</p>
    <p>Evaluation: Insertion Task</p>
    <p>?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A text is coherent even without the insertion sentence</p>
    <p>Preservation of coherence is achieved when the question-sentence is inserted in the correct place but disrupt coherence otherwise</p>
    <p>104 questions (avg. 7 sentences, 139 tokens)</p>
    <p>TOEFL iBT Insertion-type Question</p>
    <p>(A) The raising of livestock is a major economic activity in semiarid lands, where grasses are generally the dominant type of natural vegetation. (B) The consequences of an excessive number of livestock grazing in an area are the reduction of the vegetation cover and trampling and pulverization of the soil. (C) This is usually followed by the drying of the soil and accelerated erosion. (D)</p>
    <p>Question: Insert the following sentence into one of (A)-(D) question sentence = &quot;This economic reliance on livestock in certain regions makes large tracts of land susceptible to overgrazing.</p>
    <p>correct answer = B</p>
    <p>TextGraph-11, ACL 2017Semantic Similarity Graph | wiragotama.github.io</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Difference in every pair of methods is not statistically significant at p &lt; 0.05</p>
    <p>14 questions are answered incorrectly by PAV, but correctly by SSV.  In these questions, SSV tends to establish the relationship between distance</p>
    <p>sentences (dist = 2.8). For example, exemplification text</p>
    <p>Result: Insertion Task</p>
    <p>Method Accuracy</p>
    <p>PAV 0.356 SSV 0.346 MSV 0.327 Entity Graph 0.260</p>
    <p>TextGraph-11, ACL 2017Semantic Similarity Graph | wiragotama.github.io</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Coherence can be achieved through cohesion (lexical and semantic continuity)</p>
    <p>Local cohesion is more important than long-distance cohesion in evaluating coherence, but long-distance cohesion can also contribute as well  (PAV &gt; {SSV, MSV})  We need to introduce a more refined mechanism for incorporating distant sentence relations.</p>
    <p>The representation of sentences and method to establish edges would be direct targets of the refinement</p>
    <p>Conclusion and Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Appendix</p>
    <p>Discrimination Task</p>
    <p>Method Accuracy PAV 0.774 SSV 0.676 MSV 0.741 Entity Grid 0.845 Entity Graph 0.725</p>
    <p>Insertion Task</p>
    <p>Method Accuracy PAV 0.356 SSV 0.346 MSV 0.327 Entity Grid 0.346 Entity Graph 0.260</p>
    <p>TextGraph-11, ACL 2017Semantic Similarity Graph | wiragotama.github.io</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References (1)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References (2)</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
