<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Building an Infrastructure For the International</p>
    <p>Math Olympiad</p>
    <p>Rudi van Drunen Karst Koymans</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IMO Infrastructure | Agenda</p>
    <p>The IMO  Requirements  Architecture  Technology  Building  Issues encountered  Lessons learned</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IMO | Facts</p>
    <p>Yearly event  Different country every year  600+ Intl. high school students  100+ members of Jury</p>
    <p>7 days long  2 days of actual contest  5 days of preparation / translation / correction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network | Requirements</p>
    <p>5 Locations  2 Amsterdam hotels Contestants / 2nd Jury location</p>
    <p>1 Amsterdam sports complex Contest location</p>
    <p>1 Eindhoven Hotel  1st Jury location (150 mi. from Amsterdam)</p>
    <p>1 Amsterdam Data center At masters of system administration dept.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network | Requirements</p>
    <p>Controlled Internet Access  The Jury location needed to be offline for some time  Access to the logistics system  Located in the data center  Scanned work available at Jury location  Q&amp;A session before contest</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network | Requirements</p>
    <p>enough Bandwidth  Definition: Better than last year</p>
    <p>Backup scenario (s)  When connectivity fails</p>
    <p>Separate networks  Security</p>
    <p>Flexibility  Changing topology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network | Solution</p>
    <p>Use VLANS to separate traffic  Use a VPN setup  Use NAT to access internet  One internet gateway (and one firewall)</p>
    <p>Use Common Sense  Complexity  Modularity  Open, UNIX</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network | Architecture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network | Architecture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network | Technology</p>
    <p>A FreeBSD server at every location  OpenVPN  DHCP  DNS (slave server)  Router (central site)</p>
    <p>Cisco Wired switches  VLAN separation</p>
    <p>Simple Wireless APs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Central site | Technology</p>
    <p>Open VPN  4 copies of daemon on separate ports  OVPN: single treaded running on Qcore</p>
    <p>Self signed certificate / pki</p>
    <p>NAT  Large number of sessions (think Skype) use in-kernel NAT instead of Userland</p>
    <p>Multiple IP#s prevent running out of source ports</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Remote site | Technology</p>
    <p>Same setup  OpenVPN / Certificates  DNS Slave  DHCP on VLANS</p>
    <p>Anti Lockout Rule  Default route  Specific route</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Site | Setup</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sites | Building</p>
    <p>6 people, 4 days  Improvise, Improvise, Improvise  Document every step  Disseminate documentation</p>
    <p>Schedule  Reasonable deadlines !  Engineers estimate * pi</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sites | Backup</p>
    <p>3G Modems  No dongles</p>
    <p>(warm) standby machine  Replacement for every site  All configs in one directory</p>
    <p>Central site: Multiple internet feeds  Logistics system  Reachable over internet  laptop backup</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Setup | Issues</p>
    <p>Local situation  Internet Feed  Cabling / patches</p>
    <p>Changing / dynamic requirements  Routing issues  Switch configs</p>
    <p>[Logistics] 16</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Setup | Lessons learned</p>
    <p>Site Surveys  Expect the unexpected</p>
    <p>Document  Wiki</p>
    <p>DNS forever  Label everything  Tools (like wireshark)  Handtools</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Setup | Lessons learned</p>
    <p>Do not underestimate the Engineer  Some really creative solutions</p>
    <p>Flexible by design  All VLANS available on all switches  No complicated procedures: be pragmatic</p>
    <p>TEST, Test, test  Allow enough time to build  Be able to cope with politics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Setup | Lessons learned</p>
    <p>Communication !  E-mail, GSM, SMS</p>
    <p>Preparation  Rely on other parts of the organization  A good and motivated team  Is fun to work with  Can do more than you think  Is a TEAM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions | Lessons learned</p>
    <p>R.van.Drunen@xs4all.nl</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
