<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass: Secure Cloud System Administration</p>
    <p>Patrick T. Cable II, Nabil Schear</p>
    <p>Distribution Statement A: Approved for Public Release, Distribution is Unlimited. This work is sponsored by the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Research &amp; Engineering under Air Force Contract #FA8721-05-C-0002. Opinions, interpretations, conclusions and recommendations are those of the author and are not necessarily endorsed by the United States Government.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 2 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>A System Administrators Life</p>
    <p>System administrators have unrestricted access to security-sensitive infrastructure</p>
    <p>Network Switching &amp; Routing</p>
    <p>Hardware Management</p>
    <p>Operating Systems Platforms</p>
    <p>Source Code</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 3 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>The Problem</p>
    <p>Internet Cloud</p>
    <p>Controller Network</p>
    <p>The Insider</p>
    <p>Phishing</p>
    <p>Cloud Controller Network</p>
    <p>Problems for all</p>
    <p>big, and small.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 4 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>Bastion Host</p>
    <p>Lets Protect a Network</p>
    <p>Firewalling</p>
    <p>A look at how well different network devices audit and protect</p>
    <p>Virtual Private Networks</p>
    <p>Limit impact of malicious clients through secure auditable bastion host</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 5 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>Building a Better Bastion Host</p>
    <p>The Problem with Bastion Hosts  Easy to implement insecurely  Unprotected auditing  Single point of failure  Good for side-channel analysis</p>
    <p>Bastion Host</p>
    <p>Spyglass</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 6 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>Threat Model</p>
    <p>System assumptions:  Remote attacker trying to persistently</p>
    <p>access private network  May have compromised a valid users</p>
    <p>source system or credentials  Attacker can compromise applications</p>
    <p>inside of containers that face the remote network and cannot break container isolation</p>
    <p>Attacker cannot compromise control process</p>
    <p>Proper configuration of SSH and container manager</p>
    <p>Valid users must use present multiple factors to authenticate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 7 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>Spyglass Bastion Host</p>
    <p>Spyglass Architecture</p>
    <p>Cloud Controller Network</p>
    <p>Internet Web Application</p>
    <p>Container Manager</p>
    <p>Container 1</p>
    <p>Audit Manager</p>
    <p>Container N</p>
    <p>Non-Persistence</p>
    <p>Auditability</p>
    <p>Isolation</p>
    <p>Multi-Factor Authentication</p>
    <p>Log Repository</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 8 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>Spyglass: Login</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 9 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>Spyglass: Add a Key</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 10 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>Spyglass: New Session</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 11 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>Spyglass: Session Details</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 12 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>Container Instantiation Speed</p>
    <p>Start Setup (ms) Container (ms) Return (ms) Total (ms) 1 7.52 83.39 1.05 91.96 2 3.60 60.60 0.77 64.97 3 3.93 62.60 0.72 67.25 4 4.13 58.89 2.40 65.42 5 3.87 68.25 0.82 72.94</p>
    <p>Stop Delete (ms) Total (ms) 1 25.30 29.63 2 23.54 27.59 3 24.29 28.38 4 23.04 27.24 5 22.89 27.10</p>
    <p>Create Time</p>
    <p>Delete Time</p>
    <p>m ill</p>
    <p>is ec</p>
    <p>on ds</p>
    <p>m ill</p>
    <p>is ec</p>
    <p>on ds</p>
    <p>Containers are quickly available for end-admin use</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 13 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>Host Overhead</p>
    <p>Initial Sign-In SSH Session Start</p>
    <p>Containers are not a memory or CPU burden for the host</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 14 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>Attacks</p>
    <p>Host Denial of Service Network Protection Escalation &amp; Escape</p>
    <p>Was able to fill file system on container host</p>
    <p>Workarounds noted, though may have impact on performance</p>
    <p>User namespaces will make this more difficult</p>
    <p>User must escalate to root inside container</p>
    <p>No SELinux in demo implementation, would add another layer of complexity</p>
    <p>Matters to a varying degree depending on public and private networks</p>
    <p>Proper configuration options with Docker disables container/ container comms</p>
    <p>Further tweaking with IPTables allows for finer grained controls</p>
    <p>User Namespaces Coming Soon to Docker</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spyglass - 15 PTC 11/11/15</p>
    <p>Conclusion and Future Work</p>
    <p>Conclusion  Unauthorized access to control networks allow an</p>
    <p>attacker to wreak havoc on your organization  Spyglass provides an architecture to monitor your</p>
    <p>admins and protect your sensitive control networks</p>
    <p>Future Work  Provide container host key ID to web application  Make auditing collector far more resilient  Ignore sensitive details in audit log  SELinux support  Enterprise authentication tie-in  VNC session support Fork &amp; Improve Spyglass!</p>
    <p>github.com/mitll-cyber</p>
    <p>Relax system admins youre less of a liability now!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
