<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PUSHING BOULDERS UPHILL: THE DIFFICULTY OF NETWORK INTRUSION RECOVERY USENIX LISA 2009 M. Locasto, M. Burnside, &amp; D. Bethea</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Take-home Message</p>
    <p>The problem of network intrusion recovery is a particularly thorny exercise in researching, designing, and creating usable security mechanisms.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenge: Intrusion Recovery</p>
    <p>What should I do when my infrastructure is infiltrated on a massive scale?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sage Advice</p>
    <p>Damage control is much easier when the actual damage is known. If a system administrator doesnt have a log, he or she should reload his compromised system from the release tapes or CD-ROM.</p>
    <p>- Firewalls and Internet Security: Repelling the Wily Hacker (1994)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Intrusion Recovery: Art, Not Science</p>
    <p>Scenario and attack diversity  Institutional and technology differences</p>
    <p>Stigma or legal consequences to admitting breaches  Lack of public, documented scenarios</p>
    <p>Lack of techniques that smoothly handle both technical and human factors involved in recovery</p>
    <p>Thinking of detection and repair as accomplished rather than perpetually ongoing is misleading</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adding to the Lore</p>
    <p>Cliff Stolls Stalking the Wily Hacker (05/88)  Spaffords analysis of Morris Worm (06/89)  Cheswicks log of the Berferd case (01/92)  Abe Singers experiences (02/05)  Frields: Chronicle of a Server Break-in (03/09)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Intrusion Incidents</p>
    <p>March 2007  December 2007  March 2008</p>
    <p>Many other anecdotes  Virginia Prescription Monitoring Database ($10M ransom)  Breaches of U.S. electric grid</p>
    <p>Verizon 2008 Data Breach Incident Report</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Organization Details, Pre-Incident</p>
    <p>Mid-sized academic department at large university  Roughly 1000 heterogeneous workstations  ~50 infrastructure machines  Network infrastructure generally not firewalled  Three to five staff members, single manager</p>
    <p>Range of experience</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>December 2007</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>December 2007</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>December 2007</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>December 2007</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>December 2007</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>December 2007</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>December 2007</p>
    <p>Last day for half the IT staff.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>December 2007</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>December 2007</p>
    <p>Reset all passwords</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>December 2007</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons Learned</p>
    <p>Intrusions discovered through manual examination of puzzling symptoms and side effects of attacks, not Snort or a commercial anti-virus tool</p>
    <p>Complete forensics difficult to achieve  Try balancing risk of analyzing a running server</p>
    <p>providing both essential services as well as service to the attacker</p>
    <p>Operational demands can preclude the opportunity to learn from incidents</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tension: Forensics</p>
    <p>Disable Host Keep Host Up</p>
    <p>Staff Reputation Can observe host; provides service</p>
    <p>ISP Reputation Field less service calls</p>
    <p>Users Risk to confidentiality, integrity, privacy, &amp; availability</p>
    <p>Keep service</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons Learned (cont.)</p>
    <p>We rely on human memory too much:</p>
    <p>goals, suggestions, or objections [can be] misunderstood, warped, or forgotten, leaving potentially large gaps in the actual level of security achieved after repairs complete.</p>
    <p>Having no single complete &amp; coherent forensics analysis gives rise to multiple viewpoints</p>
    <p>Planning for future attacks requires a pervasive, unobtrusive recording system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons Learned (cont.)</p>
    <p>Intrusions present opportunities for the good guys!</p>
    <p>Creative ways of distributing new credentials out of band</p>
    <p>Replace an outdated, slow, or weak authentication system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons Learned (cont.)</p>
    <p>Recovery decisions can be driven by informal preferences rather than objective, quantitative comparison of security properties  E.g., switching OS platforms</p>
    <p>Improvisation seems to rule the day  Challenge: design tools that meet the engineering</p>
    <p>challenges of repairing a network and the management and usability challenges of dealing with humans</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Directions</p>
    <p>Education!  Educated users are great IDS systems  Educating students on how to put a network back together</p>
    <p>again can be even more instructive than CTF exercises  Need an Incident Archive based on a standardized</p>
    <p>encoding of intrusion scenarios and testbed / internet range scenarios</p>
    <p>Pervasive recording infrastructure: recovery trees  Objective technical comparisons of alternatives</p>
    <p>NLP on release notes  Query bug databases &amp; mailing lists</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Concluding Caveat</p>
    <p>We do not aim to lay blame with individualsour goal is to present the facts, disposition of the network, and decisionsas a way to motivate tools that ease the burden on IT staff.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>We believe the community should focus on creating mechanisms that deal with recovery as a system composed of both humans and computers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contact: mlocasto@gmu.edu</p>
    <p>Many thanks to our shepherd, Nicole, for her help, patience, and assistance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Links: Verizon Report &amp; Fedora Saga</p>
    <p>http://securityblog.verizonbusiness.com/ 2008/06/10/2008-data-breach-investigationsreport/</p>
    <p>http://www.linux-magazine.com/Online/News/ Update-Fedora-Chronicle-of-a-Server-Break-in</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tension: Forensics</p>
    <p>ISP: wants machine taken down  Staff: keep machine operational to observe it  Staff &amp; Users: Machine must be operational b/c it</p>
    <p>provides a vital service  Users: want machine taken down (e.g., it represents</p>
    <p>an invasion of privacy)  Staff: want machine disabled (e.g., no mess in my</p>
    <p>backyard!)</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
