<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UUNIVERSITY OF NIVERSITY OF MMASSACHUSETTSASSACHUSETTS, A, AMHERST  MHERST  Department of Computer Science Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>Re-thinking Data Management for Storage-Centric Sensor Networks</p>
    <p>Deepak Ganesan University of Massachusetts Amherst</p>
    <p>With: Yanlei Diao, Gaurav Mathur, Prashant Shenoy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sensor Network Data Management Live Data Management: Queries on current or recent data.</p>
    <p>Applications: Real-time feeds/queries: Weather, Fire, Volcano Detection and Notification: Intruder, Vehicle</p>
    <p>Techniques: Push-down Filters/Triggers: TinyDB, Cougar, Diffusion,  Acquisitional Query Processing: BBQ, PRESTO,</p>
    <p>Archival Data Management: Querying or Mining of past data</p>
    <p>Applications: Scientific Analysis of past events: Weather, Seismic,  Historical trends: Traffic analysis, habitat monitoring</p>
    <p>Our focus is on designing an efficient archival data management architecture for</p>
    <p>sensor networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Archival Querying in Sensor Networks</p>
    <p>Data Gathering with centralized archival query processing</p>
    <p>Efficient for low rate, small volume sensors such as weather sensors (temp, humidity, ).</p>
    <p>Inefficient energywise for rich sensor data (acoustic, video, high-rate vibration).</p>
    <p>Lossless aggregation</p>
    <p>DBMS</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>Gateway</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Archival Querying in Sensor Networks</p>
    <p>Acoustic stream</p>
    <p>Store data locally at sensors and push queries into the sensor network</p>
    <p>Flash memory energyefficiency, cost, capacity.</p>
    <p>Limited capabilities of sensor platforms.</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>Gateway</p>
    <p>Image stream</p>
    <p>Flash Memory</p>
    <p>Push query to sensors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technology Trends in Storage</p>
    <p>Generation of Sensor Platform</p>
    <p>CC1000</p>
    <p>CC2420</p>
    <p>Telos STM NOR</p>
    <p>Atmel NOR</p>
    <p>Communication</p>
    <p>Storage</p>
    <p>Micron NAND 128MB</p>
    <p>E n e r g y C o s t</p>
    <p>( u J / b y t e )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Case for Storage-centric Sensor Networks</p>
    <p>Challenges in a Storage-centric Sensor</p>
    <p>Database</p>
    <p>StonesDB Architecture</p>
    <p>Local Database Architecture</p>
    <p>Distributed Database Architecture</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimize for Flash and RAM Constraints</p>
    <p>Flash Memory Constraints Data cannot be overwritten, only erased Pages can often only be erased in blocks (16-64KB) Unlike magnetic disks, cannot modify in-place</p>
    <p>Challenges: Memory: Minimize use of memory for flash database. Energy: Organize data on flash to minimize read/write/erase operations Aging: Need to efficiently delete old data items when storage is insufficient.</p>
    <p>Erase block</p>
    <p>Memory</p>
    <p>~16-64 KB</p>
    <p>~4-10 KB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SQL-style Queries: Min, max, count, average, median, top-k,</p>
    <p>contour, track, etc</p>
    <p>Similarity Search: Was a bird matching signature S observed last</p>
    <p>week?</p>
    <p>Classification Queries: What type of vehicles (truck, car, tank, ) were observed in the</p>
    <p>field in the last month?</p>
    <p>Wireless Sensor Network</p>
    <p>Support Rich Archival Querying Capability</p>
    <p>Signal Processing: Perform an FFT to find the mode of vibration signal between time</p>
    <p>&lt;t1,t2&gt;?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>StonesDB Goals</p>
    <p>Our goal is to design a distributed sensor database for archival data management that:</p>
    <p>Supports energy-efficient sensor data storage, indexing, and aging by optimizing for flash memories.</p>
    <p>Supports energy-efficient processing of SQL-type queries, as well as data mining and search queries.</p>
    <p>Is configurable to heterogeneous sensor platforms with different memory and processing constraints.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>StonesDB Architecture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Indexing in StonesDB</p>
    <p>Nave Design: Consider a value-based index on entire stream</p>
    <p>Deletion/Aging of data triggers in-place updates involving energy-intensive block read/write/erase operations.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Indexed Storage</p>
    <p>StonesDB Design: Split data stream into partitions and build index on each partition. Age partitions as a whole cheaply.</p>
    <p>Flash</p>
    <p>Block</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Case for Storage-centric Sensor Networks</p>
    <p>Challenges in a Storage-centric Sensor</p>
    <p>Database</p>
    <p>StonesDB Architecture</p>
    <p>Local Database Architecture</p>
    <p>Distributed Database Architecture</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>StonesDB: Data Mining Queries</p>
    <p>Similarity Search: Was a bird matching signature S observed</p>
    <p>last week?</p>
    <p>Proxy Cache of Image Summaries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>StonesDB: System Operation</p>
    <p>Similarity Search: Was a bird matching signature S observed</p>
    <p>last week?</p>
    <p>Query Engine</p>
    <p>Partitioned Access Methods</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Issues</p>
    <p>Local Database Layer Impact of RAM limitations on storage organization</p>
    <p>Energy-optimized indexing and aging.</p>
    <p>New cost models for self-tuning energyefficient sensor databases.</p>
    <p>Distributed Database Layer Intelligent split of query processing between proxy and sensor tiers</p>
    <p>Adaptively tuning quality of data cached at sensor proxy based on query needs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UUNIVERSITY OF NIVERSITY OF MMASSACHUSETTSASSACHUSETTS, A, AMHERST  MHERST  Department of Computer Science Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>The End</p>
    <p>STONES: STOrage-centric Networked Embedded Systems</p>
    <p>http://sensors.cs.umass.edu/projects/stones</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sensor Data Management Taxonomy</p>
    <p>Timeline vs Prior Knowledge Q</p>
    <p>u e</p>
    <p>ry in</p>
    <p>g</p>
    <p>M in</p>
    <p>in g</p>
    <p>Current Recent Past</p>
    <p>Acquisitional Query Processing</p>
    <p>(BBQ, )</p>
    <p>Pushdown Filters (TinyDB, Cougar, )</p>
    <p>Timeline of data being processed</p>
    <p>Search/Mining on Archived Sensor Data</p>
    <p>Type of data processing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technology Trends in Sensor Platforms</p>
    <p>Cyclops Camera+ Mica2 Mote 128 x 128 resolution images</p>
    <p>OmniVision Camera + iMote2 128 x 128 resolution images 64KB - 32MB RAM, 10 MHz microcontroller</p>
    <p>Spectrum of sensing devices with different power, capability, resource constraints.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
