<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adventures in Provenance Integration</p>
    <p>Elaine Angelino, Uri Braun, David A. Holland, Peter Macko, Daniel Margo, Margo Seltzer</p>
    <p>TaPP 2011</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Integrating two provenance systems</p>
    <p>StarFlow, a workflow environment for data analysis in Python</p>
    <p>PASS, which manages provenance at the operating system level</p>
    <p>Run StarFlow on top of PASS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The dream</p>
    <p>We thought that PASS and StarFlow would get along like two peas in a pod ...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The reality</p>
    <p>... But sometimes they were more like apples and oranges</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reconciliation</p>
    <p>StarFlow and PASS each has its own world view  Different scopes, objects, granularity, goals</p>
    <p>Each produces its own account of any particular execution</p>
    <p>These accounts need to be reconciled semantically as well as physically</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem: StarFlow records information about objects that do not yet exist</p>
    <p>The OPM cannot express this</p>
    <p>Solution: Placeholder objects  The new stands-for edge connects</p>
    <p>placeholders to reality</p>
    <p>Non-existent objects</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem: When StarFlow regenerates a file, it deletes the old file and writes a new copy</p>
    <p>PASS sees no connection between the old and new objects</p>
    <p>Solution: Explicit version edges  StarFlow must tell PASS about these</p>
    <p>relationships</p>
    <p>Version disconnection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem: We let StarFlow add provenance records to the PASS database</p>
    <p>PASS needs to keep track of where individual records came from</p>
    <p>Solution: ???  What about the provenance of provenance of</p>
    <p>provenance of provenance of provenance</p>
    <p>Provenance of provenance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Is this what provenance integration looks like?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
