<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LINA: Identifying Comparable Documents from Wikipedia</p>
    <p>Emmanuel Morin1 Amir Hazem2 Elizaveta Loginova-Clouet1 Florian Boudin1</p>
    <p>BUCC-2015 Shared Task</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>I How far can we go with a language agnostic model?</p>
    <p>I We experiment with [Enright and Kondrak, 2007]s parallel document identification method</p>
    <p>I We adapt the method to the BUCC-2015 Shared task based on two assumptions: 1. Source documents should be paired 1-to-1 with target documents 2. We have access to comparable documents in several languages</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>I Fast parallel document identification [Enright and Kondrak, 2007] I Documents = bags of hapax words I Words = blank separated strings that are 4+ characters long I Given a document in language A, the document in language B that shares the largest number of words is considered as parallel</p>
    <p>I Works very well for parallel documents I 99.96% accuracy on EUROPARL [Enright and Kondrak, 2007] I 80% precision on Wikipedia [Patry and Langlais, 2011]</p>
    <p>I We use this approach as baseline for detecting comparable documents</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Improvements using 1-to-1 alignments</p>
    <p>I In baseline, document pairs are scored independently I Multiple source documents are paired to a same target document I  60% of English pages are paired with multiple pages in French or German</p>
    <p>I We remove multiply assigned source documents using pigeonhole reasoning I From 60% to 11% of multiply assigned source documents</p>
    <p>docfr 1 docfr 2 docfr 3</p>
    <p>docen 1 docen 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Improvements using cross-lingual information</p>
    <p>I Simple document weighting function  score ties</p>
    <p>I We break the remaining score ties using a third language I From 11% to less than 4% of multiply assigned source documents</p>
    <p>docfr 1</p>
    <p>docde docen</p>
    <p>docfr 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental settings</p>
    <p>I We focus on the French-English and German-English pairs</p>
    <p>I The following measures are considered relevant I Mean Average Precision (MAP) I Success (Succ.) I Precision at 5 (P@5)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results (FREN)</p>
    <p>Train Test</p>
    <p>Strategy MAP Succ. P@5 MAP Succ. P@5</p>
    <p>baseline 31.4 28.0 7.4 32.9 30.0 7.5 + pigeonhole 57.7 56.4 11.9    + cross-lingual 58.9 57.7 12.1 59.0 57.7 12.1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results (DEEN)</p>
    <p>Train Test</p>
    <p>Strategy MAP Succ. P@5 MAP Succ. P@5</p>
    <p>baseline 28.7 24.9 6.9 29.0 24.9 7.1 + pigeonhole 61.6 60.1 12.8    + cross-lingual 62.3 60.9 12.8 62.2 60.7 12.8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>I Unsupervised, hapax words-based method</p>
    <p>I Promising results, about 60% of success using pigeonhole reasoning</p>
    <p>I Using a third language slightly improves the performance</p>
    <p>I Future work I Finding the optimal alignment across the all languages I Relaxing the hapax-words constraint</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you</p>
    <p>florian.boudin@univ-nantes.fr</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References I</p>
    <p>Enright, J. and Kondrak, G. (2007). A fast method for parallel document identification. In Human Language Technologies 2007: The Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL07), pages 2932, Rochester, New York, USA.</p>
    <p>Patry, A. and Langlais, P. (2011). Identifying parallel documents from a large bilingual collection of texts: Application to parallel article extraction in wikipedia. In Proceedings of the 4th Workshop on Building and Using Comparable Corpora (BUCC11), pages 8795, Portland, Oregon, USA.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
