<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trusted Computing and Provenance:</p>
    <p>Better Together</p>
    <p>John Lyle and Andrew Martin Oxford University Computing Laboratory</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some Background</p>
    <p>My research is in security, not provenance (sorry!)</p>
    <p>We're interested in assurance of platform behaviour through reporting system state</p>
    <p>Part of provenance is knowing system state to support and guarantee consistent behaviour</p>
    <p>Growing interest in secure provenance</p>
    <p>Surely there's some overlap... Surely there's some overlap...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Secure Provenance?</p>
    <p>Provenance can provide assurance in the quality of scientific results  Many new threats: not just unintentional error</p>
    <p>highprofile science has a greater risk of malicious intervention. E.g. Climate change</p>
    <p>Provenance is a great defence against:  attacks on reputation (e.g. Climategate)</p>
    <p>attempts to influence results</p>
    <p>But only if provenance records are tamperproof</p>
    <p>Even more important with large, distributed systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trusted Computing</p>
    <p>Trusted Computing can provide tamperproof guarantees of program execution.</p>
    <p>It can provide information about hardware and software</p>
    <p>To explain how, need to go into some technical details</p>
    <p>Stop and ask me questions!  Time constraints mean I'm glossing over lots of details.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Integrity Reporting</p>
    <p>Assessing trustworthiness by asking:</p>
    <p>What programs are you running?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bios</p>
    <p>Bootloader</p>
    <p>Operating System</p>
    <p>App App App App</p>
    <p>Root of Trust</p>
    <p>Loads Measure the binary hash</p>
    <p>Trusted Platform Module (TPM)</p>
    <p>Authenticated Boot</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PCR Hash value Executable</p>
    <p>PCR10 = SHA1( A n , SHA1( ... SHA1( A</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Remote Attestation</p>
    <p>Sign a copy of your boot measurements</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What about Provenance?</p>
    <p>Security and provenance rely on establishing a complete picture of the factors influencing a remote computer's behaviour</p>
    <p>Trusted Computing can do it in a tamperresistant manner</p>
    <p>Attestations can be considered trustworthy actorstate passertions</p>
    <p>This is immediately applicable to largescale grid computing.</p>
    <p>We have the technology already!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attestationbased Provenance</p>
    <p>Result</p>
    <p>Job</p>
    <p>Provenance Store</p>
    <p>Remote Service</p>
    <p>User</p>
    <p>Send report</p>
    <p>Submit job</p>
    <p>Send report</p>
    <p>Send report</p>
    <p>Job Report: (Attestation)</p>
    <p>PCR Boot Hash, Boot log, Job Request, Job Result</p>
    <p>Remote Service</p>
    <p>Job</p>
    <p>Remote Service</p>
    <p>Other data sources...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Informa tion Co</p>
    <p>llected</p>
    <p>Platform unique</p>
    <p>identit y (AIK)</p>
    <p>All softw are iden</p>
    <p>tities</p>
    <p>Firmwa re, driv</p>
    <p>ers, ope rating s</p>
    <p>ystems,</p>
    <p>applica tions</p>
    <p>Hardwa re ident</p>
    <p>ities*</p>
    <p>Timesta mps</p>
    <p>Job info rmation</p>
    <p>**</p>
    <p>A hash of the j</p>
    <p>ob / req uest me</p>
    <p>ssage</p>
    <p>A hash of the c</p>
    <p>alculate d result</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimising Storage</p>
    <p>Job Report: ( Job ID, Boot Hash, Boot Log, Request, Result, Signature )</p>
    <p>Job ID ( Request, Result,  Boot Hash, Signature )</p>
    <p>Boot Hash [  RIM1, RIM2, ... ]</p>
    <p>Provenance StoreReference Manifest Database (Application  hash list)</p>
    <p>Service Provider</p>
    <p>RIM (Application, Date, Version, )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We Have The Technology...We Have The Technology...</p>
    <p>Software for Java, C++, .netSoftware for Java, C++, .net</p>
    <p>TPMs are cheap and availableTPMs are cheap and available</p>
    <p>Linux has native support for Authenticated Boot Linux has native support for Authenticated Boot and TPMs. Windows too*and TPMs. Windows too*</p>
    <p>Just needs to be integrated into middlewareJust needs to be integrated into middleware</p>
    <p>Virtualisation makes much of this easierVirtualisation makes much of this easier  Report on a virtual machine imageReport on a virtual machine image</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What we can't do (yet)</p>
    <p>Runtime information and configuration details  Can be added, but needs some work</p>
    <p>This is some of my future work</p>
    <p>Needs integrating with other provenance information  Purpose of experiment, sources of data, etc...</p>
    <p>Recreating results is not an automatic process  Virtual machines may also help here</p>
    <p>Need to have a frequentlyupdated software database (RMDB)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part 2:</p>
    <p>Better together?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trusted Computing and provenance have a lot of common research.</p>
    <p>Secure, transparent logging</p>
    <p>Usage control / monitoring</p>
    <p>Compilation histories</p>
    <p>Secure storage</p>
    <p>Even using the same examples  Grid, SOA, cloud</p>
    <p>Desire to automate and scale</p>
    <p>Integrity!</p>
    <p>Research in Common</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Problem SharedA Problem Shared</p>
    <p>Provenance can become more trustworthy if it takes advantage of (and influences) security architectures  A fantastic case study for Trusted Computing too.</p>
    <p>Security is about eliminating the hidden factors, the unexpected attacks and variables  Good science does the same</p>
    <p>We don't know how to process and filter data. Is provenance further ahead?  What do we do with incomplete information?</p>
    <p>Metadata, semantics, composition of data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>... is a problem doubled?</p>
    <p>Different research directions.  Cryptographic strength vs data consistency and accuracy</p>
    <p>Lots of new and interesting security challenges, maybe Trusted Computing wont help with the big ones?</p>
    <p>How do we develop secure software?  If grid middleware is vulnerable to runtime attack, have we gained</p>
    <p>anything?</p>
    <p>Other issues: PKI, performance, usability, privacy ...</p>
    <p>My literature review just became twice as long!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Two fields that are solving similar problems  We both want tamperproof identification of systems</p>
    <p>There is a lot of immediately applicable software and hardware  exciting opportunity for researchers and developers of</p>
    <p>provenance tools.</p>
    <p>If we work together, trusted provenance shouldn't be that far away.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
