<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>iPlane Nano: Path Prediction for Peer-to-Peer Applications</p>
    <p>Harsha V. Madhyastha, Ethan Katz-Bassett, Thomas Anderson, Arvind Krishnamurthy, and Arun Venkataramani!</p>
    <p>University of California, San Diego, University of Washington, and University of Massachusetts, Amherst !</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  Example application: P2P CDN!</p>
    <p>Content replicated across geographically distributed set of end-hosts!  RedSwoosh (Akamai)!  Kontiki (BBCs iPlayer)!</p>
    <p>Every client needs to be redirected to replica that provides best performance!</p>
    <p>Problem (also for BitTorrent, Skype, ):!  Internet performance neither constant nor</p>
    <p>queriable!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Need for Performance Prediction</p>
    <p>Current Best Practice:!  Each application measures the Internet</p>
    <p>independently!</p>
    <p>Desired Solution:!  Ability for end-hosts to predict performance !  Infrastructure shared across applications!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Predicted Information</p>
    <p>Cost to Scale</p>
    <p>Network Coordinates</p>
    <p>Limited to latency + Lightweight distr. system</p>
    <p>iPlane + Rich set of metrics + Arbitrary end-hosts</p>
    <p>2 GB atlas to distribute  Large memory footprint</p>
    <p>iPlane Nano + Same info as iPlane + Accurate enough</p>
    <p>+ 7 MB atlas for end-hosts + Queries serviced locally</p>
    <p>Need for iPlane Nano</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>iPlane Nano: Overview  Server-side: Use iPlanes measurements</p>
    <p>but store and process differently!  Key idea: Replace atlas of paths with atlas of</p>
    <p>links  from O(n2) to O(n) representation ! End-hosts</p>
    <p>Vantage points</p>
    <p>Links Routers</p>
    <p>Size of Atlas = O(#Nodes + #Links)</p>
    <p>Size of Atlas = O(#Vantage points X #Destinations X Avg. Path Length)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>iPlane Nano: Overview</p>
    <p>Server-side: Use iPlanes measurements but store and process differently!  Key idea: Replace atlas of paths with atlas of</p>
    <p>links  from O(n2) to O(n) representation !</p>
    <p>Client-side: Application library!  Download atlas and help disseminate atlas!  Service queries locally with prediction engine!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenge: Loss of Routing Info</p>
    <p>Routing policy information encoded in routes is lost!</p>
    <p>Need to extract routing policy from measured routes and represent compactly!</p>
    <p>V</p>
    <p>D</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Routing Policy: Strawman Approach  Common aspects of Internet routing applied!</p>
    <p>Shortest AS path + valley-free + early-exit!  Poor AS path prediction accuracy obtained!</p>
    <p>Too many valley-free shortest AS paths!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ASes filter propagation of route received from one neighbor to other neighbors!</p>
    <p>Filters inferred from measured routes!  Record every tuple of three successive ASes</p>
    <p>observed in any measured route!  Store (AS1, AS2, AS3) to imply AS2 forwards</p>
    <p>routes received from AS3 on to AS1!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Applying Inferred AS Filters</p>
    <p>AS filters help discard paths not policy-compliant!  Still have multiple policy-compliant paths !</p>
    <p>V</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>AS2</p>
    <p>AS1</p>
    <p>AS4</p>
    <p>AS5</p>
    <p>AS3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>For every measured route, alternate paths are determined in link-based atlas!  Divergence of paths indicates preference!</p>
    <p>AS1  AS2  AS3  on measured route!  Alternate paths imply AS1 prefers AS2 over</p>
    <p>AS5 and AS2 prefers AS3 over AS6!</p>
    <p>AS1 AS2</p>
    <p>AS5</p>
    <p>V D AS6</p>
    <p>AS3 AS4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenge: Routing Asymmetry</p>
    <p>Undirected edges used to compute route (S  D)!  Assuming symmetric routing!</p>
    <p>But, more than half of Internet routes asymmetric!</p>
    <p>V</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>S</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Traceroutes to random prefixes at low rate!  Uploads to central server!</p>
    <p>Each clients measurements assimilated into atlas distributed to all clients!</p>
    <p>Directed path computed for route prediction!  Fall back to undirected path if not found!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Improved Path Predictions  AS path prediction accuracy with iPlane</p>
    <p>Nano almost as good as with iPlane!</p>
    <p>(1.4MB daily update)</p>
    <p>Atlas size 81%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From Routes to Properties  To estimate end-to-end path properties</p>
    <p>between arbitrary S and D!  Use atlas to predict route!  Combine properties of links on predicted route!</p>
    <p>Ongoing challenge: Measuring link properties!</p>
    <p>Latency Sum of link latencies Loss-rate Probability of loss on any link</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Improving P2P Applications  Used iPlane Nano to improve three apps!</p>
    <p>P2P CDN!  Choose replica with best performance!</p>
    <p>VoIP!  Choose detour node to bridge hosts behind NATs!</p>
    <p>Detour routing for reliability!  Choose detour nodes with disjoint routes to route around failure !</p>
    <p>Refer to paper for VoIP and detour routing experiments!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Improving P2P CDN</p>
    <p>Clients: 199 PlanetLab nodes!  Replicas: 10 random Akamai nodes per client!  1MB file downloaded from best replica!</p>
    <p>Download time = 2 X Optimal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions  Implemented iPlane Nano!</p>
    <p>Practical solution for scalably providing predictions of Internet path performance to P2P applications !</p>
    <p>Compact representation of routing policy to predict route and path properties between arbitrary endhosts !</p>
    <p>Demonstrated utility in improving performance of P2P applications!</p>
    <p>Step towards determining minimum information required to capture Internet performance!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!</p>
    <p>iPlane Nanos atlas and traces gathered by iPlane updated daily at!</p>
    <p>http://iplane.cs.washington.edu!</p>
    <p>Send me email if you want to use iPlane Nanos or iPlanes predictions!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
