<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>POST: A Secure, Resilient, Cooperative Messaging System</p>
    <p>A. Mislove, A. Post, C. Reis, P. Willmann, P. Druschel, D. S. Wallach Rice University</p>
    <p>X. Bonnaire, P. Sens, J.-M. Busca, L. Arantes-Bezerra University of Paris 6 (LIP6)</p>
    <p>HotOS 2003</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>n Provide a generic, serverless platform for user-driven collaborative applications (email, IM, calendars, etc.)</p>
    <p>n Show that a wide range collaborative services can be supported by one serverless platform securely, with high availability</p>
    <p>n Demonstrate that p2p paradigm is mature enough to support secure, resilient, mission-critical applications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>POST Architecture</p>
    <p>n Provides three basic services to applications:  Secure single-copy message storage  User metadata based on single-writer logs  Event notification</p>
    <p>n These basic services are sufficient to support a variety of collaborative applications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sample Application: ePOST</p>
    <p>n Email service based on POST  Email is a well-understood, demanding application  Availability of realistic workloads</p>
    <p>n Interoperates seamlessly with existing email protocols and clients (IMAP, SMTP, Outlook, etc)</p>
    <p>n Participating organizations remain autonomous  Local storage controlled by local participants by scoped insertion</p>
    <p>n Provides better spam prevention  Crypto-based message authentication and privacy  Sender overhead is proportional to the number of recipients  Receivers pull messages</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Setup</p>
    <p>n Implemented ePOST prototype  Performs well</p>
    <p>n Realistic ePOST storage requirements?  Examined email usage by ~250 members of Rice CS</p>
    <p>department  Conservative assumptions:</p>
    <p>n No deletion n Local insertion n Full replication with 10 replicas n All messages are unique</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ePOST Storage Requirements</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Status and Conclusions</p>
    <p>n Ongoing work:  We plan to begin using prototype as primary email system this</p>
    <p>summer  Answer open questions</p>
    <p>n Appropriate level of replication n Measures to ensure failure independence n Administrative cost</p>
    <p>n Also working on IM and calendar applications on POST</p>
    <p>n Related effort: p2p incentives for fair sharing of resources</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Single-copy Message Storage</p>
    <p>n Achieved using convergent encryption n Allows multiple copies of encrypted data to be</p>
    <p>coalesed</p>
    <p>DES</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>MD5 key</p>
    <p>data</p>
    <p>{X}H(X)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User-specific Metadata</p>
    <p>n Based on the Ivy file system</p>
    <p>DATAn</p>
    <p>DATAn-1</p>
    <p>DATA1</p>
    <p>location: H(DATAn)</p>
    <p>location: H(DATAn-1)</p>
    <p>location: H(DATA1)</p>
    <p>HEAD1</p>
    <p>HEAD2</p>
    <p>HEADn</p>
    <p>well-known location</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Notification</p>
    <p>n Suppose A and B want to send to C</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
