<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Opera)ng System for the Home</p>
    <p>Colin Dixon (IBM Research) Ratul Mahajan Sharad Agarwal A.J. Brush Bongshin Lee Stefan Saroiu Paramvir Bahl</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HomeOS</p>
    <p>PC-like organizaGon for tech in the home  Ease management and extensibility</p>
    <p>Running in 12 real homes for 48 months</p>
    <p>Used by 42 student developers at 10 insGtuGons</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Wheres my smarthome?</p>
    <p>Remote lock</p>
    <p>Keyless entry</p>
    <p>Climate control</p>
    <p>Alerts w/ Photos</p>
    <p>Energy monitoring</p>
    <p>Tasks (soVware)</p>
    <p>Devices (hardware)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Gap between poten)al and reality</p>
    <p>Envisioned by many researchers and companies Struggling to break into the mainstream  Despite commercial availability since 1970s</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Poor extensibility Management pain</p>
    <p>or</p>
    <p>Adding devices and tasks</p>
    <p>Understanding the gap</p>
    <p>Study of homes with modern automaGon  31 people across 14 households  Enjoyed convenience, peace of mind and control  But, had difficulty in two key areas:</p>
    <p>Access control</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exis)ng abstrac)ons for home tech</p>
    <p>Network of devices  Interoperability protocols  DLNA, Z-Wave, Speakeasy,   Open, low-level device access</p>
    <p>Appliance  Monolithic systems  Crestron, Control4, EasyLiving,   Fixed tasks over fixed devices</p>
    <p>Climate control</p>
    <p>Remote monitoring</p>
    <p>Management is sGll hard  Users must manage each device/task  Developers must deal directly w/ h/w</p>
    <p>Extensibility is sGll hard  Closed set of tasks  Closed set of devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The home as a PC</p>
    <p>View the home as a computer  Networked devices  peripherals (w/drivers)  Tasks over these devices  applicaGons</p>
    <p>Adding devices  plugging in a peripheral  Adding tasks  installing an applicaGon  Managing networked devices  managing files</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HomeOS: An OS for the home</p>
    <p>HomeOS</p>
    <p>Video recording</p>
    <p>Remote unlock</p>
    <p>Climate control</p>
    <p>HomeStore</p>
    <p>Z-Wave, DLNA, UPnP, etc.</p>
    <p>HomeOS logically centralizes all</p>
    <p>devices</p>
    <p>Users interact with HomeOS, not</p>
    <p>individual devices</p>
    <p>HomeStore helps find compaGble devices and apps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges in the home</p>
    <p>Non-expert users must become network managers  Need rich, but easy to use management tools  E.g., misconfigured app may be able to unlock a door</p>
    <p>Developers struggle to build apps  Heterogeneity in tasks, control, device and topology</p>
    <p>New classes of devices arrive frequently  E.g., Kinect, energy meters, connected TVs, etc.</p>
    <p>M an</p>
    <p>ag ea b ili ty</p>
    <p>Ex te n si b ili ty</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HomeOS architecture</p>
    <p>Applica)on layer</p>
    <p>Management layer</p>
    <p>Device func)onality layer (DFL)</p>
    <p>Device connec)vity layer (DCL)</p>
    <p>Tasks</p>
    <p>Control</p>
    <p>Device</p>
    <p>Topological</p>
    <p>Heterogeneity source handled</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DCL and DFL (Drivers)</p>
    <p>DCL provides basic connecGvity to devices</p>
    <p>DFL exports device funcGonality as a service  Services are protocol-independent  IdenGfied using roles and operaGons  Kernel does not parse or understand services</p>
    <p>Layer of IndirecGon between protocols and apps</p>
    <p>Dimmer PTZ Camera</p>
    <p>Set(level) Get()  level</p>
    <p>GetImage()  bitmap Up(), Down() LeV(), Right() ZoomIn(), ZoomOut()</p>
    <p>App layer</p>
    <p>Mgmt layer</p>
    <p>DFL</p>
    <p>DCL</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Management Layer Requirements</p>
    <p>Apps as security principals</p>
    <p>Easy-to-verify seRngs</p>
    <p>Time-based access control</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Management Layer</p>
    <p>Access control policy:  Datalog-based rules</p>
    <p>[user group, device, app, tstart, tend, dayOfWeek, priority, accessMode]</p>
    <p>Rules include !me and applica!ons  Allow users to query rules to verify their intent</p>
    <p>Easier to reason about than ACLs in current OSes</p>
    <p>Scales beier than 2-D grid of users and devices</p>
    <p>App layer</p>
    <p>Mgmt layer</p>
    <p>DFL</p>
    <p>DCL</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Applica)on layer</p>
    <p>Apps consume and compose abstract device interfaces from the DFL</p>
    <p>Management layer interposes on accesses</p>
    <p>Manifests help with compaGbility tesGng  Lists of mandatory and opGonal features  E.g., mandatory: {TV, SonyTV}, {MediaServer} opGonal: {Speaker}</p>
    <p>App layer</p>
    <p>Mgmt layer</p>
    <p>DFL</p>
    <p>DCL</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evalua)ng HomeOS</p>
    <p>Key quesGons:  Can non-technical users manage HomeOS?  Can developers easily write apps and drivers?</p>
    <p>Method:</p>
    <p>Field experiences  12 real homes and 42 student developers</p>
    <p>Controlled experiments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Field experiences: The good</p>
    <p>Users could manage their HomeOS deployments</p>
    <p>Users parGcularly liked the ability to organically extend their technology</p>
    <p>Developers found the programming abstracGons and layering to be natural</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sample third-party applica)ons</p>
    <p>For more, see the HomeOS site: hip://research.microsoV.com/homeos/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Field experiences: The bad</p>
    <p>Users found it hard to diagnose faults</p>
    <p>Interoperability protocols can be fragile</p>
    <p>Not all device features may be exposed over the network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Controlled Evalua)ons</p>
    <p>Performance results in the paper</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>HomeOS eases extensibility and management by providing a PC abstracGon for home technology</p>
    <p>SGll lots of exciGng things to do!  What core capabiliGes should be in every home?  Can we provide non-intrusive idenGty inference?</p>
    <p>For more info and to request code: hip://research.microsoV.com/homeos/</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
