<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UMass Computer Science Department</p>
    <p>Jeremy Gummeson Deepak Ganesan Mark D. Corner</p>
    <p>Prashant Shenoy</p>
    <p>An Adaptive Link Layer for Range Diversity in</p>
    <p>Multi-radio Mobile Sensor Networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mobile Sensor Networks</p>
    <p>Mobile entities equipped with sensors, radios</p>
    <p>Exchange data with peer mobile nodes, infrastructure basestation</p>
    <p>High-power long-range Radio maximizes communication opportunities, but expensive at short-range</p>
    <p>Mobility Patterns difficult to predict</p>
    <p>Tracking applications require small form factor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Spectrum of Radio Choices</p>
    <p>Radio Bandwidth Energy/bit Range</p>
    <p>CC2420 250 kbps 208nJ/bit 80m</p>
    <p>XE1205 38.1kbps 5276nJ/bit 800m</p>
    <p>Xtend 9.6kbps 380.2uJ/bit 2-3km</p>
    <p>Existing radios optimized for short or long range:  Long Range, Low bit rate, Low Energy Efficiency  Short Range, High bit rate, Higher Energy Efficiency</p>
    <p>Designer chooses efficiency or range</p>
    <p>Common Small Form Factor Radios</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Approach</p>
    <p>Design a node with heterogeneous radios to exploit short range efficiency and long range connectivity</p>
    <p>Use unified link layer to manage radios and react to channel and mobility dynamics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions</p>
    <p>Our System makes the following contributions to Mobile MultiRadio Sensors Research:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation  System Design  Implementation  Results  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Arthropod: A Multi-Radio Sensor Platform  Hardware platform consists of: MSP430 MCU, CC2420 radio, and</p>
    <p>XE1205 radio:  Expansion board provides existing platform Tinynode with</p>
    <p>CC2420 radio  Board connects CC2420 to unused SPI bus and GPIO pins.</p>
    <p>Existing TinyOS-2.x drivers modified for use with new hardware</p>
    <p>Hardware Prototype</p>
    <p>Application</p>
    <p>Unified Link Layer</p>
    <p>CC2420 MAC XE1205 MAC</p>
    <p>CC2420 Radio XE1205 Radio</p>
    <p>System Block Diagram</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Utilizing Multiple Radios</p>
    <p>Problem: Need to determine energy-optimal radio at given time</p>
    <p>Approach: Unified link-layer presents multiple radios as one entity</p>
    <p>Two subcomponents:  Q-Learning Algorithm: Observe MAC retransmissions,</p>
    <p>learn/choose optimal radio interface  Switching Protocol: Manage radio power states, coordinate</p>
    <p>handoffs</p>
    <p>Q-Learning Algorithm</p>
    <p>CC2420 MAC</p>
    <p>XE1205 MAC</p>
    <p>decisio n</p>
    <p>Switching Protocol</p>
    <p>CC2420 MAC</p>
    <p>XE1205 MAC</p>
    <p>Send Receive</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Q-Learning</p>
    <p>Goal: Choose action a, arrive in state with maximal Q value  In multi-radio context, Q represents learned energy needed to send packet</p>
    <p>on given interface at particular power-level  a represents decision to send packet using particular interface/power</p>
    <p>combination  After transmission, receive reward r, where i represents retransmissions:</p>
    <p>r[i] = -(i*PacketSize*ByteTime*TxPower + AckTimeOut*RxPower) + RxPower*AckRTT + PacketSize*ByteTime*TxPower</p>
    <p>r used to update Q using simple rule with fixed parameters  Periodically explore alternate interface/power-levels by choosing random</p>
    <p>action a; allows transitions when conditions improve</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multi-Radio Switching Protocol</p>
    <p>Q-Learning finds optimal interface/power level, need handoff between radios  non-trivial problem: radio transitions occur during periods of high loss</p>
    <p>Need to handle:  State synchronization problems between sender and receiver  Graceful disconnections</p>
    <p>Solution:  Embed control flags that negotiate handoffs  Handoff state temporarily powers both radio receivers; Minimize time spent</p>
    <p>during handoff to minimize overhead</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Switching Protocol Description</p>
    <p>Sending node drives state transitions at receiver: 1. Asserting EXPLORE flag in sent packet causes both radio interfaces to</p>
    <p>become active until timeout 2. Consecutive packets may be sent on either interface; continuously</p>
    <p>asserting EXPLORE will keep both interfaces active 3. Alternatively, the next packet may be sent with HIGH_ON or LOW_ON flag</p>
    <p>asserted to commit receiver to one particular interface 4. Two consecutive timeouts force receiver into Low Power Listen (LPL) on</p>
    <p>long range interface; may proactively enter LPL by asserting END_BLOCK</p>
    <p>Low On Handoff</p>
    <p>Idle</p>
    <p>High On</p>
    <p>EXPLORE ||</p>
    <p>Timeout EXPLORE</p>
    <p>LOW_ON HIGH_ON ||</p>
    <p>Timeout</p>
    <p>EN D_</p>
    <p>BL OC</p>
    <p>K</p>
    <p>|| T im</p>
    <p>eo ut</p>
    <p>Wa ke</p>
    <p>upEND_BLOCK</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation Methodology</p>
    <p>continuous dataset</p>
    <p>Environment Mobility Pattern Example Scenario</p>
    <p>urban-indoor Continuous w/ obstruction</p>
    <p>People moving in a building</p>
    <p>urban-outdoor Continuous; Partial Line of Sight</p>
    <p>Moving vehicle</p>
    <p>urban-outdoor Nomadic Bus w/ stops</p>
    <p>foliage Nomadic Animals visiting habitat</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trace Driven Simulation Results</p>
    <p>Per Packet Energy Consumption</p>
    <p>Fraction of Lost Packets</p>
    <p>Multi-Radio approach improves per packet energy consumption while only marginally increasing packet loss</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multi-Radio Power Control Results</p>
    <p>Additional simulation looks at power control across radios:  Data set uses max/min Tx power settings on each radio</p>
    <p>Cumulative Energy Consumption for Single and Multi-power level strategies</p>
    <p>Radio/power level</p>
    <p>% packets lost</p>
    <p>Energy Consumed</p>
    <p>XE1205 @0dBm</p>
    <p>XE1205 @15dBm</p>
    <p>CC2420 @-25dBm</p>
    <p>CC2420 @0dBm</p>
    <p>Q-Learning 3.53 .430 mJ/Tx Success</p>
    <p>Summary of results for each power level</p>
    <p>Unified Link Layer successfully tracks energy-minimal radio/power setting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation Loss Rates and Energy/Packet</p>
    <p>TinyOS-2.x software implementation for Arthropod shows algorithm running online; measures performance of radio switching protocol</p>
    <p>Recreate mobility pattern of indoor continuous trace; implementation results compared to single radio performance from indoor continuous</p>
    <p>Trace Type XE1205 Utilization</p>
    <p>CC2420 Utilization</p>
    <p>Packets Lost Energy Consumed</p>
    <p>Multi-Radio Implementation</p>
    <p>XE1205@15dBm 100% 0 .6% 1.0mJ / Tx Success</p>
    <p>CC2420@0dBm O% 100% 43.0% 1.6mJ / Tx Success</p>
    <p>Summary of Implementation Results</p>
    <p>Multi-Radio implementation loses more packets, consumes substantially less energy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Breakdown of Receiver Energy Costs</p>
    <p>Energy Spent during different Rx States</p>
    <p>Multi-Radio approach uses significantly less power than an XE1205 only implementation; Loss rate comparable to the CC2420</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Showed hardware implementation of multi-radio sensor node Arthropod</p>
    <p>Designed and tested a unified link layer for multi-radio hardware:  Uses learning algorithm and MAC statistics to select radio interace  Implemented switching protocol to handoff between radios</p>
    <p>Evaluated link-layer via trace driven simulation and algorithm running online:</p>
    <p>Considerably more energy efficient for different mobility patterns, while only marginally increasing losses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Existing Multi-Radio Systems: Separate Radio Roles:</p>
    <p>Wake-On-Wireless: low-power, low-bandwidth radio wakes up high-power, high-band-width radio (Agarwal, 2007)</p>
    <p>DieselNet Throwboxes: Long-range radio maximizes utility of short-range, high-bandwidth radio in a mobile scenario (Banerjee, 2007)</p>
    <p>Dynamic Radio Selection:  Mobile Access Router: Use heterogeneous radios to maximize bandwidth</p>
    <p>and minimize stalled transfers; neglects energy (Rodriguez, 2004)  Coolspots: Use Bluetooth for communication when available, otherwise uses</p>
    <p>Mesh Networking:  MR-LQSR: Use Multiple Radios per mesh node, makes channel assignment</p>
    <p>more effective (Draves, 2004)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sender State Machine</p>
    <p>States represent senders view of the receiver  Intermediate handoff state used to activate alt. radio  Transition out of IDLE requires wakeup packet  Receiver -&gt; Both radios active during handoff</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Receiver State Machine</p>
    <p>Used to manage radio receiver power states  Flags used to coordinate handoff between radios  Two Consecutive Timeouts result in transition to IDLE state  May proactively switch to IDLE state at end of block</p>
    <p>transfer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Contributions</p>
    <p>A prototype low-power multi-radio hardware system</p>
    <p>Develop low-overhead techniques for dynamically switching between radio interfaces</p>
    <p>Evaluation methodologies for showing energy performance benefits of multi-radio systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Strategies</p>
    <p>Communication is Expensive!</p>
    <p>Use communication resources intelligently:  Minimize radio time spent in active mode  Send data when channel conditions are good</p>
    <p>Active Power Consumption (mW)</p>
    <p>Sleep Mode Power Consumption (mW)</p>
    <p>CC2420 Radio 59.1 (Rx) .02</p>
    <p>XE1205 Radio 65.4 (Rx) .03</p>
    <p>MSP430 MCU 3 .015</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Q-Learning</p>
    <p>Q-Learning is a reinforcement-learning technique used for decision-making by agents in an unknown environment:</p>
    <p>A Matrix Q contains the accumulated reward by an agent in a given state</p>
    <p>The agent has several choices of action and chooses the action a such that the Q-value of the arrival state is maximized.</p>
    <p>After Taking action a, the agent receives a reward r and adjusts Q with an update rule defined by parameters  and</p>
    <p>The agent will also periodically take a random action, , which allows unexplored state to be reached</p>
    <p>Formal definition of Q-Learning</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More Q-Learning</p>
    <p>In the context of a multi-radio system:  Each state S is an individual radio/power-level combination  An action a corresponds to sending a packet over a given radio</p>
    <p>interface.  Reward r corresponds to the negative energy used for sending the</p>
    <p>packet. The amount of energy used is defined by a combination of radio hardware characteristics and channel dynamics.</p>
    <p>Q represents cumulative energy consumption across multiple transmission attempts.  and  are used to control how quickly Q is updated as well as limiting the reward value r for staying in a given state.</p>
    <p>defines when the alternate radio interface should be explored. In a multi-radio scenario, it does not make sense to take a random action</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Defining reward value r</p>
    <p>The success of the Q-Learning algorithm depends heavily on r:  r is defined as energy required to send a packet. Energy is calculated</p>
    <p>via MAC layer statistics  The following equation shows how a reward is calculated, where i is</p>
    <p>the number of packet retransmissions:</p>
    <p>r[i] = -(i*PacketSize*ByteTime*TxPower + AckTimeOut*RxPower) + RxPower*AckRTT + PacketSize*ByteTime*TxPower</p>
    <p>A radio-agnostic quantity, energy, allows head-to-head comparison of performance across radios. Maximizing Q is synonymous with minimizing energy</p>
    <p>Congestion backoffs also contribute to power consumption, but not in practice</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
