<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bobtail: Avoiding Long Tails in the Cloud</p>
    <p>Yunjing Xu, Zachary Musgrave, Brian Noble, Michael Bailey</p>
    <p>University of Michigan</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Public clouds are used everywhere</p>
    <p>Craig Labovitz, Deep Field, April 2012</p>
    <p>Amazons Cloud</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges to large applicaHons</p>
    <p>User-facing applicaHons have Hght deadlines  E.g., 300ms for end-to-end response Hme</p>
    <p>Large applicaHons have more moving parts  A single Amazon page requires over 150 services  10ms budget for individual services</p>
    <p>The tail latency maOers, not just the average  Easy to miss deadline if any service becomes slow  More criHcal as you scale out further</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Agenda</p>
    <p>EC2 has long tail latency problem  Much worse than that in dedicated data centers  A problem of the node not the network</p>
    <p>Root cause: incompaHble sharing  Co-scheduling of I/O-bound and CPU-bound VMs</p>
    <p>SoluHon: Bobtail  Pick VMs without long tails  A customer-centric approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Agenda</p>
    <p>EC2 has long tail latency problem  Much worse than that in dedicated data centers  A problem of the node not the network</p>
    <p>Root cause: incompaHble sharing  Co-scheduling of I/O-bound and CPU-bound VMs</p>
    <p>SoluHon: Bobtail  Pick VMs without long tails  A customer-centric approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measurements Setup</p>
    <p>Live measurement in EC2s east region  Use ThriY RPC framework to measure RTT</p>
    <p>EXP1: RTT for 60 RPC servers  Measure from designated tesHng nodes  Give an overview of the problem</p>
    <p>EXP2: Pair-wise RTT for 16 RPC servers  Measure between each other  Study spaHal properHes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How bad is the latency tail?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How bad is the latency tail?</p>
    <p>Median ~0.6ms</p>
    <p>Over 10X larger</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How does it compare to dedicated DCs?</p>
    <p>Over 2 Hmes larger</p>
    <p>Measured in dedicated DC[1,29]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SpaHal ProperHes</p>
    <p>A property of nodes not the network</p>
    <p>Depends only on servers</p>
    <p>Client</p>
    <p>Server</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Agenda</p>
    <p>EC2 has long tail latency problem  Worse than that in dedicated data centers  A problem of the node not the network</p>
    <p>Root cause: incompaHble sharing  Co-scheduling of I/O-bound and CPU-bound VMs</p>
    <p>SoluHon: Bobtail  Pick VMs without long tails  A customer-centric approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Root cause analysis</p>
    <p>VirtualizaHon and sharing cause high variance  Wang et al., INFOCOM10</p>
    <p>Does the type of sharing maOer? Why?  Controlled experiments on testbed: Xen 4.1</p>
    <p>Five VMs share two CPU cores: 40% each  Vary workload combinaHon</p>
    <p>CPU-bound workload: ~85% busy  I/O-bound workload: same RPC framework</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The type of sharing maOers</p>
    <p>IncompaHble sharing causes the long tail  CPU-bound VMs vs. I/O-bound VMs</p>
    <p>Sharing is not always bad  Only when # of CPU-bound VMs &gt;= # of CPU cores</p>
    <p>Sharing with I/O-bound VMs is okay  Even when there is one CPU-bound VM mixed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why the type of sharing maOers</p>
    <p>What causes large latency  CPU-bound VMs occupy CPUs when requests arrive  Interrupt processing for I/O-bound VMs is delayed</p>
    <p>Why 30ms for the 99.9th percenHle  Default Hme slice  Could be reduced at the cost of CPU throughput</p>
    <p>Why the tail only depends on servers  Servers may need scheduling when a request comes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Agenda</p>
    <p>EC2 has long tail latency problem  Much worse than that in dedicated data centers  A problem of the node not the network</p>
    <p>Root cause: incompaHble sharing  Co-scheduling of I/O-bound and CPU-bound VMs</p>
    <p>SoluHon: Bobtail  Pick VMs without long tails  A customer-centric approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deal with it</p>
    <p>Key insight  CPU-bound VMs delay interrupt processing  Any interrupt suffers; not just network I/O  Does tesHng locally using Hme interrupt</p>
    <p>Bobtail: how it works  Launch N*K instances if N needed  one Hme cost  Sleep 0.1ms to check if overslept (e.g., &gt;10ms)  Pick the ones that rarely oversleep  kill others</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EvaluaHon</p>
    <p>Bobtail in EC2  Using two availability zones in the east region</p>
    <p>Use 40 small instances  Bobtail picks 40 out of 160 candidates  Baseline: 40 launched directly by EC2</p>
    <p>ParHHon-AggregaHon model [Zats et al., SIGCOMM12]  Call all severs in parallel and wait for the last to respond  The slowest determines the transacHon response Hme</p>
    <p>Other benchmarks have beOer results  Refer to the paper</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ParHHon-AggregaHon Workflows</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ParHHon-AggregaHon Workflows</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>What if everyone uses Bobtail  Not exclusively looking for empty space  Seek to share with compaHble workloads  Emerging parHHons  good for everyone</p>
    <p>Amazon could fix the problem  Reduce VM sharing  lower VM density  Sacrifice CPU efficiency  inherent trade-off  Smarter scheduling  do you trust users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Long tail latency problems EC2  Large-scale measurement in real cloud  Controlled experiments on local testbed</p>
    <p>Root cause of the long tail problem  Co-scheduling of incompaHble workloads  CPU-bound vs. I/O-bound</p>
    <p>Bobtail: avoid VMs with long tails  A scalable approach  A user-centric approach without providers help</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgements</p>
    <p>And of course our research sponsors and collaborators:</p>
    <p>Boeing Corporate Identity Program New: July 22, 2008</p>
    <p>Corporate Identity Style Guide | Document template 5</p>
    <p>Boeing trademarks overview</p>
    <p>A trademark is a word, name, symbol, logo, slogan, shape, or sound that identifies and distinguishes a companys products or services from those of other parties. Our companys marks are a promise. They symbolize in the minds of consumers the goodwill that Boeing has built over the decades and reflect the quality of our products and services.</p>
    <p>Treating our trademarks with care To maintain rights in our trademarks, we must use them correctly and consistently. This defends Boeing trademarks from misuse.</p>
    <p>Use of the Boeing logo and name The Boeing logo and the name Boeing that is used in the Team Boeing wordmark are trademarks that must be treated with care. This document provides guidelines for the use of the Boeing logo in graphics, in conjunction with the FIRST logo, or in co-displays with other team sponsors.</p>
    <p>Boeing logo</p>
    <p>Team Boeing wordmark</p>
    <p>hOp://nsrg.eecs.umich.edu NSRG</p>
    <p>The Students and Collaborators from the Networking and Security Research Group:</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
