<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Google Enterprise IPv6 deployment &quot;96 more bits, no magic&quot;</p>
    <p>Irena Nikolova Network Engineer iren@google.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Agenda</p>
    <p>The problem Why the migration to IPv6 is necessary?</p>
    <p>What methodology to use? Planning and design steps</p>
    <p>How we did it? The approach used within Google Enterprise and what's next?</p>
    <p>The bottom line Words of wisdom from the field</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problem Why to migrate to IPv6?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Business Case for Change (1)</p>
    <p>(Obviously) IANA IPv4 exhaustion in Feb 2011 (G Houston stats)  IPv4 Space is rarely or never reclaimed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Business Case for Change (2)</p>
    <p>Mergers &amp; acquisitions, new partners will demand IPv6 migration</p>
    <p>Provide services to all customers (even IPv6 enabled ones)</p>
    <p>Smart phones, IPTV, virtualization and cloud computing, P2P applications, network aware devices and many more</p>
    <p>Assure the continuous growth and openness of the Internet</p>
    <p>IPv4 addresses will become scarce and expensive</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Business Case for Google Enterprise</p>
    <p>Allow for development of IPv6-ready products internally - &quot;Eat your own dogfood&quot;</p>
    <p>New in-house developed applications require a multitude of new IP</p>
    <p>addresses</p>
    <p>We are running tight on private RFC1918 addresses</p>
    <p>Overlap NAT creates network complexity and operation / support cost / security considerations</p>
    <p>Strong culture of innovation  build for the future</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What methodology to use? Planing and design steps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Global and Big</p>
    <p>Distributed offices in multiple countries</p>
    <p>Different connectivity options  MPLS, ISP, etc.</p>
    <p>Diverse networking vendors equipment</p>
    <p>Heterogenous in-house developed applications and</p>
    <p>setups</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Think globally and try to enable IPv6 everywhere</p>
    <p>Tap enthusiasm (20% work and small team of volunteers)</p>
    <p>Start early, launch and iterate often</p>
    <p>Test-driven development  build labs and test!</p>
    <p>Iterate with vendors until it works</p>
    <p>Incremental, production-quality deployment</p>
    <p>Monitor and provide the same SLA as for the IPv4</p>
    <p>network</p>
    <p>Fold in IPv6 support as normal operating procedure</p>
    <p>Plan for IPv6-only</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Planning Steps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Design Decisions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How we did it? Approach used within Google Enterprise</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deployment Phases (1)</p>
    <p>Dual-stack single hosts and IPv6 in LABs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deployment Phases (2)</p>
    <p>Partial dual-stack networks with GRE tunnels</p>
    <p>Beginning of a dual-stack cloud</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deployment Phases (3)</p>
    <p>True dual-stack offices ( no GRE!!)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What's next?</p>
    <p>DS-Lite technology testing ongoing  Combines IPv4 in IPv6 encapsulation and NAT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technical Challenges</p>
    <p>Not all networking vendors supported IPv6</p>
    <p>IPv6 was still processed in software on many platforms</p>
    <p>Vendors didn't run IPv6 in their own networks</p>
    <p>Lack of DHCPv6 client support in many client OS</p>
    <p>In general - lack of ISPs which provided native IPv6 on an enterprise peering</p>
    <p>ISPs have very different SLA for IPv6</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Organizational Challenges</p>
    <p>Training and education  always the biggest challenge!</p>
    <p>Early information helps fight Fear, Uncertainty and Doubt :)</p>
    <p>Just in time (hands on) training before the rollout</p>
    <p>Resource allocation is still very IPv4 centric</p>
    <p>Internal chicken-or-egg problem (which team within the</p>
    <p>enterprise should start first with the deployment)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The migration to IPv6 is not a Layer 3 problem;</p>
    <p>it's more of a Layer 7-9 problem.</p>
    <p>Start early and definitely don't wait!</p>
    <p>What if I want to migrate to IPv6?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bottom line Remember the previous slide?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Words of wisdom</p>
    <p>It's not rocket science; IPv6 is simple to deploy, it just takes time</p>
    <p>Phased deployment gradually builds skills and confidence</p>
    <p>Design for the same quality standards as IPv4</p>
    <p>Resources, vendor relationship/management, and organizational</p>
    <p>buy-in are the biggest challenges</p>
    <p>Keep on testing!</p>
    <p>Plan for IPv6-only network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You! Q&amp;A</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The six decisions we are glad we made</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
