<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lakshmi N. Bairavasundaram Gokul Soundararajan Vipul Mathur Kaladhar Vorugan9 Steven Kleiman</p>
    <p>Italian for Beginners: The Next Steps for SLO- based Management</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We need Service Automa1on!</p>
    <p>Systems are complex, therefore  low opera9onal efficiency  low management efficiency</p>
    <p>Research has shown that  Service automa9on can help, but  Done a poor job in geIng them into products</p>
    <p>We show some direc9ons to fix the problem</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Todays Data Center Trends</p>
    <p>Sharing</p>
    <p>Scale Complexity</p>
    <p>Dynamism</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trend 1: Siloed to Shared World</p>
    <p>Problem: Understanding inter-workload interac9ons</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trend 2: Configura1on Complexity</p>
    <p>Dedup</p>
    <p>RAID</p>
    <p>Compression</p>
    <p>Replication</p>
    <p>Security</p>
    <p>Multitude of Features</p>
    <p>Hybrid Shelves</p>
    <p>Problem: Understanding the impact of technology combina9ons</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trend 3: Huge Increase in Scale</p>
    <p>Problem: A large number of administrators needed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trend 4: Applica1ons are Dynamic</p>
    <p>Problem: Need to handle sudden changes in resource requirements</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What happens in industry?</p>
    <p>How do datacenters approach the problem today?  Provision for peak demand  Do not use all features  Have many administrators</p>
    <p>They spend more!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solu1on: Automated Management with Service Level Objec1ves (SLOs)</p>
    <p>Specifica9on of applica9ons requirements in technology-independent terms  Describe applica9on needs at different levels of the soXware stack</p>
    <p>AYributes  Performance, e.g., avg. I/O latency, IOPs  Capacity  Reliability and Availability e.g., RPO/RTO  Security and Compliance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solu1on: Service Automa1on (MAPE Loop)</p>
    <p>MONITOR Examine app service levels</p>
    <p>ANALYZE Understand the problem</p>
    <p>EXECUTE Take CorrecCve</p>
    <p>AcCons</p>
    <p>PLAN Create a soluCon [Kephart, IEEE Computer03]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Difference between Research and Product</p>
    <p>Evaluated along mul9ple dimensions  SLO Specifica9on  Monitoring and repor9ng  Impact analysis  Techniques to handle SLO viola9ons</p>
    <p>Products lacking SLO-based features  Use technology dependent SLO aYributes  Lack of mul9-dimensional SLO specifica9on  Lack of impact analysis and automated planner</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reasons for Slow Adop1on</p>
    <p>John Wilkes conclusion[Wilkes,OSR-43,2009]  Need to convince that the system can be trusted  Simple-to-use, predictable  Open about decision making process</p>
    <p>There are addi9onal reasons too  Difficult to specify SLO requirements  Need to build performance/reliability models  High cost of correc9ng modeling errors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reason #1: SLO Specifica1on Complexity</p>
    <p>Administrators may not know applica9ons requirements precisely</p>
    <p>Need to combine: performance, protec9on, security, cost, etc. to provide final specifica9on</p>
    <p>Simplicity wins  Easy to specify bandwidth shares, or priori9es</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reason #2: Modeling Errors</p>
    <p>Need 9me to build performance models, e.g., white-box models or black-box models</p>
    <p>Human exper9se may be beYer that the moment</p>
    <p>M od</p>
    <p>el in</p>
    <p>g E</p>
    <p>rr or</p>
    <p>Complexity</p>
    <p>Human Computer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reason #3: High Reconfigura1on Cost</p>
    <p>Buy new storage system, or  Migrate dataset  Simpler to provision for peak load</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Improving Adop9on of SLO-based Management</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Direc1on #1: Process, Not Product</p>
    <p>More than product development  Easing requirement specifica9on by users  Building and upda9ng system models  Post-sales support for products</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Direc1on #1: Qualified SLOs</p>
    <p>Iden9fy SLOs for popular applica9ons  Leverage exper9se of customers/partners  Translate applica9on requirements to storage requirements</p>
    <p>For example,  MicrosoX Exchange with N mailboxes  Configured using best prac9ces documents as an atomic unit</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Direc1on #1: Without Qualified SLOs</p>
    <p>Compression Dedup Snapshots RAID</p>
    <p>SATA Disks HA FC Disks</p>
    <p>Latency=10ms Thgpt=100MB/s RTO=0 for up to 5 days old, 4 hours for older</p>
    <p>Corporate Mail</p>
    <p>FC Disks</p>
    <p>HA</p>
    <p>RAID</p>
    <p>Fast, highly-reliable, and user error protecCon</p>
    <p>Snapshots</p>
    <p>What is fast?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Direc1on #1: Qualified SLOs</p>
    <p>Compression Dedup Snapshot RAID</p>
    <p>SATA Disks HA FC Disks</p>
    <p>QSLO-1 Latency=10-20ms</p>
    <p>Thgpt=100-200MB/s RTO=0 for up to 5 days old, 4 hours</p>
    <p>for older</p>
    <p>QSLO-2 Latency=20-50ms</p>
    <p>Thgpt=100-200MB/s RTO=4 hours</p>
    <p>Corporate Mail</p>
    <p>This is QSLO-1</p>
    <p>Fast, highly-reliable, and user error protecCon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Direc1on #2: Low-Impact Reconfigura1on</p>
    <p>Non-disrup9ve reconfigura9on of resources  Migra9ng small amounts of data  Dynamic storage layout</p>
    <p>Flash+HDD dynamic 9ering [Guerra et al., FAST11]  pNFS [Shepler et al, RFC 5661]</p>
    <p>Deploy caches  E.g., host-side caches, storage-side caches</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Direc1on #3: Community Wisdom</p>
    <p>Leverage Qualified SLOs for comparisons  Augment internal models with addi9onal data  Share improvements across mul9ple deployments</p>
    <p>Proac9vely advise customers  Alert on misconfigura9ons [Wang et al., OSDI04]  No9fy of faults and errors [Bairavasundaram et al.,</p>
    <p>SIGMETRICS07]</p>
    <p>Guide towards best prac9ces</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Direc1on #3: Guide towards Best Prac1ces</p>
    <p>Compression Dedup Snapshot RAID</p>
    <p>SATA Disks HA FC Disks</p>
    <p>QSLO-1 Latency=10-20ms</p>
    <p>Thgpt=100-200MB/s RTO=0 for up to 5 days old, 4 hours</p>
    <p>for older</p>
    <p>Corporate Mail</p>
    <p>Latency=12ms Thgpt=150MB/s RTO=0 for up to 5 days old, 4 hours for older</p>
    <p>Corporate Mail</p>
    <p>Could be running in qualified mode</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>We need SLO-based management  Moving towards shared infrastructure  Configura9on complexity is increasing  Scale and dynamism are hard to manage</p>
    <p>The next steps to do  Develop Qualified SLOs  Build dynamic reconfigura9on techniques  Leverage community wisdom</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
