<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Diamond: Nesting the Data Center Network with Wireless Rings in 3D Space</p>
    <p>Yong Cui1, Shihan Xiao1, Xin Wang2, Zhenjie Yang1, Chao Zhu1,</p>
    <p>Xiangyang Li1,3, Liu Yang4, and Ning Ge1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Existing DCNs</p>
    <p>Hierarchical layers</p>
    <p>Oversubscription</p>
    <p>Static &amp; symmetrical topology</p>
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Large-scale: complex cabling &amp; maintenance</p>
    <p>Dynamic traffic (e.g., random hotspots):</p>
    <p>One static &amp; symmetrical topology does not fit All the traffic patterns</p>
    <p>Data center networking</p>
    <p>Fat-tree, Mohammad Al-Fares et al. Sigcomm08</p>
    <p>Dynamic topology? 2Figure source: Daniel Halperin et al. Sigcomm 2011</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dynamic topology</p>
    <p>Wireless hybrid networking: Flyway, 3D-Beamforming, Firefly</p>
    <p>Deploy directional wireless radios (60GHz or Free-Space-Optic (FSO)) at ToR</p>
    <p>Direct rack-to-rack wireless links: built on demand to remove dynamic hotspots</p>
    <p>Hybrid data center networking</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hybrid data center networking</p>
    <p>Existing wireless hybrid DCNs</p>
    <p>Wireless radios on top of rack</p>
    <p>Wireless network on top of existing wired network</p>
    <p>Rack-level reconfigurable topology to fit dynamic traffic</p>
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Limited wireless links: small rack size &amp; dense interference</p>
    <p>Easy blocking: ceiling mirror is unavailable in modern data centers</p>
    <p>Difficult cooperation: the wired part is kept unchanged, hence hard to cooperate with newly added wireless part</p>
    <p>Not hybrid enough!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Wireless on Top of Rack?</p>
    <p>The top of each rack can hold at most 8 wireless radios</p>
    <p>Small rack size: more radios on top of rack lead to denser interference</p>
    <p>Ceiling mirror?</p>
    <p>Unavailable mirror: requires a restrictedheight (3 meters) clear space above rack</p>
    <p>Modern data centers: complex steel structures &amp; air conditioner plan above racks</p>
    <p>ChallengeLimited wireless radios &amp; links!</p>
    <p>At most 8 radios per rack if installed at ToR</p>
    <p>Top of Rack Top of Rack</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solution 1Multi-reflection Ring</p>
    <p>Motivating example</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>Wireless Ring: any two racks (e.g., A &amp; B) on the ring can communicate with multi-reflections</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solution 1Multi-reflection Ring</p>
    <p>Scaling: add more wireless rings!</p>
    <p>But circular reflector board? Hard&amp;costly to produce in industry</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>Circular Reflector</p>
    <p>Multi-reflection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solution 1Multi-reflection Ring</p>
    <p>Using equal-length flat reflection board instead: easy&amp;cheap for production</p>
    <p>Racks are placed at the vertex points of regular polygon</p>
    <p>Reflection boards are placed at the edges of regular polygon</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>Ring width: stable!</p>
    <p>Rack</p>
    <p>Flat Reflector</p>
    <p>Multi-reflection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solution 1Multi-reflection Ring</p>
    <p>3D Reflection in ring space: offering much higher flexibility</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>Side view</p>
    <p>Deploy wireless radios on servers: Enable a large number of direct serverto-server wireless links</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ChallengeInterference</p>
    <p>Directional wireless link (60GHz) is not ideal thin line: it has certain beam width and small side-lobes to create interference</p>
    <p>Figure source: Ji-Yong Shin, et al. ANCS12</p>
    <p>Area of wireless beam Undesired interference in the ring!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solution 2Precise reflection</p>
    <p>Filling the reflection board with absorbing paper, while only leaving special small holes for intended reflection points</p>
    <p>Reflection hole</p>
    <p>Antenna</p>
    <p>Absorbing paper</p>
    <p>Wireless beam</p>
    <p>Any 60Ghz wireless signal will be completely absorbed if it hits the absorbing paper</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solution 3Cooperation with wires (Diamond)</p>
    <p>Function of wireless part: handling in-ring transmissions</p>
    <p>Function of wired part: handling cross-ring transmissions</p>
    <p>Overview of our Diamond architecture</p>
    <p>A real diamond</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solution 3Cooperation with wires (Diamond)</p>
    <p>Function of wireless part: handling in-ring transmissions</p>
    <p>Function of wired part: handling cross-ring transmissions</p>
    <p>Virtual Switch</p>
    <p>Row Column</p>
    <p>(a) Logical view</p>
    <p>ToR Switch</p>
    <p>Reflector</p>
    <p>(b) Physical view</p>
    <p>ToR Switch</p>
    <p>Virtual Link (Row) Virtual Link (Column)</p>
    <p>Reflector</p>
    <p>Virtual Switch</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solution 3Cooperation with wires (Diamond)</p>
    <p>Design of virtual switch: De-Bruijn graph  Without additional switches</p>
    <p>Well-defined recursive routing structures</p>
    <p>Logarithmic network diameter</p>
    <p>Design of routing  Hotspot traffic: designated centralized routing</p>
    <p>(centralized scheduled by controller)</p>
    <p>Non-hotspot traffic: real-time hybrid routing</p>
    <p>(distributed scheduled by server)</p>
    <p>Figure source: Wikipedia De-Bruijn graph</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Single &amp; Double reflection tests</p>
    <p>Testbed</p>
    <p>Oscilloscope</p>
    <p>Reflection board</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Misalignment</p>
    <p>Potential beam width is about 20: a certain degree of fault tolerance on antenna misalignment</p>
    <p>Reflection hole</p>
    <p>Proper hole size (diameter): 10cm</p>
    <p>Hole reusing: above 50% reflection holes can be reused for different wireless links (symmetrical structure)</p>
    <p>Multi-reflection</p>
    <p>Little energy loss when using flat metal board</p>
    <p>Little energy loss when using 10cm reflection holes on the flat metal board filling with absorbing paper</p>
    <p>Experiment result</p>
    <p>Reuse ratio</p>
    <p>Hole size</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation result</p>
    <p>Cover range  Cover 90% of ring within 3 reflections when ring number &lt;10</p>
    <p>Roughly, 1000 servers have potential 0.1 million wireless links within 2 reflections</p>
    <p>Different traffic patterns  Average 5 times higher throughout than others</p>
    <p>Average 70% less flow completion time than others</p>
    <p>Scheduling delay  Greedy runs each schedule within 100ms, while Optimal runs</p>
    <p>with exponential time of the problem scale</p>
    <p>Architecture cost  Diamonds cost is highest (comparable to Firefly), while it</p>
    <p>trades off a larger number of wireless links than others 17</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Diamond can bring significant performance benefits for topologyreconfigurable DCNs</p>
    <p>No need of the restricted-height clear ceiling space/ceiling mirror</p>
    <p>Enable a large number of highly-flexible server-level wireless links</p>
    <p>Better cooperation between wireless and wired transmission components</p>
    <p>Future vision: running FSO (Free-Space-Optics) in Diamond</p>
    <p>Potential Tbps bandwidth</p>
    <p>Nearly zero beam width: little interference</p>
    <p>Try it out for fun:</p>
    <p>@ http://www.4over6.edu.cn/cuiyong/app/diamond.apk 18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
