<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Provenance and Privacy</p>
    <p>Susan B. Davidson</p>
    <p>Zhuowei Bao, Sanjeev Khanna, Sudeepa Roy, Julia Stoyanovich University of Pennsylvania</p>
    <p>Sarah Cohen-Boulakia Universite Paris-Sud</p>
    <p>Tova Milo Tel Aviv University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Desiderata from men (BPs)</p>
    <p>Discrete Secure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Need for provenance TGCCGTGTGG CTAAATGTCTG TGC</p>
    <p>CCCTTTCCGT GTGGCTAAAT GTCTGTGC</p>
    <p>TGCCGTGTGG CTAAATGTCTG TGC</p>
    <p>GTCTGTGC</p>
    <p>TGCCGTGTGG CTAAATGTCTG TGC</p>
    <p>GTCTGTGC</p>
    <p>TGCCGTGTGG CTAAATGTCTG TGC ATGGCCGTGT GGTCTGTGCC TAACTAACTAA</p>
    <p>How has this tree been generated?</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Split Entries</p>
    <p>Align Sequences</p>
    <p>FuncSonal Data Curate AnnotaSons</p>
    <p>Format</p>
    <p>Format</p>
    <p>Format</p>
    <p>Construct Trees</p>
    <p>t</p>
    <p>Need for privacy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workflow Provenance Repositories</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current situaSon</p>
    <p>To enable sharing and reuse, repositories of workflow specificaSons are being created  e.g. myExperiment.org  Keyword search is used to find specificaSons of interest (tags at level of workflow)</p>
    <p>Several workflow systems are also storing provenance informaSon  Module execuSons, input parameters, input/output data</p>
    <p>Input-only 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vision</p>
    <p>Workflow Provenance repositories store specificaSons as well as execuSons (i.e. provenance)  Searchable  Queryable</p>
    <p>Searching/querying these repositories can be used to  Find/reuse workflows  Understand meaning of a workflow  Correct/debug erroneous specificaSons  See the downstream effect of bad data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problem</p>
    <p>Owners/authors of workflows may wish to keep some of the provenance informaSon private.  Intermediate data  Module behavior  Structure of the execuSon</p>
    <p>There is a tradeoff between the uSlity of provenance informaSon and privacy guarantees.</p>
    <p>Search/query must respect privacy guarantees.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>You are beeer off designing in security and privacy from the start, rather than trying to add them later.</p>
    <p>(Shapiro, CACM 53:6, June 2010)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Concerns in Data-Oriented Workflows</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy and Workflow Provenance</p>
    <p>Privacy concerns are Sed to the components of workflow provenance  Data that flows on edges  Modules that implement funcSons  Structure of provenance dependencies: connecSons between data and other data, or between data and module execuSons</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data from other groups is used in normalizaSon</p>
    <p>Example 1: Data Privacy</p>
    <p>Robots are used to perform microarray analysis</p>
    <p>Data must be normalized to be interpreted correctly NormalizaSon data</p>
    <p>should be kept secret</p>
    <p>Microarray companies provide normalizaSon methods</p>
    <p>Normalized data</p>
    <p>Microarray data obtained from the experiment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example 2: Module Privacy</p>
    <p>(X1, X2, X3, X4, X5)</p>
    <p>(X1, X2, X3) (X1, X2, X4, X5)</p>
    <p>P has cancer?</p>
    <p>Split entries</p>
    <p>Check for Cancer</p>
    <p>Check for InfecSous disease</p>
    <p>Create Report</p>
    <p>report</p>
    <p>PaSent record: Gender, smoking habits, Familial environment, blood pressure, blood test report,</p>
    <p>P has an infecBous disease?</p>
    <p>Module funcSonality should be kept secret</p>
    <p>From paBents standpoint: output should not be guessed given input data values</p>
    <p>From module owners standpoint: no one should be able to simulate the module and use it elsewhere.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example 3: Structural Privacy</p>
    <p>M1 M2 Protein</p>
    <p>+ FuncSonal annotaSon Protein</p>
    <p>M2 compares domains of proteins (more</p>
    <p>precise but more Sme consuming)</p>
    <p>M1 compares the enSre protein against already annotated genomes</p>
    <p>RelaSonships between certain data/module pairs should be kept secret</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy concerns at a glance</p>
    <p>P: (X1, X2, X3, X4)</p>
    <p>(X1, X2, X3) (X1, X2, X4)</p>
    <p>P has cancer? P has infecSous disease?</p>
    <p>Data Privacy</p>
    <p>Data items are private</p>
    <p>Module Privacy</p>
    <p>Module funcSonality is private (x, f(x))</p>
    <p>Structural Privacy  ExecuSon paths</p>
    <p>between certain data is private</p>
    <p>Split entries</p>
    <p>Check for cancer Check for infecSous disease</p>
    <p>Create Report</p>
    <p>report</p>
    <p>smoking habits, blood pressure, blood test report,</p>
    <p>Check for cancer</p>
    <p>DB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The quesSons we need to answer...</p>
    <p>Can we preserve privacy of private components in a workflow and maximize uSlity w.r.t. provenance queries with provable guarantees on both privacy and uSlity of the soluSon?</p>
    <p>We idenSfied  them! How do we ? measure privacy?</p>
    <p>How do we ? measure uSlity?</p>
    <p>What informaSon ? can we hide?</p>
    <p>How do we find ? a good soluSon? 15</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Module Privacy (a hint)</p>
    <p>A module m = a funcSon  For every input x to m, m(x) value should not be revealed</p>
    <p>Enough equivalent possible m(x) values w.r.t. visible informaSon</p>
    <p>According to required privacy</p>
    <p>guarantee</p>
    <p>Roy et al, PODS 2011</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Module Privacy (a hint)</p>
    <p>A module m = a funcSon  For every input x to m, m(x) value should not be revealed</p>
    <p>Enough equivalent possible m(x) values w.r.t. visible informaSon</p>
    <p>There is a knife, a fork and a spoon in this figure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Module Privacy (a hint)</p>
    <p>A module m = a funcSon  For every input x to m, m(x) value should not be revealed</p>
    <p>Enough equivalent possible m(x) values w.r.t. visible informaSon</p>
    <p>There is a knife, a fork and a spoon in this figure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>-privacy</p>
    <p>A module m is -private iff for every input x the actual value of m(x) is indisSnguishable from -1 other possible values wrt the visible data.  Example: Hiding a2 and a4 in the provenance table for m1</p>
    <p>guarantees 4-privacy. E.g. m1(0,0) could be (0,0,1), (0,1,1), (1,0,0) or (1,1,0).</p>
    <p>a1 a2 a3 a4 a5 0 0 0 0 1</p>
    <p>Input Output</p>
    <p>a1 a2 a3 a4 a5 0 0 0 0 1</p>
    <p>Input Output</p>
    <p>a7 a6</p>
    <p>m1</p>
    <p>m2 m3</p>
    <p>a1</p>
    <p>a3</p>
    <p>a2</p>
    <p>a4 a5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hierarchical Workflow Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Composite Modules  Composite modules encapsulate subworkflows  Extensively used in workflow design to enable reuse and sharing (top-down)</p>
    <p>Also used to hiding porSons of provenance to focus on relevant modules (boeom-up)  Biton et al, VLDB 2007, ICDE2008, ICDT2009; Sun et al, PVLDB 2009, SIGMOD2009</p>
    <p>Whether developed top-down or boeom up, composite modules can be used to create views of workflows or their provenance.</p>
    <p>Yields a hierarchical workflow model.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workflow model, revisited</p>
    <p>A simple workflow is a connected DAG whose nodes model modules and edges model potenSal dataflow between modules.</p>
    <p>A (hierarchical) workflow is a pair (W, ) where W is a finite set of simple workflows and  is a (parSal) expansion funcSon that maps some of the modules to simple workflows in W.</p>
    <p>Expansion edges can be used to define an expansion hierarchy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hierarchical workflow, example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Expansion hierarchy, example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>View: Prefix of hierarchy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Views are useful</p>
    <p>At the specificaSon level, views can be used to control what is seen of module descripSons or the expansion to a subworkflow.</p>
    <p>View can also be projected to the execuSon level (provenance) to control what data is seen, hide structural informaSon, or hide inferred module behavior</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy-aware Search and Query</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Vision, recapped</p>
    <p>Workflow Provenance repositories will store specificaSons as well as execuSons (i.e. provenance)  Searchable, queryable</p>
    <p>Query results must respect privacy guarantees.  Data, module, structure.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Search Workflows and modules are tagged.</p>
    <p>W1! M1&quot; M3&quot; M4&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>M5&quot; M6&quot; M2&quot;</p>
    <p>M7&quot;</p>
    <p>SNP&quot; disease&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>SNP&quot;</p>
    <p>W2!</p>
    <p>W5!</p>
    <p>OMIM&quot;SNP&quot;</p>
    <p>W3! join&quot;</p>
    <p>I1&quot;</p>
    <p>O1&quot;</p>
    <p>parse&quot;</p>
    <p>parse&quot;</p>
    <p>M8&quot;  M9&quot; W4! risk&quot;</p>
    <p>PubMed&quot; OMIM&quot;</p>
    <p>prognosis&quot;</p>
    <p>SNP&quot;</p>
    <p>PubMed&quot; OMIM&quot;</p>
    <p>OMIM&quot;</p>
    <p>prognosis&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Search Query: disease, parse</p>
    <p>W1! M1&quot; M3&quot; M4&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>M5&quot; M6&quot; M2&quot;</p>
    <p>M7&quot;</p>
    <p>SNP&quot; disease&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>SNP&quot;</p>
    <p>W2!</p>
    <p>W5!</p>
    <p>OMIM&quot;SNP&quot;</p>
    <p>W3! join&quot;</p>
    <p>I1&quot;</p>
    <p>O1&quot;</p>
    <p>parse&quot;</p>
    <p>parse&quot;</p>
    <p>M8&quot;  M9&quot; W4! risk&quot;</p>
    <p>PubMed&quot; OMIM&quot;</p>
    <p>prognosis&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Search result</p>
    <p>InformaSve: shows the expansion and dataflow relaSonships necessary to understand the match</p>
    <p>Concise: no subtree also contains a match</p>
    <p>WISE: Searching workflow hierarchies: Liu et al, VLDB 2007</p>
    <p>Query: disease, parse</p>
    <p>W1! M1&quot; M3&quot; M4&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot; M7&quot;</p>
    <p>SNP&quot; disease&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>SNP&quot;</p>
    <p>W2!</p>
    <p>W5!</p>
    <p>OMIM&quot;SNP&quot;</p>
    <p>I1&quot;</p>
    <p>parse&quot;</p>
    <p>SNP&quot; OMIM&quot;</p>
    <p>W1!</p>
    <p>W2*! W3!</p>
    <p>W5!</p>
    <p>M1&quot; M2&quot;</p>
    <p>M4&quot;</p>
    <p>W4!</p>
    <p>M8&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Access Control SpecificaSon  Each module/workflow S has two acSons</p>
    <p>Read: authorized users can access keywords of S  Expand: authorized users can see the structure of S.</p>
    <p>The expand privileges for a user can be used to trim the expansion hierarchy and create an access view.</p>
    <p>The users access view and read privileges can be used to control what is returned in a search.</p>
    <p>Access controlled repository  same privileges on a module and on a workflow to which it expands.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>W1!</p>
    <p>W2! W3!</p>
    <p>W5!</p>
    <p>M1&quot; M2&quot;</p>
    <p>M4&quot;</p>
    <p>W4!</p>
    <p>M8&quot;</p>
    <p>W1! M1&quot; M3&quot; M4&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>M5&quot; M6&quot;</p>
    <p>M2&quot;</p>
    <p>M7&quot;</p>
    <p>SNP&quot; disease&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;</p>
    <p>SNP&quot;</p>
    <p>W2!</p>
    <p>W5!</p>
    <p>OMIM&quot;SNP&quot;</p>
    <p>W3! join&quot;</p>
    <p>I1&quot;</p>
    <p>O1&quot;</p>
    <p>parse&quot;</p>
    <p>parse&quot;</p>
    <p>M8&quot;</p>
    <p>M9&quot;</p>
    <p>prognosis&quot; W4! risk&quot;</p>
    <p>PubMed&quot; OMIM&quot;</p>
    <p>SNP&quot; OMIM&quot;</p>
    <p>PubMed&quot; OMIM&quot;</p>
    <p>prognosis&quot;</p>
    <p>Access Controlled Search  Query: OMIM, SNP</p>
    <p>User is not allowed to expand W2 or read W3.</p>
    <p>No match</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What about structural privacy?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A C E G</p>
    <p>B D F H</p>
    <p>y1 y4 y6</p>
    <p>y3</p>
    <p>y2 y5 y7</p>
    <p>A C E G</p>
    <p>B D F H</p>
    <p>y1 y4 y6</p>
    <p>y3</p>
    <p>y2 y5 y7</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>M</p>
    <p>G</p>
    <p>B H</p>
    <p>y1 y6</p>
    <p>y2 y7</p>
    <p>Access (Security) Views Poster with Bau and Milo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A C E G</p>
    <p>B D F H</p>
    <p>y1 y4 y6</p>
    <p>y3</p>
    <p>y2 y5 y7</p>
    <p>A C E G</p>
    <p>B D F H</p>
    <p>y1 y4 y6</p>
    <p>y3</p>
    <p>y2 y5 y7</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>M</p>
    <p>G</p>
    <p>B H</p>
    <p>y1 y6</p>
    <p>y2 y7</p>
    <p>How can we separate hiding sensitive data/modules from hiding structure?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>d6 B</p>
    <p>d12</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>d5 A</p>
    <p>d13</p>
    <p>D d7</p>
    <p>d9</p>
    <p>d8</p>
    <p>d10</p>
    <p>d11</p>
    <p>Dependency and Data Edges</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>d19 d21</p>
    <p>d20 d22</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>Simple workflow</p>
    <p>d19</p>
    <p>d20 E</p>
    <p>d21</p>
    <p>F</p>
    <p>d16</p>
    <p>d22</p>
    <p>Composite module that expands to the simple workflow</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Challenges  Workflow Provenance repositories will store specificaSons</p>
    <p>as well as execuSons (i.e. provenance)  Searchable, queryable, privacy preserving</p>
    <p>Formalizing privacy noSons  Data privacy: Hiding a data value may not be enough  how</p>
    <p>much is revealed from the displayed data values?  Module privacy: how to handle workflows with both private</p>
    <p>and public modules?  Structural privacy: What techniques should be used? What</p>
    <p>are the desired guarantees?  Can we use differenSal privacy?</p>
    <p>Search: efficiently idenSfying data that users can access  Users may have different privileges, yielding many different</p>
    <p>access views.  What is an appropriate provenance query language?</p>
    <p>How does access control interact? 39</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Challenges, cont.</p>
    <p>How to express security policies and ensure they are obeyed</p>
    <p>There is also related work on secure provenance, i.e. detecSng and protecSng against provenance tampering</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Session Papers  A Framework for Policies over Provenance (Tyrone)</p>
    <p>Specify access control and redacSon policies which transform provenance graph to hide sensiSve informaSon</p>
    <p>Tracking Emigrant Data via Transient Provenance (Stephanie)  Best security policies can be compromised by trusted party with</p>
    <p>malicious intent  Ghost objects track when data leaves system</p>
    <p>One of These Records Is Not Like the Others (Carrie)  Propose various techniques (crypto, consistency checks) to detect and</p>
    <p>correct errors in provenance  Consistency checks can be thwarted by rogue generator examining</p>
    <p>provenance records to supply info for new record: may need to secure provenance record for others than creator.</p>
    <p>A Fine-Grained Wf Model with Provenance-Aware Security Views  Specify for each module (atomic or composite) the input/output</p>
    <p>dependencies. Users are given a view at which level they can see the workflow provenance. This can be used for data/module/structural privacy.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgments  Members of the PennDB group</p>
    <p>Sanjeev Khanna  Sudeepa Roy  Julia Stoyanovich  Val Tannen</p>
    <p>Friend of PennDB and Tel Aviv faculty  Tova Milo</p>
    <p>PennDB alum and ASU faculty  Yi Chen</p>
    <p>BioinformaScs collaborators  Sarah Cohen-Boulakia</p>
    <p>This work was supported in part by NSF IIS-0803524, IIS-0629846, IIS-0915438, CCF-0635084, and IIS-0904314; NSF CAREER award IIS-0845647; and CRA 0937060 42</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
