<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ExperimenTor: A Testbed for Safe and Realis7c Tor Experimenta7on</p>
    <p>Kevin Bauer1 Micah Sherr2 Damon McCoy3 Dirk Grunwald4</p>
    <p>http://crysp.uwaterloo.ca/software/exptor! 4th Workshop on Cyber Security ExperimentaGon and Test (CSET 11)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is Tor and why is it important?</p>
    <p>Tor is a low-latency overlay network and a so=ware package that allows you to use TCP-based applica7ons anonymously</p>
    <p>Tor has an es7mated 350,000 daily users world-wide and its network consists of over 2,500 volunteer-operated Tor routers Ordinary Ci7zens</p>
    <p>- Protect web browsing habits - Research sensiGve or taboo topics - Circumvent censorship</p>
    <p>Corpora7ons</p>
    <p>- Research the compeGGon - Safeguard trade secrets</p>
    <p>Ac7vists &amp; Whistleblowers - Expose human rights violaGons - Promote democracy - Protest elecGon results</p>
    <p>Law Enforcement</p>
    <p>- Online surveillance - SGng operaGons</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Get router list</p>
    <p>Directory Server</p>
    <p>Tor uses layered encrypGon to hide your online behaviors</p>
    <p>Tor provides anonymity for TCP applica1ons by tunneling traffic through a virtual circuit of three Tor routers using layered encrypGon</p>
    <p>Client</p>
    <p>Des7na7on</p>
    <p>Circuit</p>
    <p>The Tor Network</p>
    <p>Entry Guard</p>
    <p>Middle Router</p>
    <p>Exit Router</p>
    <p>CommunicaGng parGes are unlinkable as long as the entry and exit routers do not collude</p>
    <p>Tor Router</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tor is sGll an evolving research network  Past and current research aims to improve Tors:  Security and anonymity [CCS 07, NDSS 08, USENIX Security 10]  Quality of service [USENIX Security 09, CCS 10, PETS 11]</p>
    <p>Problem: There is no standard methodology for conducGng Tor research in a realis1c and safe manner; prior methods include:</p>
    <p>Network simulators Small-scale network emula7on</p>
    <p>Abstract modeling Live Tor network</p>
    <p>Distributed research networks</p>
    <p>Realism</p>
    <p>Safety</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ExperimenTor: A whole-network Tor emulaGon testbed</p>
    <p>Goal: Propose a standard experimental methodology</p>
    <p>- Replicates all components of the Tor network in isola1on - Reproduces plausible network condiGons through scalable</p>
    <p>network emula1on - Fuels experiments with empirically derived models</p>
    <p>Network simulators Small-scale network emula7on</p>
    <p>Abstract modeling Live Tor network</p>
    <p>Distributed research networks</p>
    <p>Realism</p>
    <p>Safety</p>
    <p>Allows inves7gators to study global, whole-network effects ExperimenTor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Talk outline  MoGvaGng case studies from prior Tor research  Challenges of building a Tor network testbed  Design and implementaGon of ExperimenTor  Early experiences and lessons learned  Conclusions and future work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case study: Whole-network PlanetLab experiments</p>
    <p>Uniform router selecGon: Probability of adacks success is (c/n)2, c malicious routers in a network of n total routers</p>
    <p>It is assumed that an adacker who controls an entry/exit pair can trivially link the communicaGng parGes: traffic confirma7on aUack</p>
    <p>Tor Client</p>
    <p>Des7na7on</p>
    <p>Entry Guard</p>
    <p>Middle Router Exit Router</p>
    <p>Tor routers are selected in propor7on to their perceived bandwidth capaci7es for load balancing, but malicious routers can lie</p>
    <p>[Bauer et al., WPES 07]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment: Evaluated the adack on two small Planetlab deployments with 40 and 60 honest Tor routers</p>
    <p>Details: Sample the bandwidth distribuGon of the real Tor network</p>
    <p>Limita7ons: 1. Reduced scale 2. Need to run many measurements to find suitable PlanetLab nodes 3. Repeatability? [Bauer et al., WPES 07]</p>
    <p>Case study: Whole-network PlanetLab experiments (2)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case study: Small-scale experiments with the live Tor network</p>
    <p>Tunable Tor was proposed to help users manage their risk of the previous adack</p>
    <p>High anonymity High performance</p>
    <p>User-tunable router selec7on</p>
    <p>Skewed to high bandwidth nodes Uniform selec7on</p>
    <p>[Snader and Borisov, NDSS 08]</p>
    <p>Mean 7me to fetch 1 MB Experiment : Deployed one Tunable Tor client on the live Tor network Details: Measured download Gmes at different selecGon levels Limita7ons: What happens when many Tor clients use Tunable Tor? Global effects?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A case for whole-network Tor emulaGon Goal: Capture all salient dynamics of the live Tor network and reproduce in isolaGon  RealisGc and safe experiments</p>
    <p>Desired features: 1. Allow invesGgators to deploy small-scale, large-scale, or global changes to any part of Tors design 2. Should eliminate any risk to the live Tor network 3. Experimental results should be meaningful to the live Tor network</p>
    <p>Our argument: All can be realized with whole-network Tor emula7on</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design challenges</p>
    <p>Modeling the live Tor network is difficult  Tor routers: Bandwidths, guard statuses, exit policies?  Tor clients: How many? ApplicaGons? Behaviors?</p>
    <p>Large-scale network emulaGon  Emulab and DETER have limited and shared resources</p>
    <p>Need to run unmodified Tor and applicaGon code  Avoids re-implementaGon errors; promotes realism</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MeeGng the design challenges</p>
    <p>Modeling Tor routers: - Publicly-available router metadata from Tors directories - Historical router data aggregated by the Tor Metrics Portal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MeeGng the design challenges (2)</p>
    <p>Modeling Tor clients: Leverage exisGng empirical data on Tor clients and their behaviors</p>
    <p>Telnet FTP</p>
    <p>E-Mail Instant Messenging</p>
    <p>BitTorrent SSL</p>
    <p>HTTP</p>
    <p>Number of Exit TCP Connec7ons by Protocol</p>
    <p>Instant Messaging</p>
    <p>[McCoy et al., PETS 08]</p>
    <p>Also leverage exisGng empirical studies of HTTP traffic to emulate realisGc workloads [e.g., Hernndes-Campos et al., MASCOTS 03; Google web metrics 2010]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MeeGng the design challenges (3)</p>
    <p>Modeling Tor clients: Leverage exisGng empirical data on Tor clients and their behaviors</p>
    <p>[McCoy et al., PETS 08]</p>
    <p>Telnet FTP</p>
    <p>E-Mail Instant Messenger</p>
    <p>BitTorrent SSL</p>
    <p>HTTP</p>
    <p>Aggregate Exit Traffic Volume by Protocol</p>
    <p>Instant Messaging</p>
    <p>Model the distribuGon of client traffic by connecGon and volume</p>
    <p>(GB)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MeeGng the design challenges (4)</p>
    <p>Modeling Tor clients: Can also leverage publicly-available data about Tor clients from the Tor Metrics Project</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MeeGng the design challenges (5) Large-scale network emula7on with ModelNet [Vahdat et al., OSDI 02]</p>
    <p>Emulates a specified network topology  Runs naGve code without modificaGon  Commodity hardware and OSes; can be deployed at local insGtuGon</p>
    <p>High-level system architecture  Emulator machine: Emulates a network topology in a kernel module  Virtual node machine: Runs applicaGons within the virtual topology</p>
    <p>Physical network (e.g., 1 Gbps) Linux FreeBSD</p>
    <p>Emulator Applica1ons run on virtual node machines</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Puqng it all together</p>
    <p>Prototype: FreeBSD 6.3 Linux 2.6.32</p>
    <p>Accompanying toolkit: - Topology genera7on - Configure Tor clients, routers, &amp; directories - Run experiments &amp; perform analyses</p>
    <p>Testbed and toolkit are publicly available http://crysp.uwaterloo.ca/software/exptor!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Early experiences</p>
    <p>ExperimenTor prototypes are deployed at four research insGtuGons (single emulator)</p>
    <p>Used to support two ongoing research projects:  Evaluate the effects of link-based router selecGon  Re-design Tors congesGon control and flow control</p>
    <p>Both projects require global design changes to Tor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LimitaGons and future work</p>
    <p>Scalability  Scaling experiments to Tors esGmated 350K users is likely not possible; necessary to down sample</p>
    <p>Improve client and traffic models  Data on Tor usage are limited  Is it possible to emulate diverse versions and configuraGons of Tor users?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary and conclusion</p>
    <p>ExperimenTor is a whole-network emulaGon-based testbed and toolkit for safe and realisGc Tor experiments</p>
    <p>Enables large-scale Tor experiments that:  Use real Tor router bandwidths to inform topology  Emulate Tor clients and their traffic  Enable experiments with global changes to Tors design  Can be deployed cheaply on commodity systems</p>
    <p>For more informaGon: http://crysp.uwaterloo.ca/software/exptor!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
