<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Protocols Life After Attacks lets investigate beyond</p>
    <p>Giampaolo Bella Stefano Bistarelli Fabio Massacci</p>
    <p>@ Cambridge, Catania, Pescara, Pisa, Trento</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current verification setting</p>
    <p>Yes! I found an attack!</p>
    <p>I can assure theres no such!!</p>
    <p>Focus is in fact on THE attack. Is this all??</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Glance at the physical world We own a bakery, and one morning we find the window smashed. We can:</p>
    <p>Idea: apply same concepts to security protocols</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How and Why How? Must continue analysis after THE attack</p>
    <p>For example:</p>
    <p>Model Checkers: If I find an attack, is there another one? (retaliation)</p>
    <p>Theorem Provers: If I assume there is an attack, could anyone else mount the same attack? (detection)</p>
    <p>Why? Can get novel insights about protocols For example:</p>
    <p>Is it really convenient to attempt attacks?</p>
    <p>Do we need to redesign, or the bad guys are stopped by realistic threats?</p>
    <p>What if the principals change their behaviours?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Take Lowes middle-person attack on NS: if A executes with C then C impersonates A with B</p>
    <p>Consequence (Lowe): if B is a bank, C can steal from As account C B : {Na, Nb, Transfer 1000 from As account to Cs}Kb</p>
    <p>Extra consequence (last years workshop): if A is a bank, B can steal from Cs account B A : {Na, Nb, Transfer 1000 from Cs account to Bs}Ka</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Principals behaviours Principals are divided according to their behaviours into three disjoint sets.</p>
    <p>Good: G  conform to the protocol</p>
    <p>Bad: B  attempt to break the protocol</p>
    <p>Ugly: U  conform to the protocol but would collaborate with bad</p>
    <p>Crucially: principals may decide to change behaviour!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Traces and attacks Trace T : conventional view of protocol</p>
    <p>history as log (of events or messages, or)</p>
    <p>Projection T/A : subtrace of T where some agent in A acted</p>
    <p>Attack A : some predicate A(T,G,B,U)</p>
    <p>Can make Spy, owner of the network, explicit.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current verification setting (more formal)</p>
    <p>P vulnerable to A against G if  TP. A(T,G,B,U)</p>
    <p>P immune to A against G if  TP. A(T,G,B,U)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Retaliation A protocol P allows retaliation of an attack A by B if  TP, G,B,U s.t. A(T,G,B,U),</p>
    <p>TrP extending T ,  G,B,U s.t. BGU and</p>
    <p>s.t. A(Tr,G,B,U)</p>
    <p>if B=G direct retaliation else, if BG   combined retaliation else, if BU arbitrary retaliation</p>
    <p>Appears suitable for theorem proving</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example (mvore formal) Lowes middle-person attack on NS: if A executes with C then C impersonates A with B</p>
    <p>Consequence (Lowe): if B is a bank, C can steal from As account</p>
    <p>Extra consequence (last years workshop): if A is a bank, B can steal from Cs account</p>
    <p>Whenever A(T, G:={B}, B:={C}, U:={A})</p>
    <p>T can be extended as Tr s.t. A(T, G:={A}, B:={B}, U:={C})</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>No Retaliation</p>
    <p>A protocol P allows no retaliation of an attack A by B if</p>
    <p>TP, G,B,U s.t. A(T,G,B,U),  TrP extending T ,</p>
    <p>G,B,U s.t. BGU and BGU</p>
    <p>holds A(Tr,G,B,U)</p>
    <p>Appears suitable for model checking</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Detection A protocol P allows detection of an attack A by B if</p>
    <p>TP, G,B,U s.t. A(T,G,B,U),  TrP s.t. T /G = Tr /G</p>
    <p>holds A(Tr,G,B,U)</p>
    <p>Appears suitable for theorem proving</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>No Detection</p>
    <p>A protocol P allows no detection of an attack A by B if</p>
    <p>TP, G,B,U s.t. A(T,G,B,U),</p>
    <p>TrP s.t. T /G = Tr /G and TrT holds A(Tr,G,B,U)</p>
    <p>Appears suitable for model checking</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Suspicion A protocol P allows suspicion of an attack A if  TP, G,B,U s.t. A(T,G,B,U),</p>
    <p>TrP s.t. T /G = Tr /G  B,U s.t. B B and UU</p>
    <p>s.t. A(Tr,G,B,U)</p>
    <p>Appears suitable for theorem proving</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>No Suspicion</p>
    <p>A protocol P allows no suspicion of an attack A if  TP, G,B,U s.t. A(T,G,B,U),</p>
    <p>TrP s.t. T /G = Tr /G  B,U s.t. B B and UU</p>
    <p>holds A(Tr,G,B,U)</p>
    <p>Appears suitable for model checking</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Theres life after attacks take place!</p>
    <p>Life that is worth investigating</p>
    <p>More complex properties of traces: at least two quantifiers (possibly alternated) where we used to have one only</p>
    <p>Theory now adapted. Can we adapt mechanised tool support?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
