<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BIPARTITE INDEX CODING</p>
    <p>Arash Saber Tehrani</p>
    <p>Alexandros G. Dimakis</p>
    <p>Michael J. Neely</p>
    <p>Department of Electrical Engineering University of Southern California (USC)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Index Coding Problem  Introduction  Bipartite model</p>
    <p>Our Scheme: Partition Multicast  Formulation</p>
    <p>Partition Multicast is NP-hard  Connection to clique cover</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Index Coding Problem</p>
    <p>Introduced in [Birk and Kol 98], and further developed in [Bar-Yossef, Birk, Jayram, and Kol 06 and 11].</p>
    <p>Broadcast station  Set of m packets P ={x1, x2,  , xm} from a finite alphabet X</p>
    <p>Set of n users U ={u1, u2,  , un}</p>
    <p>Each user demands exactly one packet  Each user i knows a subset of packets denoted by Nout(ui) as</p>
    <p>side info  Objective: Minimize the amount of broadcast data so that all</p>
    <p>users decode their designated packets.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bipartite model for IC</p>
    <p>The system can be represented by a bipartite graph</p>
    <p>A directed edge from packet xj to user ui indicates that user ui demands packet xj.</p>
    <p>A directed edge from user ui to packet xj indicates that user ui knows packet xj as side info.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Index Coding Problem</p>
    <p>A solution of the problem  A finite alphabet WX</p>
    <p>an encoding function E: Xm WX  each user ui is able to decode its designated packet from</p>
    <p>the broadcast message w and its side information.</p>
    <p>Optimal solution is HARD to compute.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Scheme: Partition Multicast</p>
    <p>When each user knows at least d packets as side information  We call d minimum out-degree or minimum knowledge</p>
    <p>Then there are at most m  d unknowns for each user.  With transmission of m - d independent equations in</p>
    <p>the form a1x1 + a2x2 +  + amxm where ai's are taken from some finite field F, each user can decode the packet it demands as shown in Ho et al. (Given that | F| is large enough)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Scheme: Partition Multicast</p>
    <p>Induced subgraph by a subset of packets S</p>
    <p>X1</p>
    <p>X2</p>
    <p>X3</p>
    <p>X4</p>
    <p>U1</p>
    <p>U2</p>
    <p>U3</p>
    <p>U4</p>
    <p>U5</p>
    <p>X1</p>
    <p>X2</p>
    <p>U1</p>
    <p>U2</p>
    <p>U3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Scheme: Partition Multicast</p>
    <p>We are looking for a partition (valid packet decomposition)</p>
    <p>X1</p>
    <p>X2</p>
    <p>X3</p>
    <p>X4</p>
    <p>U1</p>
    <p>U2</p>
    <p>U3</p>
    <p>U4</p>
    <p>U5</p>
    <p>X1</p>
    <p>X2</p>
    <p>X3</p>
    <p>X4</p>
    <p>|{X1,X2}| = 2, d1 = 1 |{X3,X4}| = 2, d1 = 1</p>
    <p>X1+X2 X3+X4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Scheme: Partition Multicast</p>
    <p>Partition Multicast:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Scheme: Partition Multicast</p>
    <p>The scheme is optimal for known cases such as  Cliques  trees  Directed cycles</p>
    <p>It has cycle cover schemes proposed by Chaudhry et al. and Neely et al. as a special case and outperforms them.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Partition Multicast is NP-hard</p>
    <p>Undirected case:</p>
    <p>We want to find a partition for which the sum of minimum knowledge is maximized</p>
    <p>We call this problem sum-degree cover</p>
    <p>U1, X1</p>
    <p>U2, X2</p>
    <p>U3, X3 U4, X4</p>
    <p>U5, X5</p>
    <p>X1U1</p>
    <p>U2 X2</p>
    <p>X3</p>
    <p>X4</p>
    <p>X5</p>
    <p>U3</p>
    <p>U4</p>
    <p>U5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Partition Multicast is NP-hard</p>
    <p>Sum-degree cover and clique cover are equivalent  Partitioning a clique is strictly suboptimal</p>
    <p>For any graph T(GS) 1.</p>
    <p>If GS is a clique, then T(GS) = 1, i.e., the minimum knowledge d = |S| - 1.</p>
    <p>We need to show that  Solution of sum-degree cover gives the solution of clique cover  Solution of the clique cover gives the solution of sum-degree</p>
    <p>cover</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SD cover Clique cover</p>
    <p>Let the solution of SD cover be GS1,  , GSK induced by subsets S1, S2, , Sk.</p>
    <p>Clique cover is also a graph partition where each subgraph requires exactly one transmission, so</p>
    <p>Consider subgraph GS1 with minimum knowledge d1. The complement of GS1 has maximum degree |S1| - d1 - 1.</p>
    <p>As is well known, any graph of maximum degree d has a vertex coloring of size d + 1.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SD cover Clique cover</p>
    <p>The complement of GS1 has a vertex coloring with |S1| - d1 color.</p>
    <p>Thus, GS1 has a clique cover of size |S1| - d1.</p>
    <p>That is  Repeating the same procedure over all k</p>
    <p>subgraphs, gives</p>
    <p>Jointly with the previous inequality we get</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Partition Multicast is NP-hard</p>
    <p>Maps an undirected graph G to a bipartite graph.</p>
    <p>Solve the partition multicast.  Find the clique cover of all partitions through</p>
    <p>coloring of complements of the subgraphs.  Find the clique cover.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>We introduced the bipartite graph model for the index coding problem</p>
    <p>We presented a new scheme partition multicast for index coding problem.</p>
    <p>We introduced the sum-degree cover problem.  We showed that finding the optimal partition</p>
    <p>is NP-hard.  Future work: finding a good partition</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks, Questions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Partition Multicast</p>
    <p>Partition or Cover:</p>
    <p>Let x S 1, x S 2  Delete x from S1 to get set S1</p>
    <p>New minimum knowledge for GS1, namely, d1.</p>
    <p>|S1| =|S1|-1 and d1-1  d1  d1.</p>
    <p>GS1GS1 GS2GS2 GSkGSk</p>
    <p>T(GS1)=|S1|-d1 T(GS2)=|S2|-d2 T(GSk)=|Sk|-dk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Scheme: Partition Multicast</p>
    <p>Bipartite case (Painful stuff)  For set S P, define GS = (US,S,ES) to be the subgraph induced by S:</p>
    <p>A valid packet decomposition is set of k disjoint subgraphs such that</p>
    <p>It can be checked that for a valid packet decomposition</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Index Coding Problem</p>
    <p>A solution of the problem  A finite alphabet WX</p>
    <p>an encoding function E: Xm WX  each user ui is able to decode its designated packet from the</p>
    <p>broadcast message w and its side information.</p>
    <p>The minimum coding length of the solution per input symbol:</p>
    <p>where the minimum is over all encoding functions E.  Optimal broadcast rate</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
