<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Nilton Bila, Eyal de Lara University of Toronto</p>
    <p>Matti Hiltunen, Kaustubh Joshi, H. Andres Lagar-Cavilla AT&amp;T Labs Research</p>
    <p>Mohadev Satyanarayanan</p>
    <p>Cargie-Mellon University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Offices &amp; homes crowded with desktop PCs</p>
    <p>PCs idle on average 12 hours a day (Nedevschi09)</p>
    <p>60% of desktops remain powered overnight (Webber06)</p>
    <p>Why do we care?</p>
    <p>Dell Optiplex 745 Desktop Peak power: 280W Idle power: 102.1W Sleep power: 1.2W</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Always-on semantics  Background Applications: IM, E-mail, VoIP  Remote Access: files, remote admin</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Encapsulate user session in VM  When idle, migrate VM to consolidation server</p>
    <p>and power down PC.  When busy, migrate back to users PC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Encapsulate user session in VM  When idle, migrate VM to consolidation server</p>
    <p>and power down PC.  When busy, migrate back to users PC</p>
    <p>Downside: VMs are large</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Insight: Idle VM access only a small fraction of their memory and disk state</p>
    <p>Migrate just the working set</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Small migration footprint</p>
    <p>Client  Fast migration  Low energy cost</p>
    <p>Network  Gentle on network resources</p>
    <p>Server  High consolidation ratios</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Small migration footprint</p>
    <p>Client  Fast migration over 3G or WiFi  Low energy cost mobile devices</p>
    <p>Network  Gentle on network resources</p>
    <p>Server  High consolidation ratios</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Small migration footprint</p>
    <p>Client  Fast migration over 3G or WiFi  Low energy cost mobile devices</p>
    <p>Network  Gentle on network resources wide area (IaaS)</p>
    <p>Server  High consolidation ratios</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Length of sleep times?</p>
    <p>Size of the memory footprint?</p>
    <p>Prototyped simple on-demand migration approach with SnowFlock  Monitor memory and disk page migration to clone</p>
    <p>VM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dell Optiplex 745 Desktop  4GB RAM, 2.66GHz Intel C2D  Peak power: 280W  Idle power: 102.1W  Sleep power: 1.2W</p>
    <p>VM Image:  Debian Linux 5  1GB RAM  12 GB disk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workload Description</p>
    <p>Login The login screen of a Linux desktop system (GDM).</p>
    <p>E-mail Mozilla thunderbird connected to an IMAP e-mail server. The client polls the server every 10 minutes.</p>
    <p>IM The Pidgin multi-protocol IM client connected to an IRC room with more than 100 users.</p>
    <p>Multitask A Gnome Desktop session with the E-mail client, IM client, Spreadsheet (OpenOffice Calc), PDF Reader (Evince) and file browser (Nautilus)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spatial locality  Potential benefits for pre-fetching</p>
    <p>Migration Pattern: E-mail</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>98% of request arrive in close succession</p>
    <p>Migration Pattern: E-mail</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Total sleep of 17 to 46 minutes out of 1hour  Energy savings of 50% to 0.  Sleep opportunities increase over time</p>
    <p>E-mail Multitask Email Multitask</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inefficient in 1st hour  69% energy savings overall</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A cloud node with 4GB of RAM can run ~30 VMs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Frequent power cycling reduces hw life expectancy and limits power savings  Reduce number of sleep cycles and increase sleep duration  Predict page access patterns and prefetch  Leverage content addressable memory</p>
    <p>Fast reintegration  Policies</p>
    <p>When to migrate/re-integrate?  When does the desktop go to sleep?  On re-integration, should state be maintained in the cloud? For</p>
    <p>how long?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Remote wake up: Wake-on-LAN, Wake-on-Wireless  No support for always-on applications  Short sleep times</p>
    <p>Protocol proxy: Nedevschi09, Reich10  Limited flexibility</p>
    <p>Application proxy: Somniloquy, Turducken, SleepServer  Applications must be modified  Management of applications may be complex</p>
    <p>Full VM Migration: LiteGreen  Low consolidation ratios  Bandwidth intensive</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proposed partial VM migration  Even nave partial VM migration can reduce energy</p>
    <p>use of idle desktop  32  50% over an hour-long idle interval  69% overnight</p>
    <p>Idle desktop sessions have a memory footprint an order of magnitude smaller than their RAM allocation.</p>
    <p>Partial VM migration can save medium to large size organizations tens to hundreds of thousands of dollars</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>http://sysweb.cs.toronto.edu/snowflock</p>
    <p>delara@cs.toronto.edu</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>44% to 60% reduction in energy costs</p>
    <p>D o</p>
    <p>ll ar</p>
    <p>s (t</p>
    <p>h o</p>
    <p>u sa</p>
    <p>n d</p>
    <p>s)</p>
    <p># Desktops</p>
    <p>No Sleep</p>
    <p>Partial Migration</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
