<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Asynchronous (Time-Sliced) Missed Call Duration Messaging Nokia Research Center, Africa  Nairobi (Kenya)</p>
    <p>BUZZENGER</p>
    <p>Brian Omwenga, Pauline Githinji</p>
    <p>June 2012</p>
    <p>2012 Nokia 2012-06-15 / BGO 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview - Background</p>
    <p>Cost of Mobile Communication (in developing regions) is</p>
    <p>sometimes disproportionate to data transmission size</p>
    <p>The prevalent cost structure charges a fixed cost for an SMS (150 characters) regardless of whether the message contains the entire</p>
    <p>Many situations where users only need to give small data packet</p>
    <p>messages (such as yes, no)</p>
    <p>Our research also recognized the popular phenomenon of</p>
    <p>flashing (missed call messaging) amongst youth in Africa</p>
    <p>Primarily used for notification and was expanded (to a limited scale) based on number of beeps</p>
    <p>Our project addressed the scaling challenge by measuring</p>
    <p>duration of missed calls to establish the asynchronous missed call</p>
    <p>duration interpretation messaging</p>
    <p>2012 Nokia 2012-06-15 / BGO 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GSM Call Signal</p>
    <p>Sender selects contact and uses a dial pad with iconic</p>
    <p>representations or template messages or composes a message</p>
    <p>Recipient receives new</p>
    <p>message alert ; he does</p>
    <p>not hear the phone ring</p>
    <p>during the beeping.</p>
    <p>He can then read the</p>
    <p>received message .</p>
    <p>SENDER</p>
    <p>The codes for different messages are set by the duration of the missed call (in seconds/milliseconds). Each length of time can be translated into a different</p>
    <p>message.</p>
    <p>Buzzenger  (Missed Call Duration Interpretation messaging)</p>
    <p>RECEIVER</p>
    <p>no ringtone 3. Application picks up End signal, recreates text message</p>
    <p>and alerts new message</p>
    <p>2012 Nokia 2012-06-15 / BGO 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Overview  User Interface</p>
    <p>The user interface was designed to mimic classical SMS</p>
    <p>messaging composition</p>
    <p>This covered:</p>
    <p>Iconic/pictorial messages</p>
    <p>Template messages</p>
    <p>Text composition messages</p>
    <p>2012 Nokia 2012-06-15 / BGO 4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Overview - Database</p>
    <p>The database schema mapped the pre-defined messages with</p>
    <p>coded durations</p>
    <p>Scaled our message database by representing each message</p>
    <p>with 2 duration codes generating an interpretation matrix</p>
    <p>The optimal assignment of codes for short duration messages was based</p>
    <p>on their popularity across the messaging space</p>
    <p>Call 1 duration</p>
    <p>C a</p>
    <p>ll 2 d</p>
    <p>u ra</p>
    <p>tio n</p>
    <p>y message</p>
    <p>...message x,y</p>
    <p>Optimal</p>
    <p>2012 Nokia 2012-06-15 / BGO 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Overview - Transport</p>
    <p>The transport module manages handshaking (control bits) and</p>
    <p>relay of missed call sequences</p>
    <p>The transport module also manages the suppression of typical</p>
    <p>calling functions such as ringing, caller screen, call logging, etc.</p>
    <p>2012 Nokia 2012-06-15 / BGO 6</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Overview - Collaboration diagram</p>
    <p>2012 Nokia 2012-06-15 / BGO 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some Challenges</p>
    <p>Technical</p>
    <p>Universal set of messages</p>
    <p>Calculation of latency/lag (accuracy of missed calls)</p>
    <p>Scaling vs. message relay duration</p>
    <p>Economic  Flooding service</p>
    <p>operator networks</p>
    <p>2012 Nokia 2012-06-15 / BGO 8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deployment Architectures  Further work</p>
    <p>Distributed  Each mobile device runs the application for the</p>
    <p>encoding/decoding of messages</p>
    <p>Centralized  Client/server architecture where users send</p>
    <p>message to a centralized server that interprets the message.</p>
    <p>Useful for emergency and survey situations</p>
    <p>Currently developing this in collaboration with Ushahidi.com</p>
    <p>Currently working on APIs to open source the platform</p>
    <p>2012 Nokia 2012-06-15 / BGO 9</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
