<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Speed-Breaker Early Warning System Mohit Jain, Ajeet Pal Singh (JIIT Noida, India) Soshant Bali, Sanjit Kaul (IIIT Delhi, India)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>MoJvaJon  IntroducJon  DetecJon Methodology  Data Set  EvaluaJon  Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MoJvaJon</p>
    <p>Speed-breakers reduce accidents  Reduce speed and increase safety</p>
    <p>Popular in many developing countries  Shortage of enforcement resources  India, Chile, Egypt, Ghana, Pakistan, etc.</p>
    <p>Can also cause accidents  Frequent reports of speed-breaker fataliJes  Two wheelers: motorcycles, scooters  Last row of a bus</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MoJvaJon</p>
    <p>From Reference [17]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MoJvaJon</p>
    <p>Inconspicuous under special condiJons  Night, Rain, Snow, Fog, etc.</p>
    <p>Warning signs/light  England DoT: must accompany lights  Guidelines ignored in developing countries</p>
    <p>Standard dimensions?  No, many different shapes  TransportaJon researchers consider unsafe</p>
    <p>Illegal speed-breakers  4,536 in Bangalore  Some on naJonal highways  Pakistan, Malaysia, Russia, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IntroducJon</p>
    <p>Speed-breaker early warning system (SWAS)  Smartphone applicaJon  Downloads nearby speed-breaker locaJons  Warns when approaching one</p>
    <p>PopulaJng the speed-breaker locaJon database  Smartphone applicaJon collects accelerometer readings  When it detects a speed-breaker, reports locaJon to server  Server examines reports from mulJple phones before confirming</p>
    <p>Cost? Is it an affordable soluJon for developing world?  Android phones available for &lt; $100 today, geeng cheaper  Data plan? Store known speed-breaker locaJons locally</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main ContribuJons</p>
    <p>Algorithm for detecJng speed-breakers  Feature vector, SVM, Decision Trees</p>
    <p>Amplitude vector has enough informaJon  Previous work : GPS, magnetometer  No need for expensive reorientaJon</p>
    <p>Validated using an extensive data set  678 Km of drive data from New Delhi, India  Several different vehicle types: cars, motorcycle, auto, etc.  Several different phones  22 different drivers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accelerometer ReorientaJon ?</p>
    <p>Phone axes dont always align with cars axes</p>
    <p>Given a window of 3N accelerometer samples  Transform to a window of N amplitude vectors</p>
    <p>ai = xi 2 + yi</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DetecJon Methodology</p>
    <p>X-axis</p>
    <p>Y-axis</p>
    <p>Z-axis</p>
    <p>Amplitude</p>
    <p>Feature ExtracJon</p>
    <p>ClassificaJon</p>
    <p>Decision</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Feature Vector  Standard deviaJon, number of mean crossings, maximum mean</p>
    <p>crossing interval, raJo of standard deviaJons (previous, next)</p>
    <p>{2.622,6,0.399,3.5744,5.0066}</p>
    <p>{0.34,11,0.245,0.8812,0.7729}</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Set</p>
    <p>At least two phones used in every drive  Measurer, Marker  Measurer: pant pocket, dashboard, car seat, etc.  Marker: in observers hands  Time synchronized</p>
    <p>Speed-breaker types  Type 1: 3 to 6 p long, 5 to 10 inches high  Type 2: 1 to 2 p long, 3 to 6 inches high</p>
    <p>Measurer</p>
    <p>Marker</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Set</p>
    <p>Total length: 678 Km of drive data  LocaJon: NaJonal Capital Region  Vehicles</p>
    <p>219.5 Km in Auto Rickshaw  40.15 Km in Cycle Rickshaw  290.5 Km in Car  53.6 Km in Motor Cycle  74.1 Km in Bus</p>
    <p>22 different drivers Auto rickshaw</p>
    <p>Cycle rickshaw</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EvaluaJon</p>
    <p>K-fold cross validaJon  If there are n speed-breakers in any drive  Randomly select n windows that dont have any speed-breakers  Total of 2n labeled samples  Divide 2n labeled samples into k groups  Train with k-1 groups, test with 1 group</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EvaluaJon</p>
    <p>Train and test using same type of vehicle  Motorcycle: phone in pocket, frequent stops, brake  Cycle-Rickshaw: poor/no suspension system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>False alarm probability can be reduced further  Server only accepts locaJons reported by mulJple users  Reject reports from vehicles known to have high false alarms, e.g.,</p>
    <p>motor-cycle, cycle rickshaw  Baqery consumpJon</p>
    <p>ConJnuous GPS monitoring increases baqery consumpJon  Download locaJons of nearby speed-breakers  EsJmate the drive Jme to nearest speed-breaker and stop GPS  Start monitoring GPS again aper geeng close to the speed-breaker</p>
    <p>Other applicaJons  SWAS can be integrated with navigaJon systems (Garmin,</p>
    <p>mapmyindia, etc.)  Emergency vehicles delayed by 10 seconds per speed-breaker; If</p>
    <p>locaJons of illegal speed-breakers are known emergency vehicles can drive around them</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
