<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Building Scalable and Distributed Voice Forums in the Developing World</p>
    <p>Aditya Vashistha</p>
    <p>Joint work with Bill Thies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voice Remains Primary Interface for Mobile Subscribers in India</p>
    <p>Most subscribers lack smart phones</p>
    <p>Text interfaces hindered by:</p>
    <p>Low literacy (33% of adults in India are non-literate)</p>
    <p>Language diversity (font support for tribal language?)</p>
    <p>Mobile Internet: &lt; 3% of subscribers</p>
    <p>Smart Phone: &lt; 5% Feature Phone: 50-70% (e.g., music player)</p>
    <p>Basic Phone: 30-50%</p>
    <p>Source: McKinsey, IDC India</p>
    <p>Source: McKinsey, IDC India</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interactive Voice Response in India</p>
    <p>Interactive Voice Response (IVR) allows humans to interact with computers by placing a voice call</p>
    <p>In 2010: $750M from value-added IVR services</p>
    <p>Expected to grow to $3 billion by 2020</p>
    <p>Examples:</p>
    <p>Ringtones, music, jokes, astrology</p>
    <p>Booking movie tickets, travel, mobile commerce</p>
    <p>TATAs Behtar Zindagi program: information for farmers with over 10,000 voice prompts</p>
    <p>Screening for Kaun Banega Crorepati</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voice Forums for Development Citizen News Journalism Mudliar et al. ICTD 2012</p>
    <p>Avaaj Otalo: Agriculture Discussion Forum Patel et al. CHI 2010</p>
    <p>(Phone Broadcasting System for Sex Workers) Sambasivan et al. CHI 2011</p>
    <p>(Healthline: Access to Health Information) Sherwani et al. ICTD 2007</p>
    <p>Community driven Intelligent Maps Kumar et al. ICTD 2009</p>
    <p>Community Radio Koradia et al. ICTD 2012</p>
    <p>Feedback on School Meals Grover et al. DEV 2012</p>
    <p>Content Creation and Dissemination by Rural users Agarwal et al. ICTD 2009</p>
    <p>Viral Entertainment Platform Raza et al. ICTD 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: CGNet Swara A Voice Forum for Citizen Journalism</p>
    <p>Anyone can report news, issues, etc. in local language</p>
    <p>Submissions are reviewed by moderators over the Web</p>
    <p>Appropriate submissions are published:  For playback on audio channel</p>
    <p>For browsing on Web</p>
    <p>Some submissions seed stories for posting on CGNet site + list</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to Build a Voice Forum?</p>
    <p>Option 1: Leverage a hosting provider</p>
    <p>Limited availability; can be expensive</p>
    <p>Option 2: Build and host it yourself</p>
    <p>Voice</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations of Existing Tools (Freedom Fone, FreeSWITCH, Asterisk)</p>
    <p>IVR Junction</p>
    <p>Host your own website for content moderation and distribution</p>
    <p>Utilize YouTube for hosting and content moderation</p>
    <p>Runs on Linux Runs on Windows</p>
    <p>Ad-hoc implementation, tied to single infrastructure</p>
    <p>Standardized code (VoiceXML), portable across infrastructures</p>
    <p>Centralized server implies long-distance calls</p>
    <p>Distributed servers enable local calls</p>
    <p>How to Build a Voice Forum?</p>
    <p>A new open-source system that combines other free and commercial tools into an integrated platform to facilitate creation of Distributed and Scalable voice forums.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations of Existing Tools (Freedom Fone, FreeSWITCH, Asterisk)</p>
    <p>IVR Junction</p>
    <p>Host your own website for content moderation and distribution</p>
    <p>Utilize YouTube for hosting and content moderation</p>
    <p>Runs on Linux Runs on Windows</p>
    <p>Ad-hoc implementation, tied to single infrastructure</p>
    <p>Standardized code (VoiceXML), portable across infrastructures</p>
    <p>Centralized server implies long-distance calls</p>
    <p>Distributed servers enable local calls</p>
    <p>IVR Junction offers easier setup and cost-effective, distributed access points</p>
    <p>How to Build a Voice Forum?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IVR Service Users or Listeners in Delhi</p>
    <p>A person calls voice application Recorded message is stored in Laptop</p>
    <p>How Works</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IVR Service Users or Listeners in Delhi</p>
    <p>A person calls voice application Recorded message is stored in Laptop</p>
    <p>IVR Junction uploads this message on YouTube</p>
    <p>How Works</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IVR Service Users or Listeners in Delhi</p>
    <p>A person calls voice application Recorded message is stored in Laptop</p>
    <p>IVR Junction uploads this message on YouTube</p>
    <p>How Works</p>
    <p>Moderator either approve or reject the post</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IVR Service Users or Listeners in Delhi</p>
    <p>A person calls voice application Recorded message is stored in Laptop</p>
    <p>IVR Junction uploads this message on YouTube</p>
    <p>How Works</p>
    <p>Moderator either approve or reject the post</p>
    <p>Approved posts are - accessible at YouTube for Internet</p>
    <p>audience - uploaded at SkyDrive or Dropbox - can be posted at Facebook - Available for listening to callers of IVR</p>
    <p>service</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IVR Server for NGO in New Delhi, Delhi (India)</p>
    <p>IVR Server for NGO in Jaipur, Rajasthan (India)</p>
    <p>Internet Enabled</p>
    <p>Users</p>
    <p>GSM</p>
    <p>Network GSM Modem</p>
    <p>Moderation Platform</p>
    <p>Audio Hosting</p>
    <p>Users in Delhi</p>
    <p>Users in Rajasthan</p>
    <p>GSM</p>
    <p>Network</p>
    <p>GSM Modem</p>
    <p>IVR Service</p>
    <p>Moderator</p>
    <p>Upload Audio</p>
    <p>Laptop</p>
    <p>Upload Audio</p>
    <p>Synchronize Repository</p>
    <p>Synchronize Repository</p>
    <p>Laptop Cloud Service</p>
    <p>Distributed Architecture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation</p>
    <p>Key functionality: Synchronize content across different platforms and to present a unified interface to the user</p>
    <p>Implemented</p>
    <p>Various deployments are in progress</p>
    <p>Expected to be released this summer</p>
    <p>Feature LOC</p>
    <p>Caller Interface 700 of ASP.NET, VoiceXML and C#</p>
    <p>Admin Interface 1500 of ASP.NET</p>
    <p>Synchronization with Moderators 3100 of C#</p>
    <p>Synchronization with other branches 1300 of C#</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Setting Up Your Voice Service</p>
    <p>Laptop</p>
    <p>GSM or Fixed line modem</p>
    <p>SIP and VXML interpreter software  Voxeo Prophecy 11</p>
    <p>IVR Junction and Application code  Free and Open source</p>
    <p>Utilizes free Microsoft components like IIS Express, MS SQL Server Express, .NET framework 4 etc.</p>
    <p>YouTube account (free)</p>
    <p>SkyDrive or Dropbox account (free)</p>
    <p>Facebook page</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>is Easy to Set Up</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Supports Parallel Lines</p>
    <p>Single modem which support 4 lines</p>
    <p>You can have as many parallel lines you want</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power Applications</p>
    <p>Voice forums similar to CGNet Swara and Avaaj Otalo</p>
    <p>Phone Broadcasting System utilizing distributed architecture for lower outgoing call rates</p>
    <p>Any voice forum connecting users in different countries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power Applications</p>
    <p>Voice forums similar to CGNet Swara and Avaaj Otalo</p>
    <p>Phone Broadcasting System utilizing distributed architecture for lower outgoing call rates</p>
    <p>Any voice forum connecting users in different countries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future of Scalable Voice Forums</p>
    <p>Moderating content at scale</p>
    <p>Managing call costs at scale</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Moderating Content at Scale</p>
    <p>Run a call center of content moderators  Like Just Dial  Challenge: difficult to maintain consistent judgment, quality</p>
    <p>and accountability across all moderators  Community Moderation</p>
    <p>Analogous to reddit, Digg, Slashdot, Quora, Stackoverflow  Easy to penalize those who try to game the system as phone</p>
    <p>number is unique identity  Challenge: taxing to listen to long voice posts</p>
    <p>Hybrid model: transcribe audio posts on web using crowdsourcing. Moderators can moderate a voice forum by reading text rather than by listening to posts</p>
    <p>Challenge: how to protect anonymity of participants of a sensitive voice forum before community moderation  Voice anonymizer can be used to distort the recording enough to prevent</p>
    <p>recognition of speaker</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Managing Call Cost at Scale</p>
    <p>Use Distributed Architecture</p>
    <p>Deliver audio over data rather than voice  Streaming download from Web</p>
    <p>Use content caching mobile application</p>
    <p>Can also offer meta-data, search, that reduces traffic</p>
    <p>Limitation: require users to have access to and familiarity with feature or smart phone</p>
    <p>Leveraging offline, peer to peer dissemination  Limitation: applicable only for those voice applications whose users</p>
    <p>are motivated to share the content with peers, have Bluetooth enabled cell phones and knowledge to send files via Bluetooth</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>IVR systems can provide innovative information services to mobile subscribers in the developing world</p>
    <p>Complexity in setting up IVR systems, and challenges in moderating content and managing call costs limits impact</p>
    <p>IVR Junction  is a new and open-source system built on Windows platform</p>
    <p>simplifies installation and configuration</p>
    <p>enables interplay between Internet users and phone users</p>
    <p>utilizes a distributed architecture for affordable sharing of audio content across different locations</p>
    <p>There are further opportunities to manage content and call costs at scale</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks! Seeking Users!</p>
    <p>t-avash@microsoft.com thies@microsoft.com</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
