<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Amal Fahad Zhuan Chen Kai Shen Jeffrey Bigham University of Rochester, U.S.A.</p>
    <p>Assmaa Fahad Baghdad University, Iraq</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Poor network infrastructure is the common factor across developing world.</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Poor network infrastructure is the common factor across developing world.</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Poor network infrastructure is the common factor across developing world.</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation.. In Pictures</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation.. In Pictures</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation.. In Pictures</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation.. In Pictures</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation.. In Pictures</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network Acceleration Techniques</p>
    <p>Different acceleration techniques have been suggested to improve the Internet service for clients in developing regions, such as:  Web proxy caching.  Web Prefetching.  Offline browsing.  Data de-duplication.</p>
    <p>In this paper:  We evaluate the performance of some of these</p>
    <p>techniques using real web traces.  We also suggest a new technique based on our</p>
    <p>observations from this evaluation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Used Web Traces</p>
    <p>Location Internet connection</p>
    <p>Time period</p>
    <p># of web accesses</p>
    <p>Collection site</p>
    <p>Iraq Cable (W/ satellite backup)</p>
    <p>Aug.23Aug.25 2011</p>
    <p>Zambia [Johnson et al. 2010]</p>
    <p>Satellite Jan.24Feb.14 2010</p>
    <p>Cambodia [Du et al. 2005]</p>
    <p>Satellite June 1Sep. 28 2005</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Web Proxy Caching Performance</p>
    <p>Iraq Zambia Cambodia 0</p>
    <p>Web cache traces</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>po rti</p>
    <p>on o</p>
    <p>f w eb</p>
    <p>a cc</p>
    <p>es se</p>
    <p>s (A) Cache hit ratios</p>
    <p>Cache hit Cache hit w. freshness check Cache miss</p>
    <p>Iraq Zambia Cambodia 0</p>
    <p>Web cache traces</p>
    <p>A vg</p>
    <p>. r es</p>
    <p>po ns</p>
    <p>e tim</p>
    <p>e (in</p>
    <p>s ec</p>
    <p>s) (B) Request response time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dynamic Web Applications</p>
    <p>The top rank application in each of the three traces were Facebook, Gmail, and Yahoo! search engine respectively.</p>
    <p>Dynamic web accesses ratio is 59%, 62%, and 41% among the cache misses respectively.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prefetching</p>
    <p>Predicting future web accesses and prefetching them ahead of user requests.</p>
    <p>Prefetching techniques can be classified into:  Non-history based.  History based.</p>
    <p>Early work showed:  2% hit rate for a non-history based technique with 22%</p>
    <p>bandwidth overhead[Chen et al. 2011].  10% hit rate for a history based technique with 23%</p>
    <p>bandwidth overhead [Fan et al.1999].</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prefetching Evaluation</p>
    <p>Traffic location</p>
    <p>Hit rate Overhead rate</p>
    <p>Use rate</p>
    <p>Zambia 0.2% 2.5% 1.7%</p>
    <p>Cambodia 0.2% 8.7% 1.1%</p>
    <p>Using the Prediction by Partial Matching (PPM) [Fan et al. 1999] history based prefetching:</p>
    <p>Compared with 10% hit rate reported earlier, our evaluation gave poor results why?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Analysis</p>
    <p>Zambia Cambodia 0</p>
    <p>Web cache traces</p>
    <p>P re</p>
    <p>fe tc</p>
    <p>he r h</p>
    <p>it ra</p>
    <p>te</p>
    <p>Real evaluation Hypothetical: no cache Hypothetical: no cache, all prefetchable</p>
    <p>Web proxy caching effectiveness.</p>
    <p>Dynamic requests ratio is increasing.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network Acceleration Performance</p>
    <p>So far we have seen that:  Web proxy caching is an effective solution to speed up</p>
    <p>static pages accesses.  The ratio of dynamic requests is increasing in todays</p>
    <p>network traffic.  Requests from small number of applications dominate</p>
    <p>most of the network traffic (a set of 8 applications is responsible of ~40% of the dynamic requests).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Local Application Mirroring</p>
    <p>Local Application Mirroring: Caching dynamic web applications locally in order to reduce the latency at the clients side as well as the network traffic.</p>
    <p>Similar in concept to Akamai and Amazon CloudFront but closer to their users than both.</p>
    <p>Challenges.?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Management  Web based applications can be classified into:</p>
    <p>Read-only state applications, content transformation:  Perfect for application mirroring.</p>
    <p>State-full applications, collaborative work within a group.  Locality.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Management  Web based applications can be classified into:</p>
    <p>Read-only state applications, content transformation:  Perfect for application mirroring.</p>
    <p>State-full applications, collaborative work within a group.  Locality.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Management  Web based applications can be classified into:</p>
    <p>Read-only state applications, content transformation:  Perfect for application mirroring.</p>
    <p>State-full applications, collaborative work within a group.  Locality.</p>
    <p>Hierarchical updating: local hosts report their update to the higher level nodes in the hierarchy.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deployment and Security</p>
    <p>Applications have different requirements:  Runtime environment.  Required libraries.  Configuration.</p>
    <p>Diversity between local and global platforms.</p>
    <p>Security requirements:  Among locally hosted applications.  Between an application and its hosting environment.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Virtual Machine</p>
    <p>Native machine-level virtualization, which is used in cloud computing, can be leveraged to implement our technique.</p>
    <p>Migration over unreliable network, unlike the VM migration process in the cloud.</p>
    <p>Limited bandwidth:  Transferring only the difference between the</p>
    <p>applications VM image and a local stock image. Using rsync, this difference can be as small as 43MB for a VM image that is 725MB in size.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of a Collaborative Application Performance</p>
    <p>We used Feng office, an open source web-based application for collaborative software in our measurement.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation Setup</p>
    <p>Workload: Wikipedia document revision history for collaborative editing with a 9:1 read to write ratio.</p>
    <p>We use Linux Traffic Control tool (tc) to simulate the network bandwidth and latency for users in the three different sites.</p>
    <p>Traffic location Latency Bandwidth</p>
    <p>Iraq 1.48 seconds 106Kbps</p>
    <p>Zambia 6.03 seconds 196Kbps</p>
    <p>Cambodia 1.77 seconds 208Kbps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We use a low end machine as a local server, a single-core 2.66GHz Pentium 4 processor and 512MB memory, and a high end machine as a remote server, two dual-core (four cores total) 3.00 GHz Xeon CPUs and 4 GB DRAM memory.</p>
    <p>Simulate up to 64 concurrent local clients.</p>
    <p>Evaluation Setup</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation results</p>
    <p>Number of concurrent requests</p>
    <p>Av er</p>
    <p>ag e r</p>
    <p>es po</p>
    <p>ns e t</p>
    <p>im e (</p>
    <p>in se</p>
    <p>cs )</p>
    <p>Near client local proxy server Remote global site for Iraq clients Remote global site for Zambia clients Remote global site for Cambodia clients</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Web proxy is efficient for caching static pages.</p>
    <p>Web prefetching has limited benefit since its effectiveness is diminished by the web proxy and the high ratio of the dynamic web pages.</p>
    <p>Local Application Mirroring is a promising technique to accelerate the response time of dynamic web requests.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
