<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Katib A Distributed General AutoML Platform Based on Kubernetes</p>
    <p>Jinan Zhou1, Andrey Velichkevich1, Kirill Prosvirov1, Anubhav Garg1, Yuji Oshima2, Debo Dutta1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CONTENTS</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>What is Katib  Why develop</p>
    <p>Katib</p>
    <p>AutoML Workflows</p>
    <p>Hyperparameter Tuning</p>
    <p>Neural Architecture Search</p>
    <p>System Design</p>
    <p>Design Principles  System Diagram</p>
    <p>Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part I: Introduction  What is Katib  Why develop Katib</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Automated Machine Learning (AutoML) is the automation of the end to end process of applying machine learning to real-world problems. The primary challenge is designing the model for a specific task by Hyperparameter Tuning or Neural Architecture Search.</p>
    <p>What is AutoML?</p>
    <p>Katib is a general platform to run AutoML tasks in distributed systems. It is built on k8s and is part of Kubeflow, an open source machine learning toolkit for k8s.</p>
    <p>What is Katib?</p>
    <p>Kubernetes (k8s) is an open-source system for automating deployment, scaling, and management of containerized applications.</p>
    <p>What is Kubernetes?</p>
    <p>What is Katib?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Why Develop Katib? To tackle the most central problems in deploying AutoML workflows.</p>
    <p>Problems in AutoML Solutions by Katib</p>
    <p>Diversity of AutoML Algorithms</p>
    <p>General AutoML System</p>
    <p>Expensive Computing Cost</p>
    <p>Distributed Training</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part II: AutoML Workflows  Hyperparameter Tuning  Neural Architecture Search</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A utoM</p>
    <p>L W orkflow</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Hyperparameter Tuning (HPT)</p>
    <p>Find an optimal hyperparameter so that can be minimized or maximized.</p>
    <p>is usually regarded as a black box.  Commonly used algorithms:</p>
    <p>o Bayesian Optimization o Hyberband</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A utoM</p>
    <p>L W orkflow</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Neural Architecture Search (NAS)</p>
    <p>A neural network is represented by a directed acyclic graph (DAG) , where a vertex denotes the latent representation in layer and a directed edge denotes an operation</p>
    <p>whose input is and output is given to . The value of the vertex depends on all the incoming edges:</p>
    <p>is a function to combine all the inputs. It can be weighted sum, concatenation, etc., depending on the algorithm.</p>
    <p>Layer 3</p>
    <p>Layer 2</p>
    <p>Layer 1</p>
    <p>Inputs</p>
    <p>conv</p>
    <p>pooling</p>
    <p>conv</p>
    <p>conv</p>
    <p>conv</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A utoM</p>
    <p>L W orkflow</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Neural Architecture Search (NAS)</p>
    <p>Workflow for NAS with modification approaches</p>
    <p>Workflow for NAS with generation approaches</p>
    <p>Needs a Model Constructor: o In HPT, the model is already</p>
    <p>specified. In NAS, however, we need to find the model</p>
    <p>o Interpret the representations given by the suggestion</p>
    <p>Different searching strategies o Search for a network o Search for a cell</p>
    <p>Different evolving strategies o Evolve by generation o Evolve by modification</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A utoM</p>
    <p>L W orkflow</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Unified AutoML Workflow</p>
    <p>All the AutoML Workflows run in an iterative manner.</p>
    <p>Integrate all model representation interpretation functions needed by different NAS algorithms into Model Manager.</p>
    <p>HPT and NAS workflows can be naturally unified in one system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part III: System Design  System Design Principles  System Diagram</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Compatible Universally compatible with</p>
    <p>all AutoML algorithms.</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>Scalable Can be deployed at large scale.</p>
    <p>Complete support for parallel training.</p>
    <p>User friendly Powerful CLI for experts</p>
    <p>and intuitive GUI for novice.</p>
    <p>Extendible Easy to be customized for</p>
    <p>the users own propose</p>
    <p>S ystem</p>
    <p>D esign</p>
    <p>Design Principles</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>S ystem</p>
    <p>D esign</p>
    <p>System Diagram</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part IV: Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Katib D em</p>
    <p>o</p>
    <p>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WAK37UW7spo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>T H A N K Y O U F O R L I S T E N I N G Please feel free to ask any questions!</p>
    <p>Katib A Distributed General AutoML Platform Based on Kubernetes</p>
    <p>Copyright  Cisco Systems, Inc. All Rights Reserved.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
