<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOSN10 June 22 2010June 22, 2010</p>
    <p>A geometric model for on-line social networks</p>
    <p>A th B tAnthony Bonato Ryerson University</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Complex NetworksComplex Networks</p>
    <p>web graph social networks biological networks internet web graph, social networks, biological networks, internet networks,</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>On-line Social Networks (OSNs)( ) Facebook, Twitter, LinkedIn, MySpace</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Properties of OSNsProperties of OSNs  observed properties: observed properties:</p>
    <p>power law degree distribution, small world it t t community structure</p>
    <p>densification power law and shrinking distances</p>
    <p>(Kumar et al,06):</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why model complex networks?Why model complex networks?</p>
    <p>uncover and explain the generative mechanisms underlying complex networksmechanisms underlying complex networks</p>
    <p>predict the future  nice mathematical challenges  models can uncover the hidden reality ofmodels can uncover the hidden reality of</p>
    <p>networks</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Many different modelsMany different models</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 6</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Models of OSNsModels of OSNs</p>
    <p>relatively few models for on-line social networks</p>
    <p>l fi d d l hi h i l t goal: find a model which simulates many of the observed properties of OSNs  must evolve in a natural way</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All models are wrong, but some are more useful.  G.P.E. Box</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TransitivityTransitivity</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 9</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Iterated Local Transitivity (ILT) modely ( ) (Bonato, Hadi, Horn, Praat, Wang, 08)</p>
    <p>key paradigm is transitivity: friends of friends are more likely friendsmore likely friends</p>
    <p>start with a graph of order n  to form the graph Gt+1 for each node x from time g p t 1</p>
    <p>t, add a node x, the clone of x, so that xx is an edge, and x is joined to each node joined to xg j j</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>G = CG0 = C4</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Properties of ILT modelProperties of ILT model</p>
    <p>densification power law</p>
    <p>distances decrease over time</p>
    <p>community structure: bad spectral expansion (Estrada 06)(Estrada, 06)</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Degree distributionDegree distribution</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Geometry of OSNs?Geometry of OSNs?</p>
    <p>OSNs live in social space: proximity of nodes depends on p y p common attributes (such as geography, gender, age, etc.)g g p y, g , g , )</p>
    <p>IDEA: embed OSN in 2 3 IDEA: embed OSN in 2-, 3or higher dimensional space</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dimension of an OSNDimension of an OSN  dimension of OSN: minimum number of dimension of OSN: minimum number of</p>
    <p>attributes needed to classify or group users</p>
    <p>like game of 20 Questions: each question narrows range of possibilitiesq g p</p>
    <p>what is a credible mathematical formulawhat is a credible mathematical formula for the dimension of an OSN?</p>
    <p>New Science of Networks 15</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Random geometric graphsRandom geometric graphs nodes are randomly nodes are randomly placed in space</p>
    <p>each node has a constant sphere of co sta t sp e e o influence</p>
    <p>nodes are joined if their sphere of influence overlapoverlap</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 16</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation with 5000 nodesSimulation with 5000 nodes</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 17</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spatially Preferred Attachment (SPA) model (Aiello, Bonato, Cooper, Janssen, Praat, 08)</p>
    <p>ol me of sphere of volume of sphere of influence proportional to in degreeto in-degree</p>
    <p>nodes are added andnodes are added and spheres of influence shrink over time</p>
    <p>asymptotically almost surely (a.a.s.) leads to power laws graphs</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protean graphs (F t t Fl i i M 06)(Fortunato, Flammini, Menczer,06),</p>
    <p>(uczak, Praat,06), (Janssen, Praat,09)  parameter:  in (0,1)  each node is ranked 1,2, , n by some function r</p>
    <p>1 is best, n is worst</p>
    <p>t h ti t d i b d l at each time-step, one new node v is born, one randomly node chosen dies (and ranking is updated)</p>
    <p>link probability r- link probability r-</p>
    <p>many ranking schemes a.a.s. lead to power law graphs: random initial ranking, degree, age, etc.</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 19</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Geometric model for OSNsGeometric model for OSNs  we consider a geometric</p>
    <p>model of OSNs, where  nodes are in m</p>
    <p>dimensional hypercube in E lidEuclidean space</p>
    <p>volume of sphere of i fl i blinfluence variable: a function of ranking of nodesnodes</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 20</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Geometric Protean (GEO-P) Model (Bonato, Janssen, Praat, 10)</p>
    <p>parameters: ,  in (0,1), + &lt; 1; positive integer mparameters: ,  in (0,1),   1; positive integer m</p>
    <p>nodes live in m-dimensional hypercubenodes live in m dimensional hypercube  each node is ranked 1,2, , n by some function r</p>
    <p>we use random initial rankingg</p>
    <p>at each time-step, one new node v is born, one randomly node chosen dies (and ranking is updated)</p>
    <p>each existing node u has a sphere of influence with volume r-n-</p>
    <p>add edge uv if v is in the region of influence of u</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Notes on GEO P modelNotes on GEO-P model</p>
    <p>models uses both geometry and ranking  number of nodes is static: fixed at nnumber of nodes is static: fixed at n</p>
    <p>order of OSNs at most number of people (roughly )(roughly)</p>
    <p>top ranked nodes have larger regions of influence</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation with 5000 nodesSimulation with 5000 nodes</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation with 5000 nodesSimulation with 5000 nodes</p>
    <p>random geometric GEO-P</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 24</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Properties of the GEO-P modelp (Bonato, Janssen, Praat, 2010)</p>
    <p>a.a.s. the GEO-P model generates graphs with the following properties:  power law degree distribution with exponent</p>
    <p>b = 1+1/  average degree d = (1+o(1))n(1--)/21-</p>
    <p>densification  diameter D = O(n/(1-)m log2/(1-)m n)</p>
    <p>small world: constant order if m = Clog nsmall world: constant order if m = Clog n</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 25</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Degree DistributionDegree Distribution f k M h b f d f d l k for m &lt; k &lt; M, a.a.s. the number of nodes of degree at least k equals</p>
    <p>/1/)1(3/1</p>
    <p>+ + knnO</p>
    <p>m = n1 -  -  log1/2 n m should be much larger than the minimum degree</p>
    <p>m should be much larger than the minimum degree</p>
    <p>M = n1  /2 -  log-2 -1 n g  for k &gt; M, the expected number of nodes of degree k is too small</p>
    <p>to guarantee concentration</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 26</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DensityDensity  i-n- = probability that new node links to node of rank i</p>
    <p>average number of edges added at each time-step</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>nni 1 1</p>
    <p>parameter  controls density = i 1 1</p>
    <p>if  &lt; 1  , then density grows with n (as in real OSNs)</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 27</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Diameter  eminent node:</p>
    <p>old: at least n/2 nodes are youngery g  highly ranked: initial ranking greater than</p>
    <p>some fixed R titi h b i t ll h b partition hypercube into small hypercubes</p>
    <p>choose size of hypercubes and R so that  a a s each hypercube contains at leasta.a.s. each hypercube contains at least</p>
    <p>log2n eminent nodes  sphere of influence of each eminent</p>
    <p>d h h b d llnode covers each hypercube and all neighbouring hypercubes</p>
    <p>choose eminent node in each hypercube: yp backbone</p>
    <p>show a.a.s. all nodes in hypercube distance at most 2 from backboneat most 2 from backbone</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spectral propertiesSpectral properties the spectral gap  of G is defined by the difference the spectral gap  of G is defined by the difference between the two largest eigenvalues of the adjacency matrix of G</p>
    <p>for G(n,p) random graphs,  tends to 0 as order grows  in the GEO-P model,  is close to 1  bad expansion/big spectral gaps in the GEO-P model</p>
    <p>found in social networks but not in the web graph (Estrada 06)(Estrada, 06)  in social networks, there are a higher number of intra</p>
    <p>rather than inter-community linksy</p>
    <p>New Science of Networks 29</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dimension of OSNsDimension of OSNs</p>
    <p>given the order of the network n, power law exponent b, average degree d, and p , g g , diameter D, we can calculate m</p>
    <p>gives formula for dimension of OSN: gives formula for dimension of OSN:</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>m b b</p>
    <p>D m</p>
    <p>log =</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 30</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Uncovering the hidden realityUncovering the hidden reality  reverse engineering approachreverse engineering approach</p>
    <p>given network data (n, b, d, D), dimension of an OSN gives smallest number of attributes needed to identify g y users</p>
    <p>that is, given the graph structure, we can (theoretically) recover the social space</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 31</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OSN Dimension</p>
    <p>YouTube 6 Twitter 4Twitter 4 Flickr 4</p>
    <p>Cyworld 7</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 32</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research directionsResearch directions  fitting GEO P model to data fitting GEO-P model to data</p>
    <p>is theoretical estimate of log n dimension accurate?</p>
    <p>find similarity measures (see PPI literature)  community detection</p>
    <p>first map network in social space? first map network in social space?  spread of influence</p>
    <p>SIS, SIR models  Graph theory: firefighting Cops and RobbersGraph theory: firefighting, Cops and Robbers</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 33</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>preprints, reprints, contact: search: Anthony Bonato</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>journal relaunch  new editors</p>
    <p>ti accepting theoretical and empirical papersempirical papers on complex networks, OSNs, biological networks</p>
    <p>Geometric model for OSNs 35</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
