<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Generation of Conformance Generation of Conformance Test Suites for Compositions Test Suites for Compositions of Web Services Using Model of Web Services Using Model</p>
    <p>CheckingChecking Jos Garca-FanjulJos Garca-Fanjul, Claudio de la Riva and Javier Tuya, Claudio de la Riva and Javier Tuya</p>
    <p>University of Oviedo (Spain)University of Oviedo (Spain)</p>
    <p>This work is supported by the Ministry of Science and Education (Spain) under This work is supported by the Ministry of Science and Education (Spain) under the National Program for Research, Development and Innovation, projects the National Program for Research, Development and Innovation, projects</p>
    <p>IN2TEST (TIN2004-06689-C03-02) and REPRIS (TIN2005-24792-E).IN2TEST (TIN2004-06689-C03-02) and REPRIS (TIN2005-24792-E).</p>
    <p>TAIC PART. Testing: Academic &amp; Industrial Conference.TAIC PART. Testing: Academic &amp; Industrial Conference.</p>
    <p>Windsor (UK) - August, 2006Windsor (UK) - August, 2006</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TAIC PART  Windsor (UK) August, 2006</p>
    <p>Jos Garca-Fanjul (Page 2)</p>
    <p>MotivationMotivation</p>
    <p>Investment in web services software Investment in web services software is increasing [IDC, 2006]:is increasing [IDC, 2006]:  Doubling from 2003 to 2004 (reaching Doubling from 2003 to 2004 (reaching</p>
    <p>$2,3 billion).$2,3 billion).  (Expectedly) becoming $15 billion by (Expectedly) becoming $15 billion by</p>
    <p>works on testing web services works on testing web services software.software.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TAIC PART  Windsor (UK) August, 2006</p>
    <p>Jos Garca-Fanjul (Page 3)</p>
    <p>Do we need new testing methods Do we need new testing methods for web services?for web services?</p>
    <p>Testing web services software is different.Testing web services software is different.  Some unresolved challenges (from [Zhang Some unresolved challenges (from [Zhang</p>
    <p>and Zhang, 2005] and [Canfora and Di and Zhang, 2005] and [Canfora and Di Penta, 2006])Penta, 2006])  The need to remotely test web services, with The need to remotely test web services, with</p>
    <p>its associated cost.its associated cost.  Lack of observability of the service code and Lack of observability of the service code and</p>
    <p>structurestructure..  The ability to dynamically search and invoke The ability to dynamically search and invoke</p>
    <p>web services.web services.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TAIC PART  Windsor (UK) August, 2006</p>
    <p>Jos Garca-Fanjul (Page 4)</p>
    <p>The research hypothesisThe research hypothesis</p>
    <p>A new method for generating test suites A new method for generating test suites for compositions of web services is for compositions of web services is needed, with these characteristics:needed, with these characteristics:  It will be static (no need to execute the It will be static (no need to execute the</p>
    <p>software for obtaining the test cases).software for obtaining the test cases).  The selection of the test cases will be guided The selection of the test cases will be guided</p>
    <p>by adequacy criteria.by adequacy criteria.  The only required input will be a specification The only required input will be a specification</p>
    <p>of the composition (BPEL).of the composition (BPEL).  No knowledge about the partners particular No knowledge about the partners particular</p>
    <p>behaviour.behaviour.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TAIC PART  Windsor (UK) August, 2006</p>
    <p>Jos Garca-Fanjul (Page 5)</p>
    <p>Background: Model checkingBackground: Model checking</p>
    <p>A formal verification technique to automatically A formal verification technique to automatically ascertain if a property holds in a model.ascertain if a property holds in a model.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TAIC PART  Windsor (UK) August, 2006</p>
    <p>Jos Garca-Fanjul (Page 6)</p>
    <p>Using model checking for Using model checking for software testing software testing [Ammann, 1998][Ammann, 1998]</p>
    <p>To obtain a test case for a certain condition C.To obtain a test case for a certain condition C.</p>
    <p>Model of the software</p>
    <p>C NEVER holds</p>
    <p>Counterexample (fulfilling C)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TAIC PART  Windsor (UK) August, 2006</p>
    <p>Jos Garca-Fanjul (Page 7)</p>
    <p>Overview of the methodOverview of the method 1) A model will be built from the BPEL specification of the business process.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TAIC PART  Windsor (UK) August, 2006</p>
    <p>Jos Garca-Fanjul (Page 8)</p>
    <p>Preliminary workPreliminary work</p>
    <p>The method has been applied to a The method has been applied to a sample composition called loan sample composition called loan approval.approval.  Its objective is to conclude whether a Its objective is to conclude whether a</p>
    <p>certain request for a loan will be certain request for a loan will be approved or not.approved or not.</p>
    <p>The chosen criterion has been a The chosen criterion has been a transition coverage criterion.transition coverage criterion.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A representation of the loan approval sample composition.A representation of the loan approval sample composition.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test cases for the loan approval sample composition.Test cases for the loan approval sample composition.</p>
    <p>First test case: Transition #1</p>
    <p>LTL property: [] (!tran1)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TAIC PART  Windsor (UK) August, 2006</p>
    <p>Jos Garca-Fanjul (Page 11)</p>
    <p>Proce Statement customer customer customer customer Proce Statement customer customer customer customer</p>
    <p>Proce Statement bpel_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa customer Proce Statement bpel_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa customer customer customer customer customer customer customer</p>
    <p>Proce Statement BPEL_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa Proce Statement BPEL_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa bpel_loa customer customer customer customer customer customer customer customer</p>
    <p>[...][...]</p>
    <p>Extracting a test case from the counterexampleExtracting a test case from the counterexample..</p>
    <p>customer: request.amount = 3</p>
    <p>customer: BPEL_loanApprovalPort_IN!request</p>
    <p>bpel: request.amount&lt;4</p>
    <p>bpel: tran1 = true</p>
    <p>bpel: loanassessor_riskAssessmentPort_IN!request</p>
    <p>assessor: riskAssessment.risk = low</p>
    <p>assessor: loanassessor_riskAssessmentPort_OUT! riskAssessment</p>
    <p>bpel: tran3 = true</p>
    <p>bpel: approvalInfo.accept = yes</p>
    <p>bpel: tran5 = true</p>
    <p>bpel: BPEL_loanApprovalPort_OUT!approvalInfo</p>
    <p>bpel: bpel_ends = true</p>
    <p>INPUTS</p>
    <p>EXPECTED OUTPUT</p>
    <p>The reply to the customer is affirmative.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test cases for the loan approval sample composition.Test cases for the loan approval sample composition.</p>
    <p>First test case: It covers transition #1 but also #3 and #5.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test cases for the loan approval sample composition.Test cases for the loan approval sample composition.</p>
    <p>First test case: It covers transition #1 but also #3 and #5.</p>
    <p>Second test case: It covers transitions 2 and 6.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test cases for the loan approval sample composition.Test cases for the loan approval sample composition. First test case: It covers transition #1 but also #3 and #5.</p>
    <p>Second test case: It covers transitions 2 and 6. Third test case: It covers transition 4 (and also 1 and 6).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TAIC PART  Windsor (UK) August, 2006</p>
    <p>Jos Garca-Fanjul (Page 15)</p>
    <p>Expected contributionsExpected contributions</p>
    <p>Main contribution:Main contribution:  Definition of a new method to obtain conformance test Definition of a new method to obtain conformance test</p>
    <p>suites for compositions of web services. suites for compositions of web services. The method will The method will rely on a model checking tool (SPIN) for obtaining the rely on a model checking tool (SPIN) for obtaining the test cases specifications.test cases specifications.</p>
    <p>Specifically, research will address how to:Specifically, research will address how to:  Transform a BPEL specification to a PROMELA model.Transform a BPEL specification to a PROMELA model.  Instrument PROMELA code, considering the adequacy Instrument PROMELA code, considering the adequacy</p>
    <p>criteria.criteria.  Construct LTL properties for the counterexamples to Construct LTL properties for the counterexamples to</p>
    <p>show sample executions of the model that meet the show sample executions of the model that meet the criteria.criteria.</p>
    <p>Automatically obtain a test suite specification from the Automatically obtain a test suite specification from the counterexamples that SPIN provides.counterexamples that SPIN provides.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you for your attentionThank you for your attention</p>
    <p>Jos Garca-FanjulJos Garca-Fanjul</p>
    <p>jgfanjul@uniovi.esjgfanjul@uniovi.es</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
