<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cost-Aware Live Migration of Services in the Cloud</p>
    <p>David Breitgand -- IBM Haifa Research Lab</p>
    <p>Gilad Kutiel, Danny Raz -- Technion, Israel Institute of Technology</p>
    <p>The research leading to these results has received funding from the European Union's Seventh Framework Programme under grant agreement n 257448, 215605</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Agenda</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>The Cost of Live Migration</p>
    <p>Fixed Bandwidth Migration</p>
    <p>Variable Bandwidth Migration  Related Work</p>
    <p>The CALM (Cost Aware Live Migration) Algorithm</p>
    <p>Evaluation Study</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>We consider pre-copy live migration model (but results hold for post-copy approach as well)</p>
    <p>We consider in-band migration</p>
    <p>We focus on network bandwidth as primary bottleneck (but the presented framework is general)</p>
    <p>We provide analytical study of our approach</p>
    <p>We validate our proposal using trace-driven simulations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Cost of Live Migration 1/2</p>
    <p>Clearly no service is available during downtime</p>
    <p>If migration is done in-band then some of the bandwidth used to serve clients is used now for the migration</p>
    <p>We define the cost to be the probability to violate the SLA at a given time</p>
    <p>It is a function of the available bandwidth for the service and we denote it by F(Bs)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Cost of Live Migration 2/2</p>
    <p>P e</p>
    <p>rc e</p>
    <p>n te</p>
    <p>g e</p>
    <p>o f</p>
    <p>re q</p>
    <p>u e</p>
    <p>st s</p>
    <p>n o</p>
    <p>t co</p>
    <p>n fo</p>
    <p>rm in</p>
    <p>g t</p>
    <p>o t</p>
    <p>h e</p>
    <p>S LA</p>
    <p>Available bandwidth in KB / sec</p>
    <p>Quality of Service Degredation</p>
    <p>Cost per time unit</p>
    <p>Apache Nutch search engine  Workload using Poisson distribution  SLA is 1 second</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fixed Bandwidth Migration 1/5</p>
    <p>We start with a simple case</p>
    <p>The bandwidth for the migrations is predefined  and fixed through the migration process</p>
    <p>Recall that memory is updated during the migration process, how much bandwidth should we use?  More, faster but more degradation</p>
    <p>Less, better service while migrating but we might need to transfer pages again and again</p>
    <p>The optimal bandwidth depends on the cost function and other factors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fixed Bandwidth Migration 2/5</p>
    <p>T o</p>
    <p>ta l</p>
    <p>C o</p>
    <p>st o</p>
    <p>f th</p>
    <p>e M</p>
    <p>ig ra</p>
    <p>ti o</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>Bandwidth Used for the Migration</p>
    <p>Simulated Cost of a Fixed Bandwidth Migration</p>
    <p>Migrating 10,000 pages.  p = 0.001  C = 100  Cost function B =</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fixed Bandwidth Migration 3/5</p>
    <p>Formulation:  Virtual machine with M pages  Total available bandwidth (service + migration) is B  Bm is the bandwidth used for the migration  BS is the bandwidth available for the service  p is the probability for a page to be updated during a</p>
    <p>single time unit, we assume that it is uniform and independent (q = 1  p)</p>
    <p>A clean page is one that was copied and hasnt been updated since then</p>
    <p>N pages are transferred during the pre-copy phase (and the rest during the copy phase)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fixed Bandwidth Migration 4/5  The expected cost of the migration process is</p>
    <p>given by:</p>
    <p>Where:</p>
    <p>And:</p>
    <p>Optimal bandwidth can be found by</p>
    <p>minimizing the cost function (analytically / numerically).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fixed Bandwidth Migration 5/5</p>
    <p>T o</p>
    <p>ta l</p>
    <p>C o</p>
    <p>st o</p>
    <p>f th</p>
    <p>e M</p>
    <p>ig ra</p>
    <p>ti o</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>Bandwidth Used for the Migration</p>
    <p>Simulated Cost of a Fixed Bandwidth Migration</p>
    <p>Simulated Cost</p>
    <p>Calculated Cost</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trace Driven Simulation</p>
    <p>We found an optimal migration when the bandwidth is fixed and the dirtying probability is uniform</p>
    <p>What is the dirtying probability for a realworld application?</p>
    <p>We generated traces of dirtying patterns for several services and used those traces to simulate migration of a real-world services</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dirtying Probability of Real Application</p>
    <p>N u</p>
    <p>m b</p>
    <p>e r</p>
    <p>O f</p>
    <p>W ri</p>
    <p>te s</p>
    <p>D u</p>
    <p>ri n</p>
    <p>g T</p>
    <p>h e</p>
    <p>T ra</p>
    <p>ce</p>
    <p>Page Number</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dirtying Probability (top 100)</p>
    <p>N u</p>
    <p>m b</p>
    <p>e r</p>
    <p>O f</p>
    <p>W ri</p>
    <p>te s</p>
    <p>D u</p>
    <p>ri n</p>
    <p>g T</p>
    <p>h e</p>
    <p>T ra</p>
    <p>ce</p>
    <p>Page Number</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dirtying Probability (top 500)</p>
    <p>N u</p>
    <p>m b</p>
    <p>e r</p>
    <p>O f</p>
    <p>W ri</p>
    <p>te s</p>
    <p>D u</p>
    <p>ri n</p>
    <p>g T</p>
    <p>h e</p>
    <p>T ra</p>
    <p>ce</p>
    <p>Page Number</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dirtying Probability (Over Time)</p>
    <p>N u</p>
    <p>m b</p>
    <p>e r</p>
    <p>O f</p>
    <p>W ri</p>
    <p>te s</p>
    <p>p e</p>
    <p>r se</p>
    <p>co n</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>Time (seconds)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Migration's Cost With Real Dirtying Trace</p>
    <p>C o</p>
    <p>st (</p>
    <p>R e</p>
    <p>q u</p>
    <p>e st</p>
    <p>s T</p>
    <p>h a</p>
    <p>t W</p>
    <p>e re</p>
    <p>N o</p>
    <p>t S</p>
    <p>e rv</p>
    <p>e d</p>
    <p>W it</p>
    <p>h in</p>
    <p>T h</p>
    <p>e S</p>
    <p>LA L</p>
    <p>im it</p>
    <p>a ti</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>)</p>
    <p>Bandwidth Used For The Migration Process</p>
    <p>Calculated Cost</p>
    <p>Simulated Cost</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Variable Bandwidth Migration</p>
    <p>In reality we are not limited to a predefined, fixed, bandwidth.</p>
    <p>Bandwidth can be dynamically adjusted during the migration process.</p>
    <p>Intuitively, we should use a low bandwidth at the beginning of the process and increase it as we proceed, why ?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work 1/2</p>
    <p>Clark et al. suggested the following algorithm:  The first pre-copy round copies all the pages from the source host to</p>
    <p>the destination host using initial bandwidth defined by the system administrator.</p>
    <p>Each subsequent round copies only the dirty pages using a bandwidth equal to</p>
    <p>where is a fixed addition defined by the administrator.</p>
    <p>Continue until bandwidth calculation exceed a maximum limit defined by the administrator or when there are less than 256KB to transfer.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work 2/2</p>
    <p>Xens migration algorithm uses similar principles, the stop conditions are defined as follows:</p>
    <p>Less than 50 pages were dirtied during the last precopy iteration.</p>
    <p>29 pre-copy iterations have been carried out.</p>
    <p>More than 3 times the total amount of RAM allocated to the VM has been copied to the destination host.</p>
    <p>What are the problems with the above algorithms ?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The CALM (Cost Aware Live Migration) Algorithm 1/2</p>
    <p>The bandwidth for the migrations can change over time</p>
    <p>the algorithm determines</p>
    <p>the bandwidth to be used at each phase of the migration process.</p>
    <p>the end of the pre-copy phase.</p>
    <p>works in steps</p>
    <p>each step moving from i clean pages to i+1 clean pages.</p>
    <p>decides whether to continue or move to copy phase.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The CALM (Cost Aware Live Migration) Algorithm 2/2</p>
    <p>During step bandwidth is fixed so we can use previous results, the cost of the ith step is given by: where</p>
    <p>Find best Bi (with minimal cost)</p>
    <p>Move to copy phase when:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation Study 1/2</p>
    <p>We compare the CALM algorithm against the one suggested by Clark et al by simulating a live migration of a real-world services.</p>
    <p>Our simulations show that the CALM algorithm outperform Clarks algorithm even when used to migrate a real-world services.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation Study 2/2 RAM Bandwidth Algorithm Cost Total Time (sec) Down Time (sec)</p>
    <p>CALM 0.01 85.78 0.0078</p>
    <p>Fixed 0.01 19.93 0.0035</p>
    <p>CALM 0.01 79.03 0.0078</p>
    <p>Fixed 0.02 142.55 0.0069</p>
    <p>CALM 12.05 56.58 11.940</p>
    <p>Fixed 12.42 31.90 12.232</p>
    <p>CALM 4.05 56.37 0.3940</p>
    <p>Fixed 4.52 35.60 4.2325</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>We presented a novel model that accounts for the total cost of migration: pre-copy &amp; copy phases</p>
    <p>Optimal migration strategy depends on various factors (available bandwidth, memory size, type of the service etc).</p>
    <p>Cost-Aware migration algorithm is beneficial.</p>
    <p>CALM algorithm performs well also on real-world applications.</p>
    <p>The fixed algorithm performs well in certain cases.</p>
    <p>Future work is needed in order to better adjust the CALM algorithm to a real-world page dirtying pattern.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bandwidth Usage on Different Scenarios</p>
    <p>B a</p>
    <p>n d</p>
    <p>w id</p>
    <p>th U</p>
    <p>sa g</p>
    <p>e (</p>
    <p>M B</p>
    <p>/ s</p>
    <p>e c)</p>
    <p>/ M</p>
    <p>e m</p>
    <p>o ry</p>
    <p>C o</p>
    <p>p ie</p>
    <p>d (</p>
    <p>M B</p>
    <p>)</p>
    <p>Time (millisec)</p>
    <p>BW Usage (XEN 512)</p>
    <p>Clean Pages (XEN 512)</p>
    <p>BW Usage (CALM 512)</p>
    <p>Clean Pages (CALM 512)</p>
    <p>BW Usage (XEN 256)</p>
    <p>Clean Pages (XEN 256)</p>
    <p>BW Usage (CALM 256)</p>
    <p>Clean Pages (CALM 256)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fixed Bandwidth Migration 4/7</p>
    <p>We would like to calculate the expected number of clean pages (N2) after t time units when at time = 0 the number of clean pages was N1. This give us the following:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fixed Bandwidth Migration 5/7</p>
    <p>Using the formula above we can calculate the expected time (T) it takes until there are N2 clean pages, when in time = 0 there were N1 clean pages, we get:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fixed Bandwidth Migration 6/7</p>
    <p>Finally, the cost of the pre-copy phase is given by:</p>
    <p>And the total cost by:</p>
    <p>Optimal bandwidth can be found by minimizing the cost function (analytically / numerically).</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
