<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Maximizing the Contact Opportunity for Vehicular Internet Access</p>
    <p>Authors: Zizhan Zheng, Zhixue Lu, Prasun Sinha,</p>
    <p>and Santosh Kumar</p>
    <p>The Ohio State University,  University of Memphis</p>
    <p>INFOCOM 2010, San Diego, CA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation  Three Metrics</p>
    <p>Contact Opportunity in Distance  Contact Opportunity in Time  Average Throughput</p>
    <p>Evaluations  Summary and Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation: Internet Access for Mobile Vehicles</p>
    <p>Applications  Infotainment  Cargo tracking  Burglar tracking  Road surface monitoring</p>
    <p>Current Approaches  Full Coverage  Opportunistic Service  Sparse Coverage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Approach I (of III): Full Coverage</p>
    <p>Wireless Wide-Area Networking  3G Cellular Network  3GPP LTE (Long Term Evolution)  WiMAX</p>
    <p>Either long range coverage (30 miles) or high data rates (75 Mbps per 20 MHz channel)</p>
    <p>3 Mbps downlink bandwidth reported in one of the first deployments in US (Baltimore, MD)</p>
    <p>Google WiFi for Mountain View  12 square miles, 500+ APs, 95% coverage  1 Mbps upload and download rate  Not very practical for large scale deployment</p>
    <p>due to the prohibitive cost of deployment and management</p>
    <p>Google Wifi Coverage Map http://wifi.google.com/city/mv/apmap.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Approach II (of III): Opportunistic Service via In-Situ APs</p>
    <p>Prototype  Drive-Thru Internet (Infocom04,05)</p>
    <p>In-Situ Evaluation  DieselNet (Sigcomm08, Mobicom08)</p>
    <p>Interactive WiFi connectivity (Sigcomm08)  Cost-performance trade-offs of three infrastructure enhancement alternatives</p>
    <p>(Mobicom08)</p>
    <p>MobiSteer (Mobisys07)  Handoff optimization for a single mobile user in the context of directional</p>
    <p>antenna and beam steering</p>
    <p>Cabernet (Mobicom08)  Fast connection setup (QuickWiFi) and end-to-end throughput improvement</p>
    <p>(CTP)</p>
    <p>Problems  Opportunistic service, no guarantee  Unpredictable interconnection gap</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>AP</p>
    <p>AP</p>
    <p>AP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Approach III (of III): Sparse Coverage with Performance Guarantees6  Basic Idea</p>
    <p>Planned deployment  Sparse coverage with performance guarantees</p>
    <p>Alpha Coverage (Infocom 09 mini)  Placing an upper bound on the maximum</p>
    <p>diameter of coverage holes in a road network  Pure geometric  Does not correspond to the quality of data</p>
    <p>service directly</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contact Opportunity: A More Expressive Sparse Coverage Mode</p>
    <p>Contact Opportunity  fractional distance/time within range of APs  Closer to user experience  Can be translated to average throughput if all</p>
    <p>uncertainties resolved  Our Approach</p>
    <p>Worst Case perspective  Start with distance measure that involves least</p>
    <p>uncertainties  Extend to time measure by modeling road traffic  Further extend to average throughput by also</p>
    <p>modeling data rates, user density, and association</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions 8</p>
    <p>Propose Contact Opportunity, an expressive sparse coverage mode.</p>
    <p>Propose efficient solutions with provable performance bounds to maximize the worst-case Contact Opportunity with various uncertainties considered.</p>
    <p>Develop the foundations towards providing scalable data service to disconnection-tolerant mobile users with guaranteed performance.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline 9</p>
    <p>Motivation  Three Metrics</p>
    <p>Contact Opportunity in Distance  Contact Opportunity in Time  Average Throughput</p>
    <p>Evaluations  Summary and Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Models and Assumptions 10</p>
    <p>Road Network  An undirected graph G  Assumption 1: A set of candidate deployment</p>
    <p>locations is given, denoted as A.  Mobile Trace</p>
    <p>A set of paths on G  Assumption 2: A set of frequently traveled paths</p>
    <p>is known, denoted as P.  AP Coverage</p>
    <p>Geometric model is used  Assumption 3: The covered region for each</p>
    <p>candidate location is known (but not necessary a disk).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contact Opportunity in Distance</p>
    <p>For a subset S  A, a path p 2 P, the Contact Opportunity in Distance of p:</p>
    <p>- the cost of S</p>
    <p>m</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Properties of Set Function d</p>
    <p>The set function d(, p): 2A ! [0,1] is  Normalized: d(;, p) = 0  Nondecreasing: d(S, p)  d(T, p) if S  T  Submodular: adding a new AP to a small</p>
    <p>set helps more than adding it to a large set</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Submodular Set Function 13</p>
    <p>A set function F : 2A ! R is submodular if for all S  T  A and a 2 AnT, F(S [ {a})  F(S)  F(T [ {a})  F(T)  Discrete counterpart of convexity  Example: F(S) = d(S, p)S</p>
    <p>T</p>
    <p>a</p>
    <p>a</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Approximation Algorithm (for a relaxed version)</p>
    <p>Hard to approximate directly  An instance of budgeted submodular set covering problem  No polynomial time approximation unless P = NP</p>
    <p>Relaxing the budget B - a binary search based algorithm  For a given  2 [0,1], solve the subproblem - find a</p>
    <p>deployment S of minimum cost that provides worst-case Contact Opportunity of ;  An instance of submodular set covering problem  A greedy algorithm has a logarithmic factor (L.A. Wolsey</p>
    <p>OPT(B) achieved if B is allowed (Andreas Krause 2008)  OPT(B) - max-min Contact Opportunity of an optimal solution   - a logarithmic function of problem parameters</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contact Opportunity in Time 15</p>
    <p>For a subset S  A, a path p 2 P, the Contact Opportunity in Time of p:</p>
    <p>Challenge - uncertain contact time and travel time  Traffic jams, accidents, stop signs, etc.</p>
    <p>Solution  Worst-Case perspective  Interval based modeling - for each road segment, an</p>
    <p>interval of possible travel times is known.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contact Opportunity in Time (Cont.)</p>
    <p>A traffic scenario k - an assignment of travel time (any value from the interval) to each road segment</p>
    <p>kS - the worst traffic scenario</p>
    <p>Unfortunately, t(S, p, kS) 8S  A is not submodular  Approximation by the mean scenario</p>
    <p>mean scenario assigns the average travel time to each road segment</p>
    <p>- an upper bound on the ratios of maximum and minimum travel times for all road segments</p>
    <p>Factor  achieved by using mean scenario</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From Contact Opportunity to Average Throughput</p>
    <p>More Assumptions  Each candidate location a 2 A is associated</p>
    <p>with a worst case data rate ra  The maximum number of users moving on</p>
    <p>each road segment is known  The maximum number of users in the range of</p>
    <p>an AP at a 2 A can be computed, denoted as va  A user always selects the AP with the</p>
    <p>highest normalized rate (ra/va) in range to associate</p>
    <p>Handoff time is small enough to be ignored</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From Contact Opportunity to Average Throughput (Cont.)</p>
    <p>For a subset S  A, a path p 2 P, the Average Throughput when moving through p can be estimated as:</p>
    <p>Solution similar to Contact Opportunity in Time  Limitations</p>
    <p>Simplified association protocol  Fairness has been ignored</p>
    <p>ra = 1 Mbps</p>
    <p>m</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline 19</p>
    <p>Motivation  Three Metrics</p>
    <p>Contact Opportunity in Distance  Contact Opportunity in Time  Average Throughput</p>
    <p>Evaluations  Summary and Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulations 20</p>
    <p>Baseline Algorithms  Uniform random sampling  Max-min distance sampling</p>
    <p>Road network  A 6x6km2 region, 1802 intersections,  Obtained from 2008 Tiger/Line Shapefiles  Each edge is associated with an interval of travel</p>
    <p>speed [-5, ] (m/s),  2 [10,20]  Movements: all pair shortest paths</p>
    <p>based coverage model with radius in [100,200](m)</p>
    <p>To evaluate average throughput  Ns-2 based simulation  Restricted random waypoint  1Mbps for each AP  CBR traffic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation Results 21</p>
    <p>A small controlled experiment in a parking lot at OSU (result in paper)</p>
    <p>Min Contact Opp in Time Avg Contact Opp in Time Avg Throughput (2x2km 2,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline 22</p>
    <p>Motivation  Three Metrics</p>
    <p>Contact Opportunity in Distance  Contact Opportunity in Time  Average Throughput</p>
    <p>Evaluations  Summary and Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary and Future Work 23</p>
    <p>We have proposed Contact Opportunity, an expressive sparse coverage mode for providing data service to mobile users, and efficient solutions that maximize the worstcase Contact Opportunity with various uncertainties considered.</p>
    <p>Future Work - Expected Contact Opportunity or Throughput  Offline - stochastic modeling of</p>
    <p>uncertainties on mobility and data flows  Online scheduling to improve fairness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contact Opportunity in Time (Cont.)</p>
    <p>A traffic scenario k - an assignment of travel time (any value from the interval) to each road segment</p>
    <p>KS - the worst traffic scenario that minimizes t (S, p) for each p, which assigns the minimum travel time to every segment covered by S and maximum travel time to every segment not covered</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contact Opportunity in Time (Cont.)</p>
    <p>Unfortunately, t(S, p, kS) 8S  A is normalized, nondecreasing, but not submodular</p>
    <p>Approximation by a single scenario independent of S  mean scenario assigns the average travel time</p>
    <p>to each road segment, denoted as k0  S0 - optimal deployment with respect to k0  S* - optimal deployment with respect to kS  If the ratio between the maximum and the</p>
    <p>minimum travel time is bounded by  for all road segments, then t(S*, p, kS*)   t(S0, p, kS0).</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
