<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Detecting Research Topics via the Correlation between</p>
    <p>Graphs and Texts</p>
    <p>Yookyung Jo Dept. of Computer Science, Cornell University</p>
    <p>Carl Lagoze, and C. Lee Giles  Dept. of Computer Science, Cornell University,  Information Sciences an d Technology, The Pennsylvania State University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgment</p>
    <p>John E. Hopcroft  Thorsten Joachims  Simeon Warner  Isaac G. Councill</p>
    <p>NSF IIS-0430906, 0227648, 0227888, and 042 4671</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Topic detection</p>
    <p>Problem Statement :</p>
    <p>Our strategy :  The correlation between</p>
    <p>Distribution of terms representing a topic</p>
    <p>Distribution of citation links</p>
    <p>How to detect topics in a linked corpus (e.g. Ci teseer, arXiv, the Web )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Correlation between Terms and Links</p>
    <p>Term citation graph for  Term citation graph for</p>
    <p>Term  : representing a topic (e.g. sensor network, or association rule )</p>
    <p>Term  : not representing a topic (e.g. six months, or practical examples )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Term citation graph for a term</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Correlation between Terms and Links</p>
    <p>Term citation graph for  Term citation graph for</p>
    <p>Term  : representing a topic (e.g. sensor network, or association rule )</p>
    <p>Term  : not representing a topic (e.g. six months, or practical examples )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Detecting a topic via a single term</p>
    <p>H1 : A represents a topic  H0 : A does not represent a topic  GA : The term citation graph for A  O(GA) : Link connectivity observation on GA</p>
    <p>)0|)(Pr(</p>
    <p>)1|)(Pr( ln)(TopicScore</p>
    <p>HGO</p>
    <p>HGO A</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>Finally, a ranked list of terms</p>
    <p>Given a term A,  Binary decision of whether A represents a topic or not</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Loglikelihood of H1</p>
    <p>Observation O(GA) :  For each node i in GA, is it connected to other nodes in GA</p>
    <p>by at least one link?</p>
    <p>Under H1  pc1 : estimation of pc  pc1 set to a value close to 1 (e.g. pc1 = 0.9)</p>
    <p>)1ln()()ln(</p>
    <p>i AiA</p>
    <p>pnnpn</p>
    <p>HGOHGO</p>
    <p>This probability = pc</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Loglikelihood of H0</p>
    <p>A within falls</p>
    <p>in node a oflink a</p>
    <p>y that probabilit the: 1</p>
    <p>G</p>
    <p>G N</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>GA</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>pc0 : estimation of pc</p>
    <p>il A</p>
    <p>c N</p>
    <p>n p</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>arXiv  A Physics literature collection  Year 1991-2006, 7 major arXiv areas  214,546 papers, 2,165,170 citation links  Abstract as document  137,098 bi-gram terms after low-frequency prune</p>
    <p>Citeseer  A Computer Science related collection  Year 1994-2004  716,771 papers, 1,740,326 citation links  Abstract + title as document  631,839 bi-gram terms after low-frequency prune</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>arXiv (physics) : topic terms at top ranks top rank Topic (term) &lt;n, nc, |E|&gt;</p>
    <p>Black hole Quantum hall Black holes Higgs boson Renormalization group Quantum gravity Standard model Heavy quark Cosmological constant Quantum dot Chiral perturbation Form factors Lattice qcd String theory Hubbard model</p>
    <p>&lt;4978, 4701, 38952&gt; &lt;1863, 1493, 4862&gt; &lt;3131, 2896, 22824&gt; &lt;2079, 1896, 12607&gt; &lt;3738, 2920, 8490&gt; &lt;2014, 1724, 9693&gt; &lt;7848, 7145, 53829&gt; &lt;1671, 1473, 6570&gt; &lt;2141, 1815, 7134&gt; &lt;1366, 1031, 2926&gt; &lt;1132, 1050, 5578&gt; &lt;1578, 1354, 5616&gt; &lt;1425, 1265, 5240&gt; &lt;3818, 3539, 26250&gt; &lt;1702, 1167, 2678&gt;</p>
    <p>n : number of n odes in GA</p>
    <p>nc : number of n odes with at least one con nection withi n GA</p>
    <p>|E| : number of edges in GA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>arXiv(Physics): Term citation graphs f or intermediate rank topic terms</p>
    <p>Research communities</p>
    <p>time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>arXiv(Physics): terms at bottommost ranks</p>
    <p>)0|)(Pr(</p>
    <p>)1|)(Pr( ln</p>
    <p>)(TopicScore</p>
    <p>HGO</p>
    <p>HGO</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>Bottom entries are stop-phrases</p>
    <p>rank term</p>
    <p>we show has been we find we present we study we have we also have been we discuss we consider does not our results we investigate into account we propose</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>rank topic (term) up to 1999 topic (term) since 2000</p>
    <p>logic programs model checking semidefinite programming inductive logic petri nets genetic programming interior point kolmogorov complexity automatic differentiation complementarity problems congestion control complementarity problem conservation laws linear logic timed automata situation calculus real-time database motion planning duration calculus volume rendering chain monte association rules</p>
    <p>sensor networks hoc networks logic programs image retrieval support vector congestion control model checking decision diagrams wireless sensor ad hoc intrusion detection vector machines mobile ad binary decision sensor network energy consumption content-based image semantic web fading channels xml data source separation timed automata</p>
    <p>Citeseer(CS): top rank ter ms</p>
    <p>Top rank terms from two different time periods</p>
    <p>Time up to 1999</p>
    <p>Time since 2000</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Citeseer: Topic time evolution ``sensor networks</p>
    <p>``support vector ``congestion control</p>
    <p>``logic programs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Citeseer: Topic time evolution ``petri nets ``association rules</p>
    <p>``genetic programming ``semantic web</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithm Extension</p>
    <p>To detect topics represented by a single term  Algorithm</p>
    <p>Evaluation on arXiv, Citeseer</p>
    <p>To detect topics defined by a set of terms  Algorithm</p>
    <p>Evaluation on arXiv</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion (poster session : #7)</p>
    <p>Topic detection via the correlation between terms a nd links</p>
    <p>Our algorithm (in its evaluation on arXiv, Citeseer)</p>
    <p>Effectively discovers topics represented by a single-term or by a set of terms</p>
    <p>Identifies stop-phrases as a by-product</p>
    <p>Discovers topics in their natural scale</p>
    <p>Demonstrates its utility in trend analysis</p>
    <p>Shows the association between topic scale and specificity</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
