<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Personal Social Screen</p>
    <p>A Dynamic Privacy Assignment System</p>
    <p>for Social Sharing in</p>
    <p>Complex Social Object Networks</p>
    <p>Florida International University</p>
    <p>&amp; Xerox Corporation</p>
    <p>Lei Li, Tong Sun and Tao Li</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Privacy within social networking sites is often not expected</p>
    <p>or is undefined, which might render potential privacy risks.</p>
    <p>Sometimes people would like to share interesting posts</p>
    <p>with a specific group of his/her friends who have similar</p>
    <p>hobbies or interest.</p>
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>How to find people with similar hobbies?</p>
    <p>How trust to people that you are going to share with?</p>
    <p>Motivation and Challenges</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy issues are unconcerned by online users.  Gross and Acquisti, Information revelation and privacy in</p>
    <p>online social networks, 2005.</p>
    <p>Dwyer et al., Trust and privacy concern within social networking sites: A comparison of facebook and myspace, 2007.</p>
    <p>Google+ uses the concept of social circle to allow people explicitly manage their friend lists into friend circles.</p>
    <p>Pros: People have choice on which circles he/she would like to</p>
    <p>share.</p>
    <p>Cons: Circles are static, i.e., managing the contact list.</p>
    <p>Fail to address the issues of selective sharing in users extended social network.</p>
    <p>Related Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Framework Overview</p>
    <p>Conversations</p>
    <p>Tagging</p>
    <p>Activities</p>
    <p>Topic-Sensitive Trust Modeling</p>
    <p>And Hierarchical Clustering</p>
    <p>Community Detection Personalized Hierarchy Generation</p>
    <p>Submodularity Modeling for Community</p>
    <p>Hierarchy Personalization</p>
    <p>Object</p>
    <p>Community</p>
    <p>Navigation</p>
    <p>Privacy</p>
    <p>Assignment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Atomic Community Generation:  Choose online users friendships as the base.</p>
    <p>Calculate their trustiness as</p>
    <p>Dynamically select a subset of friends based on tij.  Hierarchical clustering on atomic communities:</p>
    <p>Decide the best layer using Dunns Index:</p>
    <p>Community Hierarchy Generation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Personalized Hierarchy Generation</p>
    <p>Submodular Function: Let E be a finite set and f be a real valued</p>
    <p>non-decreasing function defined on the subsets of E that satisfies</p>
    <p>)(}){()(}){( SfSfTfTf</p>
    <p>where S  T , S and T are two subsets of E, and   E \ T .</p>
    <p>Budgeted Maximum Coverage: Given E, where each element is</p>
    <p>associated with an influence and a cost defined over a domain of these</p>
    <p>elements and a budget B, the goal is to find out a subset of E which has</p>
    <p>the largest possible influence while the total cost does not exceed B.</p>
    <p>NP-Hard!!! (11/e)-approximation.</p>
    <p>(Khuller et al., 1999)</p>
    <p>Greedy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Personalized Hierarchy Generation</p>
    <p>Landscape</p>
    <p>Canon D50</p>
    <p>Hometown</p>
    <p>A picture might belong to different</p>
    <p>categories. How to make the recommended</p>
    <p>community list more relevant to the picture?</p>
    <p>A users privacy requirement might be</p>
    <p>regressive over time. How to capture</p>
    <p>such privacy regression?</p>
    <p>Submodularity!!!</p>
    <p>),(</p>
    <p>),( ||</p>
    <p>SoSim</p>
    <p>cuTrust S</p>
    <p>Sf Sc</p>
    <p>Trust!</p>
    <p>Relevance!</p>
    <p>Why Submodularity?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Evaluation</p>
    <p>Gather users, photo, comments, tags, groups etc. from Flickr by</p>
    <p>specifying a group of seed users.</p>
    <p>Preprocessing</p>
    <p>Remove comments that are not English.</p>
    <p>Remove users without frequent activities, e.g., posting photos,</p>
    <p>commenting or tagging.</p>
    <p>Remove user groups whose group members are less than 5.</p>
    <p>Statistics</p>
    <p>Real-world Data Set</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation Metrics</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluation (Cont.)</p>
    <p>j</p>
    <p>j</p>
    <p>ji</p>
    <p>i i</p>
    <p>ji ji</p>
    <p>ij</p>
    <p>ij</p>
    <p>N</p>
    <p>N N</p>
    <p>N</p>
    <p>N N</p>
    <p>NN</p>
    <p>NN N</p>
    <p>NMI</p>
    <p>loglog</p>
    <p>log2 ,</p>
    <p>Normalized mutual information (NMI):</p>
    <p>N  the confusion matrix of the result and the ground truth;</p>
    <p>Nij  the number of nodes in both cluster Xi and Yj;</p>
    <p>Ni is the sum over row i of N and Nj is the sum over column j of N.</p>
    <p>Jaccard Index (JI):</p>
    <p>nnn</p>
    <p>n CCJI</p>
    <p>n11 is the number of sample pairs in the same cluster for both C1 and C2;</p>
    <p>n10 and n01 are the number of sample pairs belonging to the same</p>
    <p>cluster in one solution, but not in the other.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Evaluation (Cont.)</p>
    <p>We compare the NMI and JI of different community detection approaches to demonstrate the efficacy of our proposed method:</p>
    <p>The modularity-based methods perform poorly when small communities are dominant in the dataset  resolution limit;</p>
    <p>The methods that aim to detect overlapping communities perform better than the hard partition-based ones on our Flickr dataset;</p>
    <p>PerCial is capable to deal with communities with different cardinalities since we not only consider the social graph structure, but also take the topic-sensitive information and activities into account.</p>
    <p>Community Detection Evaluation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Evaluation (Cont.)</p>
    <p>Hire volunteers to experience PerCial</p>
    <p>Define different experience indices  The response time of recommending communities for privacy assignment;</p>
    <p>The relatedness of the recommended communities to their interest;</p>
    <p>The diversity of the recommended community list.</p>
    <p>Community Selection Evaluation (User Study)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Formalize the topic-sensitive trust relations among users by analyzing available resources in multi-modal social networks.</p>
    <p>Propose to loosely separate the entire social network and organize it as a two-level community hierarchy.</p>
    <p>Propose to recommend communities to users for privacy preference assignment by modeling the community selection problem as a budgeted maximum coverage problem.</p>
    <p>Concluding Remarks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>Domanda?</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>Pregunta?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
