<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alpha Coverage: Bounding the Interconnection Gap for</p>
    <p>Vehicular Internet Access</p>
    <p>Presented by: Prasun Sinha Authors: Zizhan Zheng, Prasun Sinha and Santosh Kumar*</p>
    <p>The Ohio State University, * University of Memphis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Internet Access for Mobile Vehicles</p>
    <p>Applications  Infotainment  Cargo tracking  Burglar tracking  Road surface monitoring</p>
    <p>Current Approaches Full Coverage</p>
    <p>Wireless Wide-Area Networking (WWAN)  Fully Covered WiFi Mesh</p>
    <p>Opportunistic Service  Roadside WiFi</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Approach I (of II): Full Coverage Wireless Wide-Area Networking</p>
    <p>3G Cellular Network  3GPP LTE (Long Term Evolution)  WiMAX</p>
    <p>Either long range coverage (30 miles) or high data rates (75 Mbps per 20 MHz channel)</p>
    <p>3 Mbps downlink bandwidth reported in one of the first deployments in US</p>
    <p>Google WiFi for Mountain View  12 square miles, 400+ APs  1 Mbps upload and download rate  Not very practical for large scale</p>
    <p>deployment due to the prohibitive cost of deployment and management</p>
    <p>Google Wifi Coverage Map http://wifi.google.com/city/mv/apmap.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Approach II (of II): Opportunistic Service via In-Situ APs Prototype</p>
    <p>Drive-Thru Internet (Infocom04,05)</p>
    <p>In-Situ Evaluation  DieselNet (Sigcomm08, Mobicom08)</p>
    <p>Interactive WiFi connectivity (Sigcomm08)  Cost-performance trade-offs of three infrastructure enhancement alternatives</p>
    <p>(Mobicom08)</p>
    <p>MobiSteer (Mobisys07)  Handoff optimization for a single mobile user in the context of directional</p>
    <p>antenna and beam steering</p>
    <p>Cabernet (Mobicom08)  Fast connection setup (QuickWiFi) and end-to-end throughput improvement</p>
    <p>(CTP)</p>
    <p>Problems  Opportunistic service, no guarantee  Unpredictable interconnection gap</p>
    <p>Our solution: an intermittent coverage model that provides predictable data service to mobile users at low cost</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>AP</p>
    <p>AP</p>
    <p>AP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Alpha Coverage  An Intermittent Coverage</p>
    <p>Model A general definition  intuitive but intractable Two simplifications</p>
    <p>Alpha Network Coverage (N -Coverage)  Applies when route information is unknown</p>
    <p>Ex: Burglar tracking  Allows a factor log (n) approximation</p>
    <p>Alpha Path Coverage (P -Coverage)  Applies when route information is given</p>
    <p>Ex: bus trace in DieselNet, cached model in Mobisteer  Allows a more efficient factor log (n) approximation</p>
    <p>Evaluation Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Road Network Model and Problem Statement  Model</p>
    <p>Model a road network R as an undirected graph GR with edge length at most  (by inserting artificial intersections if needed).</p>
    <p>Model a movement as a path on GR (not necessarily ending at intersections).</p>
    <p>Model access points as points on GR (modeling the worst case of communication range).</p>
    <p>Given GR and A0  V [GR] that models a set of APs previously deployed  Determine if the deployment provides the desired</p>
    <p>coverage (to be defined), and if not</p>
    <p>Find a minimum set of points A in GR so that when new APs are deployed at these locations, A0 [ A provides the desired coverage.</p>
    <p>v5</p>
    <p>v1 v2 v3</p>
    <p>v4</p>
    <p>v6 v7 v8</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>t</p>
    <p>v9 v4 v5</p>
    <p>v1 v2 v3</p>
    <p>v6 v7 v8</p>
    <p>v9</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alpha Coverage: an Intermittent Coverage Model</p>
    <p>A deployment provides -Coverage to a road network R if any path of length  on GR touches at least one point representing an access-point.</p>
    <p>Features  Provides a guarantee on the worst case inter</p>
    <p>contact gap  Provides an estimation of the cumulative data</p>
    <p>service Challenges</p>
    <p>Even verifying -Coverage is NP-complete since there is a reduction from HAMILTONIAN PATH to it</p>
    <p>Simplified models are needed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alpha Coverage w/o Route Information A deployment provides Network Coverage of</p>
    <p>distance  ( N -Coverage for short) if any path f(a,b) with dist(a,b) (graph distance) at least  is covered by at least one AP   Coverage implies  N Coverage, but not</p>
    <p>vice versa</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>t</p>
    <p>v9 v4 v5</p>
    <p>v1 v2 v3</p>
    <p>v6 v7 v8</p>
    <p>= 5</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>t</p>
    <p>v9 v4 v5</p>
    <p>v1 v2 v3</p>
    <p>v6 v7 v8 -Coverage N -Coverage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alpha Coverage w/o Route Information (Cont.)</p>
    <p>Polynomial time verifiable The optimization problem (</p>
    <p>N -Cover) is NP-hard  Reduction from VERTEX COVER</p>
    <p>restricted to triangle-free, 3connected, cubic planar graphs</p>
    <p>O(log |V|) approximation  Assumption: New APs are deployed only</p>
    <p>at the vertices of GR (real or artificial road intersections)  Introducing a factor of 2</p>
    <p>Reduce  N -Cover to node version low diameter graph decomposition  GVY algorithm</p>
    <p>High computation time complexity for large networks</p>
    <p>v1 v2 v3</p>
    <p>v4 v5</p>
    <p>v6 v7 v8</p>
    <p>v9</p>
    <p>v1 v3</p>
    <p>v4</p>
    <p>v6 v8</p>
    <p>= 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alpha Coverage with Route Information Motivation: use route information to design a more efficient</p>
    <p>algorithm</p>
    <p>Assumption: a set of paths F is given where |F| = O(p(|V|))  Ex 1) a set of shortest paths obtained from a road network database  Ex 2) a set of most frequently traveled paths learned from historical traffic data  Decompose each given path into -paths</p>
    <p>A deployment provides Path Coverage of distance  ( P -Coverage for short) if any -path in F is covered by at least one AP.</p>
    <p>Polynomial time verifiable, the optimization problem is still NP-hard</p>
    <p>O(log |V|) approximation: reduce P -Cover to Minimum Set Cover</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation Setting Road network</p>
    <p>A 4km x 4km region around the center of Franklin County, OH</p>
    <p>About 1000 intersections, 1300 road segments  Obtained from 2007 Tiger/Line Shapefiles + Mercator</p>
    <p>projection</p>
    <p>Moving scenarios  Restricted random way point: each movement</p>
    <p>follows a shortest path and has length at least   5 mobile nodes, moving 1 hour each, 10 scenarios  Various speed limits</p>
    <p>Ns-2 simulation  The transmission range of each AP is 100m</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deployment methods  P Coverage  Rand-1: a set of randomly</p>
    <p>selected vertices of GR  Rand-2: a set of points on</p>
    <p>randomly selected edges of GR</p>
    <p>Rand-3: the region is divided into 50m x 50m cells; APs are deployed at the centers of a set of randomly selected cells.</p>
    <p>An instance of P -Cover,  = 3000 m</p>
    <p>Simulation Setting (Cont.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation Results</p>
    <p>21 APs are used The maximum gap for P -Coverage is about 214 sec,</p>
    <p>bounded by the time spent on two adjacent moves The maximum gap for a random deployment can be larger</p>
    <p>than 2000 sec</p>
    <p>Inter-contact gap (sec)</p>
    <p>= 3000m</p>
    <p>(m)</p>
    <p>C D</p>
    <p>F</p>
    <p>S ta</p>
    <p>n d</p>
    <p>a rd</p>
    <p>d e v ia</p>
    <p>ti o n</p>
    <p>(s</p>
    <p>e c )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work Improve the efficiency of  N-Coverage</p>
    <p>Combinatorial algorithms for fractional vertex multicut</p>
    <p>Connected -Coverage  Connect each AP to at least one of the gateways with</p>
    <p>Internet backhaul  Joint Coverage and connectivity optimization  A bound on the number of hops to gateways</p>
    <p>(,)-Coverage: Enabling Assured Data Service  Guarantees that each user moving through a path of length</p>
    <p>has access to at least  units of data.  Challenges: variable data rates, traffic density, and contact</p>
    <p>durations; unknown association schedules</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alpha Coverage w/o Route Information (Cont.)</p>
    <p>Polynomial time verifiable</p>
    <p>The optimization problem, called N-Cover, is NP-hard  There is a reduction from VERTEX COVER restricted to triangle</p>
    <p>free, 3-connected, cubic planar graphs</p>
    <p>O(log |V|) approximation: reduce N-Cover to Minimum Vertex Multicut  Assumption: New APs are deployed only at the vertices of GR</p>
    <p>(real or artificial road intersections) =&gt; introducing a factor 2  Step1: Find the set of -pairs, treat their midpoints as terminals  Step2: Solving the fractional vertex multicut problem -- the dual</p>
    <p>of node version maximum multicommodity flow problem  Step 3: Rounding the solution by low diameter graph</p>
    <p>decomposition (GVY).</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
