<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis of Incomplete Data Analysis of Incomplete Data and anand an</p>
    <p>IntrinsicIntrinsic--Dimension Dimension HellyHelly TheoremTheorem</p>
    <p>JieJie GaoGao</p>
    <p>Stony Brook UniversityStony Brook University</p>
    <p>Joint work with Michael Joint work with Michael LangbergLangberg and Leonard Schulman @ Caltechand Leonard Schulman @ Caltech</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ClusteringClustering</p>
    <p>General framework::</p>
    <p>InputInput: data elements: data elements</p>
    <p>Points in high dimension.</p>
    <p>ObjectiveObjective: extract pattern: extract pattern</p>
    <p>k-median centers (min:  dist).</p>
    <p>k-means centers (min:  dist2).</p>
    <p>k-center (min: maximum dist).</p>
    <p>Extensively studied:</p>
    <p>Roughly speaking: NP-hard.</p>
    <p>Exact and approximate algorithms studied.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>This work: incomplete dataThis work: incomplete data</p>
    <p>Typically:Typically:</p>
    <p>Data elements are points.</p>
    <p>Represent complete data.  Answers to questionnaire.</p>
    <p>Sensor readings.</p>
    <p>This talk This talk -- incompleteincomplete data:data:</p>
    <p>Incomplete data:  Blank question in questionnaire.</p>
    <p>Missing reading from sensor. Missing reading from sensor.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model: incomplete dataModel: incomplete data</p>
    <p>IncompleteIncomplete data:data:  Blank question in questionnaire.</p>
    <p>Missing reading from sensor.</p>
    <p>Model data elements as Model data elements as lineslines (or (or</p>
    <p>flats of higher dimension).flats of higher dimension).  Missing answer: axis parallel line.</p>
    <p>We consider general lines: correspond to correlations.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>kk--center on incomplete datacenter on incomplete data</p>
    <p>InputInput::</p>
    <p>n lines in Rd.</p>
    <p>Parameter k.</p>
    <p>OutputOutput::</p>
    <p>k centers that minimize maximum dist. to lines.</p>
    <p>k minimum radius balls that cover all lines.</p>
    <p>At least as hard as kAt least as hard as k--center center</p>
    <p>for points, for general k.for points, for general k.</p>
    <p>r</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Complete vs. Incomplete dataComplete vs. Incomplete data</p>
    <p>Complete data (points in Complete data (points in RRdd):):</p>
    <p>distances between points imply a metric.</p>
    <p>Locality is crucial to success of clustering algorithms.</p>
    <p>Incomplete data (lines):Incomplete data (lines):</p>
    <p>Distances between lines are not a metric.</p>
    <p>Can one still argue locally?Can one still argue locally?</p>
    <p>aa close to close to b, bb, b close to close to c c</p>
    <p>aa close to close to cc</p>
    <p>a</p>
    <p>b</p>
    <p>c</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HellyHelly TheoremTheorem</p>
    <p>Suppose the lines can be covered by a radius Suppose the lines can be covered by a radius rr ballball. We . We</p>
    <p>blow up each line to a cylinder with radius blow up each line to a cylinder with radius rr. .</p>
    <p>All the cylinders have a common intersection All the cylinders have a common intersection iffiff every every</p>
    <p>d+1d+1 cylinders have a common intersection.cylinders have a common intersection.</p>
    <p>HellyHelly: In : In RRdd, given , given nn lines, if every set of lines, if every set of d+1d+1 lines can lines can</p>
    <p>be covered by a ball of radius be covered by a ball of radius rr then all lines can be then all lines can be</p>
    <p>covered by a ball of radius covered by a ball of radius r.r.</p>
    <p>Helly: In Rd, if every set of d+1 convex sets intersect then all convex sets intersect.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HellyHelly TheoremTheorem</p>
    <p>HellyHelly: In : In RRdd, given , given nn lines, if every set of lines, if every set of d+1d+1 lines can lines can</p>
    <p>be covered by a ball of radius be covered by a ball of radius rr then all lines can be then all lines can be</p>
    <p>covered by a ball of radius covered by a ball of radius r.r.</p>
    <p>Not very useful as Not very useful as dd can be very large (depends on can be very large (depends on nn).).</p>
    <p>Goal:Goal: remove the dependence on remove the dependence on dd in locality argument in locality argument</p>
    <p>and apply to clustering.and apply to clustering.</p>
    <p>In In RR22: if every : if every 33 lines intersectlines intersect  all lines intersect.all lines intersect.</p>
    <p>Every two intersectEvery three intersect</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main idea Main idea</p>
    <p>HellyHelly:: In In RRdd, if every set of , if every set of d+1d+1 lines can be covered by a ball lines can be covered by a ball</p>
    <p>of radius of radius rr then all lines can be covered by a ball of radius then all lines can be covered by a ball of radius r.r.</p>
    <p>Exploit the fact that we work on Exploit the fact that we work on lines (lowlines (low--dim dim</p>
    <p>objects) objects) in in high dimensional (dhigh dimensional (d--dim)dim) space.space.</p>
    <p>IntrinsicIntrinsic--dimension rather than dimension of the dimension rather than dimension of the</p>
    <p>ambient space.ambient space.</p>
    <p>Can replace with any convex set</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our resultsOur results HellyHelly: In : In RRdd, if every set of , if every set of d+1d+1 lines can be covered by a ball of lines can be covered by a ball of</p>
    <p>radius radius rr then all lines can be covered by a ball of radius then all lines can be covered by a ball of radius r.r.</p>
    <p>Intrinsic Intrinsic HellyHelly II: In : In RRdd, given , given nn lines, if every set of lines, if every set of 33</p>
    <p>lines can be covered by a ball of radius lines can be covered by a ball of radius rr then all lines then all lines</p>
    <p>can be covered by a ball of radius can be covered by a ball of radius 2r.2r.</p>
    <p>Intrinsic Intrinsic HellyHelly IIII: Given : Given nn lines, if every set of ~ lines, if every set of ~ 1/1/22</p>
    <p>lines can be covered by a ball of radius lines can be covered by a ball of radius rr then all lines then all lines</p>
    <p>can be covered by a ball of radius can be covered by a ball of radius (1+(1+)r.)r.</p>
    <p>Independent of d!</p>
    <p>Relax quality</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theorem is constructiveTheorem is constructive</p>
    <p>Intrinsic Intrinsic HellyHelly II: Given : Given nn lines, if every set of lines, if every set of 33 lines can be lines can be</p>
    <p>covered by a ball of radius covered by a ball of radius rr then all lines can be covered by a ball then all lines can be covered by a ball</p>
    <p>of radius of radius 2r.2r.</p>
    <p>Intrinsic Intrinsic HellyHelly IIII: Given : Given nn lines, if every set of ~ lines, if every set of ~ 1/1/22 lines can be lines can be</p>
    <p>covered by a ball of radius covered by a ball of radius rr then all lines can be covered by a ball then all lines can be covered by a ball</p>
    <p>of radius of radius (1+(1+)r.)r.</p>
    <p>Given set of Given set of nn lines with minimum enclosing ball of radius at least lines with minimum enclosing ball of radius at least rr, ,</p>
    <p>we find a subset of lines of size ~ we find a subset of lines of size ~ 1/1/22 with minimum enclosing ball with minimum enclosing ball</p>
    <p>of radiusof radius at leastat least (1(1--)r )r inin timetime ~ n~ npoly(1/poly(1/))..</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Application to clusteringApplication to clustering</p>
    <p>Minimum enclosing ball of lines (Minimum enclosing ball of lines (11--center)center)  InputInput: : nn lines.lines.</p>
    <p>OutputOutput: minimum radius ball covering all lines: minimum radius ball covering all lines..</p>
    <p>Can be computed by convex programming in time ~ Can be computed by convex programming in time ~ nn3/23/2poly(d)poly(d)..</p>
    <p>Using our algorithmUsing our algorithm: can find approximation to radius of minimum : can find approximation to radius of minimum</p>
    <p>enclosing ball within ratio enclosing ball within ratio (1+(1+)) in time ~ in time ~ nnpoly(1/poly(1/))..</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What next?What next?</p>
    <p>Prove Prove Intrinsic Intrinsic HellyHelly I I ((22 approximation).approximation).</p>
    <p>Sketch proof for Sketch proof for Intrinsic Intrinsic HellyHelly II II ( ( (1+(1+)) app. ).app. ).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>If every set of If every set of 33 lines can be covered by a ball of radius lines can be covered by a ball of radius rr then all lines then all lines</p>
    <p>can be covered by a ball of radius can be covered by a ball of radius 2r.2r.</p>
    <p>ClaimClaim: We can find a ball of radius : We can find a ball of radius 2r2r that covers every line.that covers every line.</p>
    <p>Pick arbitrary line Pick arbitrary line ll11..</p>
    <p>Consider Consider 22 lines lines ll22, , ll33, there is a ball centered at , there is a ball centered at oo with radius with radius rr</p>
    <p>that covers the three lines that covers the three lines ll11, , ll22, , ll33..</p>
    <p>l1 r</p>
    <p>ll22 ll33</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ProofProof  For each of the For each of the 22 lines lines ll22, , ll33, define interval , define interval II22, I, I33 on on ll11 consisting consisting</p>
    <p>of points within distance of points within distance 2r2r from from ll22, , ll33, respectively., respectively.</p>
    <p>ClaimClaim: the two intervals : the two intervals II22, I, I33 intersect.intersect.</p>
    <p>In fact, any two intervals In fact, any two intervals IIii, , IIjj for line for line llii, , lljj, intersect., intersect.</p>
    <p>By By HellyHelly theorem, all theorem, all nn--11 intervals intersect intervals intersect  take the ball take the ball</p>
    <p>centered at a point in the common intersection. It cover all thecentered at a point in the common intersection. It cover all the</p>
    <p>lines with radius lines with radius  2r2r. QED. QED</p>
    <p>If every set of If every set of 33 lines can be covered by a ball of radius lines can be covered by a ball of radius rr then all lines can be covered by a ball of radius then all lines can be covered by a ball of radius 2r.2r.</p>
    <p>Helly: In Rd, if every set of d+1 convex sets intersect then all convex sets intersect.</p>
    <p>l1 r</p>
    <p>ll22 ll33</p>
    <p>II22 II33</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(1+(1+) approx. (Theorem II)) approx. (Theorem II)</p>
    <p>If every set of If every set of ~~ 1/1/22 lines can be covered by a ball of radius lines can be covered by a ball of radius rr then then</p>
    <p>all lines can be covered by a ball of radius all lines can be covered by a ball of radius (1+(1+)r.)r.</p>
    <p>InputInput: : nn lines (optimal ball that covers has radius lines (optimal ball that covers has radius 11).).</p>
    <p>OutputOutput: ~ : ~ 1/1/22 lines that have covering radius lines that have covering radius  (1(1--))..</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AlgorithmAlgorithm</p>
    <p>We wish to follow the We wish to follow the algalg for points [BHI02].for points [BHI02].</p>
    <p>StartStart with with 33 lines which are lines which are 22 approximation, denote set by approximation, denote set by LL..</p>
    <p>These lines have minimum cover radius of at least These lines have minimum cover radius of at least : : r(Lr(L) )  ..</p>
    <p>Find additional line Find additional line ll s.ts.t. . r(L+lr(L+l) &gt;&gt; ) &gt;&gt; r(Lr(L))..</p>
    <p>ClaimClaim: :  If r(L) &lt; 1-, find a line l for which r(L+l)r(L)(1+2).  After ~ 1/2 steps algorithm will stop as r(all lines)=1.</p>
    <p>If every set of ~ If every set of ~ 1/1/22 lines can be covered by a ball lines can be covered by a ball of radius of radius rr then all lines can be covered by a ball of then all lines can be covered by a ball of radius radius (1+(1+)r.)r.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AlgorithmAlgorithm  ClaimClaim: If : If r(Lr(L) &lt; 1) &lt; 1--, , always exists linealways exists line l l for for</p>
    <p>whichwhich r(L+l)r(L+l)r(L)(1+r(L)(1+22))..</p>
    <p>Actually claim is Actually claim is notnot true: true:</p>
    <p>Can proveCan prove existence of existence of twotwo lines lines s.ts.t. . r(L+lr(L+l11+l+l22))r(L)(1+r(L)(1+</p>
    <p>Technically involved</p>
    <p>AlgorithmAlgorithm: in each iteration find : in each iteration find 22 lines that lines that</p>
    <p>will increase the radius substantially. After ~ will increase the radius substantially. After ~</p>
    <p>L</p>
    <p>If every set of If every set of 1/1/22 lines can be covered by a ball of lines can be covered by a ball of radius radius rr then all lines can be covered by a ball of then all lines can be covered by a ball of radius radius (1+(1+)r.)r.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extensions to Extensions to dim flatsdim flats</p>
    <p>Intrinsic Intrinsic HellyHelly II: In : In RRdd, given n , given n dim flats, if every dim flats, if every</p>
    <p>set of set of +2+2 flats can be covered by a ball of radius flats can be covered by a ball of radius rr</p>
    <p>then all flats can be covered by a ball of radius then all flats can be covered by a ball of radius 2r.2r.</p>
    <p>Intrinsic Intrinsic HellyHelly IIII: Given : Given nn dim flats, if every set of dim flats, if every set of</p>
    <p>~ ~ 44//22 flats can be covered by a ball of radius flats can be covered by a ball of radius rr then then</p>
    <p>all flats can be covered by a ball of radius all flats can be covered by a ball of radius (1+(1+)r.)r.</p>
    <p>Tight!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Connection to LPConnection to LP--type problemstype problems</p>
    <p>Intrinsic Intrinsic HellyHelly II: In : In RRdd, given n , given n dim flats, if every set of dim flats, if every set of +2+2</p>
    <p>flats can be covered by a ball of radius flats can be covered by a ball of radius rr then all flats can be then all flats can be</p>
    <p>covered by a ball of radius covered by a ball of radius 2r.2r.</p>
    <p>Minimum intersecting ball is an LPMinimum intersecting ball is an LP--type problem with type problem with</p>
    <p>combinatorial dimension combinatorial dimension d+1d+1..</p>
    <p>With With 22--approx. we can restrict the center to be in one of the approx. we can restrict the center to be in one of the</p>
    <p>dim flats dim flats  LPLP--type problem has combinatorial dimension type problem has combinatorial dimension +1+1..</p>
    <p>Nina Nina AmentaAmenta [1996] showed LP[1996] showed LP--type problems with combinatorial type problems with combinatorial</p>
    <p>dimension c have dimension c have HellyHelly number number  c+1.c+1.</p>
    <p>This is another proof of This is another proof of Intrinsic Intrinsic HellyHelly II..</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Concluding remarksConcluding remarks</p>
    <p>Initiated study of clustering on incomplete data.Initiated study of clustering on incomplete data.</p>
    <p>Presented Presented Intrinsic dimension Intrinsic dimension HellyHelly theoremstheorems + +</p>
    <p>applications applications to to (1+(1+))--approximate approximate 11--center clustering.center clustering.</p>
    <p>Existence of small representative subset (coreExistence of small representative subset (core--set).set).</p>
    <p>The 1The 1--center result also implies preliminary results on center result also implies preliminary results on</p>
    <p>(1+(1+))--approximate approximate kk--centercenter problem on lines with problem on lines with</p>
    <p>running time ~ (n/running time ~ (n/d+1d+1))kk ..</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Facility location for mobile Facility location for mobile clientsclients  InputInput::</p>
    <p>n clients moving along lines in Rd.</p>
    <p>Parameter k.</p>
    <p>OutputOutput::</p>
    <p>k gas stations such that each client has a nearby gas station.</p>
    <p>At least as hard as kAt least as hard as k--center center</p>
    <p>for points, for general k.for points, for general k.</p>
    <p>r</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
