<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perspective: Semantic data management for the home</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon, Steve Schlosser*, Lorrie Cranor,</p>
    <p>Greg Ganger * Intel Research Pittsburgh</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Marys music</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/ 2</p>
    <p>Roommates listen to music on Carols desktop  It has better speakers</p>
    <p>Mary wants U2 for an upcoming party  So, shell copy U2 files to Carols desktop</p>
    <p>Using a USB dongle</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Moving U2</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/ 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Moving U2</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/ 4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>x x</p>
    <p>U2 moves in mysterious ways</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/089 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/ 5</p>
    <p>x</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How did this get so complicated?  Naming mismatch between app and tool</p>
    <p>Application (iTunes): semantic naming  Management tool (Finder): hierarchical naming  Not just an interface problem</p>
    <p>Design of the system is critical</p>
    <p>The big problem is management  Problems occur when system and usage diverge  Even simple tasks can become complex  End user is a real person, not a techie</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/ 6</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our methodology  Explored what home users need</p>
    <p>In-situ, semi-structured interviews</p>
    <p>Built a prototype filesystem: Perspective  Addresses discovered management challenges</p>
    <p>Tested Perspectives usability in lab  Have shown view-based management is more</p>
    <p>usable than directory and volume approaches  We tested real users  not tech gurus</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 7 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contextual analysis  In-situ semi-structured interviews</p>
    <p>Interviewed 24 people in 8 households  Asked about data management practices  Also asked about data and device specifics</p>
    <p>For example: Describe the last time you backed up your data. Can you step</p>
    <p>me through a backup right now?</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 8 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Core home management tenets  Users are comfortable with semantic naming  Devices are decentralized and dynamic  Users require control over automation  User place data infrequently and explicitly  Users require low cost / high utilization</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/ 9</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our methodology  Explored what home users need</p>
    <p>In-situ, semi-structured interviews</p>
    <p>Built a prototype filesystem: Perspective  Addresses discovered management challenges</p>
    <p>Tested Perspectives usability in lab  Have shown view-based management is more</p>
    <p>usable than directory and volume approaches  We tested real users  not tech gurus</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 10 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perspective addresses core tenets  Peer-to-peer architecture</p>
    <p>Loosely coupled devices</p>
    <p>Semantic management  Move data, set reliability on semantic groupings</p>
    <p>Rule-based data placement  Placement rules automatically place new data</p>
    <p>Transparent automation  Human-understandable language for tools</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 11 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perspective is a distributed fs  Global namespace</p>
    <p>Can read/write data from any accessible device  Can search for data from any device</p>
    <p>Files accessible through FUSE  Can be accessed by unmodified applications</p>
    <p>Eventual consistency  Data can always be modified from any device  All replicas of file converge to same version  Topology independent  Conflicts are handled similarly to previous systems</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/ 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Views  View specifies the files stored on a device</p>
    <p>Uses a semantic query to specify a set of files  Perspective ensures view files are stored on device</p>
    <p>Semantic query  Query on name-value pair attributes  Example: files where album = The White Album files where task = Taxes and create time &gt; January</p>
    <p>Use queries to manage data, not just locate it  Views provide data placement, fault tolerance</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 13 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>View provide: update routing</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 14</p>
    <p>name = Galileo type = TV Show series = West Wing owner = Brian</p>
    <p>Mary cell: type=address book and owner=Mary</p>
    <p>Family desktop: all files</p>
    <p>DVR: type=TV Show</p>
    <p>DVR: sharing=Family</p>
    <p>Brian laptop: owner=Brian</p>
    <p>http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
    <p>Also used to limit costs on synchronization, and direct searches to appropriate devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>View-based management</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 15 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rule-based management</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 16</p>
    <p>Mary laptop: owner=Mary</p>
    <p>http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Semantic management</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 17</p>
    <p>Mary laptop: owner=Mary and create time &gt; 2007 Desktop: owner=Mary</p>
    <p>and create time &lt;= 2007</p>
    <p>http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
    <p>Mary laptop: owner=Mary</p>
    <p>Marys laptop is short on disk space, but the Desktop has extra disk space. Should I put Marys old files on the Desktop to free up space?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transparent automation</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 18</p>
    <p>Mary laptop: owner=Mary and create time &gt; 2007 Desktop: owner=Mary</p>
    <p>and create time &lt;= 2007 Mary laptop: owner=Mary And type=Music</p>
    <p>Desktop: owner=Mary</p>
    <p>http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Loosely coupled devices</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 19</p>
    <p>Mary laptop: owner=Mary and create time &gt; 2007</p>
    <p>Mary laptop: owner=Mary And type=Music</p>
    <p>Desktop: owner=Mary</p>
    <p>Mary laptop: owner=Mary and create time &gt; 2007</p>
    <p>Mary laptop: owner=Mary And type=Music</p>
    <p>http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our methodology  Explored what home users need</p>
    <p>In-situ, semi-structured interviews</p>
    <p>Built a prototype filesystem: Perspective  Addresses discovered management challenges</p>
    <p>Tested Perspectives usability in lab  Have shown view-based management is more</p>
    <p>usable than directory and volume approaches  We tested real users  not tech gurus</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 20 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Usability evaluation  Is view-based management easier than</p>
    <p>directory or volume-based management?  Between-group lab usability study</p>
    <p>Non-technical university students and staff  Tested 30 users, each using one system  Each user did 10 tasks in latin square ordering</p>
    <p>Use the same interface, change system  View-based system (semantic, p2p)  Directory-based system (hierarchical, p2p)  Volume-based system (hierarchical, client/server)</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 21 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>View manager interface</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 22 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/ Expandable grids, Reeder et al. CHI 2008</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data organization tasks  Test semantic/hierarchy mismatch</p>
    <p>Applications are semantic  View-base system matches application naming  Directory / Volume systems are hierarchical</p>
    <p>Require user to map from semantic to hierarchy  Example task:</p>
    <p>Mary and Brian share music at home. However, when Mary is on trips, she finds that she can't listen to all the songs by U2 on her laptop.  Make sure she can listen to all music by the artist U2 on her trips.</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 23 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>U2 RF TV TB TM Avg</p>
    <p>P er</p>
    <p>ce nt</p>
    <p>c or</p>
    <p>re ct</p>
    <p>Task</p>
    <p>View Directory</p>
    <p>Data organization tasks</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 24 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/ Users found semantic model simpler than hierarchical</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LH CB Average</p>
    <p>P er</p>
    <p>ce nt</p>
    <p>c or</p>
    <p>re ct</p>
    <p>Task</p>
    <p>View Volume Client/server tasks</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 25 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/</p>
    <p>Users found peer-to-peer model easier to use</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other results  Tasks w/ clear but tedious mappings</p>
    <p>Example: playlists, photo albums  Completion time varied, not accuracy  Views users 70s compared to 428s for directory</p>
    <p>Performance acceptable for day-to-day use  It has stored my data for 1 1/2 years  It also supports several multi-tuner DVRs  Latency acceptable, throughput ok for HDTV</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/ 26</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  We present analysis of home management</p>
    <p>Found that environment was decentralized  Found disconnect in application and tool naming</p>
    <p>Perspective simplifies management tasks  Through semantic, decentralized management  User studies show up to 6x gain in accuracy</p>
    <p>Brandon Salmon  2/09 http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/ 27</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
