<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LightFlood:LightFlood: An Efficient Flooding Scheme for File An Efficient Flooding Scheme for File Search in Unstructured P2PSearch in Unstructured P2P SystemsSystems</p>
    <p>Song Jiang, Lei Guo, and Xiaodong ZhangSong Jiang, Lei Guo, and Xiaodong Zhang College of William and MaryCollege of William and Mary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Unstructured P2P OverlayUnstructured P2P Overlay</p>
    <p>P2P overlay  Application level network over physical network</p>
    <p>Self-organized by peers voluntarily</p>
    <p>Characteristics  Power-law distribution: a small number of peers have</p>
    <p>high connectivity</p>
    <p>Dynamic population: peers come and go frequently</p>
    <p>Resilient to random node failures</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Search in P2P OverlaySearch in P2P Overlay</p>
    <p>Flooding</p>
    <p>Expanding ring (ICS02)</p>
    <p>Random walk (ICS02, SIGCOM03)</p>
    <p>Iterative deepening (ICDCS02)</p>
    <p>Directed BFS (ICDCS02)</p>
    <p>Super peer (ICDE03)</p>
    <p>Interested-based Locality (INFOCOM03)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FloodingFlooding</p>
    <p>Simple and robust  No state maintenance needed  High tolerance to node failures</p>
    <p>Effective and of low latency  Always find the shortest / fastest routing paths</p>
    <p>Fundamental operation for  Broadcasting in distributed systems</p>
    <p>P2P communications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problems of Flooding Problems of Flooding</p>
    <p>Loops in Gnutella networks  Caused by redundant links  Result in endless message routing</p>
    <p>Current solutions by Gnutella  Detect and discard redundant messages</p>
    <p>Limit TTL (time-to-live) of messages</p>
    <p>Unnecessary traffic is still too much  The redundant links are still there</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Traffic Minimization: Traffic Minimization: Spanning TreeSpanning Tree</p>
    <p>Reduce traffic without changing P2P overlay</p>
    <p>How much bandwidth can we save?  Average degree of Gnutella nodes: about 3 ~ 5</p>
    <p>N-node spanning tree  N-1 links  N-1 messages for a broadcast</p>
    <p>Estimated traffic reduction: about 67% ~ 80%</p>
    <p>Bandwidth efficiency is not the only objective</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problems of Spanning TreeProblems of Spanning Tree</p>
    <p>Long latency for flooding  More than 30 hops to cover 95% of nodes  Only 7 hops to cover 95% of nodes by</p>
    <p>Gnutella flooding</p>
    <p>Weak reliability due to node failures  A node failure can disconnect a large portion</p>
    <p>of network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>P2P Overlay</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flooding in Spanning Tree</p>
    <p>HOPS = 7HOPS = 8HOPS = 9HOPS = 10HOPS = 11HOPS = 0HOPS = 1HOPS = 2HOPS = 3HOPS = 4HOPS = 5HOPS = 6</p>
    <p>Spanning Tree</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HOPS = 0HOPS = 1HOPS = 2HOPS = 3HOPS = 4HOPS = 5HOPS = 6</p>
    <p>Flooding in P2P Overlay</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Node Failure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trade-offs Trade-offs</p>
    <p>Traffic efficiency and routing latency</p>
    <p>Redundancy and robustness</p>
    <p>Let us take a look at pure flooding in Gnutella</p>
    <p>NEED to update</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observations of Pure FloodingObservations of Pure Flooding</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observations of Pure FloodingObservations of Pure Flooding</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MotivationsMotivations</p>
    <p>Pure flooding is efficient in the initial hops  Node coverage grows quickly, while</p>
    <p>Only account for a small portion of redundant msgs</p>
    <p>Most redundant messages are generated in high hops</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our SolutionOur Solution</p>
    <p>Combining both merits of pure flooding and spanning tree</p>
    <p>Constructing FloodNet: a tree-like structure over P2P network</p>
    <p>Flooding over P2P network in initial hops</p>
    <p>Flooding over FloodNet in rest hops</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FloodNet: a Tree-like Sub-overlayFloodNet: a Tree-like Sub-overlay</p>
    <p>States maintained in each node  Number of neighbors  The node degree of each neighbor</p>
    <p>Topology construction  Father node: the neighbor with the highest</p>
    <p>degree  Tie breaking  Dynamic updating: very low overhead</p>
    <p>A tree-like structure over Gnutella overlay</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Constructing FloodNet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Constructing FloodNet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Constructing FloodNet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Constructing FloodNet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FloodNet: Loops?FloodNet: Loops?</p>
    <p>At most one loop in the structure</p>
    <p>Nodes in a loop have the same degree  Root candidates</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LOOP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FloodNet: Loops?FloodNet: Loops?</p>
    <p>At most one loop in the structure</p>
    <p>Nodes in a loop have the same degree  Root candidates</p>
    <p>Endless routing  Easy to detect and avoid: same as Gnutella</p>
    <p>Redundant messages  At most one redundant message per flooding</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FloodNet: Multiple Trees?FloodNet: Multiple Trees?</p>
    <p>Possible but the number is very small</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FloodNet: Multiple Trees?FloodNet: Multiple Trees?</p>
    <p>Possible but the number is very small  Only high degree nodes can be tree roots  Only a few nodes have high connectivity</p>
    <p>(recall the power law distribution)</p>
    <p>These high degree nodes may connect each other</p>
    <p>Normally less than 10 trees in Gnutella overlay according to our simulation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Broadcast in FloodNetBroadcast in FloodNet</p>
    <p>Aims  Reach all FloodNet trees  Cover most nodes in a few hops</p>
    <p>Problems  How can a node initiating a broadcast know</p>
    <p>other FloodNet trees?</p>
    <p>Flooding from a leaf node needs long hops to cover most portion of the tree</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LightFloodLightFlood</p>
    <p>Basic idea  Broadcasting messages in parallel from</p>
    <p>multiple nodes of different trees</p>
    <p>2-stage broadcasting  Low hops: the initial M flooding hops</p>
    <p>High hops: the rest N flooding hops</p>
    <p>Denoted as (M, N) policy</p>
    <p>(7, 0) is same as Gnutella flooding</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LightFloodLightFlood</p>
    <p>Low hops: utilizing redundant links  Flooding in P2P overlay  Reach many nodes of different trees with</p>
    <p>small overheads</p>
    <p>High hops: keep away from redundant links  Flooding in FloodNet</p>
    <p>Flooding from multiple nodes in parallel</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>High hops</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance EvaluationPerformance Evaluation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Coverage vs. LatencyCoverage vs. Latency</p>
    <p>(4,*) takes only additional 3 hops to reach same coverage as (7,0)</p>
    <p>(7, 0)</p>
    <p>(4, *)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Traffic EfficiencyTraffic Efficiency</p>
    <p>(7, 0): 28.1%</p>
    <p>(4, *): 90.8%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Degradation Due to Node FailuresDegradation Due to Node Failures</p>
    <p>Nearly same coverage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Expanding Ring: TrafficExpanding Ring: Traffic</p>
    <p>LightFlood</p>
    <p>Pure Flood</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ConclusionConclusion</p>
    <p>FloodNet is easy to construct and maintain  Using local and neighboring information  Dynamically updated with little overhead</p>
    <p>LightFlood is both broadcast effective and bandwidth efficient  Large coverage  Small routing hops  Small amount of redundant messages</p>
    <p>An efficient and effective flooding scheme</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
