<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>You Are How You Click Clickstream Analysis for Sybil Detection</p>
    <p>Gang Wang, Tristan Konolige, Christo Wilson, Xiao Wang Haitao Zheng and Ben Y. Zhao</p>
    <p>UC Santa Barbara Northeastern University Renren Inc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sybils in Online Social Networks</p>
    <p>Sybil (sbl): fake identities controlled by attackers  Friendship is a pre-cursor to other malicious activities  Does not include benign fakes (secondary accounts)</p>
    <p>Large Sybil populations*</p>
    <p>*Numbers from CNN 2012, NYT 2013</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sybil Attack: a Serious Threat</p>
    <p>Social spam  Advertisement, malware, phishing</p>
    <p>Steal user information</p>
    <p>Sybil-based political lobbying efforts</p>
    <p>Malicious URL</p>
    <p>Taliban uses sexy Facebook profiles to lure troops into giving away military secrets&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sybil Defense: Cat-and-Mouse Game</p>
    <p>Social Networks A&gt;ackers</p>
    <p>Stop automated account creation  CAPTCHA</p>
    <p>Detect suspicious profiles  Spam features, URL blacklists  User report</p>
    <p>Detect Sybil communities  [SIGCOMM06], [Oakland08],</p>
    <p>[NDSS09], [NSDI12]</p>
    <p>Crowdsourcing CAPTCHA solving  [USENIX10]</p>
    <p>Realistic profile generation  Complete bio info, profile pic</p>
    <p>[WWW12]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Graph-based Sybil Detectors</p>
    <p>A key assumption  Sybils have difficulty friending normal users  Sybils form tight-knit communities</p>
    <p>Measuring Sybils in Renren social network [IMC11]</p>
    <p>Ground-truth 560K Sybils collected over 3 years  Most Sybils befriend real users, integrate into real-user communities  Most Sybils dont befriend other Sybils</p>
    <p>Is This True?</p>
    <p>Sybils dont need to form communiGes!</p>
    <p>Sybil Real</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sybil detection with static profiles analysis [NDSS13]  Leverage human intuition to detect fake profiles (crowdsourcing)  Successful user-study shows it scales well with high accuracy</p>
    <p>Profile-based detection has limitations</p>
    <p>Some profiles are easy to mimic (e.g. CEO profile )  Information can be found online</p>
    <p>A new direction: look at what users do!</p>
    <p>How users browse/click social network pages  Build user behavior models using clickstreams</p>
    <p>Sybil Detection Without Graphs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clickstreams and User Behaviors</p>
    <p>Clickstream: a list of server-side user-generated events  E.g. profile load, link follow, photo browse, friend invite</p>
    <p>Intuition: Sybil users act differently from normal users</p>
    <p>Goal-oriented: concentrate on specific actions  Time-limited: fast event generation (small inter-arrival time)</p>
    <p>UserID Event Generated Timestamp</p>
    <p>Analyze ground-truth clickstreams for Sybil detecGon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Clickstream Similarity Graph  Ground-truth Dataset  Modeling User Clickstreams  Generating Behavioral Clusters</p>
    <p>Real-time Sybil Detection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ground-truth Dataset</p>
    <p>Renren Social Network  A large online social network in China (280M+ users)  Chinese Facebook</p>
    <p>Ground-truth  Ground-truth provided by Renrens security team  16K users, clickstreams over two months in 2011, 6.8M clicks</p>
    <p>Dataset Users Sessions Clicks Date (2011)</p>
    <p>Sybil 9,994 113,595 1,008,031 Feb.28-Apr.30</p>
    <p>Normal 5,998 467,179 5,856,941 Mar.31-Apr.30</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Normal users use many social network features  Sybils focus on a few actions (e.g. friend invite, browse profiles)</p>
    <p>Basic Analysis: Click Transitions</p>
    <p>Sybil Clickstream</p>
    <p>Friend Invite</p>
    <p>Photo</p>
    <p>Browse Profiles</p>
    <p>IniGal Final</p>
    <p>Spammers</p>
    <p>Crawlers</p>
    <p>Normal Clickstream</p>
    <p>Photo IniGal Final 39%</p>
    <p>Share</p>
    <p>Blog NoGficaGon</p>
    <p>Browse Profiles</p>
    <p>Sybils and normal users have very different click pa&gt;erns!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Identifying Sybils From Normal Users</p>
    <p>Goal: quantify the differences in user behaviors  Measure the similarity between user clickstreams</p>
    <p>Approach: map users clickstreams to a similarity graph</p>
    <p>Clickstreams are nodes  Edge-weights indicate the similarity of two clickstreams</p>
    <p>Clusters in the similarity graph capture user behaviors  Each cluster represents certain type of click/behavior pattern  Hypothesis: Sybils and normal users fall into different clusters</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Legit Sybils</p>
    <p>Clickstream Log</p>
    <p>Behavior Clusters</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>Unknown User Clickstream</p>
    <p>Similarity Graph</p>
    <p>Labeled Clusters</p>
    <p>Good Clusters</p>
    <p>Sybil Cluster</p>
    <p>Model Training DetecDon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Capturing User Clickstreams</p>
    <p>User1:</p>
    <p>User2:</p>
    <p>X X X X X X Time A B C D A A</p>
    <p>X X D B</p>
    <p>X X A A</p>
    <p>X X E A</p>
    <p>X X X X X X Time B B C D E C</p>
    <p>X X B A</p>
    <p>X X B D</p>
    <p>X X D E</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!!,! = !&quot;#$%!!&amp;!!&quot;#$%! !&quot;#$%!!|!!&quot;#$%!</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>Clickstream Similarity Functions</p>
    <p>Similarity of sequences  Common subsequence</p>
    <p>Common subsequence with counts</p>
    <p>Adding time to the sequence  Bucketize inter-arrival time, encode time into the sequence  Apply the same sequence similarity function</p>
    <p>ngram1= {A, B, AA, AB, AAB} ngram2= {A, C, AA, AC, AAC}</p>
    <p>S1= AAB S2= AAC</p>
    <p>ngram1= {A(2), B(1), AA(1), AB(1), AAB(1)} ngram2= {A(2), C(1), AA(1), AC(1), AAC(1)}</p>
    <p>S1= AAB S2= AAC</p>
    <p>Euclidean Distance</p>
    <p>V1=(2,1,0,1,0,1,1,0) V2=(2,0,1,1,1,0,0,1)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clickstream Clustering</p>
    <p>Similarity graph (fully-connected)  Nodes: users clickstreams  Edges: weighted by the similarity score of two users clickstreams</p>
    <p>Clustering similar clickstreams together  Minimum edge weight cut  Graph partitioning using METIS</p>
    <p>Perform clustering on ground-truth data  Complete model produces very accurate behavior clusters  3% false negatives and 1% false positives</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Clickstream Similarity Graph</p>
    <p>Real-time Sybil Detection  Sybil Detection Using Similarity Graph  Unsupervised Approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Detection in a Nutshell</p>
    <p>? Normal</p>
    <p>Sybil</p>
    <p>Fastest, scalable</p>
    <p>Sybil detection methodology  Assign the unclassified clickstream to the nearest cluster  If the nearest cluster is a Sybil cluster, then the user is a Sybil</p>
    <p>Assigning clickstreams to clusters  K nearest neighbor (KNN)  Nearest cluster (NC)  Nearest cluster with center (NCC)</p>
    <p>New Clickstreams Clustered Similarity Graph</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Detection Evaluation</p>
    <p>Split 12K clickstreams into training and testing datasets  Train initial clusters with 3K Sybil + 3K normal users  Classify remaining 6K testing clickstreams</p>
    <p>KNN NC NCC</p>
    <p>Er ro r Ra</p>
    <p>te</p>
    <p>DetecDon Algorithm</p>
    <p>False PosiGve</p>
    <p>False NegaGve</p>
    <p>NCC (fastest) is as good as the others</p>
    <p>&lt; 0.7% false posiGve rate</p>
    <p>K-nearest neighbor Nearest Cluster Nearest Cluster (center)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>400 random good users are enough to color all behavior clusters  For unknown dataset, add good users unGl diminishing returns  SGll achieve high detecGon accuracy (1% fp, 4% fn)</p>
    <p>(Semi) unsupervised Approach</p>
    <p>What if we dont have a big ground-truth dataset?  Need a method to label clusters</p>
    <p>Use a (small) set of known-good users to color clusters  Adding known users to existing clusters  Clusters that contain good users are good clusters</p>
    <p>Good Clusters</p>
    <p>Sybil Cluster</p>
    <p>Known Good Users</p>
    <p>Details here</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Real-world Experiments</p>
    <p>Deploy system prototypes onto social networks  Shipped our prototype code to Renren and LinkedIn  All user data remained on-site</p>
    <p>Scanned 40K ground-truth users clickstreams  Flagged 200 previous unknown Sybils</p>
    <p>Scanned 1M users clickstreams  Flagged 22K suspicious users  Identified a new attack</p>
    <p>Image Spammers  Embed spam content in images  Easy to evade text/URL based detectors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evasion and Challenges</p>
    <p>In order to evade our system, Sybils may   Slow down their click speed  Generate normal actions as cover traffic</p>
    <p>Practical challenges  How to update behavior clusters over time (incrementally)?  How to integrate with other existing detection techniques?</p>
    <p>(e.g. profile, content based detectors )</p>
    <p>Force Sybils to mimic normal users</p>
    <p>= Win</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
