<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Velocity of Censorship: High-Fidelity Detection of Microblog Post Deletions</p>
    <p>Tao Zhu Independent Researcher David Phipps Bowdoin College Adam Pridgen Rice University</p>
    <p>Jedidiah R. Crandall University of New Mexico Dan S. Wallach Rice University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>March 2006</p>
    <p>July 2009</p>
    <p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microblogging_in_China</p>
    <p>August 2009</p>
    <p>Microblogging sites in China</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sina Weibo</p>
    <p>503 million registered users as of Dec 2012.  More than half are from mobile devices.</p>
    <p>About 100 million messages are posted each day on Sina Weibo.</p>
    <p>Promote visibility of social issues.</p>
    <p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sina_Weibo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Weibos influence: Wukan incident - 2011</p>
    <p>(The village name) vs  (Neologism)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sina Weibo</p>
    <p>Strict controls over the posts.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction of our research</p>
    <p>Detecting a censorship event within 1-2 minutes of its occurrence.</p>
    <p>Three strategies Weibo system uses to target sensitive content quickly.</p>
    <p>Performing a topical analysis of the deleted posts.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Identifying the sensitive user group</p>
    <p>Use outdated sensitive keywords from China Digital Times</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Identifying the sensitive user group  Use outdated sensitive keywords from China Digital</p>
    <p>Times.  Start with 25 sensitive users.</p>
    <p>Repost</p>
    <p>Identifying the sensitive user group</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Identifying the sensitive user group  Use outdated sensitive keywords from China Digital</p>
    <p>Times.  Start with 25 sensitive users.  Sensitive group reaches 3,567 users after 15 days.  More than 4,500 deletion daily</p>
    <p>Identifying the sensitive user group</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User timeline:  Weibo user timeline API returns the most recent 50</p>
    <p>posts of the specified user.</p>
    <p>Query 3,567 sensitive users once per minute  100 accounts for API call  300 concurrent Tor circuits.</p>
    <p>Four-node cluster running Hadoop and Hbase  2.38 million posts from July 20 to September 8,</p>
    <p>Crawling</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Diff</p>
    <p>Our databaseLatest 50 posts Deleted Post</p>
    <p>Detecting deletions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>t0 t1 t2 tn</p>
    <p>The lifetime of deleted Post = tn - t0</p>
    <p>Detecting deletions</p>
    <p>...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Permission-denied or system deletion  Permission denied error.  Caused by censorship events.  The post still exists but cannot be accessed by users.</p>
    <p>General deletion  Post does not exist error.  May caused by user self deletion or censorship</p>
    <p>events.  The post does not exist.</p>
    <p>Detecting deletions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Detecting deletions</p>
    <p>Permission-denied deletion 4.5%</p>
    <p>General deletion 8.3%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Permission-denied deletion or system deletion</p>
    <p>Around 1,500 permission denied deletions.</p>
    <p>Comparing with WeiboScope, which is tracking around 300,000 users and have no more than 100 permission denied deletions daily.</p>
    <p>Detecting deletions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distribution of deleted posts</p>
    <p>Whole lifetime First two hours</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Strategies to target sensitive contents 1. Weibo has filtering mechanisms as a</p>
    <p>proactive, automated defense.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Weibo has filtering mechanisms as a proactive, automated defense</p>
    <p>Explicit filtering</p>
    <p>Sorry, The content violates the relevant</p>
    <p>laws and regulations. If need help, please contact customer service.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Weibo has filtering mechanisms as a proactive, automated defense</p>
    <p>Explicit filtering  Implicit filtering</p>
    <p>Your post has been submitted successfully. Currently, there is a</p>
    <p>delay caused by server data synchronization. Please wait for 1 to</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Weibo has filtering mechanisms as a proactive, automated defense</p>
    <p>Explicit filtering  Implicit filtering  Camouflaged posts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Weibo has filtering mechanisms as a proactive, automated defense</p>
    <p>Explicit filtering  Implicit filtering  Camouflaged posts  Surveillance keywords list ?</p>
    <p>If no such list the cost will be too expansive  Suppose to censor 70,000 new posts in one minute, it needs</p>
    <p>Assuming 8 hour shift, 4200 works is required.  It is not cost efficient</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Weibo targets specific users, such as those who frequently post sensitive content.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>When a sensitive post is found, a moderator can find all of its related reposts, and delete them all at once</p>
    <p>Standard deviation (minutes)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Censors work in the night</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Censors catch up on overnight posts by late morning</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Whole lifetime First two hours</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>Q &amp; A</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
