<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Investigating the Computer Security Needs and Practices of Journalists</p>
    <p>Susan McGregor Columbia Journalism School</p>
    <p>Polina Charters, Tobin Holliday, Franziska Roesner</p>
    <p>University of Washington</p>
    <p>USENIX Security 2015</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation: Securing JournalistSource Communications</p>
    <p>Huntley &amp; Marquis-Boire, BlackHat Asia, 2014</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation: Securing JournalistSource Communications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation: Securing JournalistSource Communications</p>
    <p>Despite these and other examples... even investigative journalists rarely use secure communication tools.</p>
    <p>PEW RESEARCH CENTER</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Not?! Observation: The computer security community builds a</p>
    <p>lot of tools that might be useful for journalists, but we dont deeply understand the journalistic process!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Work Investigating the Computer Security Needs and</p>
    <p>Practices of Journalists</p>
    <p>We are: Experts from the journalism and</p>
    <p>computer security communities</p>
    <p>Our subjects: 15 full-time journalists working at a range of</p>
    <p>news media organizations in the</p>
    <p>U.S. and France</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Design</p>
    <p>Interview questions focused on &quot;typical&quot; workflows, communications and information storage and retrieval.</p>
    <p>Threat models were elicited through questions about risk and consequence of information exposure.</p>
    <p>Qualitative data analysis: interviews were coded for themes by 2 independent coders. (average inter-coder agreement by Cohens kappa: 0.88)</p>
    <p>Conduct in-depth interviews with full-time journalists at recognized media organizations operating across a range of media, including print, digital, broadcast and wire services</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Participants</p>
    <p>Organizations ranged from large multinational media outlets to smaller, more single-subject oriented outfits.</p>
    <p>Participants' beats ranged from government to city life, capturing a range of risks and sensitivities.  One participant reported having only his laptop stolen</p>
    <p>from his home while working on sensitive stories.  Another reported strange technical glitches when</p>
    <p>communicating by phone with sources overseas.  Others report being physically surveilled.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings Research Questions</p>
    <p>What are journalists:  General practices?  Security concerns?  Defensive strategies?  Computer security needs?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings General Practices</p>
    <p>Participants use a wide range of communication methods, usually whatever is preferred by the source.</p>
    <p>[The source] probably understand[s] the threat model theyre under better than I would. So, it brings up an interesting question: do you go with what theyre comfortable with? Or do you say, alright, actually let me assess whats going on and get back to you with what would be appropriate. [...] Peoples first impression is that they would go by what the source feels comfortable doing. As opposed to stepping in and being paternalistic about it.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings</p>
    <p>Long-term sources are common, and often connect journalists to new sources.  The Snowden use case is rare!</p>
    <p>Audio recording and digital note-taking were primary forms of interview documentation.  Many participants use third-party cloud services, but few</p>
    <p>voiced concern about possible security risks.</p>
    <p>General Practices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings</p>
    <p>Primary concerns:  Negative effects on source  Loss of credibility if source information was exposed  Government identification of sources  Disciplinary actions (e.g., losing job)</p>
    <p>Additional concerns (unexpected for us!):  Loss of competitive advantage  Potential financial consequences</p>
    <p>Security Concerns</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings</p>
    <p>Non-technical  Example: Meeting with sources in person (though</p>
    <p>often more for journalistic than security reasons!)  Example: Using intermediaries or code names</p>
    <p>Ad hoc  Example: Asking a source to prove ownership of a</p>
    <p>Twitter account by posting a sentence provided by the journalist.</p>
    <p>Security Strategies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings</p>
    <p>Technical  Most common:</p>
    <p>Encrypted email/chat (especially within org.)  Encrypted files (e.g. FileVault)</p>
    <p>Rarely used: Tor, VPN, other secure messaging apps  (More details in the paper!)</p>
    <p>Security Strategies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings</p>
    <p>Common reasons for using security tools:  a source required them  explicit digital-security training</p>
    <p>Where participants did make efforts to protect information, they often succeeded in one area but left it exposed in another.  Example: meeting a source in person but</p>
    <p>bringing a phone and/or using it to record.</p>
    <p>Security Strategies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings</p>
    <p>Because journalists often defer to sources' preferences, the digital divide is a significant barrier to better communication security.</p>
    <p>Obstacles to Better Security Practice</p>
    <p>&quot;Most of the [sensitive sources] Ive worked with [are] also people who probably arent very tech-savvy. Like, entry-level people in prisons, or something like that. So if they were really concerned about communication, I dont quite know what a secure, non-intimidatingly techy way would be. [...] Some of them dont even necessarily have email addresses.&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings</p>
    <p>Absence of clear, authoritative indicators about the protections offered by particular tools.</p>
    <p>Lack of institutional support in the form of installed software, machine admin rights, or educational resources.</p>
    <p>Obstacles to Better Security Practice</p>
    <p>&quot;A lot of services out there say theyre secure, but having to know which ones are actually audited and approved by security professionals  it takes a lot of work to find that out.&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations</p>
    <p>Why dont journalists use more technical security tools?</p>
    <p>Its not just usability -- tools must be built with an understanding of the journalistic process!</p>
    <p>For example, secure anonymous document drops are useful for sources like Snowden, but less so for the (more common) case of long-term sources that may not initially provide sensitive information.</p>
    <p>Insights for Tool Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations</p>
    <p>In the vast majority of cases, journalists depend on knowing a source's identity.</p>
    <p>Insights for Tool Design</p>
    <p>&quot;If I dont know who they are and cant check their background, Im not going to use the information they give. Anonymous sourcing is fine if I know who they are, and Ive checked who they are, and my editor knows who they are, but they cant keep that from me and then expect me to use the information they provide.&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations</p>
    <p>The technological requirements of secure communications raise barriers to working with less-expert or lower-income sources, who may be the most vulnerable.</p>
    <p>Usability, stability, &amp; reliability remain ongoing issues, especially for organizations.</p>
    <p>Insights for Tool Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations</p>
    <p>Knowledge management (e.g. storing, searching, syncing and tagging story-related media) remains a significant unmet need.</p>
    <p>Ad-hoc solutions (e.g., third-party services) may introduce vulnerabilities.</p>
    <p>Audio transcription presents a particular bottleneck, as well as potential vulnerability.</p>
    <p>Opportunities for Future Research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations Opportunities for Future Research</p>
    <p>&quot;There were different kinds of litigation software that I was familiar with as a lawyer, where, lets say, you have a massive case, where you have a document dump that has 15,000 documents. [...] There are programs that help you consolidate and put them into a secure database. So its searchable [and provides a secure place where you can see everything related to a story at once]. I dont know of anything like that for journalism.&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations</p>
    <p>Exploring methods of secure first-contact and ways to manage the tension between anonymity and authentication.</p>
    <p>Opportunities for Future Research</p>
    <p>&quot;The first contact is never or very rarely anonymous or protected. If someone wants to give me some information and we dont already know each other, how would he do it? He could send me an email, yeah, okay  but then how could I be sure its him? Unless he contacts me with his real identity first. Its very difficult to have the first contact secure.&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations</p>
    <p>Effective metadata protection for digital communications and storage.</p>
    <p>Deeper exploration of the journalistic process and the needs of sources.</p>
    <p>Understanding of the role of journalistic organizations in influencing security practices.</p>
    <p>Opportunities for Future Research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Investigating the Computer Security Needs and Practices of Journalists</p>
    <p>Susan McGregor Columbia Journalism School</p>
    <p>Polina Charters, Tobin Holliday, Franziska Roesner</p>
    <p>University of Washington</p>
    <p>USENIX Security 2015</p>
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings General practices</p>
    <p>Tool/technology Number of participants Inter-coder agreement</p>
    <p>Email (unencrypted) Google Docs/Drive Microsoft Word SMS Social media Dropbox Skype Evernote Text editor Chat (unencrypted) Scrivener</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings Security concerns</p>
    <p>Category Concern No. of participants</p>
    <p>Inter-coder agreement</p>
    <p>Threats to sources</p>
    <p>Discovery by government Disciplinary action (e.g., lost job) Reputation/personal consequences Generally vulnerable populations (e.g., abuse victims) Discovery by others wishing to reveal identity Physical danger Prison</p>
    <p>Threats to journalists or organizations</p>
    <p>Reputation consequences (incl. loss of sources trust) Being scooped (i.e., journalistic competition) False or misleading information from a source Physical threats (incl. theft) Financial consequences</p>
    <p>Threats to others</p>
    <p>Political / foreign relations consequences Other</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations Insights for Tool Design</p>
    <p>Category Reasons for not using security technology No. of</p>
    <p>participants Inter-coder agreement</p>
    <p>Usability and adoption</p>
    <p>Not enough people using it Digital divide: sources dont have/understand technology Security technology is too complicated Hard to evaluate credibility/security of a tool</p>
    <p>Interference with journalism</p>
    <p>Creates barrier to communication with sources Doesnt want to impose on sources Interferes with some other part of their work</p>
    <p>Other Work isnt sensitive enough / no one is looking Uses a non-technical strategy instead Insufficient support from organization Tool doesnt provide the needed defense</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
