<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PowerSpy Location Tracking using Mobile Device Power Analysis</p>
    <p>Yan Michalevsky(1), Gabi Nakibly(2), Aaron Schulman(1), Gunaa Arumugam Veerapandian(1) and Dan Boneh(1)</p>
    <p>(1) Stanford University, (2) National Research and Simulation Center, Rafael Ltd.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Smartphones have many sensors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work on Information Leakage Through Sensors Speaker on/off status [Zhou et al. '13] Accelerometers [Hua et al. '15, Han et al. '12] Microphone [Schlegel at al. '11] and many more...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accessing Location Requires Permissions</p>
    <p>Even coarse location based on cellular network information</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reading Voltage and Current Requires NO Permissions</p>
    <p>/sys/class/power_supply/battery/voltage_now /sys/class/power_supply/battery/current_now</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reading Voltage and Current Requires NO Permissions</p>
    <p>/sys/class/power_supply/battery/voltage_now /sys/class/power_supply/battery/current_now</p>
    <p>Nexus 4, Nexus 5, HTC Desire, iPhone 6... Sampling at order of 100 Hz</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power Meter Reveals Location</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A seemingly innocent application can read the power meter</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Signal Strength Depends on Location and Environment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Signal Strength is Stable Across Days 06/23/2014 06/24/2014</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power = f (Signal Strength) More power used upon transmission under low SNR Signal amplification, error correction on the receive part Verified experimentally in [Schulman et al. '10]Bartendr</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power Profile is Consistent Across Devices</p>
    <p>Two phones of same model, same route Different models, same route</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What can we achieve with that?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goal 1: Route Distinguishability Determine the route taken by the user from a given set Learn past locations Application: advertisement, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goal 2: Real-Time Tracking along a known (or assumed) route</p>
    <p>Perform tracking of the user's current location on a given route</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goal 3: New Route Inference Learn the route using previously measured power profiles of many short road segments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distinguishing Routes Each power profile is a time-series</p>
    <p>Classifier based on time series comparison using Dynamic Time Warping (DTW) [Sakoe and Chiba 1978]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dynamic Time Warping</p>
    <p>Euclidean distance DTW distance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DTW Alignment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Processing DC offset removal and normalization</p>
    <p>Compensate for background appications introducing a constant offset Compensate for gain differences</p>
    <p>Smoothing: Moving Average filter (obtain general trends) Downsampling (important for computation reduction)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goal 1: We can Distinguish between Routes Unique Routes</p>
    <p># Ref. Profiles/Route</p>
    <p># Test Routes</p>
    <p>Success %</p>
    <p>Random Guess %</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Real-Time Tracking A window of received samples is a subsequence of the reference power profile Using Subsequence-DTW determine the offset of the subsequence Infer location from reference profile</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goal 2: We can Track Along a Route</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goal 2: We can Track Along a Route</p>
    <p>Error(time) Error histogram</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goal 2: We can Track Along a Route</p>
    <p>Error(time) Error histogram</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goal 2: We can Track Along a Route</p>
    <p>Error(time) Error histogram</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>And compensate for obvious errors...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Improved tracking using Optimal Subsequence Bijection (OSB) [Latecki et al. '07]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tracking using OSB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goal 3: New Route Inference based on Road Segments</p>
    <p>Points on map represented by nodes Connecting road segments represented by edges Probabilistic graphical model of location</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>New Route Inference based on Road Segments: The Area Map</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation metric based on Levenshtein Distance</p>
    <p>Route Inference based on Road Segments</p>
    <p>d = 0.125 d = 0.25 d = 0.43</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work Build a big dataset of power profiles for US routes Improved route inference (Hidden Markov Model, Viterbi...)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Warning! HTML5 provides battery API that enables receving notifications about changes in battery level. The derivative of the battery level is a very coarse power consumption profile. Keep power measurement coarse!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Defenses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Non-Defenses Adding noise Limiting power sampling rate (1 Hz)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Defenses Secure hardware design</p>
    <p>Exclude TX/RX chain from power measurement Power consumption as a coarse location indicator Provide abstractions, not raw data [Jana et al. '13]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion Sensors can have unintended consequences Power meter access should be restricted Permissions needed to address sensor access</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you for attending</p>
    <p>Questions? yanm2@cs.stanford.edu</p>
    <p>www.stanford.edu/~yanm2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A phone call can be easily distinguished and removed from a power profile</p>
    <p>Phone Call Profile</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
