<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mo(bile) Money, Mo(bile) Problems:</p>
    <p>Security Analysis of Branchless Banking Apps in the Developing</p>
    <p>World</p>
    <p>Brad Reaves, Nolen Scaife, Adam Bates, Patrick Traynor, and Kevin Butler</p>
    <p>Florida Institute for Cyber Security University of Florida</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Branchless Banking a.k.a Mobile Money</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why this is important  Millions are relying on mobile money everyday, and even</p>
    <p>more will continue to do so</p>
    <p>We looked at all 46 currently available mobile money apps</p>
    <p>Application (client side) security</p>
    <p>Server side practices</p>
    <p>Policy environment</p>
    <p>We did a deep dive into 7 of the most popular</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Automated Analysis We used the Mallodroid* framework to analyze the TLS implementation of 46 mobile money apps for Android</p>
    <p>*Fahl et al: An Analysis of Android SSL (In)Security, CCS 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Automated Analysis</p>
    <p>Over 50% of apps had a critical TLS vulnerability</p>
    <p>We later discovered both false positives and false negatives in these results</p>
    <p>In original Mallodroid work, only 9.3% had problems discovered statically</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Manual Analysis</p>
    <p>Seven popular apps</p>
    <p>Over 1.3 Million Users</p>
    <p>Security analysis of: Registration and Login</p>
    <p>User authentication after login Money transfers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Manual Analysis: Apps</p>
    <p>GCash Phillipines</p>
    <p>Zuum Brazil</p>
    <p>MCoin Indonesia</p>
    <p>Money on Mobile India</p>
    <p>Mpay Thailand</p>
    <p>Airtel Money India</p>
    <p>Oxigen Wallet India</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings: High Level</p>
    <p>fabricate or modify transactions  I.e. STEAL MONEY</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vulnerabilities / App</p>
    <p>GCash 7</p>
    <p>Money on Mobile 6</p>
    <p>Oxigen Wallet 6</p>
    <p>Mpay 4</p>
    <p>MCoin 3</p>
    <p>Airtel Money 2</p>
    <p>Zuum 0</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings: Trends</p>
    <p>Error Type Number of Apps Vulnerable Number of</p>
    <p>Vulnerabilities</p>
    <p>TLS Certificate Verification 4 4</p>
    <p>Non-standard Cryptography 4 6</p>
    <p>Access Control 4 7</p>
    <p>Information Leakage 5 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TLS: Client Side</p>
    <p>Android correctly validates TLS certificates by default</p>
    <p>Four of seven apps overrode Androids default certificate verification routines</p>
    <p>Developers likely did this to silence certificate warnings during development or deployment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TLS: Server Side App Qualys Score Noteworthy Vulnerability</p>
    <p>GCash C Vulnerable to POODLE attack</p>
    <p>Money on Mobile N/A No TLS</p>
    <p>Oxigen Wallet F SSL 2 support, MD5 cipher suite</p>
    <p>Mpay F SSL 2, Client-initiated renegotiation, POODLE Attack</p>
    <p>MCoin N/A Expired, self-signed certificate for localhost</p>
    <p>Airtel Money A- Uses SHA-1 with RSA</p>
    <p>Zuum A- Uses SHA-1 with RSA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DIY Crypto: Airtel Money</p>
    <p>This key is used to encrypt the user PIN, used to authenticate with the service</p>
    <p>All of these fields are available in previous messages protected  by broken TLS</p>
    <p>Because TLS certificate validation is effectively disabled, we can 0wn this account</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DIY Crypto: Oxigen Wallet</p>
    <p>Oxigen Wallets secure registration flow:</p>
    <p>Keyenc = Random.Random[17] k phone# k date k 0 128n</p>
    <p>* Random.Random() clearly labeled in the docs as not for crypto</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DIY Crypto</p>
    <p>Crypto implementation in Money On Mobile.</p>
    <p>All messages are sent over plaintext HTTP.</p>
    <p>This is the only crypto used in this app</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Poor Authentication</p>
    <p>Money On Mobile only checked the PIN to move between screens in the app</p>
    <p>The server did nothing to authenticate the users in all sensitive calls.</p>
    <p>Oxigen Wallet allows password reset with an unauthenticated SMS sent from a users phone</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Aftermath</p>
    <p>We reached out to six companies with critical vulnerabilities</p>
    <p>Only two responded to our messages</p>
    <p>Oxigen: We knew there are problems and are working on it</p>
    <p>Money On Mobile: Well get back to you</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Aftermath: Impact</p>
    <p>Money On Mobile has released a new product (as of July 27) that they claim addresses the security concerns raised in the paper, and plan to sunset their vulnerable app this week.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Who Takes The Fall</p>
    <p>These systems fail to safeguard user data confidentiality and transaction integrity</p>
    <p>ToS: User is responsible for all authenticated transactions</p>
    <p>When these systems are attacked, the user pays the price</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What About Regulation?</p>
    <p>Many countries have modified their financial regulations to make it easier for mobile money systems to operate</p>
    <p>The Reserve Bank of India offers a one-page Illustrative Framework for data and communications security</p>
    <p>Oxigen Wallet and Airtel Money both fell within the letter (though not spirit) of these guidelines</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Takeaways</p>
    <p>Mobile Money is revolutionizing finance in the developing world, but its initial deployment on smart phones is a security disaster.</p>
    <p>Poor security, combined with liability models that hold the users almost entirely responsible for any losses, place the mobile money experiment in jeopardy.</p>
    <p>Best practices may help, but the state of the art for secure app development still has a long way to go</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
