<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Los Angeles September 27, 2006</p>
    <p>MOBICOM 2006</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Localization in Sparse Networks using Sweeps</p>
    <p>D. K. Goldenberg P. Bihler M. Cao J. Fang</p>
    <p>B. D. O. Anderson A. S. Morse Y. R. Yang</p>
    <p>Los Angeles September 27, 2006</p>
    <p>Yale University</p>
    <p>MOBICOM 2006</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Localization in Sparse Networks using Sweeps</p>
    <p>D. K. Goldenberg P. Bihler M. Cao J. Fang</p>
    <p>B. D. O. Anderson A. S. Morse Y. R. Yang</p>
    <p>Los Angeles September 27, 2006</p>
    <p>Yale University</p>
    <p>MOBICOM 2006</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Localization in Sparse Networks using Sweeps</p>
    <p>D. K. Goldenberg P. Bihler M. Cao J. Fang</p>
    <p>B. D. O. Anderson A. S. Morse Y. R. Yang</p>
    <p>Los Angeles September 27, 2006</p>
    <p>Yale University</p>
    <p>MOBICOM 2006</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Location necessary in order for sensed data to be meaningful: e.g., Forest fire detection.</p>
    <p>Location information is taken for granted in many network designs: e.g., Geographic routing.</p>
    <p>Equipping each node with GPS is not always feasible due to power constraints and other limitations inherent to sensor networks.</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Localize using inter-node distances!</p>
    <p>Nodes can often measure their distances to nearby nodes: Acoustic ranging (e.g. L. Girod et al.), ultra-wideband ranging (e.g. Ubisense), radio interferometry (e.g. Vanderbilt).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The network localization problem is to determine the positions of all the nodes.</p>
    <p>Anchors are nodes whose positions are known.</p>
    <p>The distances between some nodes are known.</p>
    <p>? ?</p>
    <p>? ?</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>The network is localizable if there exists exactly one position in the plane corresponding to each non-anchor node so that all known inter-node distances are satisfied.</p>
    <p>A network in the plane.</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>A node is localizable if its position is uniquely determined by the known inter-node distances and anchor positions.</p>
    <p>Anchor positions from GPS or manual configuration.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The network localization problem is NP-Hard. (Aspnes et al.)</p>
    <p>The localization problem is solvable if and only if the network is localizable.</p>
    <p>Even assuming exact distance measurements, there is currently no algorithm that can localize a large class of localizable networks without requiring high connectivity while giving correctness guarantees.</p>
    <p>Our contribution  An algorithm that provably and tractably localizes a class of localizable networks with average degree as low as three under the assumption of exact distance measurements.</p>
    <p>Techniques to adapt our algorithm to noisy measurements - No proven results.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A network in the plane whose node position coordinates are algebraically independent over the rationals is localizable if and only if it has at least three non-collinear anchors and its graph is generically globally rigid in the plane. (Eren et al.)</p>
    <p>Consider the network nodes as vertices in a graph.</p>
    <p>There is an edge between two vertices if the distance between the corresponding nodes are known.</p>
    <p>This is the graph of the network.</p>
    <p>There are polynomial time algorithms to determine if a graph is generically globally rigid in the plane.</p>
    <p>Can almost always efficiently check if a network in the plane is localizable by analyzing its graph!</p>
    <p>Assume the node position coordinates of the networks we consider are algebraically independent over the rationals.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Global Approach</p>
    <p>Global optimization susceptible to local minimums.</p>
    <p>Typically assume uniform deployment of nodes.</p>
    <p>May not be effective for networks where average degree is low.</p>
    <p>Nodes are localized by processing all nodes at once.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Nodes are localized by sweeping through the network in some order and processing the nodes one by one.</p>
    <p>Sequential Approach</p>
    <p>Multilateration Trilateration based(Savvides et al.) (e.g. Eren et al., Moore et al.)</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>Our work extends the trilateration based methods in order to localize sparse networks where average degree is as low as three.</p>
    <p>Experimental evaluations suggest trilateration based method is not effective for sparse networks where average degree is low even assuming exact distances.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A graph has a trilateration ordering if its vertices can be relabeled as v1,...,vn so that</p>
    <p>(ii) each vi, i&gt;3, is adjacent to at least three distinct vertices vj, j&lt; i.</p>
    <p>(i) the subgraph induced by {v1,v2,v3} is complete.</p>
    <p>v1, v2, v3 are the seeds of the ordering.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A graph has a trilateration ordering if its vertices can be relabeled as v1,...,vn so that</p>
    <p>(ii) each vi, i&gt;3, is adjacent to at least three distinct vertices vj, j&lt; i.</p>
    <p>(i) the subgraph induced by {v1,v2,v3} is complete.</p>
    <p>v1, v2, v3 are the seeds of the ordering.</p>
    <p>v1</p>
    <p>v2</p>
    <p>v3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A graph has a trilateration ordering if its vertices can be relabeled as v1,...,vn so that</p>
    <p>(ii) each vi, i&gt;3, is adjacent to at least three distinct vertices vj, j&lt; i.</p>
    <p>(i) the subgraph induced by {v1,v2,v3} is complete.</p>
    <p>v1, v2, v3 are the seeds of the ordering.</p>
    <p>v1</p>
    <p>v2</p>
    <p>v3</p>
    <p>v4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A graph has a trilateration ordering if its vertices can be relabeled as v1,...,vn so that</p>
    <p>(ii) each vi, i&gt;3, is adjacent to at least three distinct vertices vj, j&lt; i.</p>
    <p>(i) the subgraph induced by {v1,v2,v3} is complete.</p>
    <p>v1, v2, v3 are the seeds of the ordering.</p>
    <p>v1</p>
    <p>v2</p>
    <p>v3</p>
    <p>v4</p>
    <p>v5</p>
    <p>Suppose this is the graph of a network.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>q1</p>
    <p>q2</p>
    <p>q3</p>
    <p>v1</p>
    <p>v2</p>
    <p>v3</p>
    <p>v4</p>
    <p>v5</p>
    <p>A graph has a trilateration ordering if its vertices can be relabeled as v1,...,vn so that</p>
    <p>(ii) each vi, i&gt;3, is adjacent to at least three distinct vertices vj, j&lt; i.</p>
    <p>(i) the subgraph induced by {v1,v2,v3} is complete.</p>
    <p>v1, v2, v3 are the seeds of the ordering.</p>
    <p>Suppose this is the graph of a network.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>q1</p>
    <p>q2</p>
    <p>q3</p>
    <p>v1</p>
    <p>v2</p>
    <p>v3</p>
    <p>v4</p>
    <p>v5</p>
    <p>A graph has a trilateration ordering if its vertices can be relabeled as v1,...,vn so that</p>
    <p>(ii) each vi, i&gt;3, is adjacent to at least three distinct vertices vj, j&lt; i.</p>
    <p>(i) the subgraph induced by {v1,v2,v3} is complete.</p>
    <p>v1, v2, v3 are the seeds of the ordering.</p>
    <p>Suppose this is the graph of a network.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>q1</p>
    <p>q2</p>
    <p>q3</p>
    <p>v1</p>
    <p>v2</p>
    <p>v3</p>
    <p>v4</p>
    <p>v5</p>
    <p>q4</p>
    <p>A graph has a trilateration ordering if its vertices can be relabeled as v1,...,vn so that</p>
    <p>(ii) each vi, i&gt;3, is adjacent to at least three distinct vertices vj, j&lt; i.</p>
    <p>(i) the subgraph induced by {v1,v2,v3} is complete.</p>
    <p>v1, v2, v3 are the seeds of the ordering.</p>
    <p>Suppose this is the graph of a network.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>q1</p>
    <p>q2</p>
    <p>q3</p>
    <p>v1</p>
    <p>v2</p>
    <p>v3</p>
    <p>v4</p>
    <p>v5</p>
    <p>q4</p>
    <p>q5</p>
    <p>A graph has a trilateration ordering if its vertices can be relabeled as v1,...,vn so that</p>
    <p>(ii) each vi, i&gt;3, is adjacent to at least three distinct vertices vj, j&lt; i.</p>
    <p>(i) the subgraph induced by {v1,v2,v3} is complete.</p>
    <p>v1, v2, v3 are the seeds of the ordering.</p>
    <p>Suppose this is the graph of a network.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A network with three anchors can be localized using just trilaterations followed by an Euclidean transformation if and only if its graph has a trilateration ordering.</p>
    <p>q1</p>
    <p>q2</p>
    <p>q3</p>
    <p>v1</p>
    <p>v2</p>
    <p>v3</p>
    <p>v4</p>
    <p>v5</p>
    <p>q4</p>
    <p>q5</p>
    <p>A graph has a trilateration ordering if its vertices can be relabeled as v1,...,vn so that</p>
    <p>(ii) each vi, i&gt;3, is adjacent to at least three distinct vertices vj, j&lt; i.</p>
    <p>(i) the subgraph induced by {v1,v2,v3} is complete.</p>
    <p>v1, v2, v3 are the seeds of the ordering.</p>
    <p>Suppose this is the graph of a network.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sweeps also identifies all localizable nodes.</p>
    <p>Sweeps is a sequential localization algorithm that provably and tractably localizes a class of sparse localizable networks with average degree as low as three assuming exact distance measurements.</p>
    <p>We propose techniques to deal with noisy measurements, which experimental evaluations suggest is promising, but no proven results.</p>
    <p>We can efficiently check if Sweeps will successfully localize a network by just analyzing the networks graph.</p>
    <p>Experimental evaluations suggest Sweeps is feasible and consistently localizes 90% or more of the nodes in sparse networks of 1000 nodes with average degree five.</p>
    <p>Our work is an extension of the trilateration based localization method for networks whose graphs may not have a trilateration ordering.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(ii) each vi, i&gt;3, is adjacent to at least two distinct vertices vj , j &lt; i.</p>
    <p>(i) the subgraph induced by {v1,v2,v3} is complete.</p>
    <p>A graph has a bilateration ordering if its vertices can be relabeled as v1,...,vn so that</p>
    <p>v1, v2, v3 are the seeds of the ordering.</p>
    <p>v2</p>
    <p>v1</p>
    <p>v3</p>
    <p>v4</p>
    <p>v5</p>
    <p>Sweeps is for localizable networks whose graphs have a bilateration ordering, but not necessarily a trilateration ordering.</p>
    <p>Experimental evaluations suggest such networks occur with high probability even in networks with average degree as low as three.</p>
    <p>No trilateration ordering.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bilateration - Determining a finite candidate positions set for a node using its distances to two or more nodes with finite candidate positions sets.</p>
    <p>Candidate position set of a node is a set of points in the plane which contains the node's position.</p>
    <p>Bilateration with consistency checking is where only a subset of a finite candidate positions set is chosen to use in a bilateration operation.</p>
    <p>{pa p'a} {pb}</p>
    <p>{pc p'c1 p'c2 p'c3}</p>
    <p>If nodes A and B are positioned at pa and pb, then that determines at most two positions for node C, one of which must be the position of node C.</p>
    <p>If nodes A and B are positioned at p'a and pb, then that determines at most two positions for node C.</p>
    <p>A B</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>The algorithm Sweeps consists of performing a sequence of bilaterations and set reductions, combined with consistency checking.</p>
    <p>Bilateration at node c</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Set reduction - Removing points from a node's finite candidate positions set using its distances to one or more nodes with finite candidate positions sets.</p>
    <p>{p2, p'2}</p>
    <p>{p1, p'1}</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>p'2 - p1  d</p>
    <p>p'2 - p'1  d</p>
    <p>Remove point p'2 from the candidate positions set of node 2 because the true position of node 2 must be distance d to at least one point in the candidate positions set of node 1.</p>
    <p>Set reduction with consistency checking reduces a nodes candidate positions set even further using an additional criteria. (See paper for details)</p>
    <p>Set reduction at node 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>pv2</p>
    <p>P</p>
    <p>pv6</p>
    <p>Q</p>
    <p>pv3</p>
    <p>pv1 v1</p>
    <p>v5</p>
    <p>v4</p>
    <p>v6</p>
    <p>v3</p>
    <p>v2</p>
    <p>Sweep through the network according to the bilateration ordering, and perform a bilateration operation at each unlocalized node.</p>
    <p>Localizable network whose graph has a bilateration ordering.</p>
    <p>Sweeps</p>
    <p>This graph does not have a trilateration ordering, so cannot be localized by a trilateration based method!</p>
    <p>Assign positions to seed vertices so their inter-node distances are satisfied.</p>
    <p>This determines a unique position for each vertex relative to the seed vertices.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>pv6</p>
    <p>P</p>
    <p>v1</p>
    <p>v5</p>
    <p>v4</p>
    <p>v6</p>
    <p>v3</p>
    <p>v2</p>
    <p>p1 p2</p>
    <p>p3</p>
    <p>Sweep through the network in a different order performing set reduction at each unlocalized node.</p>
    <p>QSweep through the network according to the bilateration ordering, and perform a bilateration operation at each unlocalized node.</p>
    <p>Localizable network whose graph has a bilateration ordering.</p>
    <p>This graph does not have a trilateration ordering, so cannot be localized by a trilateration based method!</p>
    <p>Assign positions to seed vertices so their inter-sensor distances are satisfied.</p>
    <p>This determines a unique position for each vertex relative to the seed vertices.</p>
    <p>Sweeps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sweep through the network in a different order performing set reduction at each unlocalized node.</p>
    <p>pw6</p>
    <p>pw5</p>
    <p>pv6</p>
    <p>P</p>
    <p>w1</p>
    <p>w6</p>
    <p>w5</p>
    <p>w4</p>
    <p>w3</p>
    <p>w2</p>
    <p>p2</p>
    <p>p3</p>
    <p>p1</p>
    <p>Localizable in two sweeps plus Euclidean transformation.</p>
    <p>QSweep through the network according to the bilateration ordering, and perform a bilateration operation at each unlocalized node.</p>
    <p>Localizable network whose graph has a bilateration ordering.</p>
    <p>This graph does not have a trilateration ordering, so cannot be localized by a trilateration based method!</p>
    <p>Assign positions to seed vertices so their inter-sensor distances are satisfied.</p>
    <p>This determines a unique position for each vertex relative to the seed vertices.</p>
    <p>Sweeps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>There are localizable networks whose graphs do not have bilateration orderings, and so cannot be sweepable.</p>
    <p>A networks graph must have a bilateration ordering for the network to be sweepable.</p>
    <p>Theorem: A localizable network whose graph has a bilateration ordering can be localized with two sweeps followed by a Euclidean transformation.</p>
    <p>We say such networks are sweepable.</p>
    <p>However, experimental evaluations suggest sweepable networks occur with high probability even in networks with average degree as low as three.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>R a</p>
    <p>tio</p>
    <p>Average Degree</p>
    <p>Percentage of localizable nodes localized by Sweeps.</p>
    <p>Percentage of localizable nodes localized by Trilateration.</p>
    <p>Uniformly random 250 node network.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C u</p>
    <p>m u</p>
    <p>la tiv</p>
    <p>e P</p>
    <p>ro p</p>
    <p>o rt</p>
    <p>io n</p>
    <p>o f N</p>
    <p>o d</p>
    <p>e s</p>
    <p>Maximum Size of Candidate Positions Sets</p>
    <p>Worst case complexity of Sweeps is exponential, but experimental evaluations suggest Sweeps is practically feasible.</p>
    <p>Sweeps localizes more nodes than trilateration at the expense of computational complexity.</p>
    <p>At average degrees 3 and 9.5, the maximum size of the candidate positions sets is at most 8 for 95% of the nodes.</p>
    <p>At average degree 6, the maximum size of the candidate positions sets is at most 8 for just 75% of the nodes.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C u</p>
    <p>m u</p>
    <p>la tiv</p>
    <p>e p</p>
    <p>ro p</p>
    <p>o rt</p>
    <p>io n</p>
    <p>o f n</p>
    <p>o d</p>
    <p>e s</p>
    <p>Position Error (% of Sensing Range)</p>
    <p>Proportion of nodes with less than given position error</p>
    <p>Uniformly random deployment of 100 nodes, 5 anchors, average degree 8.</p>
    <p>Zero-mean Gaussian noise with std 5% of sensing range added to distance measurements.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Roadmap Motivation</p>
    <p>Problem Formulation</p>
    <p>Theoretical Foundation Related Work</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
    <p>Experimental Evaluations</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Obtain theoretical results on the effectiveness of Sweeps in the presence of noisy distance measurements.</p>
    <p>Extending sweeps to 3-D.</p>
    <p>Obtain theoretical results relating the probability of a networks graph having bilateration ordering with the average degree of the network.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
