<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Empirical Study of Textual Key-Fingerprint Representations</p>
    <p>Sergej Dechand, Dominik Schrmann, Karoline Busse, Yasemin Acar, Sascha Fahl, Matthew Smith</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Title: Do Users Verify SSH Keys?</p>
    <p>Abstract: No - Peter Gutman, 2011</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Fingerprints</p>
    <p>Mostly not checked</p>
    <p>Error prone</p>
    <p>Partial preimages</p>
    <p>Hard to compare</p>
    <p>Meaningless?</p>
    <p>Still relevant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Goal Which text representation is best?</p>
    <p>High attack detection</p>
    <p>Partial preimages</p>
    <p>Low false positive rate</p>
    <p>Efficient</p>
    <p>Fast comparisons</p>
    <p>Low cognitive load</p>
    <p>Best user perception</p>
    <p>Robust</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tested Representation Schemes</p>
    <p>Hexadecimal 18e2 55fd b51b c808  Base32 ddrf l7nv dpea  Numeric 2016 507 6420 1070  PGP List locale voyager waffle disable  Peerio List bates talking duke slurps  Sentences That lazy snow agrees upon our tall offer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Threat Model Which attacks are feasible?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack Methods</p>
    <p>Ideal: Preimage for an existing key fingerprint  Expensive  Infeasible</p>
    <p>Workaround: Generate partial preimage  Fingerprints almost match (except of a few chars)  Exploit peoples attention limitations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attacker Strength</p>
    <p>Assumptions  The fingerprints include key and metadata  New fingerprints without generating new keys  Only hashing needs to be performed</p>
    <p>80 of 112 bits controlled by attacker  First and last few bits are controlled</p>
    <p>Still high costs to generate partial preimages  Although not impossible</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulated Attacks</p>
    <p>Inverting uncontrolled bits  Inversions within a logical sequence</p>
    <p>Characters  Words  Digits</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Design Controlled experiment followed by a survey</p>
    <p>Conducted on MTurk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Design</p>
    <p>Users compare fingerprints  Match vs. Doesnt match</p>
    <p>Survey with usability questions  Pre-study before setting study parameters  4 tested schemes, factorial design (mixing</p>
    <p>within and between groups)  Hex or Base32  Numeric  PGP or Peerio word list  Sentences</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hexadecimal  Base32  Numeric  OpenPGP Wordlist  Big Wordlist  Sentences</p>
    <p>Experiment Task</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Design</p>
    <p>40 comparisons in randomized order  Avoids fatigue and learning effect  Each scheme attacked once (randomized order)  Higher attack rate leads to higher detection rate</p>
    <p>Attention tests with obvious mismatches  Users failing the attention tests are excluded</p>
    <p>Training sets for each scheme  Reported typo search in language-based schemes  Not considered in the results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Survey</p>
    <p>Survey after finishing all tasks  Rating the schemes  Demographics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>High number of participants required  High attack detection rate  Low differences between some approaches</p>
    <p>No parameter testing  Condition explosion if parameters are tested  Font settings  Chunking  Colors</p>
    <p>Additional experiment testing the chunking</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Controlled experiment and survey</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>1047 participants from MTurk  46 excluded due to failed attention tests  Mixed demographics  No performance differences based on age,</p>
    <p>gender, education</p>
    <p>Relatively high attack detection rate for all schemes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment Results</p>
    <p>Speed (median)</p>
    <p>Undetected Attacks</p>
    <p>False Positives</p>
    <p>Hexadecimal 10s 10.44% 0.5%</p>
    <p>Base32 8.9s 8.50% 2.6%</p>
    <p>Numeric 9.5s 6.34% 0.3%</p>
    <p>PGP Word List 11.2s 8.78% 0.5%</p>
    <p>Peerio Word List 7.3s 5.75% 0.4%</p>
    <p>Sentences 10.7s 2.99% 1.5%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Chunking Results</p>
    <p>Speed (median)</p>
    <p>Undetected Attacks</p>
    <p>False Positives</p>
    <p>Hex 2 11.3s 8.15% 0.38%</p>
    <p>Hex 3 10.3s 6.14% 0.29%</p>
    <p>Hex 4 10.4s 6.78% 0.38%</p>
    <p>Hex 5 11.6s 7.89% 0.78%</p>
    <p>Hex 8 13.6 8.13% 0.5%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Survey Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations</p>
    <p>No guarantee if verification is performed  Validity of MTurk (as with any MTurk study)</p>
    <p>More tech-savvy  Younger  Used to textual and visual tasks</p>
    <p>No tests for additional parameters due to condition explosion  Font settings (type, size, etc.)  Use of colors  Line break settings</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion Takeaways?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Hex has shown the worst performance  Lower attack detection rate  Slower than most approaches  Perceived to be more annoying</p>
    <p>Generated sentences with best results  Highest attack detection rate  Best results regarding usability</p>
    <p>Numeric best non language-based scheme</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
