<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I HAVE NO IDEA WHAT IM DOING  ON THE USABILITY OF DEPLOYING HTTPS Katharina Krombholz, Wilfried Mayer, Martin Schmiedecker, Edgar Weippl</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I HAVE NO IDEA WHAT IM DOING</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I HAVE NO IDEA WHAT IM DOING</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I HAVE NO IDEA WHAT IM DOING</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation and Goals</p>
    <p>Explore reasons for TLS misconfigurations  usability from the administrators perspective</p>
    <p>Study Task: Configure HTTPS on Apache o HTTP -&gt; HTTPS o get a certificate o integration, hardening o testing o done!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>source: (mis)adventures in setting up HTTPS by Yan Zhu https://www.youtube.com/watch ?v=Q0VdlLG7t1w</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Study  The Experts Perspective</p>
    <p>Lab study with 28 knowledgeable participants  Expert interviews with 7 security auditors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lets Encrypt</p>
    <p>Eases the interaction with the CA  Hardening and integration still needs to be done at</p>
    <p>least once  Our study focuses on integration and hardening</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology - Data Collection</p>
    <p>Questionnaire</p>
    <p>N=117  Multiple choice  Top 30</p>
    <p>candidates were invited to participate in the study</p>
    <p>Study</p>
    <p>N=28  Think-aloud</p>
    <p>protocol  Bash/browser</p>
    <p>history  VM images</p>
    <p>Questionnaire</p>
    <p>N=28  Open/closed</p>
    <p>ended questions</p>
    <p>Demographics, previous experience</p>
    <p>Interviews</p>
    <p>N=7  Semi</p>
    <p>structured interviews</p>
    <p>Ecological validity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lab Study - Participants</p>
    <p>N=28  Gender: 2 female, 26 male  Experienced admins: 17  configured TLS before: 17</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Analysis</p>
    <p>Observation protocols: Qualitative analysis with open/axial/selective coding</p>
    <p>Bash/browser history, Apache log files: o Quantitative analysis o Metrics based on Qualys SSL Test (grades A-F)</p>
    <p>Statistical significance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Evaluation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Evaluation</p>
    <p>Only 4 participants deployed an A grade configuration (25%)</p>
    <p>15 deployed a B grade configuration (67%)  4 participants did not manage to deploy any valid</p>
    <p>configuration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Evaluation</p>
    <p>Only 4 participants deployed an A grade configuration (25%)</p>
    <p>15 deployed a B grade configuration (67%)  4 participants did not manage to deploy any valid</p>
    <p>configuration</p>
    <p>(Source: SSLPulse)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Evaluation</p>
    <p>2 participants used self-signed certificates  No participant chose a key size smaller than 2048 for</p>
    <p>their RSA key  forward secrecy: 14  HSTS headers: 11  HPKP: 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TLS Deployment Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TLS Deployment ModelLets Encrypt</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perceptions of Usability</p>
    <p>Finding the best-practice workflow is hard (19)  Misleading terminology (15)  Weak default configuration (12)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Online Sources</p>
    <p>(P23)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Online Sources</p>
    <p>The configuration process is fiddly and one has to google tons of pages to get it right. Even then one</p>
    <p>cannot be sure to have a good configuration because vulnerabilities are discovered almost on a regular</p>
    <p>basis. (P9)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Online Sources</p>
    <p>Average number of visited websites: 60  Number of visited websites had no impact on the</p>
    <p>quality of the resulting configuration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Online Sources</p>
    <p>Decision-making process is mostly based on online sources</p>
    <p>No in-depth understanding of underlying fundamentals o e.g. choosing cipher suites</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Impact of prior experience</p>
    <p>There is an association between prior experience and quality of the resulting configuration</p>
    <p>No evidence that previous employment impacts configuration quality</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Confusing File Structure and Terminology</p>
    <p>Configuring virtual host and port is time consuming  Apache configuration files are perceived as</p>
    <p>confusing and as a distraction from the main task  Multiple configuration files and options</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More Usability Challenges</p>
    <p>High effort for hardening  Confusion: Is the site still reachable via HTTP?  Finding the right balance between security and</p>
    <p>compatibility</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interviews with Security Auditors</p>
    <p>Goal: confirm the ecological validity of our results  Participants: 7 security auditors</p>
    <p>o from well-respected security consulting firms o with experience as security auditor &gt; 2 years</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interviews with Security Auditors</p>
    <p>Auditing TLS connections o Activated versions? o Activated cipher suites? o Cert recognized by web browsers? o HSTS, key pinning etc.</p>
    <p>Tools: o Qualys SSL Test o NMap o Nessus modules o OpenVAS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Configurations in the Wild</p>
    <p>poor ciphers  no hardening  self-signed certificates  Two auditors had never seen HTTPS public key</p>
    <p>pinning during an audit</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Configurations in the Wild</p>
    <p>Administrators who are afraid of using crypto  TLS deployment was not sufficiently streamlined in</p>
    <p>companies o Multiple servers  updated separately o Varying configurations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Compatibility</p>
    <p>In most cases backward compatibility is the showstopper regarding proper TLS configurations (E3)</p>
    <p>.. Sometimes just a mock argument  But finding the best fit is hard, even for experts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Suggested improvements</p>
    <p>Lets Encrypt  Security by default (Caddy web server)  Compatibility flags  Guidelines: deploy everything that doesnt impact</p>
    <p>compatibility: e.g. HSTS  HTTPS should fully replace HTTP  Concept of having CAs is flawed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Configuring TLS on Apache is a challenging task, even for experienced users and we should take this serious!</p>
    <p>Administrators struggle with important security decisions</p>
    <p>Concerns are mainly driven by compatibility  Hard to find reliable information sources</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
