<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Toby Lauinger, Abdelberi Chaabane, Ahmet S. Buyukkayhan,</p>
    <p>Kaan Onarlioglu, William Robertson</p>
    <p>Game of Registrars: An Empirical Analysis of</p>
    <p>Post-Expiration Domain Name Takeovers</p>
    <p>Usenix Security 2017</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Internet Domain Names</p>
    <p>Used in many, often security-critical ways</p>
    <p>Typically, assumption of constant ownership  However, hundreds of thousands of domains expire every day</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Attacks Involving Expired Domains</p>
    <p>Abuse of residual trust  Schlamp et al., The Abandoned Side of the Internet (2014)</p>
    <p>Re-register domains to take over email addresses used to manage critical resources (e.g., IP prefix or AS)</p>
    <p>Lever et al., Domain-Z (2016)  Take over software update/repository servers  Take over name servers used by non-expired domains</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Attacks Involving Expired Domains</p>
    <p>Abuse of residual trust  Schlamp et al., The Abandoned Side of the Internet (2014)</p>
    <p>Re-register domains to take over email addresses used to manage critical resources (e.g., IP prefix or AS)</p>
    <p>Lever et al., Domain-Z (2016)  Take over software update/repository servers  Take over name servers used by non-expired domains</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Also, Undesirable Behaviour</p>
    <p>When re-registered, domains often not what visitors expect  E.g., formerly useful website turned into spam page</p>
    <p>ICANN:  () websites featuring nothing but advertisements, thus</p>
    <p>leading to a form of Internet graffiti.</p>
    <p>() profit-making abuse of the domain name system  https://www.icann.org/news/announcement-2009-08-12-en</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Also, Undesirable Behaviour</p>
    <p>When re-registered, domains often not what visitors expect  E.g., formerly useful website turned into spam page</p>
    <p>ICANN:  () websites featuring nothing but advertisements, thus</p>
    <p>leading to a form of Internet graffiti.</p>
    <p>() profit-making abuse of the domain name system  https://www.icann.org/news/announcement-2009-08-12-en</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Contribution: The Big Picture</p>
    <p>Attack potential known, but how many opportunities?  Quantification of domain name recycling; two scenarios:</p>
    <p>Drop-catch: Re-registered instants after general availability  Pre-release: Sold by registrar before general availability</p>
    <p>Frequent and competitive domain takeovers  Impact of this practice on domain registration ecosystem</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Domain Expiration &amp; Takeover Opportunities</p>
    <p>After expiration, two grace periods allow recovery before deletion  See Whois Lost in Translation (IMC 2016) for the details of</p>
    <p>domain expiration states</p>
    <p>Re-register immediately when deleted (drop-catch)  Old registrar: sell before deletion (pre-release)</p>
    <p>time</p>
    <p>expiration date</p>
    <p>auto-renew grace period redemption period pending delete (available)</p>
    <p>domain deleted drop-catchpre-release</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Data Collection Overview</p>
    <p>Drop-catch services and pre-release platforms promote lists of available domains use as seed for measurement</p>
    <p>Whois lookups every 14 days to detect status changes  All listed domains during 4 weeks in July/August 2016</p>
    <p>com net org biz name</p>
    <p>Pre-release total 1.2M 135k 116k 21k 182</p>
    <p>Median/day 43.5k 4.9k 4k 710 7</p>
    <p>com net org biz</p>
    <p>Pending delete total 2.1M 255k 169k 51k</p>
    <p>Median/day 76.4k 9.2k 6.1k 1.7k</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Expiration, Pre-Release and Drop-Catch</p>
    <p>August 2016:  131M .com domains registered  2.2M .com domains deleted after expiration (1.7% of zone)  2.6M .com domains created (new &amp; re-registrations)</p>
    <p>Measurement (28 days):  1.2M .com domains available pre-release; 71k sold  10.1% of deleted .com domains re-registered as drop-catch</p>
    <p>Domain reuse is a frequent phenomenon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Re-Registrations During the Drop</p>
    <p>The drop: Domains deleted (and re-registered) during same daily time span  Re-registration as early as possible hints at significant competition</p>
    <p>.org</p>
    <p>drop begins at 14:30</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Drop-Catch Registrars</p>
    <p>Registries impose rate limits on each registrar  Drop-catch services use multiple registrars to increase</p>
    <p>success rates  DropCatch.com n LLC  Charlemagne 888, LLC, George Washington 888, LLC,</p>
    <p>Napoleon Bonaparte, LLC, ...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Top 3 clusters are well-known drop-catch services  They account for over 75% of all accredited registrars</p>
    <p>(but only 8% of monthly domain creations)</p>
    <p>These clusters have been growing in size  Significant resources are deployed to compete in the drop</p>
    <p>Name Cluster Size %</p>
    <p>DropCatch.com 1252 42.6%</p>
    <p>Pheenix.com 498 16.9%</p>
    <p>SnapNames.com 466 15.8%</p>
    <p>LogicBoxes.com 53 1.8%</p>
    <p>MyDomain.com 43 1.5%</p>
    <p>F e</p>
    <p>b ru</p>
    <p>a ry</p>
    <p>Registrar Clustering</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Cluster Size Domain Registrations</p>
    <p>Large cluster not necessary to create many domains  99.9% of domain creation attempts fail; drop-catch responsible for at least 80%  Drop-catch has large impact on domain registration ecosystem</p>
    <p>F e</p>
    <p>b ru</p>
    <p>a ry</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Discussion &amp; Recommendations</p>
    <p>Results show frequent, professionally organised recycling of domains, expending significant resources</p>
    <p>Security consequences of domain recycling:  Attacks related to residual trust abuse  Annoyance (Internet graffiti)  Pre-release risks (potential to evade registration-time detection)</p>
    <p>Recommendation: Domain Transparency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEU SECLAB</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Take-away points:  Domain-based trust mechanisms should anticipate ownership changes</p>
    <p>as a common, expected event.</p>
    <p>Anti-abuse tools may need improved detection of ownership changes that are not re-registrations.</p>
    <p>Paper-exclusive material:  Drop-catch domain tasting, auctions and prices, age and traffic  More on pre-release, drop-catch registrar characteristics &amp; arms race...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Secure Systems Lab https://seclab.ccs.neu.edu/</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
