<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>When the Weakest Link is Strong: Secure Collaboration in the Case of the Panama Papers</p>
    <p>Susan E. McGregor Columbia Journalism School</p>
    <p>USENIX Security 2017</p>
    <p>Franziska Roesner University of Washington</p>
    <p>This work is supported in part by the National Science Foundation under Awards CNS-1513575, CNS-1513875, and CNS-1513663.</p>
    <p>Elizabeth Anne Watkins Columbia University</p>
    <p>Kelly Caine Clemson University Mahdi Nasrullah Al-Ameen Clemson University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Failure is common in computer security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>And users are often implicated</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How do we transform this narrative?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>~400 journalists  &gt;120 news organizations  &gt;2.5TB of leaked documents  Led by the International Consortium of</p>
    <p>Investigative Journalists (ICIJ).</p>
    <p>Case Study</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Journalism, computer</p>
    <p>security and human factors</p>
    <p>experts</p>
    <p>In-depth interviews with all ICIJ team members on the project (5)</p>
    <p>Analysis of 118 survey responses from participating journalists</p>
    <p>Our Team | Our Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Over the year-long investigation, this diverse and globally-distributed group maintained key security goals:</p>
    <p>Protecting the source of the data  Maintaining control of the documents and preventing</p>
    <p>their early disclosure  Maintaining access to the documents for</p>
    <p>collaborators and protecting them from attackers  Keeping the project secret</p>
    <p>The Panama Papers Security: What We Know</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>To the best of ICIJ's knowledge, they met their own security goals. We note, however, that:</p>
    <p>We cannot know definitively that there were zero security compromises</p>
    <p>These systems/approaches aren't perfect  Seeking expert advice (as ICIJ did) and following</p>
    <p>best practices is always essential; threats and capacities will change</p>
    <p>The Panama Papers Security: What We Dont Know</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Blacklight document search platform</p>
    <p>Background: ICIJs Collaboration Systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Global I-Hub forum</p>
    <p>Background: ICIJs Collaboration Systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Linkurious network visualization</p>
    <p>Background: ICIJs Collaboration Systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Not entire governments, but implicated politicians</p>
    <p>Companies whose activities were revealed</p>
    <p>Other newsrooms</p>
    <p>Criminals</p>
    <p>Findings: Threat Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data and document systems were centralized in order to support the scale and control requirements of the project</p>
    <p>All systems relied on well-tested HTTPS</p>
    <p>Findings: System Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Though designers considered approaches like CryptDB they had concerns about its efficacy for their use case, and about the maturity/support for the system</p>
    <p>Keeping system URLs secret was essential, as they lacked the resources to handle DDoS attacks.</p>
    <p>Findings: System Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>At the start of the project Findings: Security Technology Use</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>By the end of the project Findings: Security Technology Use</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multiple forms of two-factor were considered, including:</p>
    <p>Virtual machines  Browser extensions  Smartphone app</p>
    <p>Findings: System Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In the 3 months prior to publication Findings: ICIJ Technology Use</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Blacklight document search platform Global I-Hub forum</p>
    <p>Both platforms required two-factor for every sign-on!</p>
    <p>Findings: ICIJ Technology Use</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>And yet... Findings: Security Technology Use</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Usable, flexible security protocols can help minimize the use of workarounds</p>
    <p>For colleagues who are not that experienced with PGP or Signal or whatever...[the I-Hub is] a good way to write secure emails or messages to each other.</p>
    <p>Takeaway</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The fact that these tools helped journalists complete core job tasks made the relatively stringent security requirements an acceptable tradeoff.</p>
    <p>Takeaway</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings: ICIJ Technology Use</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Collaboration and communitybuilding was an explicit goal for the system designers</p>
    <p>Adapted I-Hub from the open-source social network Oxwall in part because of its community-oriented features</p>
    <p>Findings: Collaboration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>As one ICIJ editor described it:</p>
    <p>You cannot collaborate on email, or encrypted email, or Signal. You need a real space that feels comfortable and friendly and its colorful, and [I-Hub] was.</p>
    <p>You can upload files, you can like a topic...that simple kind of liking thing also helped reporters bond together and encourage one another. it just helped tremendously with providing a sense of team.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings: ICIJ Technology Use</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In every editorial note I would write, I would remind [contributors] about some security measure, how it takes one of us to make a mistake for the whole thing to basically fall to hell, and you would lose an entire year of work, and we would bea joke basically. Nobody would ever come to us again with any confidential information. So, I would remind them so they didnt feel comfortable and too confident.</p>
    <p>Findings: Ongoing Emphasis on Security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Normalize security practices and establish secure defaults</p>
    <p>In this project we just routinely encrypted everything we wrote...Because we were just used to doing it and that helped us a lot as a team, that we understood that its not such a big thing, its not such a pain in the assbut youre always on the safe side of it.</p>
    <p>Takeaway</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>One of the most-valued system features -- batch search on Blacklight -- was suggested by a user.</p>
    <p>Findings: User Involvement</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Open communications between technologists and users is key</p>
    <p>Its great, its just software that is designed for journalists. . . and thats all we care about.</p>
    <p>Takeaway</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cultivate organizational commitment to sustainable technology solutions</p>
    <p>There is a tendency... to have this kind of quick solution and where it puts the load of the problem onto staff.Selling [long-term technical solutions] is a little difficult to directors But when you do implement it, it works beautifully I think, and becomes an example to other organizations.</p>
    <p>Takeaway</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We worked closely with ICIJ to understand the systems and processes they used to achieve support &amp; adoption for strong security protocols in the Panama Papers project through:  Building security buy-in and resource dedication from</p>
    <p>both editorial and technology personnel  Actively engaging with users to ensure secured systems</p>
    <p>were as useful as possible  Normalizing secure, flexible defaults with applicability</p>
    <p>beyond the immediate project  Seeking professional security advice and treating</p>
    <p>security as an ongoing effort</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>This work would not have been possible without the support of the following:</p>
    <p>ICIJ editors and Data Team  The Panama Papers journalists and survey participants  Paper shepherd and session chair Adrienne Porter Felt  NSF Awards CNS-1513575, CNS-1513875, and</p>
    <p>CNS-1513663  Advisory board for NSF project:</p>
    <p>Sarah Cohen, Bryan Ford, Roxana Geambasu, Angela Sasse and Trevor Timm</p>
    <p>Thanks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>When the Weakest Link is Strong: Secure Collaboration in the Case of the Panama Papers</p>
    <p>Susan E. McGregor Columbia Journalism School</p>
    <p>USENIX Security 2017</p>
    <p>Franziska Roesner University of Washington</p>
    <p>This work is supported in part by the National Science Foundation under Awards CNS-1513575, CNS-1513875, and CNS-1513663.</p>
    <p>Elizabeth Anne Watkins Columbia University</p>
    <p>Kelly Caine Clemson University Mahdi Nasrullah Al-Ameen Clemson University</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
