<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TRANSCENDING DISCIPLINES, TRANSFORMING LIVES</p>
    <p>A Privacy Analysis of Cross-device Tracking Sebastian Zimmeck, Jie S. Li, Hyungtae Kim, Steven M. Bellovin, Tony Jebara</p>
    <p>Vancouver, BC, Canada</p>
    <p>August 17, 2017</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is cross-device tracking?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is cross-device tracking?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Talk Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>google.com; buy pet food - Google Search</p>
    <p>m.petsmart.com; PetSmart</p>
    <p>google.com; buy watch - Google Search</p>
    <p>m.homedepot.com; Top Freezer Refrigerators</p>
    <p>amazon.com; search for refrigerator</p>
    <p>samsung.com; Galaxy TabPro S - 2-in-1 Tablet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A. Mobile Device Identification</p>
    <p>B. Similarity (s) Calculation</p>
    <p>C. Find max s &gt; Threshold t</p>
    <p>D. Add device pair to graph</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Feature Mapping based on Bhattacharyya Coefficient (could also use Jaccard, Cosine, )</p>
    <p>Feature Mapping</p>
    <p>Precision Recall F-1</p>
    <p>Stage 1 Mob IPs to Desk IPs</p>
    <p>Stage 2 Mob URLs to Desk URLs</p>
    <p>Stage 3 Mob Apps to Desk URLs</p>
    <p>Stage 1-3 Same as above 0.88 0.95 0.91</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Feature Mapping</p>
    <p>Bhatta F-1, Threshold (s)</p>
    <p>Cosine F-1, Threshold (s)</p>
    <p>Jaccard F-1, Threshold (s)</p>
    <p>Stage 2 Mob URLs to Desk URLs</p>
    <p>There is a tradeoff between reach vs. correctness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Predicting interest in finance improves if both mobile and desktop domains are available</p>
    <p>Logistic Regression Orange: positive predictions, i.e., users have interest in finance Blue: negative predictions, i.e., user do not have such interest</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Detailed results for predicting interest in finance; same trend for predicting value shoppers, but not for gender (interesting observation for predicting religion)</p>
    <p>Precision Recall F-1 ROC</p>
    <p>A. Mob  91 Features</p>
    <p>B. Desk  107 Features</p>
    <p>C. Desk  2,923 Features</p>
    <p>D. Mob &amp; Desk  108 Features</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We identified 124 cross-device trackers (that is, trackers (1) occurring on both mobile app/web and desktop web (2) belonging to companies who disclose on their website that they engage in cross-device tracking)</p>
    <p>118 trackers that appeared on both mobile and desktop websites and six software development kits associated with a desktop tracker</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Self-regulation by Digital Advertising Alliance (DAA) and Network Advertising Initiative, particularly, DAA Guidance</p>
    <p>We manually checked for 40 randomly selected cross-device ad networks (DAA members) whether their privacy policies disclose cross-device tracking</p>
    <p>17 omitted mentioning cross-device tracking at all</p>
    <p>As we contacted those received a response from seven (two pointed us to other documents. One explained that their cross-device functionality is not yet fully rolled out. Three others announced that they will change their policy. One simply claimed that they are not violating anything.)</p>
    <p>Five silently changed their policies and are compliant.</p>
    <p>Results as of June 9, 2017</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>sebastian@sebastianzimmeck.de</p>
    <p>We gratefully acknowledge partial funding for this study received from Comcast, DARPA, and NSF. The views and conclusions herein are our own.</p>
    <p>Dataset and Cross-device Tracking Software: https://github.com/SebastianZimmeck/Cross_Device_Tracking Paper: https://www.usenix.org/conference/usenixsecurity17/technical-sessions/presentation/zimmeck</p>
    <p>Cross-device tracking is tracking in the IoT space</p>
    <p>This form of tracking has substantial privacy implications in need to be further explored</p>
    <p>A personalized privacy assistant?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
