<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rewarding Users for Stronger Passwords: Linking Password</p>
    <p>Lifetime to Strength Ingolf Becker, Simon Parkin, M. Angela Sasse</p>
    <p>University College London 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Old Policy</p>
    <p>150 days fixed expiration  Exactly 8 characters  Last 10 passwords are not</p>
    <p>allowed  3 out of:</p>
    <p>Lowercase character  Uppercase character  Numbers  Symbols</p>
    <p>New Policy</p>
    <p>Variable expiration  8-30 characters  Cant be the same as previous  3 out of:</p>
    <p>Lowercase character  Uppercase character  Numbers  Symbols</p>
    <p>Discount if substring part of a 306k dictionary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Strength calculation  Shannon information</p>
    <p>entropy  Not a good measure of</p>
    <p>guessing resistance (see Weir et al., 2010 and de Carnavalet and Mannan, 2014)</p>
    <p>But entropy is still widely used!</p>
    <p>50 bits get you 100 day,  120 bits get you 350 days</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The environment  Single Sign On (ish), eduroam,</p>
    <p>Computer room / library machines  Large research university</p>
    <p>20k undergraduates accounts  30k postgraduate accounts  20k research/admin staff accounts  100k alumni accounts 4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The data  Pseudo-anonymised log</p>
    <p>data  16 months of data  3 million interactions</p>
    <p>with the password change system</p>
    <p>200k password changes  115k password resets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Password expiration over time for the whole university</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Frequency of changes and resets over time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Changes and Resets  66% of users had to reset their passwords  On average, 1.1 resets per user, 2.4 changes per user  Reasons for resetting:</p>
    <p>Forgotten password; expired password  Cost of a reset is significantly higher than a change</p>
    <p>requires either physical presence at help desk or using a phone-based reset system  Strong positive correlation between password strength and likelihood of reset</p>
    <p>before expiration (Spearmans  = 0.95, p&lt;10-15)  A user with 300 days lifetime is 4 times as likely to forget their password than a user with</p>
    <p>a lifetime of 100 days  The more password resets, the weaker the password choice.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Password lifetime by number of resets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Frequency of changes and resets per user</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Frequency of password changes relative to password expiration (day 0)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User feedback  Qualitative feedback from 93 users in early 2017  Users:</p>
    <p>Appreciated the flexibility of the new system  If they noticed the change in policy  Difficult to create a password that is not weak</p>
    <p>Even though I could remember it wasnt practically very helpful if you have to put in you know twenty characters. Its not great. So then I changed it to something that was shorter and last a little less time I just could remember that. 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion  Intervention clearly successful  users choose stronger</p>
    <p>passwords  How long should one measure an intervention?</p>
    <p>Took a long time to gain traction, still ongoing  Not a useful intervention:</p>
    <p>100 day password is already strong enough to withstand an online attack (106 guesses)</p>
    <p>350 day password is not strong enough to withstand an offline attack (1014 guesses)  (Florncio, Herley and Van Oorschot 2014)</p>
    <p>Stronger passwords -&gt; higher reset frequency 15</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions  Studied a novel password policy:</p>
    <p>Stronger password longer lifetime at a University with 100k users for over 16 months</p>
    <p>Users play the game: all user groups choose stronger passwords over time</p>
    <p>More than 1 reset / year costs password strength  Security benefit negligible</p>
    <p>Maybe dynamic lifetime for online attackable passwords (&lt;106 guesses), but no expiration for stronger passwords</p>
    <p>We are continuing to work with our IT services</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
