<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Unveiling and Quantifying Facebook Exploitation of</p>
    <p>Sensitive Personal Data for Advertising Purposes</p>
    <p>Jos Gonzlez Cabaas ngel Cuevas Rubn Cuevas</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>How many people in Europe were assigned with sensitive personal information in the context of the GDPR definition of sensitive data?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Processing of personal data revealing racial or ethnic origin, political opinions, religious or philosophical beliefs, or trade union membership, and the processing of genetic data, biometric data for the purpose of uniquely identifying a natural person, data concerning health or data concerning a natural persons sex life or sexual orientation shall be prohibited</p>
    <p>Collect sensitive data of the users without obtaining their explicit consent. Indeed, no specific information on the sensitive nature of the data is provided to users when they complete their profiles with such data</p>
    <p>The data on ideology, sex, religious beliefs, personal preferences or browsing activity are collected directly, through interaction with their services or from third party pages without clearly informing the user about how and for what purpose will use those data. Facebook does not obtain unambiguous, specific and informed consent from users to process their data since the information it offers is not adequate</p>
    <p>Article 9 GDPR regulates Sensitive Data use</p>
    <p>French DPA fined FB 150K in May. 2017</p>
    <p>Spanish DPA fined FB 1.2M in Sep. 2017 (before GDPR)</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dataset</p>
    <p>Data * Oct 16  Oct 17</p>
    <p>* Cabaas, J.G., Cuevas, ., Cuevas R. FDVT: Data Valuation Tool for Facebook users. In Proceedings of the 2017 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (Denver, CO, USA, 2017), ACM, pp. 37993809.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Classification of each interest as sensitive or not</p>
    <p>Unfeasible to manually label 126K interests  Subset of likely sensitive interests</p>
    <p>Automatic detection of likely sensitive interests  High semantic similarity with at least one of the 5 sensitive categories  List of 264 keywords mapping 5 sensitive categories  Sematic similarity computed using Spacy package</p>
    <p>Methodology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dataset reduction</p>
    <p>similarity value</p>
    <p>C D</p>
    <p>F</p>
    <p>Threshold = 0.6</p>
    <p>Methodology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>12 panellists were given contextual information for classification  In 1 of the 5 sensitive categories  Or in other or not known</p>
    <p>Each interests received 5 votes  We use majority voting to classify interests as sensitive</p>
    <p>At least 3 votes as sensitive</p>
    <p>Methodology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>How many people in France are interested in Communism OR Islam OR Veganism</p>
    <p>How many users in a given country are interested in ad preference 1 OR ad preference 2 OR ad preference 3... OR ad preference N</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Between 1/3 and 2/3 of citizens for each country are assigned with some potentially sensitive interest</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FB users</p>
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Citizens in the EU assigned with some of the 20 interests list: 23%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reason of assignment of an interest</p>
    <p>Very few cases (0.03%) in which users proactively include potentially sensitive interests in their list of ad preferences</p>
    <p>Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AD Campaigns</p>
    <p>Religion: Islam, Judaism, Christianity, Buddhism  Politics: Communism, Anarchism, Radical feminism, Socialism  Sexuality: Transsexualism, Homosexuality</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hate campaigns  Neo-Nazi organization targeting</p>
    <p>people interested in Judaism or Homosexuality</p>
    <p>Identification attack  Phishing-like attack with sexy ads  Ball-park estimation cost of</p>
    <p>identification  35 reach 26k users  Attack success rate 9% (from</p>
    <p>literature)  0.015 per user (even with 0.9%</p>
    <p>cost is 1.5)</p>
    <p>Risks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Impact</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Impact</p>
    <p>The ICO accepts that indicating a person is interested in a topic is not the same as formally placing them within a special personal information category. However, a risk clearly exists that advertisers will use core audience categories in a way that does seek to target individuals based on sensitive personal information. In the context of this investigation, the ICO is particularly concerned that such categories can be used for political advertising.</p>
    <p>The ICO believes that this is part of a broader issue about the processing of personal information by online platforms in the use of targeted advertising; this goes beyond political advertising. It is clear from academic research conducted by the University of Madrid on this topic that a significant privacy risk can arise. For example, advertisers were using these categories to target individuals with the assumption that they are, for example, homosexual. Therefore, the effect was that individuals were being singled out and targeted on the basis of their sexuality.</p>
    <p>ICO Report</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Facebook should avoid labelling users with sensitive information (at least obvious sensitive) unless they obtain a clear consent from users</p>
    <p>This may avoid Facebook running afoul of Article 9 of the GDPR  It may protect users from threats that exploit this sensitive data.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>After GDPR analysis</p>
    <p>Removed 17 interests out from the 2092 sensitive</p>
    <p>Communism  Islam  Quran  Socialism  Christianity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Unveiling and Quantifying Facebook Exploitation of</p>
    <p>Sensitive Personal Data for Advertising Purposes</p>
    <p>Jos Gonzlez Cabaas ngel Cuevas Rubn Cuevas</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
