<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cost-based labeling of groups of mass spectra</p>
    <p>SIGMOD Conference 2004</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Problem formulation</p>
    <p>Proposed Algorithms</p>
    <p>Theoretical cost analysis</p>
    <p>Experimental results and discussion</p>
    <p>Comments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Working of Aerosol Time of Flight Mass Spectrometer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mass Spectrum Labeling</p>
    <p>A time series of observations, one per collected particle, where each observation is a set of labels (ion-quantity pair)</p>
    <p>A time series of transactions, each recording the items purchased by a customer while visiting the store.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Formulation  A mass spectrum can be represented as a normalized vector b, where i bi = 1 and bi is the relative signal intensity at m/z value i.</p>
    <p>The signature of an ion is a vector s, such that i si = 1, representing the distribution of its isotopes, i.e., si is the relative abundance of isotopes with m/z value i.  A signature library is a set of signatures S = { s1, s2, ..., sn} where sj is the signature of chemical ion j.  If we arrange the n signatures in the signature library in order, the signature library can be represented as a matrix A = [s1, s2, ..., sn], where the kth column in matrix A presents signature k. The labeling task consists of finding an ndimensional vector x such that x[j] is the relative abundance of chemical ion j.</p>
    <p>Ax =b, x  0 To account for noise, measurement errors and calibration discrepancies define a</p>
    <p>distance function D and error bound E, then the solution space of spectrum b is Lb = {a | D(Aa,b) &lt; E and a  0}</p>
    <p>The solution can be found using the LP model</p>
    <p>min i si s.t (Aa - b) s and (Aa - b) -s where a0,s 0</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solution to the Problem  The LP model has infinite number of solutions  We care about solutions which are significantly different  How to deal with continuous infinite space??</p>
    <p>DISCRETIZATION</p>
    <p>A threshold vector T = { t1, t2, ..., td} divides each dimension of the search space into d ranges and the index vector I = { &lt;l1, h1&gt;, &lt;l2 ,h2&gt;, ...,&lt;ln ,hn&gt;}</p>
    <p>The of SINGLE spectrum labeling reduces to subspace searching (Zheng Huang et al)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Group Spectrum labeling  A group of spectra that is collected at a single location</p>
    <p>over a short time-span is likely be similar.  Given a group of spectra {bi} we can find a label set {Li}</p>
    <p>which consist of labels of the form {xi} each of length n</p>
    <p>Define support(x) = |{Li | xi  Li }|/| Li |</p>
    <p>Group label : Given a group of spectra B = {bi} and a threshold Min Sup, x is a group label if the support of x w.r.t. B is greater than Min Sup.</p>
    <p>HOW TO SOLVE THIS???</p>
    <p>MINING FREQUENT PATTERNS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method1: DFS Voting Algorithm</p>
    <p>Depth First Search(subspace S)</p>
    <p>if (is feasible(S))</p>
    <p>RETURN</p>
    <p>else</p>
    <p>if (S is a cell) // cell corresponds to the finest granularity</p>
    <p>output the corresponding label of S</p>
    <p>else</p>
    <p>pick dimension(j)</p>
    <p>split S into a set of subspaces {Si} s.t. each Si is not divisible on dimension j</p>
    <p>for each result subspace Si</p>
    <p>Depth First Search(Si)</p>
    <p>end for</p>
    <p>DFSVoting( Si,C)</p>
    <p>C = {b|b  C, S is feasible w.r.t. b}</p>
    <p>|C|&lt; Min_Sup*w</p>
    <p>DFSVoting(subspace S,set of spectra C)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method 2: Candidate Generation and Test GenTest</p>
    <p>L = {} B0 = {(1  Min Sup) * w + 1 spectra randomly chosen from B}</p>
    <p>for each b in B0</p>
    <p>Find Fi, the label set of b</p>
    <p>L = L U Fi</p>
    <p>for each label l in Fi</p>
    <p>l.count++</p>
    <p>for each spectrum b in B  B0</p>
    <p>for each l in L</p>
    <p>if l is a label for the b</p>
    <p>l.count++;</p>
    <p>for each label l in L</p>
    <p>if (l.count &gt; Min Sup * w)</p>
    <p>output l as a solution group label</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cost Analysis  Estimate the effect of various inputs on the overall cost of the algorithm</p>
    <p>Study the characteristics of the data / input w.r.t to the algorithm</p>
    <p>Notations:</p>
    <p>CSingle Cost of labeling a single spectrum CSingle = d*(n-1)*m</p>
    <p>CVoting Cost of DFSVoting algorithm CGenTest Cost of GenTest algorithm CGenTest = CSingle*(w  t + 1)+(t  1) * m *((1  s/w ) *(w  t + 1) +</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithm profile</p>
    <p>Algorithm choice depends on the choice of Min_Sup value</p>
    <p>Algorithm choice also depends on s</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Decision Plot</p>
    <p>The boundary between the two regions corresponds to the intersection points between the two methods in the algorithm profile</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Graph</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results and Discussion</p>
    <p>How close are the derived estimates based on cost metrics to experimental results?</p>
    <p>How good is the cost estimation in terms of deriving the right decision plot?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results and Discussion</p>
    <p>How good is the theoretically derived decision plot in making decisions regarding algorithm selection</p>
    <p>The differences observed were found to be tolerable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comments</p>
    <p>Problem formulation in data mining framework</p>
    <p>Evaluation of different algorithms</p>
    <p>Algorithm profiling and cost based optimization</p>
    <p>Analogy to market basket analysis</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
