<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Empirical</p>
    <p>An Empirical Analysis of Anonymity in Zcash</p>
    <p>George Kappos, Haaroon Yousaf, Mary Maller, Sarah Meiklejohn</p>
    <p>University College London</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity(?) in cryptocurrencies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity(?) in cryptocurrencies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>But that didnt work out very well</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>But that didnt work out very well</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>But that didnt work out very well</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some better approaches  DASH</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some better approaches  DASH</p>
    <p>Dash is based on CoinJoin transactions</p>
    <p>CoinJoin suffers from availability problems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some better approaches - Monero</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some better approaches - Monero</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What about Zcash?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What about Zcash?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What about Zcash?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Zcash in a nutshell</p>
    <p>2 types of addresses: 1. Transparent t-address 2. Private z-address</p>
    <p>The set of z-addresses is a shielded pool</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Contributions</p>
    <p>Performed a blockchain analysis on Zcash</p>
    <p>Created clusters of users based on t-to-t transactions</p>
    <p>Defined and implemented new heuristics that deanonymized 69.1% of transactions interacting with the shielded pool</p>
    <p>Used our heuristics to investigate the activity of a hacker collective in Zcash (the Shadow Brokers, see paper)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interactions in Zcash</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interactions in Zcash</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transparent transactions (t-to-t)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transparent transactions (t-to-t)</p>
    <p>85% of the total transactions</p>
    <p>We clustered addresses belonging to the same logical entity and tagged them</p>
    <p>Exploited the techniques used for Bitcoin</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transparent transactions (t-to-t)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Private transactions (z-to-z)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Private transactions (z-to-z)</p>
    <p>Less than 1% of the total transactions</p>
    <p>Underlying cryptography is still secure</p>
    <p>No obvious deanonymisation techniques</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Private transactions (z-to-z)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Shielded and deshielded transactions (t-to-z &amp; z-to-t)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Who is using the pool?</p>
    <p>Miners 1. Come in 2 flavours, independent and mining pools 2. They get 10 ZEC from each block mined 3. They can be trivially identified as the recipients of coin</p>
    <p>generations</p>
    <p>Founders 1. They get 2.5 ZEC from each block mined 2. Their addresses are publicly known</p>
    <p>Others Individual users, exchanges, wallets, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deposits and Withdrawals</p>
    <p>Almost perfect symmetry</p>
    <p>Pool as a pass-through mechanism</p>
    <p>Interesting spikes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deposits in the shielded pool using trivially identifiable addresses</p>
    <p>Almost 80% of the total deposits come from miners</p>
    <p>Founders however create all the visible steps since they deposit bigger values</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Withdrawals from the shielded pool using trivially identifiable addresses</p>
    <p>Almost 90% of the total withdrawals were unidentifiable using the trivial addresses</p>
    <p>Need for heuristics for tagging addresses and transactions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Founders Behaviour</p>
    <p>Founders almost always deposited 249.999 ZEC into the pool</p>
    <p>But there were 0 withdrawals of this value</p>
    <p>And they never withdrew with their known addresses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Founder deposits and withdrawals of 250.001 ZEC</p>
    <p>We did however find a lot of withdrawals of value 250.001 ZEC!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Heuristic  Identifying Founders</p>
    <p>Any z-to-t transaction carrying 250.001 ZEC in value is done by the founders</p>
    <p>False Positives</p>
    <p>There were only ever 5 deposits into the pool of approximately 250 ZEC that did not come from the founders</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Heuristic  Identifying Founders  Results</p>
    <p>We flagged 1,953 transactions as founders withdrawals</p>
    <p>Identified a big percentage of the shielded pools activity as founder activity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mining pools behaviour</p>
    <p>We investigated more than 15 different pools but 2 were by far the most dominant ones, Flypool and F2Pool</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mining pools behaviour</p>
    <p>There are usually hundreds of recipient addresses!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Heuristic  Identifying Miners</p>
    <p>If a z-to-t transaction has over 100 output t-addresses, one of which belongs to a known mining pool, then we label the transaction as a mining withdrawal (associated with that pool), and label all non-pool output t-addresses as belonging to miners</p>
    <p>False Positives</p>
    <p>The inclusion of a mining pool address makes it unlikely to be a transaction not related to miners</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deanonymization of Hidden Transactions in Zcash, Alex Biryukov, Daniel Feher, University of Luxembourg</p>
    <p>Heuristic  Identifying Miners  Results</p>
    <p>We flagged 110,918 new addresses as miners</p>
    <p>We associated a large part of the shielded pools activity as miner activity</p>
    <p>-And we didnt even capture Flypool! (Other people did)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Capturing everyone Unique deposits-withdrawals</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>J. Quesnelle. On the linkability of Zcash transactions</p>
    <p>Heuristic  Identifying Others</p>
    <p>For a value v, if there exists exactly one t-to-z transaction carrying value v and one z-to-t transaction carrying value v, where the z-to-t transaction happened after the t-to-z one and within some small number of blocks, then these transactions are linked.</p>
    <p>False Positives</p>
    <p>98.9% of the unique values had at least 3 decimal points  The heuristic was implemented prior to our work*</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Keypoints</p>
    <p>Usage of the pool is very limited -Incentives for people to use it?</p>
    <p>Those who do, mostly do it badly -We deanonymized 69.1% of transactions</p>
    <p>The underlying crypto is still secure so Zcash has the potential to provide better anonymity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TTHANK YOU QUESTIONS?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
