<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Sinisa Matetic (ETH Zurich), Moritz Schneider (ETH Zurich), Andrew Miller (UIUC), Ari Juels (Cornell Tech), Srdjan Capkun (ETH Zurich)</p>
    <p>Usenix Security Symposium, August 12-17, 2018, Baltimore, MD, USA</p>
    <p>DelegaTEE: Brokered Delegation using Trusted Execution Environments</p>
    <p>Sinia Mateti</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>|| 17.8.2018Sinia Mateti 2</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>X Motivation  Account sharing with restrictions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>|| 17.8.2018Sinia Mateti 3</p>
    <p>GOOD FROM HERE EXAMPLESMotivation  Account sharing with restrictions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>|| 17.8.2018Sinia Mateti 4</p>
    <p>GOOD FROM HERE EXAMPLESMotivation  Account sharing with restrictions</p>
    <p>Bob really wants to make Alice happy  Bob is fine sharing his account  But, he doesnt really want to reveal his login credentials to Alice and also</p>
    <p>give her unlimited spending capabilities</p>
    <p>(since Bob is very security aware and uses the same password in all web service that he has :D)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>|| 17.8.2018Sinia Mateti 5</p>
    <p>GOOD FROM HERE EXAMPLESMotivation  Account sharing with restrictions</p>
    <p>If only the service would support such a scheme  Applicable to all types of online services and action performed on the web</p>
    <p>Delegation is only possible if directly supported by the service provider</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>|| 17.8.2018Sinia Mateti 6</p>
    <p>DemoSolution  Brokered Delegation</p>
    <p>Bob Alice</p>
    <p>Service</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>OR</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>DelegaTEE: Brokered Delegation using Trusted Execution Environments</p>
    <p>GOOD FROM HERE EXAMPLES</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Enable isolated execution within a users system  ARM Trustzone, Intel SGX,</p>
    <p>Intel SGX  secure enclaves  Runtime isolation, ecall/ocall interfaces, sealing, attestation  Memory content encrypted</p>
    <p>NOTE: Recent work shows successful compromise of such environments  Side-channel attacks, Spectre, Meltdown, Foreshadow (see talks from yesterday)  Patches on the way</p>
    <p>GOOD FROM HERE EXAMPLESTrusted Execution Environments</p>
    <p>Images taken from software.intel.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>A new concept that seems very familiar  Flexibly, securely and selectively share and delegate access (credentials and</p>
    <p>rights)  No explicit support (or even knowledge) of the service providers  Fine-grained delegation without trust between the credential owner and other</p>
    <p>users  Supported with the usage of TEEs  Credential Owners (give access) and Delegatees (receive restricted access)</p>
    <p>GOOD FROM HERE EXAMPLESOur contribution: Brokered Delegation with enclaves</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>The Owners credentials remain confidential.  The Owner can restrict access to his account, e.g., in terms of time, duration</p>
    <p>of access, no. of reads/writes etc. - with rich contextual policies  The system logs the actions of Owners and Delegatees so that post-hoc</p>
    <p>attribution of their behaviour is possible (as a means of resolving disputes)  The system minimizes the ability of a service to distinguish between access</p>
    <p>by the Delegatee and that of the legitimate Owner</p>
    <p>Owner does not have to always be online</p>
    <p>GOOD FROM HERE EXAMPLESDelegaTEE - Challenges and desired properties</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Peer-to-peer system model  Centrally brokered system model</p>
    <p>GOOD FROM HERE EXAMPLESDelegaTEE  two system designs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Owners A1n Delegatee B1n Services G1n</p>
    <p>owner registration 1</p>
    <p>login information acquired</p>
    <p>user registration 1</p>
    <p>login information acquired</p>
    <p>store credentials for Services G1n</p>
    <p>any informal communication channel</p>
    <p>agreement on credential delegation</p>
    <p>establish secure communication</p>
    <p>exchange unique identifiers for the system 4</p>
    <p>Owner Ai Delegatee Bj</p>
    <p>Owner Ai: delegate</p>
    <p>credentials Cx to Bj for service Gk with access control policy Pijxk</p>
    <p>ok 6</p>
    <p>X establish secure communicationavailable delegated credentials7</p>
    <p>if expired, terminate access</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>Centrally Brokered system</p>
    <p>service access* 8 * enforced and constrained under specified</p>
    <p>access control policy in the central system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Trust assumptions and security</p>
    <p>Intel SGX enclaves are trusted for confidentiality and attestation  The Owner is to be fully protected</p>
    <p>Server and the operator per se do not need to be trusted</p>
    <p>System works as trusted a proxy, a man-in-the-middle  End-to-end TLS from enclave-to-delegatee and enclave-to-service</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Delegatee</p>
    <p>PayPal</p>
    <p>Merchant</p>
    <p>Centrally Brokered system</p>
    <p>API enclave</p>
    <p>PayPal enclave</p>
    <p>Owner Username Password</p>
    <p>Policy: - To whom - Restrictions</p>
    <p>DemoCase Study Implementation 1: PayPal</p>
    <p>Confirmation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Case Study Implementation 2: Credit Card - Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Case Study Implementation 3: Email - Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Case Study Implementation 4: General website browsing - Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Performance</p>
    <p>In line with the original performance of the use case scenario  P2P system</p>
    <p>Minimal and negligible overhead  Functions as a local proxy  Supports all provided use-cases</p>
    <p>Centrally Brokered System  Serves all delegation request through a central system  All use cases except video streaming handled almost instantaneously  No. of concurrent users depends on the server hardware</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Brokered Delegation may undermine services policy enforcement</p>
    <p>MAC-to-DAC  Similar to the setuid in Unix systems</p>
    <p>Building secondary markets for any service  Netflix, and any other video streaming service  Paid subscription services, such as news portals, etc.</p>
    <p>Services expect the difficulty of broadly sharing credentials</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Discussion, Challenges and Limitations</p>
    <p>Identity-based model  Anonymous model</p>
    <p>Policy creation and enforcement  Easy for standardized protocols and messages  More difficult for a general use-case example  Curated policy app store for different use cases?</p>
    <p>For more details please see the paper!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Discussion, Challenges and Limitations</p>
    <p>Authentication challenges  Two-step authentication  CAPTCHA</p>
    <p>Authentication Collisions  Usability  Deployment  Service Prevention  Scalability</p>
    <p>For more details please see the paper!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Summary &amp; Conclusion</p>
    <p>Secure and flexible delegation of user access rights and credentials  Applicable for online transactions with password-based authentication</p>
    <p>Can be developed to support brick-and-mortar transactions  No changes needed on the service side  Compatibility with wide range of services  Rise of new sharing economies and business models  A potential game changer? Market disruptor?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>||</p>
    <p>Sinisa Matetic</p>
    <p>ETH Zurich System Security Group Institute of Information Security Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>www.syssec.ethz.ch</p>
    <p>sinisa.matetic@inf.ethz.ch</p>
    <p>ETH Zurich, August 2018</p>
    <p>Thank you for your attention! Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
