<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BlackIoT: IoT Botnet of High Wattage</p>
    <p>Devices Can Disrupt the Power Grid</p>
    <p>Saleh Soltan, Prateek Mittal, H. Vincent Poor</p>
    <p>Department of Electrical Engineering, Princeton University</p>
    <p>USENIX Security18</p>
    <p>August 2018</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Electric Power Systems</p>
    <p>One of the most essential infrastructure systems</p>
    <p>Source: http://www.greatachievements.org/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Major Components of Power Systems</p>
    <p>Generators Transmission</p>
    <p>Network</p>
    <p>Distribution</p>
    <p>Network Loads</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>North America Transmission Network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power Grids SCADA System</p>
    <p>Power Grid</p>
    <p>Physical Infrastructuree</p>
    <p>Supervisory Control and Data</p>
    <p>Acquisition (SCADA) system</p>
    <p>Commands</p>
    <p>Data</p>
    <p>Cyber Attacks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cyber Attack on Ukraine Grids SCADA</p>
    <p>Unplugged 225,000 people from the Ukrainian electricity grid in</p>
    <p>December 2015</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cyber Attacks on U.S. Grid SCADA</p>
    <p>Smaller scale attacks on reginal U.S. grids have been investigated in a</p>
    <p>recent report, April 2018</p>
    <p>Hackers are developing a penchant for attacks on energy infrastructure</p>
    <p>because of the impact the sector has on peoples lives.&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>U.S. Grids SCADA Breaches</p>
    <p>They got to the point where they could have thrown switches and</p>
    <p>disrupted power flows, July 2018</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Grid Cyber Security Efforts</p>
    <p>Previously: the power demand can be predicted reliably on an hourly</p>
    <p>and daily basis</p>
    <p>Now: with growth in the number of Wi-Fi enabled high-wattage</p>
    <p>devices such as air conditioners and heaters, is this still a safe</p>
    <p>assumption?</p>
    <p>Electricity</p>
    <p>Generator</p>
    <p>Transformers</p>
    <p>step up</p>
    <p>voltage</p>
    <p>Transmission</p>
    <p>Network</p>
    <p>Transformers</p>
    <p>step down</p>
    <p>voltage</p>
    <p>Distribution</p>
    <p>Network</p>
    <p>Electricity</p>
    <p>Consumers</p>
    <p>or Loads</p>
    <p>Previous Security Efforts ?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IoT Botnet of High-Wattage Devices</p>
    <p>Smart appliances power usage</p>
    <p>The Mirai botnet  600,000 bots</p>
    <p>A Mirai sized botnet of water heaters</p>
    <p>can change the demand instantly in</p>
    <p>an area by 3000MW!</p>
    <p>Appliance Power Usage (W)</p>
    <p>Air conditioner 1,000</p>
    <p>Space heater 1,500</p>
    <p>Air purifier 200</p>
    <p>Electric water heater 5,000</p>
    <p>Electric oven 4,000</p>
    <p>Similar to having access to the largest</p>
    <p>currently deployed nuclear power plant!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Manipulation of demand via IoT (MadIoT)</p>
    <p>High wattage IoT devices, once compromised, give the adversary a</p>
    <p>unique capability to manipulate the demand in the power grid</p>
    <p>Compromised</p>
    <p>High Wattage</p>
    <p>IoT Devices</p>
    <p>Target of</p>
    <p>the Attack</p>
    <p>Power Grid</p>
    <p>Compromised</p>
    <p>High Wattage</p>
    <p>IoT Devices</p>
    <p>Adversary</p>
    <p>Synchronous On/Off</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tertiary Control</p>
    <p>Consequences of MadIoT Attacks</p>
    <p>Different ways these attacks can disrupt normal operation of the grid:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Causing Frequency Disturbance</p>
    <p>Frequency response of the WSCC 9-bus system after a MadIoT attack</p>
    <p>Effectiveness of an attack depends on the attacks scale as well as the</p>
    <p>systems total inertia at the time of the attack</p>
    <p>Sufficiently large simultaneous increase in the demand can result in a</p>
    <p>significant drop in the systems frequency and cause generation tripping</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Initiating a Cascading Line Failures</p>
    <p>Sequence of line failures after 1% increase in the demand in Polish grid</p>
    <p>Requires access to</p>
    <p>Polish Grid 2008</p>
    <p>Only 1% increase in the</p>
    <p>demand in Polish grid</p>
    <p>cascading line failure</p>
    <p>resulting in 263 line</p>
    <p>failures and 86% outage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cascading Failures (Critical Factor)</p>
    <p>An attack with similar consequences requires at least 10% increase in</p>
    <p>the demand in Polish grid 2004  about 2 million smart ACs</p>
    <p>Histogram of the Polish grid lines</p>
    <p>power flow to capacity ratio in</p>
    <p>Summer 2004 compared to</p>
    <p>Summer 2008</p>
    <p>It is important how saturated the</p>
    <p>powerlines are at the time of an attack</p>
    <p>Attacks resulting in cascading line failures require fewer number of bots</p>
    <p>than the attacks resulting in critical frequency disturbances</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overloading Tie-lines</p>
    <p>Tie-lines connect neighboring countries or states</p>
    <p>Increasing demand at the receiving region and decreasing the demand</p>
    <p>at the sending region of a tie-line (using IP addresses)</p>
    <p>The ratios of tie-lines power</p>
    <p>flows to their nominal capacity 1.5% increase of demand in the</p>
    <p>yellow area and 1.5% decrease of</p>
    <p>demand in the blue area</p>
    <p>By overloading a tie-line, an attacker can force it to trip resulting in</p>
    <p>significant imbalance between supply and demand in two neighboring areas</p>
    <p>and major frequency disturbances  Italy 2003 blackout</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Increasing the Operating Cost</p>
    <p>Increasing the operating cost of the grid by forcing the operator to</p>
    <p>use [expensive] reserve generators</p>
    <p>An adversarys attack may be for the benefit a particular utility in the</p>
    <p>electricity market rather than damaging the infrastructure</p>
    <p>In certain situations, only 5% increase in the demand can result in 20%</p>
    <p>increase in the operating cost</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Required Botnet Size Comparison</p>
    <p>Assuming all the bots are 1000W air conditioners</p>
    <p>Estimates based on only publicly and freely available test grids</p>
    <p>May be different in grids with different characteristics</p>
    <p>More detailed analysis on the effects of MadIoT attacks should be</p>
    <p>performed by system operators</p>
    <p>Substantial number of IoT devices are required to cause a significant</p>
    <p>drop in the frequency of the system</p>
    <p>They should all be in the same geographical region</p>
    <p>ACs have delay in reaching their maximum power (10-15 seconds)</p>
    <p>It is easier to achieve these numbers few years from now</p>
    <p>Adversarys Goal Required Botnet size</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Unique Properties of MadIoT Attacks</p>
    <p>Indirect attacks  no need to access the well-protected (?) SCADA</p>
    <p>Very hard to detect and disconnect by the grid operator  the security</p>
    <p>breach is in the IoT devices, yet the attack is on the power grid</p>
    <p>Easy to repeat  repeat until successful</p>
    <p>Black-box  An adversary does not need to know the underlying</p>
    <p>topology or the detailed operational properties of the grid</p>
    <p>Power grids are not prepared to defend against the MadIoT attacks</p>
    <p>not part of the contingency list</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Countermeasures</p>
    <p>Improving the frequency stability of the system:</p>
    <p>The operators should account for possible attacks and require minimum</p>
    <p>spinning reserve such that grid has enough inertia at the time of an attack</p>
    <p>Devices that provide virtual inertia such as flywheels, batteries, and super</p>
    <p>capacitors can increase the total inertia of the system at a lower cost</p>
    <p>Prevent line failures</p>
    <p>Operate the grid at an operating point such that after any potential attack</p>
    <p>no line gets overloaded</p>
    <p>In general a nonconvex problem new paper to find such an operating</p>
    <p>point efficiently at https://arxiv.org/abs/1808.03826</p>
    <p>Remove sensitive online data such as power flow on the tie-lines</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Protecting the grid against MadIoT attacks requires efforts from</p>
    <p>researchers in power systems as well as systems security communities</p>
    <p>Power systems operators: Rigorously analyze the effects of potential</p>
    <p>MadIoT attacks on their systems and develop preventive methods to</p>
    <p>protect the grid</p>
    <p>IoT Security: Insecure IoT devices can have devastating consequences far</p>
    <p>beyond individual security/privacy losses  rigorous pursuit of security of</p>
    <p>IoT devices, including regulatory frameworks</p>
    <p>Interdependency: Interdependency between infrastructure networks may</p>
    <p>lead to hidden vulnerabilities  System designers and security analysts</p>
    <p>should explicitly study threats introduced by interdependent infrastructure</p>
    <p>networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!</p>
    <p>ssoltan@princeton.edu</p>
    <p>http://ssoltan.mycpanel.princeton.edu/</p>
    <p>This work was supported in part by the U.S. National Science Foundation under Grants DMS-1736417, ECCS</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
