<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quack: Scalable Remote Measurement of</p>
    <p>Application-Layer Censorship</p>
    <p>Benjamin VanderSloot, Allison McDonald, Will Scott, J. Alex Halderman, and Roya Ensafi</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Censorship Policy of information control that harms citizens</p>
    <p>Spreading beyond the large powers</p>
    <p>Frequently opaque in topic and technique</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Application Layer Quack</p>
    <p>Censorship Measurement</p>
    <p>Examples of censorship Often in policy work</p>
    <p>Cooperation from inside the country</p>
    <p>DNS IP</p>
    <p>Anecdotal</p>
    <p>Probe Based</p>
    <p>Remote Satellite</p>
    <p>Augur 2017</p>
    <p>OONI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HTTP error or RST</p>
    <p>GET / HTTP/1.1 Host: blocked.com</p>
    <p>Application-Layer Censorship</p>
    <p>Web server In-Country ComputerCensor DPI</p>
    <p>HTTP/1.1 200 OK</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HTTP error or RST</p>
    <p>GET / HTTP/1.1 Host: blocked.com</p>
    <p>Echo Behavior</p>
    <p>Measurement Server In-Country ServerCensor DPI</p>
    <p>GET / HTTP/1.1 Host: blocked.com</p>
    <p>The connection is reset or data has been injected into the protocol</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protocol Selection Protocols we know can provide echo behavior</p>
    <p>TLS</p>
    <p>Telnet</p>
    <p>FTP</p>
    <p>Echo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>port 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Goals Detection of keywords are being blocked.</p>
    <p>Minimizing risk for the safety of people in censored countries.</p>
    <p>Robustness in the face of intermittent network failures.</p>
    <p>Performing censorship measurement at scale.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Design, Inside-Out</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GET / HTTP/1.1\r\nHost: example.com\r\n\r\n</p>
    <p>A Single Trial</p>
    <p>Measurement Server Echo Server</p>
    <p>GET / HTTP/1.1\r\nHost: example.com\r\n\r\n</p>
    <p>Test liveness, random string\r\n</p>
    <p>Test liveness, random string\r\n</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Single Test</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adding further redundancy</p>
    <p>Ignore countries with Blocked results in one autonomous system</p>
    <p>We validate countries we classify as being true positives N</p>
    <p>um be</p>
    <p>r o f</p>
    <p>D om</p>
    <p>ai ns</p>
    <p>Tests Blocked</p>
    <p>Country C</p>
    <p>Classification</p>
    <p>N um</p>
    <p>be r o</p>
    <p>f D</p>
    <p>om ai</p>
    <p>ns</p>
    <p>Tests Blocked</p>
    <p>Country A</p>
    <p>N um</p>
    <p>be r o</p>
    <p>f D</p>
    <p>om ai</p>
    <p>ns</p>
    <p>Tests Blocked</p>
    <p>Country B</p>
    <p>N um</p>
    <p>be r o</p>
    <p>f D</p>
    <p>om ai</p>
    <p>ns</p>
    <p>Tests Blocked</p>
    <p>Country D</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ethical Considerations We can provide useful transparency into censorship However, we create potential risks for Echo server operators</p>
    <p>Is participation voluntary? Is informed consent feasible? Do subjects incur no more than minimal risk? Is this risk reasonable?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Upholding our Principles We opt not to use informed consent,</p>
    <p>but we minimize risk and respect blacklist requests</p>
    <p>Our measurements look unlike real traffic on several network layers</p>
    <p>Sought IRB approval, but were deemed outside their scope</p>
    <p>Servers dont connect to real sites Our servers indicate our research use</p>
    <p>DNS PTR WHOIS Explanatory webserver</p>
    <p>Connections are port 7 to ephemeral Real website data never sent to echo server Requests have different headers Echo servers are normally not user devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discovering Echo Servers</p>
    <p>Only 57,000 complete a trial, from 3,766 ASes (172 countries)</p>
    <p>Only 47,000 are there a day later, from 3,463 ASes (167 countries)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What are Echo servers? TCP-level detection could work at scale, but tells kernel level behavior</p>
    <p>Take a 1% sample, and perform NMap OS detection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hand curated and labeled list of ~1000 domains</p>
    <p>Topics and domains that are either censored or interesting</p>
    <p>What can we learn from testing with HTTP formatted echo scans?</p>
    <p>Citizen Lab List</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Censorship observed in 12 countries: China, Egypt, Iran, Jordan, Kazakhstan, Saudi Arabia, South Korea, Thailand, Turkey, UAE, Uzbekistan</p>
    <p>Most frequent categories: News, Anonymization, Pornography</p>
    <p>Citizen Lab List HTTP Experiments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Censorship observed in 12 countries: China, Egypt, Iran, Jordan, Kazakhstan, Saudi Arabia, South Korea, Thailand, Turkey, UAE, Uzbekistan</p>
    <p>Most frequent categories: News, Anonymization, Pornography</p>
    <p>Citizen Lab List HTTP Experiments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Censorship observed in 12 countries: China, Egypt, Iran, Jordan, Kazakhstan, Saudi Arabia, South Korea, Thailand, Turkey, UAE, Uzbekistan</p>
    <p>Most frequent categories: News, Anonymization, Pornography</p>
    <p>Citizen Lab List HTTP Experiments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Censorship observed in 12 countries: China, Egypt, Iran, Jordan, Kazakhstan, Saudi Arabia, South Korea, Thailand, Turkey, UAE, Uzbekistan</p>
    <p>Most frequent categories: News, Anonymization, Pornography</p>
    <p>Citizen Lab List HTTP Experiments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Validating Detected Disruption Freedom on the Net by Freedom House and OpenNet Initiative as ground truth</p>
    <p>All countries from the previous list are known to have deployed technical means!</p>
    <p>Several countries that are Not Free that we tested. e.g. Pakistan deploys DNS based censorship</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TLS Server Name Indication allows web-hosts to serve the correct certificate</p>
    <p>Of our original countries, the bold blocked HTTPS:</p>
    <p>China, Egypt, Iran, Jordan, Kazakhstan, Saudi Arabia, South Korea, Thailand, Turkey, UAE, Uzbekistan</p>
    <p>Iran censored 374 domains when tested with HTTPS vs 25 with HTTP</p>
    <p>HTTP vs HTTPS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alexa Top 100,000 Significant improvement in domain test list size</p>
    <p>Achieved by restricting to 20 tests per domain per country,</p>
    <p>We require 100 servers, so we only test 40 countries</p>
    <p>Took less than three days on one test machine</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>China, Egypt, Iran, Saudi Arabia, South Korea, Thailand, Turkey</p>
    <p>Number of domains blocked by country does not correlate with our earlier tests</p>
    <p>Censored category not seen in Citizen Lab List testing: Shopping</p>
    <p>Alexa Top 100,000 Blocking Experiments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Popularity of Blocked Domains</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations Quack is easier to block due to minimal collateral damage</p>
    <p>Further research is required to explore further</p>
    <p>Countries could be blocking block TCP direction that sent SYN</p>
    <p>May not detect heterogenous deployments</p>
    <p>Coverage reduces as we require more tests in each country</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions Application-layer censorship can be measured remotely</p>
    <p>We test an order of magnitude more domains than prior work</p>
    <p>Future work should combine Quack with other remote measurements</p>
    <p>We would like to acknowledge Bill Marczak Adam Bates</p>
    <p>Our Reviewers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quack: Scalable Remote Measurement of</p>
    <p>Application-Layer Censorship</p>
    <p>Benjamin VanderSloot, Allison McDonald, Will Scott, J. Alex Halderman, and Roya Ensafi</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measuring Asymmetry in HTTP Blocking</p>
    <p>Many Echo servers are also Discard servers</p>
    <p>$ netcat -l 9 &gt; /dev/null</p>
    <p>Of our original countries, the bold required echo behavior: China, Egypt, Iran, Jordan, Kazakhstan, Saudi Arabia, South Korea, Thailand, Turkey, UAE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Churn</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Coverage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Validation</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
