<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EnTrust: Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs</p>
    <p>Giuseppe Petracca gxp18@cse.psu.edu</p>
    <p>The Pennsylvania State University</p>
    <p>Ahmad-Atamli Reineh atamli@turing.ac.uk</p>
    <p>Alan Turing Institute, UK</p>
    <p>Yuqiong Sun yuqiong_sun@symantec.com Symantec Research Labs, US</p>
    <p>Jens Grossklags jens.grossklags@in.tum.de</p>
    <p>Technical University of Munich, DE</p>
    <p>Trent Jaeger tjaeger@cse.psu.edu</p>
    <p>The Pennsylvania State University</p>
    <p>Patrick McDaniel mcdaniel@cse.psu.edu</p>
    <p>The Pennsylvania State University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cooperating Program Abstraction</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Voice Assistant Camera</p>
    <p>Camera App</p>
    <p>take a selfie</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Can Go Wrong?</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack Vectors</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Voice Assistant</p>
    <p>Screen Capture Service</p>
    <p>Screen</p>
    <p>Confused Deputy</p>
    <p>Camera App Trusted</p>
    <p>Assistant GPS</p>
    <p>Trojan Horse</p>
    <p>Camera</p>
    <p>Microphone</p>
    <p>Camera App Banking</p>
    <p>App Camera</p>
    <p>Man-In-The-Middle</p>
    <p>Trusted Assistant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Man-In-The-Middle Attack</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Camera App Banking</p>
    <p>App Camera</p>
    <p>Man-In-The-Middle</p>
    <p>Trusted Assistant</p>
    <p>deposit bank check</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>First-Use Authorization Model</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Ask user for permission ONLY the first time sensor X is accessed by program Y</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proposed Defenses (Related Work)</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Bind User Input Events and User Interface To Sensor Access Restrict context of use for sensors Do not model input event delegation</p>
    <p>Regulate Inter-Process Communication (IPC) Restrict programs interactions Too restrictive (reduce callees permissions based on caller)</p>
    <p>Enforce Decentralized Information Flow Control (DIFC) Restrict how information flows between programs Solve the orthogonal problem of controlling how program share data</p>
    <p>Classify Sensor Access via Machine Learning (ML) Model patterns in user decisions Users need the right information to make the right decision (learning depends on users decision)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Model</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Trust Model System is booted securely (e.g., kernel, OS, system services, sensor drivers) Mandatory Access Control (MAC) enforced from boot time (no direct access to sensors for user-level programs) User-level programs isolated via sandbox Trusted Paths (UI &gt; OS &gt; UI)</p>
    <p>Focus &gt; How programs access sensors Out Of Scope &gt; How programs share collected data (solutions exist)</p>
    <p>Threat Model Users may install programs from unknown sources (grant access at first-use) Programs communicate via Inter-Process Communications (e.g, intents, broadcast messages) Programs may leverage IPC to exploit the three attack vectors mentioned</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Insight</p>
    <p>Track how an input event is delegated among cooperating programs</p>
    <p>Expose delegation information to users (informed authorization decisions)</p>
    <p>Allow users to restrict the set of permissions of the delegated program</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Track the input event delegation (from the user input to the sensor operation)</p>
    <p>Resolve ambiguities with multiple (concurrent) events</p>
    <p>Authorize the right set of permissions given the input event</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach: Track Input Event Delegation</p>
    <p>Input Event e = (c, s, pi, t0)</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Handoff Event h = (pi, pj, ti)</p>
    <p>Sensor Request r = (pj, o, d, tj)</p>
    <p>Delegation Graph</p>
    <p>pi pj e h r</p>
    <p>ds</p>
    <p>c = context s = source sensor p = program t = timestamp o = sensor operation d = destination sensor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach: Resolve Ambiguities (Delegation Path)</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Queue and deliver sequentially (events are consumed faster than produced)</p>
    <p>Prioritize handoff events deriving from input event</p>
    <p>pi h</p>
    <p>en</p>
    <p>e1</p>
    <p>pj r</p>
    <p>hn</p>
    <p>h1</p>
    <p>dpj</p>
    <p>pk</p>
    <p>pj</p>
    <p>pi e</p>
    <p>r</p>
    <p>h1</p>
    <p>h2</p>
    <p>Invali d edg</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>e = input event h = handoff event p = program r = operation request d = destination sensor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach: Authorize The Right Set Of Permissions</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>take a selfie</p>
    <p>EnTrust Authorization Request</p>
    <p>In response to your voice command take a selfie, allow Google Assistant to activate the Basic Camera app to capture pictures and record audio?</p>
    <p>Deny Allow</p>
    <p>Trusted Assistant Camera</p>
    <p>Camera App</p>
    <p>take a selfie</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Man-In-The-Middle Attack (Prevented by EnTrust)</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Camera App Banking</p>
    <p>App</p>
    <p>Man-In-The-Middle</p>
    <p>Trusted Assistant</p>
    <p>deposit bank check</p>
    <p>ENTRUST Authorization Request In response to your voice command deposit bank check, allow Google Assistant to activate Basic Camera to capture pictures? Also, allow Basic Camera to activate Mobile Banking to capture pictures?</p>
    <p>Deny Allow</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EnTrust: Evaluation</p>
    <p>Prototyped (Android OS 7.1.1_r3) Tested (Nexus 5X smartphones)</p>
    <p>Research Questions: What is the decision overhead imposed by EnTrust on users due to explicit authorization of constructed delegation graphs? (Field Study, 9 Subjects, 7 Days, 10 Apps, 5 Voice Assistant)</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Is EnTrust backward-compatible with existing programs? How many operations from legitimate programs are incorrectly blocked by EnTrust? (Android Compatibility Test Suite (CTS), 1k Apps, 5 Augmented Reality Gaming Apps)</p>
    <p>What is the performance overhead imposed by EnTrust for delegation graph construction and enforcement? (Graph Construction, Graph Caching, Graph Enforcement, Ambiguity Prevention, Memory Requirements)</p>
    <p>To what degree is the EnTrust authorization assisting users in avoiding Confused Deputy, Trojan Horse, and Man-In-TheMiddle attacks? (Laboratory Study, 60 subjects, 4 Groups, 3 Attacks)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ENTRUST Delegation Graph</p>
    <p>EnTrust: Laboratory Study</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Directive: Ask Google Assistant to deposit bank check (After logging into Mobile Banking with the provided credentials, deposit the provided check)</p>
    <p>Attack Scenario: (Man-In-The-Middle) Google Assistant launches Basic Camera registered for the voice intent deposit bank check. The Basic Camera runs in the background, captures a picture of the check and - via a spoofed intent - launches the Mobile Banking app registered for the voice intent deposit check. The collected data is sent to the remote service controlled by the adversary.</p>
    <p>Allow Basic Camera to take pictures and record videos?</p>
    <p>DENY ALLOW</p>
    <p>Allow Mobile Banking to take pictures and record videos?</p>
    <p>DENY ALLOW</p>
    <p>First-Use EnTrust</p>
    <p>Camera</p>
    <p>Google Assistant</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>a1</p>
    <p>o1</p>
    <p>Mobile Banking App</p>
    <p>a2 o2</p>
    <p>Group-FR Unprimed 47% 13% 67%</p>
    <p>Group-FR Primed 47% 0%</p>
    <p>Group-EN Unprimed 100%</p>
    <p>Group-EN Primed 100%</p>
    <p>(Prompted) (Explicit Allows) (Attack Success)</p>
    <p>ENTRUST Authorization Request In response to your voice command deposit bank check, allow Google Assistant to activate Basic Camera to capture pictures? Also, allow Basic Camera to activate Mobile Banking to capture pictures?</p>
    <p>Deny Allow</p>
    <p>Basic Camera App</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings and Takeaway</p>
    <p>Improved Attack Vectors Prevention: Can reach 47-67% improvement compared to first-use authorization (delegation path authorization)</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Low User Decision Overhead: No more than 4 explicit authorizations per program (caching of authorized delegation paths)</p>
    <p>Compatible With Existing Programs: No discernible slowdown, glitch, crashes, or responsiveness issues (no apps modification required)</p>
    <p>Negligible Performance Slowdown and Memory Overhead: Less than 1% performance slowdown and 5.5 KB of cache per program</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You For Your Attention!</p>
    <p>Giuseppe Petracca gxp18@cse.psu.edu</p>
    <p>https://sites.psu.edu/petracca/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Backup Slides for Q&amp;A</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Demographics</p>
    <p>All participants reported being active smartphone users (1-5 hours/day).</p>
    <p>Available participants as evenly as possible for both laboratory and field study.</p>
    <p>Each lab group had 9 long-term Android users, the remaining 6 long-term Android users participated in our field study.</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Laboratory Study (Experimental Procedures)</p>
    <p>Two Phases: (Users where not aware of the two phases) Preliminary Phase:</p>
    <p>No attacks Meant to avoid cold start Users interacted with voice assistants Users authorized sensor operations at first-use</p>
    <p>Attack Phase: Users interacted with programs performing 3 attacks</p>
    <p>Randomized Order: In each phase, tasks were presented to users in a different randomized order</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ENTRUST Delegation Graph</p>
    <p>Laboratory Study (Confuse Deputy)</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Directive: Ask Smart Assistant to create a note. Dictate a voice note to Notes. For example, remind me to buy milk on the way home.</p>
    <p>Attack Scenario: (Confused Deputy) Smart Assistant launches Notes and adds the specified note, however, it also requests the Screen Capture service to capture the content on the screen. Credit card information and passwords, visible in the notes summary, are captured and sent to a remote server controlled by the adversary</p>
    <p>Smart Assistant will start capturing everything thats displayed on your screen.</p>
    <p>DENY ALLOW</p>
    <p>First-Use EnTrust</p>
    <p>Screen</p>
    <p>Smart Assistant</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>a</p>
    <p>Screen Capture Service</p>
    <p>o</p>
    <p>Group-FR Unprimed 40% 27% 87%</p>
    <p>Group-FR Primed 47% 0%</p>
    <p>Group-EN Unprimed 100% 20% 20%</p>
    <p>Group-EN Primed 100%</p>
    <p>(Prompted) (Explicit Allows) (Attack Success)</p>
    <p>ENTRUST Authorization Request In response to your voice command create a note, allow Smart Assistant to activate the Screen Capture service to capture the capture on the screen?</p>
    <p>Deny Allow</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ENTRUST Delegation Graph</p>
    <p>Laboratory Study (Trojan Horse)</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
    <p>Directive: Ask Google Assistant to take a selfie</p>
    <p>Attack Scenario: (Trojan Horse) Google Assistant activates the Basic Camera app, which is a Trojan app that takes a selfie but also records a short audio and the users location. The collected data is then sent to a remote server controlled by the adversary.</p>
    <p>Allow Basic Camera to take pictures and record videos?</p>
    <p>Allow Basic Camera to access this devices location?</p>
    <p>First-Use EnTrust</p>
    <p>Camera Google</p>
    <p>Assistant</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>a o1</p>
    <p>Group-FR Unprimed 40% 20% 80%</p>
    <p>Group-FR Primed 53% 0%</p>
    <p>Group-EN Unprimed 100% 13% 13%</p>
    <p>Group-EN Primed 100%</p>
    <p>(Prompted) (Explicit Allows) (Attack Success)</p>
    <p>ENTRUST Authorization Request In response to your voice command take a selfie, allow Google Assistant to activate the Basic Camera app to capture pictures, record audio, and access the GPS receiver to record your location?</p>
    <p>Deny Allow</p>
    <p>App</p>
    <p>Microphone</p>
    <p>GPS</p>
    <p>o2</p>
    <p>o3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Statistical Significance</p>
    <p>Hypothesis: The information in EnTrust authorizations helps unprimed users identify attacks</p>
    <p>Calculated the difference in explicit allows, across the three experimental tasks, for subjects in Group-FR-U versus subjects in Group-EN-U.</p>
    <p>Result: Statistically significant difference (2 = 19.3966; p = 0.000011)</p>
    <p>Hypothesis: EnTrust better helps primed and unprimed users in preventing attacks than first-use</p>
    <p>Calculated the difference in successful attacks, across the three experimental tasks, for subjects in Group-FR-U and GroupFR-P, versus subjects in Group-EN-U and Group-EN-P.</p>
    <p>Result: Statistically significant difference (2 = 65.5603; p = 0.00001)</p>
    <p>Standard Bonferroni correction would be applied for multiple testing, but not necessary due to the small p-values.</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Field Study (Experimental Procedures)</p>
    <p>Loan Device: Pre-installed 5 voice assistants and 10 apps Mock accounts for apps requiring log-in Transferred participants SIM card, data and apps (no data collected from such apps)</p>
    <p>Required Actions: Everyday tasks for 7 days Pre-specified voice commands for pre-installed voice assistants Pre-specified action for pre-installed apps Free interaction with pre-installed apps</p>
    <p>IRB Approved: Advertised as a generic voice assistants and apps testing No mentioning of security implications (mere propose was to measure decision overhead)</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Field Study (Findings)</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Measurements</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Time Constraints Analysis</p>
    <p>Regulating Sensor Access by Cooperating Programs via Delegation Graphs [Petracca et al.]</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
