<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I am uncomfortable sharing what I cant see: Privacy Concerns of the Visually Impaired with Camera Based Assistive Applications</p>
    <p>Indiana University, Syracuse University</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter, Bryan Dosono, Tousif Ahmed, Apu Kapadia, Bryan Semaan</p>
    <p>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</p>
    <p>USENIX Security Symposium 2020</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Visual impairment is not total blindness</p>
    <p>Retinitis Pigmentosa Source: Wikipedia</p>
    <p>Macular degeneration Source: Wikipedia</p>
    <p>Glaucoma Source: ACBVI</p>
    <p>Low Vision/Cataract Source: cs.utah.edu</p>
    <p>Diabetic Retinopathy Source: CNIB</p>
    <p>Hemianopia Source:visionsimulators</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter1</p>
    <p>It is sight loss that cannot be fully corrected using glasses or contact lenses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AI-based assistive tools help in everyday tasks</p>
    <p>Seeing AI recognizing people Lookout recognizing objects Orcam identifying currency</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Source: theverge.com Source:.timesofisrael.comSource: seeingai.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AI-based tools cannot always infer human intent Insufficient and inaccurate responses by Seeing AI</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Source: www.dailydot.com/debug/microsoft-seeing-ai-app</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Human assisted technologies are gaining popularity More than 100,000 people with visual impairments (VIPs) are using human assisted technology</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Aira helping in navigation Source: portseattle.org</p>
    <p>Be My Eyes identifying buttons Source: doyouremember.com</p>
    <p>Friendsourcing identifying medicine Source: hcii.cmu.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy and security risks associated with cameras VIPs can intentionally or unintentionally share sensitive information with assistive systems</p>
    <p>Credit card Medicine</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Source: https://vizwiz.org/</p>
    <p>Photo frame</p>
    <p>Bystander</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy and security risks associated with cameras VIPs can intentionally or unintentionally share sensitive information with assistive systems</p>
    <p>Credit card Medicine</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Photo frame Bystander</p>
    <p>Lasceki et al. (2014), Ahmed et al. (2016), Branham et al. (2017).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We seek to understand the privacy implications of human assisted technologies</p>
    <p>Research Question</p>
    <p>What are the privacy concerns of people with visual impairments in the context of different of background objects (credit cards, people, prescriptions) and human assistants (friends, family, volunteers or crowd-workers)?</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment design (online survey)</p>
    <p>Between subjects (3 types of human assistants)</p>
    <p>W ith</p>
    <p>in s</p>
    <p>ub je</p>
    <p>ct s</p>
    <p>(3 s</p>
    <p>ce na</p>
    <p>rio s)</p>
    <p>Family Friends Volunteers</p>
    <p>Home</p>
    <p>Office</p>
    <p>Restaurant</p>
    <p>Scenarios</p>
    <p>Assistants</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter8</p>
    <p>We studied three types of human assistants in three different scenarios</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We considered one foreground object per scenario</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Matching dress</p>
    <p>(home)</p>
    <p>Distinguish medicines</p>
    <p>(office)</p>
    <p>Identify soda can</p>
    <p>(restaurant) Source: https://vizwiz.org/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We experimented with ten background objects per scenario Six background objects were common across all scenarios</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Source: https://vizwiz.org/</p>
    <p>Body part Prescription Laptop screen Food Messy area Credit card</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We used 5-point Likert items to measure comfort (dependent variable, within subjects)</p>
    <p>Level of comfort with the list of background objects</p>
    <p>Suppose while taking the picture there were some other objects captured along with the [soda/medicine/dress]. How comfortable would you feel if the following were present in the photo and visible to your [family/friends/volunteers] along with the [soda/medicine/dress]?</p>
    <p>Open text explanation</p>
    <p>Can you please briefly explain your selection above?</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter11</p>
    <p>Extremely uncomfortable</p>
    <p>Somewhat uncomfortable</p>
    <p>Neither comfortable nor uncomfortable</p>
    <p>Somewhat comfortable</p>
    <p>Extremely comfortable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Male, 63, 41%</p>
    <p>Female, 92, 59%</p>
    <p>We collected data from 155 participants with visual impairments</p>
    <p>Recruited participants through National Federation of the Blind (NFB) and American Council of the Blind (ACB)</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Totally blind, 101,</p>
    <p>Low vision, 64,</p>
    <p>Age Range</p>
    <p>Age Distribution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PII impression laptop_screen general Types of objects</p>
    <p>C om</p>
    <p>fo rt</p>
    <p>le ve</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>object    PII impression laptop_screen general</p>
    <p>PII Impression Laptop screen General</p>
    <p>Co m</p>
    <p>fo rt</p>
    <p>le ve</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>Type of objects</p>
    <p>Selective content disclosure Participants are most concerned about personally identifiable information (PII)</p>
    <p>Participants are more concerned about bystanders than self</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Comfort levels for different group of objects Comfort levels for self and bystander</p>
    <p>Self-disclosure Bystander</p>
    <p>Co m</p>
    <p>fo rt</p>
    <p>le ve</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>Types of people</p>
    <p>Im very picky about being messy, I wouldnt want people to get the wrong impression of me by watching other peoples mess! - P144</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Selective content disclosure Participants are most concerned about personally identifiable information (PII)</p>
    <p>Participants are more concerned about bystanders than self</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Comfort levels for different group of objects Comfort levels for self and bystander</p>
    <p>Self-disclosure Bystander</p>
    <p>Co m</p>
    <p>fo rt</p>
    <p>le ve</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>Types of people</p>
    <p>I have no problem having parts of myself visible, even my face . I wouldnt take pictures of people at other tables, in case they would be uncomfortable. -P34</p>
    <p>PII impression laptop_screen general Types of objects</p>
    <p>C om</p>
    <p>fo rt</p>
    <p>le ve</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>object    PII impression laptop_screen general</p>
    <p>PII Impression Laptop screen General</p>
    <p>Co m</p>
    <p>fo rt</p>
    <p>le ve</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>Type of objects</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>friends volunteer family Audiences</p>
    <p>C om</p>
    <p>fo rt</p>
    <p>le ve</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>object    general impression laptop_screen PII</p>
    <p>Friends Crowd-sourced Family Types of human assistants</p>
    <p>Co m</p>
    <p>fo rt</p>
    <p>le ve</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>Contents General Impression Laptop screen PII</p>
    <p>Interaction between audience and objects Participants are more concerned sharing PII with volunteers</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Interaction between objects and human assistants</p>
    <p>Volunteers</p>
    <p>Identity theft</p>
    <p>Impersonal trust</p>
    <p>Anonymous</p>
    <p>Family</p>
    <p>Trust</p>
    <p>Social cost</p>
    <p>Friends</p>
    <p>Privacy</p>
    <p>Impression management</p>
    <p>I would feel extremely uncomfortable with the visibility of all the items which are personal to me or to a coworker because they could be potentially misused by the stranger who is looking at the picture. - P100</p>
    <p>Reasons for selective audience disclosure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>friends volunteer family Audiences</p>
    <p>C om</p>
    <p>fo rt</p>
    <p>le ve</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>object    general impression laptop_screen PII</p>
    <p>Friends Crowd-sourced Family Types of human assistants</p>
    <p>Co m</p>
    <p>fo rt</p>
    <p>le ve</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>Contents General Impression Laptop screen PII</p>
    <p>Interaction between audience and objects Participants trust family but dont want to be a burden</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Interaction between objects and human assistants</p>
    <p>Volunteers</p>
    <p>Identity theft</p>
    <p>Impersonal trust</p>
    <p>Anonymous</p>
    <p>Family</p>
    <p>Trust</p>
    <p>Social cost</p>
    <p>Friends</p>
    <p>Privacy</p>
    <p>Impression management</p>
    <p>I trust my family and friends but dont like to bother them if I can help it. - P47</p>
    <p>Reasons for selective audience disclosure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>friends volunteer family Audiences</p>
    <p>C om</p>
    <p>fo rt</p>
    <p>le ve</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>object    general impression laptop_screen PII</p>
    <p>Friends Crowd-sourced Family Types of human assistants</p>
    <p>Co m</p>
    <p>fo rt</p>
    <p>le ve</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>Contents General Impression Laptop screen PII</p>
    <p>Interaction between audience and objects Participants are concerned about impression management with friends</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Interaction between objects and human assistants</p>
    <p>Volunteers</p>
    <p>Identity theft</p>
    <p>Impersonal trust</p>
    <p>Anonymous</p>
    <p>Family</p>
    <p>Trust</p>
    <p>Social cost</p>
    <p>Friends</p>
    <p>Privacy</p>
    <p>Impression management</p>
    <p>I wouldnt really want my friends to see financial or medical information. Also, if they have a picture on their phone that contains personal info about me, this creates an opportunity for someone other than my friend to see the picture on my friends phone (e.g., friends family members, romantic partner), which would jeopardize the privacy and security of the information. - P30</p>
    <p>Reasons for selective audience disclosure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Results</p>
    <p>Participants were more concerned about the privacy of bystanders than their own when it came to capturing people in images.</p>
    <p>Participants have strong concerns about sharing personally identifiable information with crowd-workers because of concerns about identity theft.</p>
    <p>Participants were less comfortable sharing about self-presentation with friends.</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter18</p>
    <p>The right volunteer depends on the context.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implications: Humanizing assistive technology</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter19</p>
    <p>Computer vision algorithms should be trained to better understand context to serve the human</p>
    <p>Source: www.gcn.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Appropriate assistant selection based on the context</p>
    <p>Implications: Selecting the right assistant</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter20</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implications: Obscuring sensitive content</p>
    <p>Source: https://vizwiz.org/</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Sensitive contents should be obscured based on the audience</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implications: Identifying primary objects</p>
    <p>Source: https://vizwiz.org/</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter</p>
    <p>Primary objects should be identified automatically</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter23</p>
    <p>The information disclosure preferences of our participants vary according to the types of objects and human assistants.</p>
    <p>Assistive technologies can create a lack of personal security in the lives of the people with visual impairments</p>
    <p>We identify avenues for technical research to make such systems more humanistic and empathetic, to assist rather than harm.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Apu Kapadia kapadia@indiana.edu</p>
    <p>Tousif Ahmed touahmed@iu.edu</p>
    <p>Bryan Semaan bsemaan@syr.edu</p>
    <p>Bryan Dosono bdosono@syr.edu</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter takter@iu.edu</p>
    <p>Thank you</p>
    <p>Taslima Akter24</p>
    <p>This material is based upon work supported in part by the US National Science Foundation under awards CNS-1408730, CNS-1252697, and IIS-1657429. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the sponsors.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
