<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Actions Speak Louder than Words: Entity-sensitive Privacy Policy and Data Flow Analysis with PoliCheck</p>
    <p>Benjamin Andow,1* Samin Yaseer Mahmud,2 Justin Whitaker,2 William Enck,2 Bradley Reaves,2 Kapil Singh,3 and Serge Egelman4</p>
    <p>* This work was completed while the lead author was at NCSU and IBM Research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Disclaimer</p>
    <p>This work was completed while the I was at North Carolina State University and IBM Research. None of this work or statements made</p>
    <p>within this presentation reflects the views of Google and should not be construed as statements from Google or from my current role as a</p>
    <p>Google employee.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IMEI</p>
    <p>Android ID</p>
    <p>Ad ID</p>
    <p>Advertisers</p>
    <p>Flow-to-Policy Consistency</p>
    <p>com.Bingo.Fighter Sky Fighters 3D</p>
    <p>Are these data flows disclosed within the applications privacy policy?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow-to-Policy Consistency</p>
    <p>Privacy Policy Excerpt: When you launch any of our applications, we collect information regarding your device type, operating system and version, carrier provider, IP address, Media Access Control (MAC) address, International Equipment Mobile ID (IMEI), whether you are using a point package, the game version, the devices geo-location, language settings, and unique device ID.</p>
    <p>IMEI</p>
    <p>Android ID</p>
    <p>Ad ID</p>
    <p>Advertisers</p>
    <p>com.Bingo.Fighter Sky Fighters 3D</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow-to-Policy Consistency</p>
    <p>Privacy Policy Excerpt: When you launch any of our applications, we collect information regarding your device type, operating system and version, carrier provider, IP address, Media Access Control (MAC) address, International Equipment Mobile ID (IMEI), whether you are using a point package, the game version, the devices geo-location, language settings, and unique device ID.</p>
    <p>IMEI</p>
    <p>Android ID</p>
    <p>Ad ID</p>
    <p>Advertisers</p>
    <p>x x</p>
    <p>x x</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>Inconsistent!</p>
    <p>com.Bingo.Fighter Sky Fighters 3D</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prior works [1, 2, 3] would incorrectly mark this data flow as consistent with its privacy policy due to entity-insensitive analysis</p>
    <p>[1] Sebastian Zimmeck et al. Automated Analysis of Privacy Requirements for Mobile Apps, Proceedings of the ISOC Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS), 2017. [2] Rocky Slavin et al. Toward a Framework for Detecting Privacy Policy Violation in Android Application Code, Proceedings of the ACM/IEEE International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), 2016. [3] Xiaoyin Wang et al. UILeak: Detecting Privacy Policy Violations on User Input Data for Android Applications, Proceedings of the ACM/IEEE International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), 2017.</p>
    <p>Prior Flow-to-Policy Consistency Models</p>
    <p>IMEI</p>
    <p>Android ID</p>
    <p>Ad ID</p>
    <p>Advertisers</p>
    <p>Wrong!</p>
    <p>com.Bingo.Fighter Sky Fighters 3D</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prior works [1, 2, 3] would incorrectly mark this data flow as consistent with its privacy policy due to entity-insensitive analysis</p>
    <p>[1] Sebastian Zimmeck et al. Automated Analysis of Privacy Requirements for Mobile Apps, Proceedings of the ISOC Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS), 2017. [2] Rocky Slavin et al. Toward a Framework for Detecting Privacy Policy Violation in Android Application Code, Proceedings of the ACM/IEEE International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), 2016. [3] Xiaoyin Wang et al. UILeak: Detecting Privacy Policy Violations on User Input Data for Android Applications, Proceedings of the ACM/IEEE International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), 2017.</p>
    <p>Prior Flow-to-Policy Consistency Models</p>
    <p>IMEI</p>
    <p>Android ID</p>
    <p>Ad ID</p>
    <p>Advertisers</p>
    <p>com.Bingo.Fighter Sky Fighters 3D</p>
    <p>Entity-insensitive analysis may result in:  Reasoning over up to 55.8% of data flows with irrelevant policy</p>
    <p>statements  Misclassifying up to 37.1% of data flows as consistent</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goals</p>
    <p>sentiment  Contradiction-sensitivity [4]: Holistic analysis of the policy</p>
    <p>[1] Benjamin Andow, Samin Yaseer Mahmud, Wenyu Wang, Justin Whitaker, William Enck, Bradley Reaves, Kapil Singh, and Tao Xie. PolicyLint: Investigating Internal Privacy Policy Contradictions on Google Play, Proceedings of the USENIX Security Symposium (SECURITY), August 2019. Santa Clara, CA, USA. 8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Entity, sentiment, and contradiction-sensitive data flow to privacy policy consistency model</p>
    <p>Built on top of PolicyLint and AppCensus  Heuristics to resolve domains to entities and classify first party flows  Extends PolicyLints ontologies to ensure coverage over entities/data types</p>
    <p>PoliCheck</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Policy Disclosures</p>
    <p>Goal: Characterize how data flows are disclosed (or not disclosed) by privacy policies</p>
    <p>Intuition:  Consistent does not always mean transparent:</p>
    <p>Explicitly discloses the data flow in exact terms (Clear)  Discloses the data flow using broad terms (Vague)</p>
    <p>Several ways for an inconsistency to occur:  Does not disclose the data flow (Omitted)  States that the data flow does not occur (Incorrect)  States that the data flow both does and does not occur (Ambiguous)</p>
    <p>See paper for our formalization of each disclosure type 10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consistent: Clear Disclosure</p>
    <p>A clear disclosure discusses that the flow occurs in exact terms</p>
    <p>A clear disclosure of a data flow f occurs iff:  A policy statement discusses that the flow exists in exact terms for the data type and entity  No policy statement discusses that the flow does not occur</p>
    <p>p  Pf s.t. p.c =collect  f.d  p.d  f.e  p.e and  p  Pf s.t. p.c = not_collect</p>
    <p>Privacy Policy Excerpt: Unity collects the following information through our Games: unique device ID and AD ID.</p>
    <p>com.drpanda.town.holiday</p>
    <p>Ad ID</p>
    <p>Dr. Panda Town: Vacation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consistent: Vague Disclosure</p>
    <p>A vague disclosure discusses that the data flow occurs using broad terms for the entity, data type, or both.</p>
    <p>A vague disclosure of a data flow f occurs iff:  No clear disclosure exists  A policy statement discusses that the flow occurs in broad terms for the data type or entity  No policy statement discusses that the flow does not occur   p  Pf s.t. p.c = collect  f.d  p.d  f.e  p.e and  p  Pf s.t. p.c = collect  f.d</p>
    <p>p.d  f.e  p.e and  p  Pf s.t. p.c = not_collect 12</p>
    <p>Privacy Policy Excerpt: A device identifier and in-game or user session activity may be shared with the advertiser.</p>
    <p>Ad ID</p>
    <p>Advertiser com.yx.sniper</p>
    <p>Elite Killer: SWAT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Policy Disclosures</p>
    <p>Goal: Characterize how data flows are disclosed (or not disclosed) by privacy policies</p>
    <p>Intuition:  Consistent does not always mean transparent:</p>
    <p>Explicitly discloses the data flow in exact terms (Clear)  Discloses the data flow using broad terms (Vague)</p>
    <p>Several ways for an inconsistency to occur:  Does not disclose the data flow (Omitted)  States that the data flow does not occur (Incorrect)  States that the data flow both does and does not occur (Ambiguous)</p>
    <p>See paper for our formalization of each disclosure type 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inconsistent: Omitted Disclosure</p>
    <p>An omitted disclosure does not discuss the data flow in the policy</p>
    <p>An omitted disclosure of a data flow f occurs iff:  No policy statements discuss the data flow  Pf =  14</p>
    <p>Phone # com.xime.latin.lite</p>
    <p>Ad ID</p>
    <p>IMEI x</p>
    <p>Privacy Policy Excerpt: When you access our Services, we automatically record and upload information from your device including, but not limited to attributes such as the operating system, hardware version, device settings, battery and signal strength, device identifiers...</p>
    <p>Pf = Flow-relevant statements</p>
    <p>Flash Emoji Keyboard &amp; Themes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inconsistent: Incorrect Disclosure</p>
    <p>An incorrect disclosure discusses only that the data flow does not occur or uses a narrowing definition to discuss the data flow</p>
    <p>Furby BOOM! com.hasbro.FurbyBoom</p>
    <p>IMEI x Privacy Policy Excerpt: Our Apps do not send the device ID or IP address to us or to any third-party, and our App does not make further use of this information.</p>
    <p>Pf = Flow-relevant statements Pc = Contradictions PN = Narrowing definitions</p>
    <p>An incorrect disclosure of a data flow f occurs iff:  All policy statements discuss that the flow does not occur  Or a narrowing definitions exist, but not a contradictory</p>
    <p>statement   p  Pf , p.c = not_collect or ( Pf  PN    Pf  PC = )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inconsistent: Ambiguous Disclosure</p>
    <p>An ambiguous disclosure discusses that the data flow both occurs and does not occur</p>
    <p>Flip Diving com.motionvolt.flipdiving</p>
    <p>Ad ID x</p>
    <p>Privacy Policy Excerpt: On our apps, these third party advertising companies will collect and use your data to provide you with targeted advertising  We dont give or sell your data to third parties for them to market to you.</p>
    <p>Pf = Flow-relevant statements Pc = Contradictions</p>
    <p>An ambiguous disclosure occurs for a data flow f iff:  The policy contains contradictory policy statements  Pf  PC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Empirical Study</p>
    <p>Dataset: 13,796 Android applications with 45,603 data flows  Selected top 100 free Google Play apps across 35 categories (3,500 apps)  Randomly selected 42,129 apps from AppCensus</p>
    <p>Exclude apps with no data flows reported by AppCensus (23,488 apps)  Exclude apps with no privacy policy, no reachable policy, and not written in English</p>
    <p>(6,039 apps)</p>
    <p>Research Questions: 1. How are apps disclosing their client-side third-party data flows in their privacy</p>
    <p>policies? 2. How does entity-sensitive analysis impact the soundness of flow-to-policy</p>
    <p>consistency? 17</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>43.5% of flows were classified as omitted, incorrect, or ambiguous disclosures</p>
    <p>Some apps had over 15 omitted or incorrect disclosures!</p>
    <p>Flow-to-Policy Consistency Results</p>
    <p>Clear Vague Omit Incorrect Ambig</p>
    <p>First Party</p>
    <p>Flows 216 2,211 208 18 358</p>
    <p>Apps 206 1,600 154 11 224</p>
    <p>Third Party</p>
    <p>Flows 7 23,367 14,201 1,912 3,105</p>
    <p>Apps 7 6,833 5,076 708 892</p>
    <p>Total Flows 223 25,578 14,409 1,930 3,463</p>
    <p>Apps 213 7,626 5,155 719 1,101</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Highlighted Finding</p>
    <p>49.5% of applications are disclosing their third party sharing practices using vague terms</p>
    <p>Flows to third parties involving Ad IDs and Android IDs were disclosed by:</p>
    <p>(3rd party, collect, PII): 40.7% of flows  (3rd party, collect, info): 25.2% of flows</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Highlighted Finding</p>
    <p>719 applications make incorrect statements about their data practices.  Ad IDs and Android IDs most common</p>
    <p>data type involved in incorrect disclosures  15.7% of flows involve to Crashlytics  13.7% of flows involve to Unity  9.6% of flows involve Flurry</p>
    <p>(third party, not_collect, PII) accounted for 63.4% of these disclosures.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>8.0% of apps have ambiguous privacy policies  Android IDs and Ad IDs are involved in 88.8% (3,074 / 3,494) of ambiguous</p>
    <p>disclosures.  C1 contradictions involving PII are most common</p>
    <p>where policy states that a specific entity both collects and does not collect PII</p>
    <p>Highlighted Finding</p>
    <p>Android ID</p>
    <p>com.gokids.chydofon</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>Privacy Policy Excerpt: We DO NOT collect your unique identificator [sic].  Anonymous identifiers, we use anonymous identifiers when you interact with services, such as advertising services and others.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Highlighted Finding</p>
    <p>31.1% of data flows were classified as omitted disclosures*</p>
    <p>Only 6.9% (208) of first party flows were omitted</p>
    <p>Crashlytics and Unity receiving Android IDs and Ad IDs accounted for 27.8% (3,168) and 24.7% of third party omitted disclosures, respectively.</p>
    <p>Raises questions on developers understandings of third party SDKs and their responsibility for disclosing privacy practices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!</p>
    <p>PoliCheck provides a flow-to-policy consistency model that is entitysensitive, sentiment-sensitive, and contradiction-sensitive.</p>
    <p>Benjamin Andow Google*</p>
    <p>Code Available on Github: https://github.com/benandow/PrivacyPolicyAnalysis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>Dataset:153 data flows across 151 applications  POLICHECK achieves an overall 90.8% overall precision (139/153) for</p>
    <p>performing flow-to-policy consistency analysis.  95.6% precision for identifying clear and vague disclosures  92.1% precision for identifying incorrect disclosures  72.0% precision for identifying omitted disclosures</p>
    <p>Primarily due to incomplete policy statement extraction  Policy statements distributed across multiple sentences or sections  Took much more effort to validate FPs for</p>
    <p>omitted disclosures, as many were difficult to comprehend</p>
    <p>Clear Vague Incorrect Omitted</p>
    <p>TP 30 56 35 18</p>
    <p>FP 0 4 3 7</p>
    <p>Precision 100% 93.3% 92.1% 72.0%</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
