<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Yuxuan Chen1,2,3, Xuejing Yuan1,2, Jiangshan Zhang1,2, Yue Zhao1,2, Shengzhi</p>
    <p>Zhang4, Kai Chen1,2, and XiaoFeng Wang5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voice Input is near ubiquitous  Cell phones, smart home devices, computers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attacks for Speech Systems  Traditional Attacks</p>
    <p>Adversarial Attacks  Audio adversarial examples(AEs)</p>
    <p>Good Morning!</p>
    <p>Open the door!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  Can we propose a method to generate audio AEs for several</p>
    <p>commercial black box speech recognition devices?</p>
    <p>General</p>
    <p>Practical</p>
    <p>Stealthy</p>
    <p>Automatic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Approach Overview  Black Box Platforms</p>
    <p>Commercial Speech APIs (Google API)</p>
    <p>Commercial Speech Devices (Amazon Echo)</p>
    <p>Transferability Based Approach (TBA)  Gradient descent/white box</p>
    <p>Alternate Models based Generation Approach (AGA)  Local Large Base Model and Substitute Model</p>
    <p>Ensemble AE generation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Substitute Model  Substitute Model</p>
    <p>Local trained model to simulate black box model</p>
    <p>Audio corpus labelled by target black box model</p>
    <p>Input Audio Black Box Text Output</p>
    <p>Substitute Model</p>
    <p>simulate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack Approach</p>
    <p>Training Set</p>
    <p>Train Substitute Model</p>
    <p>May be overfitting!</p>
    <p>Training set augment: add noise/change voice speed</p>
    <p>Limited data set -&gt; potential model overfitting problem</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack Approach</p>
    <p>Training Set</p>
    <p>Train Substitute Model</p>
    <p>Small Model</p>
    <p>Supplemental Set</p>
    <p>Large Base Model</p>
    <p>Adversarial sample Ensemble Generation</p>
    <p>Supplemental set: open-sourced voice data for training</p>
    <p>Large base model: already trained ASR model (e.g. Kaldi Aspire model)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Generate Adversarial Sample  Momentum based Iterative Fast Gradient Method (MI-FGM)</p>
    <p>Song/music as carrier</p>
    <p>Pdf-id sequence matching method (CommanderSong Yuan et al.)</p>
    <p>Momentum</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Understand The Attack  Base Model</p>
    <p>Generate features in a coarse-grained manner</p>
    <p>Substitute Model  Fine-tunes the features to attack black box model</p>
    <p>Case example, target phrase clear notification</p>
    <p>Lyrics of original music</p>
    <p>I dont clear notificationnotification</p>
    <p>Base model AE generation Substitute model AE generation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Evaluations  Device Attack Effectiveness</p>
    <p>Target devices: Google Assistant (cell phone), Google Home, Microsoft Cortana (cell phone), Amazon Echo, IBM Wav-To-Air</p>
    <p>Effective distance: 5 cm- 200 cm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Evaluations  Robustness test</p>
    <p>Successful tests over total 30 tests</p>
    <p>Same test environment (distance/volume/position)</p>
    <p>76% (38/50) of the commands: 10 successful cases over 30 total playing tests (1/3)</p>
    <p>Target Model Target Command Success Rate</p>
    <p>Google Home Ok Google, call 911 25/30</p>
    <p>Google Home Ok Google, Turn on the Bluetooth 21/30</p>
    <p>Amazon Echo Echo, turn off the light 28/30</p>
    <p>Microsoft Cortana Hey Cortana, open the website 29/30</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Human Perception Evaluations  Human Perception Test</p>
    <p>Amazon MTurk Survey</p>
    <p>84% of users think the samples sounds like normal speech or noise speech</p>
    <p>only 1.4% of users could tell over 50% words in the target commands</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluations of Other Approaches  Devils Whisper vs Nave command/music mixture?</p>
    <p>Simple music + command combination using Adobe tools</p>
    <p>Under similar success rate with Devils Whisper</p>
    <p>Only 6% users think the samples sounds like normal speech or noise speech</p>
    <p>Command Voice Original Song</p>
    <p>Devils Whisper</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions  First adversarial attack against commercial speech devices</p>
    <p>Targeting commercial and home-use devices like Echo or Google Home</p>
    <p>Overcome black box challenges (No inside information/parameters)</p>
    <p>Towards more complicated speech system rather than image system</p>
    <p>Novel model ensemble AE generation approach</p>
    <p>Effective and Stealthy  Show physical robustness in real world scenario</p>
    <p>Human survey</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack Workflow</p>
    <p>AE Generation  Generate AEs with base model and substitute model.</p>
    <p>Efficient query of the black-box API</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Original Song Selection  10 songs from soft and classic music of CommanderSong</p>
    <p>Run Devils Whisper approaches on 10 songs  Okay Google, navigate to my home  Google API</p>
    <p>Hey Cortana, turn off the bedroom light  Bing API</p>
    <p>6 songs were selected</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementations  Target API systems and speech devices</p>
    <p>Google Speech API, Bing API, Amazon Transcribe API, IBM Speech API</p>
    <p>Google Home/Assistant, Cortana App, Amazon Echo, IBM Wav-to-Air</p>
    <p>Phrase Selection  Commonly used commands turn off light, call 911, open the door etc.</p>
    <p>10 commands for each target</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluations of Other Approaches  Train the substitute model with a larger training set</p>
    <p>Larger training data -&gt; better approximation -&gt; better results ?</p>
    <p>New dataset: 5.17 times larger</p>
    <p>G1: Google Command API, G2: Google Assistant, G3: Google Home</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluations of Other Approaches  Ensemble AE generation without model approximation</p>
    <p>Kaldi Aspire model and Mini LibriSpeech model: ensemble AE generation</p>
    <p>No model simulation (No substitute model training)</p>
    <p>G1: Google Command API, G2: Google Assistant, G3: Google Home</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
