<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distance-1 Constrained Channel Assignment in Single Radio Wireless Mesh Networks</p>
    <p>Ehsan Aryafar Rice University (Houston, Texas, USA) Omer Gurewitz Ben Gurion University (Beer Sheva, Israel) Edward Knightly Rice University (Houston, Texas, USA)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation: Mesh Networks</p>
    <p>Two-Tier Mesh Architecture  Access tier  clients (homes and mobiles) to mesh nodes  Backhaul tier - mesh nodes wirelessly hop to gateway  Gateways - Limited number of nodes connected to wired</p>
    <p>internet</p>
    <p>City-wide mesh network deployments  e.g.  Philadelphia  Tempe  Washington DC  San Francisco  Houston</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Model</p>
    <p>Two-tier mesh architecture  Single half-duplex Radio for backhaul-tier  K orthogonal frequency channels</p>
    <p>Single Radio for access tier  Multiple channels for backhaul tier</p>
    <p>Predetermined data forwarding links by an existing routing protocol</p>
    <p>Bidirectional links selected by the routing protocol</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Low channel utilization and high throughput imbalance are well known problems in single channel mesh</p>
    <p>Our objective: Design a single radio channel allocation architecture that maintains high channel utilization while keeping fair bandwidth allocation between flows</p>
    <p>GW</p>
    <p>Multi Channel Backbone</p>
    <p>Objective</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>State of the art: Transceiver based assignment schemes  Transceivers dynamically select channel for</p>
    <p>data transmission based on local channel Information</p>
    <p>Example: DCA00, MMAC04, AMCP06,   Considered by 802.11s multi-channel mesh standard</p>
    <p>proposals</p>
    <p>Problem is solved?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inherent limitations within transceiver based channel assignment schemes:</p>
    <p>Inaccurate channel availability:  Corrupted reception of control</p>
    <p>packets due to collisions  Loss of reception when tuned to</p>
    <p>a different channel</p>
    <p>Why Change?</p>
    <p>Reserve Control Channel ReserveReserve</p>
    <p>DATA ?Channel 2 Channel 1</p>
    <p>If it is not broken,</p>
    <p>why mess with it?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inherent limitations within transceiver based channel assignment schemes:</p>
    <p>Inaccurate channel availability:  Corrupted reception of control</p>
    <p>packets due to collisions  Loss of reception when tuned to</p>
    <p>a different channel</p>
    <p>Inconsistent topology seen by neighboring nodes  Unique to multihop, as in</p>
    <p>single hop all nodes are within transmission range</p>
    <p>A B</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>E</p>
    <p>F</p>
    <p>Why Change? If it is not broken,</p>
    <p>why mess with it?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inherent limitations within transceiver based channel assignment schemes:</p>
    <p>Inaccurate channel availability:  Corrupted reception of control</p>
    <p>packets due to collisions  Loss of reception when tuned to</p>
    <p>a different channel</p>
    <p>Inconsistent topology seen by neighboring nodes  Unique to multihop, as in</p>
    <p>single hop all nodes are within transmission range</p>
    <p>Why Change? If it is not broken,</p>
    <p>why mess with it?</p>
    <p>Local greedy channel selection can lead to poor channel utilization with severe throughput imbalance between flows</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inherent limitations within transceiver based channel assignment schemes:</p>
    <p>Inaccurate channel availability:  Corrupted reception of control</p>
    <p>packets due to collisions  Loss of reception when tuned to</p>
    <p>a different channel</p>
    <p>Inconsistent topology seen by neighboring nodes  Unique to multihop, as in</p>
    <p>single hop all nodes are within transmission range</p>
    <p>Why Change? If it is not broken,</p>
    <p>why mess with it?</p>
    <p>In contrast to prior work we used one of the nodes as a central point to compute static channel assignment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Channel Assignment Protocol  A Network Controller allocates channels to all</p>
    <p>active links  This procedure is run only once during network setup and is</p>
    <p>updated based on deployment of new nodes or node failures.</p>
    <p>Each active link is notified of:  the channel assigned to the link  the number of interfering links</p>
    <p>Medium access algorithm mechanism which coordinates between each sender and receiver to schedule transmission</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Channel Assignment Objective</p>
    <p>Assigning different channels to any two links that can be active at the same time only if their transmission occurs on two different channels</p>
    <p>x vu</p>
    <p>Remark: With this assignment any set of links that form a matching can be active at the same time</p>
    <p>y z</p>
    <p>u x</p>
    <p>a b c d</p>
    <p>Define Distance-1 as the distance between links that do not share a common node but still interfere with each other, e.g., links u-x and y-z are Distance-1 apart</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distance-1 Edge Coloring Problem</p>
    <p>Definition (D1EC Problem) : Given a physical graph G and a selected subgraph , the distance-1 edge coloring problem seeks a mapping of colors to links in A such that any two links that are at distance-1 with respect to G are assigned different colors.</p>
    <p>Roota : 1</p>
    <p>b : 2 c : 1</p>
    <p>d : 3 e : 3</p>
    <p>g : 4</p>
    <p>f : 1 A new coloring problem!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Minimum required number of channels  Theorem 1: The decision problem whether k</p>
    <p>colors are sufficient to have a valid D1EC is NPcomplete Basic proof idea: Reduction from graph K colorability.</p>
    <p>Graph H Graph G</p>
    <p>U V W</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>e e U V W</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Upper bounds for typical topologies</p>
    <p>Theorem 3 : For a geometric graph of maximum degree , KD1EC is upper bounded by 18 X ( + 1)</p>
    <p>Basic proof idea: 1: Physical graph division into cells 2: Assign channel pools to each cell 3: Reuse pools at appropriate distances 4: Good bound depends on the shape and size of cell</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Upper bounds for typical topologies</p>
    <p>Theorem 4: minimum number of colors to have a valid D1EC of links in typical grid topologies such as  = 3,4,6,8 is upper bounded by 3,4,7,10, respectively</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Minimum required number of channels exceeds the number of available channels  Interference-free links can communicate whenever</p>
    <p>sender and receiver pairs are available  Interference on interfering links should be balanced</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Channel Assignment Algorithm for MESH Network</p>
    <p>Basic Algorithm Steps:  Visiting nodes vs. edges  Reserve interference-free links</p>
    <p>for gateway nodes  Greedy assignment for all links</p>
    <p>GW</p>
    <p>Theorem 6: Under geometric graph model, if the number of channels is C1 times the number of channels needed to have a valid D1EC coloring the suggested algorithm guaranty to find a conflict free coloring</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Common Channel Reference MAC</p>
    <p>Two common problems in Multi-Channel MAC protocols  Contaminated channel availability data base  Mutual deafness deadlock</p>
    <p>Basic MAC properties:  Separate control channel  Use information provided by network controller for</p>
    <p>medium access</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation Results: Setup  Setup:</p>
    <p>NS-2 Simulator  Rice TFA topology + Grid  Number of channels 1 to 9  25 flows, CBR over UDP  Switching delay, 80 sec  Routing: Shortest Path  Competitors:</p>
    <p>AMCP: Leading scheme  One channel per gateway 802.11</p>
    <p>Metric  Aggregate Throughput (pkt/sec)  Per flow Throughput</p>
    <p>Rice TFA Topology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation Results: Aggregate Upload</p>
    <p>Maximum throughput of a link in isolation = 184 pkt/sec  Maximum achieved throughput = 150 pkt/sec</p>
    <p>Sufficient Channels Found</p>
    <p>TFA Grid</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation Results: Aggregate Upload</p>
    <p>D1C-CA efficiently utilizes additional increase in number of channels  Packet selection schemes do not efficiently utilize additional</p>
    <p>increase in channels and saturate with small channels  802.11: High interference within each subnetwork</p>
    <p>TFA Grid</p>
    <p>Insufficient Channels</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation Results: Aggregate download</p>
    <p>Gateway node becomes heavy bottleneck for download in AMCP  Two channels are sufficient to guarantee a high performance in our</p>
    <p>scheme due to gateway bottleneck removal</p>
    <p>TFA Grid</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Introduced and investigated distance-1 channel assignment coloring problem</p>
    <p>Designed an efficient channel assignment algorithm for mesh networks based on D1EC</p>
    <p>Designed a random access MAC protocol that exploits the channel assignment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BACKUP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation Single-channel  Link interference</p>
    <p>Low channel utilization and high throughput imbalance e.g., Garreto05, Garreto06</p>
    <p>GW</p>
    <p>Single Channel Backbone</p>
    <p>IEEE 802.11 supports multiple channels e.g., 802.11a  12 orthogonal channels , 802.11b  3 orthogonal channels</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In contrast to prior work</p>
    <p>We propose quasi-static link based channel assignment that minimizes interference among links</p>
    <p>The gateway node has global information about network topology and can be used as a central point to compute channel assignment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Minimum needed number of channels Theorem 1: The decision problem whether k colors are sufficient to have a valid D1EC is NP-complete Basic proof idea: Reduction from graph K colorability: For every</p>
    <p>graph H, we construct another graph G such that H is K-colorable if and only if G has a D1EC with K colors.</p>
    <p>Lemma 1 : In any distance-1 edge coloring of TK,d with K colors, the colors of all vyj edges is the same.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proof Outline</p>
    <p>Construction of G from H: Corresponding of each vertex v of degree d in H, we put a copy Cv of TK,d in G. Each head of Cv corresponds to one of the edges incident to v</p>
    <p>Graph H Graph G</p>
    <p>U V W</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>e e U V W</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>If two vertices u and v in H are joined by an edge e, their corresponding heads in Cu and Cv are connected through e in the resulting graph G</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Upper bounds on KD1EC: Geometric Graphs</p>
    <p>Basic proof idea: 1: Physical graph division into cells 2: Assign channel pools to each cell 3: Reuse pools at appropriate distances 4: Good bound depends on the shape and size of cell</p>
    <p>Geometric Graph Model: All nodes have the same transmission and interference range</p>
    <p>Theorem 3 : For a geometric graph of maximum degree , KD1EC is upper bounded by 18 X ( + 1)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Preview: Context</p>
    <p>Channel assignment in multi-channel wireless networks can increase achievable throughputs</p>
    <p>Multi-channel, multi-hop wireless mesh networks with single radio for backhaul tier</p>
    <p>Channel assignment: For each node, which channel should we operate at any given point in time?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithm Performance Analysis</p>
    <p>Theorem 6: Under geometric graph model, algorithm D1C-CA needs at most C1 . OPT (KD1EC) channels for all links to have a valid D1EC coloring</p>
    <p>OPT (KD1EC): Minimum number of channels used by an optimum algorithm</p>
    <p>Theorem 7: Under geometric graph model, algorithm D1C-CAs maximum contention degree is at most C2 . OPTmin (Co) as</p>
    <p>OPTmin (Co): Minimum contention degree found by an optimal algorithm C2 depends on the number of available channels</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithm Performance Analysis</p>
    <p>Two main properties of the algorithm that provide constant approximation:</p>
    <p>Looking at nodes instead of edges Greedy channel assignment behavior</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithm Performance Analysis</p>
    <p>Definition: An independent set is a set of vertices in a graph no two of which are adjacent.</p>
    <p>v</p>
    <p>v</p>
    <p>&gt; R# colors of algorithm &lt; 39 X ( + 1)</p>
    <p>Constant approximation is achieved!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation Results: Per-flow Throughput</p>
    <p>Same performance irrespective of topology and number of channels Starvation in 802.11 with fully backlogged flows Sufficient number of channels guarantees minimum rate in other schemes With insufficient channels starvation may occur in other schemes</p>
    <p>Saturation Region Fully Backlogged Flows</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation Results: Effect of Traffic Load</p>
    <p>Same performance irrespective of number of channels With small load all approaches handle traffic Severe throughput degradation in 802.11 with increased traffic due to hidden terminals</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation Results: Effect of Channel Switching Delay</p>
    <p>Low throughput degradation up to 200 sec: switching delay is small compared to packet transmission time Big switching delay can be compensated by sending multiple back to back packets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Preview: Context (contd)</p>
    <p>Granularity of Assignment Packet: Channel assignment on a per-packet [DCA00,MMAC04,AMCP06,802.11s Multi-Channel Mesh,] Flow: All links in a flow are sent along the same channel [MCP05] Component: Channel assignment on a component basis [COM07]</p>
    <p>Packet level assignment schemes select their next channel purely based on local inference of channel availability state</p>
    <p>In a single gateway mesh, Component and Flow level assignments have same or worse performance compared to single channel 802.11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Commercial Technologies Vendor Product Radios for</p>
    <p>client access Radios for backhaul</p>
    <p>BelAir Networks BelAir 200 1 802.11b/g Up to 3 proprietary 5GHz</p>
    <p>Cisco Aironet 1500 1 802.11b/g 1 802.11a</p>
    <p>Firetide HotPort 3203 1 802.11a/b/g Same as for client access</p>
    <p>Nortel Wireless AP 7220 1 802.11b 1 802.11a</p>
    <p>Strix Systems OWS 3600 Up to 3 802.11b/g Up to 3 802.11a</p>
    <p>Tropos Networks 5210 MetroMesh Router</p>
    <p>Source: Network World</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Channel Assignment with Insufficient Number of Channels</p>
    <p>Definition: Suppose A is a subset of the network graph G, and a channel assignment C to the links of A is given. The contention degree of a link e in A; Co(e); is the maximum cardinality matching of a set M with the following properties: M is a subgraph of A containing e and the following set</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work: Graph Theoretic Techniques</p>
    <p>Graph Theory Based Coloring L(h, k) labeling problem List Coloring Problem</p>
    <p>Graph Theory Based Channel Assignment Unified Framework and Algorithm for Channel Assignment in Wireless Networks</p>
    <p>Including several time, code and frequency assignments</p>
    <p>D1EC Problem First to introduce and investigate the problem Study also includes the case of insufficient channels</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work: Protocols to Exploit Frequency Diversity</p>
    <p>Single radio protocols: Packet based: [AMCP06, MMAC04, DCA00, 802.11s, ] Flow based: [MCP05] Component based: [Comp07]</p>
    <p>Multiple radio protocols MAC modified: [xRDT07, DAS01, ] Unmodified MAC: Load balancing, Topology control, External Interference [DAS05, RAM06, ASH05, ASH06]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distance-1 Edge Coloring Problem</p>
    <p>Definition (D1EC Problem) : Given a physical graph G and a selected subgraph of it , the distance-1 edge coloring problem seeks a mapping of colors to links in A such that any two links that are at distance-1 with respect to G are assigned different colors.</p>
    <p>Roota : 1</p>
    <p>b : 2 c : 1</p>
    <p>d : 3 e : 3</p>
    <p>g : 4</p>
    <p>f : 1 Definition : The distance-1 chromatic index, KD1EC, of a subgraph , is the minimum number of colors to have a valid D1EC of links in A.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Minimum required number of channels  Theorem 1: The decision problem whether k colors are</p>
    <p>sufficient to have a valid D1EC is NP-complete Basic proof idea: Reduction from graph K colorability: For every</p>
    <p>graph H, we construct another graph G such that H is K-colorable if and only if G has a D1EC with K colors.</p>
    <p>For any graph with maximum degree :</p>
    <p>For arbitrary graphs, KD1EC can be lower bounded with a function of square degree of :</p>
    <p>KD1EC</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
