<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Measurement Study of Multiplicative Overhead Effects in Wireless Networks</p>
    <p>Joseph Camp, Vincenzo Mancuso, Omer Gurewitz, and Edward W. Knightly</p>
    <p>INFOCOM 2008 http://networks.rice.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System: Large-scale, Multi-tier Mesh Network</p>
    <p>Serving 4,000 users over 3 km2</p>
    <p>802.11b access and backhaul tiers</p>
    <p>802.11a directional tier for capacity injection</p>
    <p>Multiple radios at gateway nodes, single radios elsewhere</p>
    <p>TFA-Rice Mesh Deployment http://tfa.rice.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Homogeneous Topology Symmetric Topology</p>
    <p>Two key components driving this study are present in all wireless networks, not just mesh networks (e.g., TFA):</p>
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Node Down!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions</p>
    <p>Heterogeneous connectivity matrix produces two key effects:</p>
    <p>Control frames force multiplicative degradation on data plane  Overhead traffic at rate r can reduce</p>
    <p>data throughput by up to 50 times r  Wireless Overhead Multiplier driven</p>
    <p>primarily by non-forwarding links</p>
    <p>Competing data flows have severe throughput imbalance and poor network utilization  RTS/CTS ineffectiveness coupled with</p>
    <p>heterogeneous links  Lower rate forces longer transmission</p>
    <p>time, decreasing success probability</p>
    <p>data</p>
    <p>control</p>
    <p>data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Impact of Overhead</p>
    <p>Without network overhead (small-sized packets including AODV, beacons):</p>
    <p>Minimal control overhead from only TX and RX  With network overhead:</p>
    <p>All the overhead of the control protocols from all other nodes  Experiment Details:</p>
    <p>All one-hop nodes from gateway  UDP traffic (1500B)  No user data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Diverse Overhead Effects</p>
    <p>Identical hardware platform</p>
    <p>Identical configuration  TX power 200 mW, RTS</p>
    <p>disabled, Autorate enabled</p>
    <p>Overhead of 80 kbps (approx. 10 kbps/node)</p>
    <p>Vastly different performance with and without overhead  800 to 1800 kbps degradation  10-20 times injected overhead</p>
    <p>n1 n2 n3 n4 n6 n7 n8</p>
    <p>TFA Backhaul Node</p>
    <p>isolated</p>
    <p>with overhead</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Wireless Overhead Multiplier Definition</p>
    <p>Define WOM to quantify the effect of the bits of overhead  O is a set of OH-injecting nodes, where o  O  O is bits/sec of injected overhead from O  t sr {s,r} is saturation throughput of tx (s) and rx (r)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Link Behavioral Classes for Heterogeneity</p>
    <p>Typical WOM experiment set-up  TX (s) fully backlogged to RX (r)  UDP, TCP traffic, RTS disabled</p>
    <p>Node o (OH-injecting node) has various link quality to s and r</p>
    <p>Classes of transmitter behavior according to IEEE 802.11 (o to s)  Decode Transmission  Detect Channel Activity  Unable to Detect Channel Activity</p>
    <p>In-lab experiments on widely used chipsets (Prism and Atheros) and drivers (HostAP and MadWiFi)  No threshold where carrier sense</p>
    <p>occurs</p>
    <p>QuickTime and a TIFF (LZW) decompressor</p>
    <p>are needed to see this picture.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transmission Range Out of Range</p>
    <p>W ir e le</p>
    <p>ss O</p>
    <p>v e rh</p>
    <p>e a d M</p>
    <p>u lt ip</p>
    <p>li e r</p>
    <p>Data Set of 3-node Topologies  All one-hop nodes around GW  TCP and UDP traffic  Autorate enabled, RTS off  Measured injected overhead: 10</p>
    <p>kbps</p>
    <p>Transmission Range (link o to s)  Overhead effectively sent at base</p>
    <p>rate (2 Mbps)  On average, quality of TFA links</p>
    <p>enables 11 Mbps operation</p>
    <p>Out of Range (link o to s)  Average WOM: 10 (high variance)  What is causing the high variance</p>
    <p>in WOM? TCP data traffic (1500 byte), Autorate enabled, RTS off</p>
    <p>WOM for Two TFA Link Classes</p>
    <p>QuickTime and a TIFF (LZW) decompressor</p>
    <p>are needed to see this picture.</p>
    <p>Header Payload Base Rate High Rate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>-5 -4 -3 -2 -1 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7</p>
    <p>Relative SNR (link 1 - link 2)</p>
    <p>UDP data traffic (1500 byte), Autorate disabled, RTS off</p>
    <p>link 1 &gt; link 2</p>
    <p>Relative Link Quality of Competing Links</p>
    <p>Same link behavior as defined by 802.11 (unable to carrier sense) but high variance - why?  Same injected overhead</p>
    <p>and non-forwarding links  Expect high WOM values</p>
    <p>(low variance)</p>
    <p>Find impact of relative forwarding link quality</p>
    <p>Expected high WOM as data flow has lower quality</p>
    <p>Asymmetric WOM with forwarding link differences</p>
    <p>physical layer capture DATA_s</p>
    <p>link 1 &lt; link 2</p>
    <p>DATA_s OHOH</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reconsidering Link Classes for WOM</p>
    <p>Asymmetry of hidden terminal class, must reconsider WOM classes  Split hidden terminal link</p>
    <p>class</p>
    <p>Node winning capture has minimal WOM  Slightly better than</p>
    <p>transmission range</p>
    <p>Node losing capture has WOM of up to 30</p>
    <p>TCP data traffic (1500 byte), Autorate enabled, RTS off</p>
    <p>Out of Range Capture Win</p>
    <p>Transmission Range</p>
    <p>Out of Range Capture Lose</p>
    <p>W ir e le</p>
    <p>ss O</p>
    <p>v e rh</p>
    <p>e a d M</p>
    <p>u lt ip</p>
    <p>li e r</p>
    <p>QuickTime and a TIFF (LZW) decompressor</p>
    <p>are needed to see this picture.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rice Networks GroupCumulative Link Effects</p>
    <p>Measure injected overhead as it scales with TFA backhaul nodes  Measure achievable throughput with increasing number of OH-injectors</p>
    <p>Measured Overhead (AODV, Beacons)  Reference point for overhead of other networks (no TFA nodes on the channel)  10 kbps overhead per node</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>n2 n7 n6 n8 n1 n3</p>
    <p>TFA Backhaul Node</p>
    <p>TCP data traffic (1500 byte),</p>
    <p>Autorate enabled, RTS off</p>
    <p>Cumulative Link Effects</p>
    <p>Findings in 3-node topology hold for more complex topologies  Node n4 sends data to GW</p>
    <p>Wins capture with n2 (20 kbps)  Loses capture with n7 (520 kbps)  Hidden, unclear capture result with n6 and n8 (differ &lt; 1dB at GW)  Transmission range with n1 and n3  Span of throughput degradation from 20 to 520 kbps</p>
    <p>data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Worst Case WOM Scenario for Data Flows</p>
    <p>Capture-losing data flow with competing OH</p>
    <p>Capture-losing data flow with competing data  Frequency of loses sufficient to</p>
    <p>trigger autorate policy (unlike OH)  Prolongs transmissions of capture</p>
    <p>losing node, less likely to transmit successful packet</p>
    <p>Even RTS ineffective for capture losing node  RTS packet also captured and</p>
    <p>must fit into backoff window of capture winning node</p>
    <p>dataB</p>
    <p>Worst Case</p>
    <p>dataA OH physical layer capture</p>
    <p>dataAdataBOH</p>
    <p>RTS dataARTS ACKCTS RTS</p>
    <p>CWA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rice Networks GroupIn Summary</p>
    <p>Low-rate control frames can produce multiplicative throughput degradation effects on the forwarding links  Up to 50 times the actual overhead load!  Protocol designers forced to reconsider tradeoff of injected</p>
    <p>overhead bits with protocol gains  Potentially zero-overhead control algorithms</p>
    <p>Severe throughput imbalance and aggregate throughput degradation due to coupling of:  Physical layer capture effect yields RTS/CTS ineffective  Prolonged transmissions from falsely triggering rate lower</p>
    <p>decreasing ability of capture losing node to transmit packets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rice Networks GroupQuestions?</p>
    <p>Contact Info: Joseph Camp E-mail: camp@rice.edu RNG: http://networks.rice.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rice Networks GroupBackup Slides</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Asymmetry between Hidden Nodes</p>
    <p>Choose two nodes with large relative difference in link quality at GW</p>
    <p>Relative SNR difference of 5 dB at mutual receiver</p>
    <p>Physical layer capture occurs at node</p>
    <p>n7 has WOM of 1  n2 has WOM of 10</p>
    <p>TCP/UDP perform similarly with respect to WOM</p>
    <p>TCP/UDP data traffic (1500 byte), Autorate disabled, RTS off</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Energy Detect and Carrier Sense in OTS Card</p>
    <p>In-lab measurements shows no carrier sense threshold</p>
    <p>Set-up: 3 different cards (2Mbps fixed modulation rate, UDP traffic)</p>
    <p>Constant Noise  External 802.11 source heard</p>
    <p>only at transmitter (not shown)</p>
    <p>Throughput degradation due to transmitter becoming deaf to ACK</p>
    <p>Producing excessive backoff  Continues to transmit  MAC traces taken with Kismet</p>
    <p>Card at TX becomes deaf to ACK packets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rice Networks GroupRTS Effect on WOM</p>
    <p>RTS/CTS designed to overcome hidden terminal problem  Tradeoff of using RTS/CTS mechanism when capture occurs</p>
    <p>WOM reduced with the use of RTS in both cases (winning and losing)  However, aggregate throughput is lower when using RTS</p>
    <p>Overall, RTS mechanism ineffective</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rice Networks GroupRelated Work</p>
    <p>Mesh Network: Increasing mesh node density increases throughput and connectivity [1], in contrast, we show backhaul link degradation</p>
    <p>Scaling Overhead: AODV shown to be linearly increasing [2], while we confirm w/ measurements, we show severe multiplicative effects</p>
    <p>Collision-aware Multirate: [3] shows adaptively enabling RTS able to make loss-based multirate collision-aware, we show RTS ineffective</p>
    <p>Measurement Study: [4] and related works measure performance of routing metrics in mesh networks, in contrast, we show the multiplicative losses due to routing and beaconing overhead</p>
    <p>[1] J. Bicket, S. Biswas, D. Aguayo, and R. Morris, Architecture and Evaluation of the MIT Roofnet Mesh Network, MobiCom05. [2] A. Iwata, C. Chiang, G. Pei, M. Gerla, and T. Chen, Scalable routing strategies for ad hoc wireless networks, Selected Areas of Communica- tion, 1999. [3] J. Kim, S. Kim, S. Choi, and D. Qiao, CARA: Collision-aware rate adaptation for IEEE 802.11 WLANs, Infocom06. [4] D. De Couto, D. Aguayo, J. Bicket, and R. Morris, A high-throughput path metric for multi-hop wireless routing, MobiCom03.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
