<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Impact of Ad-Blockers on Product Search and Purchase Behavior:</p>
    <p>A Lab Experiment</p>
    <p>Alisa Frik,* Amelia Haviland, Alessandro Acquisti UC Berkeley/ICSI,* Carnegie Mellon University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>If the role of advertising:</p>
    <p>persuasive informative</p>
    <p>H1</p>
    <p>Ad blockers</p>
    <p>increase decrease .. the price of chosen products</p>
    <p>H2 decrease increase .. searching time</p>
    <p>H3</p>
    <p>decrease increase .. consumer satisfaction in short term (with the product choice and browsing experience)</p>
    <p>H4 decrease decrease .. consumer satisfaction in long</p>
    <p>term (with the product choice)</p>
    <p>$107 billion$55</p>
    <p>billion</p>
    <p>Ad revenue in Europe</p>
    <p>Ad blocker users</p>
    <p>[1] IAB. 2018. https://iabeurope.eu/all-news/european-digital-advertising-market-exceeds-e55bn-in-2018/ [2] IAB. Internet advertising revenue report, 2018 full year results. Technical report, 2018. [3] PageFair. The state of the blocked web: 2017 global adblock report. 2017.</p>
    <p>Ad revenue in the US</p>
    <p>Internet users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ad-blockers</p>
    <p>%</p>
    <p>VS.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Effectiveness and usability of ad-blockers  Impact on ad content removal [4,5], battery</p>
    <p>life[6], CPU and memory usage [7,8], usability [9], etc.</p>
    <p>[4] Balebako, R., P Leon, R Shay, B Ur, Y Wang, and L Cranor. Measuring the effectiveness of privacy tools for limiting behavioral advertising. In WEB , 2012.</p>
    <p>[5] Merzdovnik, G., M Huber, D Buhov, N Nikiforakis, S Neuner, M Schmiedecker, and E Weippl. Block me if you can: A large-scale study of tracker-blocking tools. In IEEE European Symposium on Security and Privacy, pages 319333, 2017.</p>
    <p>[6] Rasmussen, K., A Wilson, and A Hindle. Green mining: energy consumption of advertisement blocking methods. In Proceedings of the 3rd International Workshop on Green and Sustainable Software, pages 3845. ACM, 2014.</p>
    <p>[7] Mughees, MH, Z Qian, and Z Shafiq. Detecting anti ad-blockers in the wild. Proceedings on Privacy Enhancing Technologies, 2017(3):130146, 2017.</p>
    <p>[8] Shuba, A., A Markopoulou, and Z Shafiq. Nomoads: Effective and efficient cross-app mobile ad-blocking. Proceed. on Privacy Enhancing Technologies, (4):125140, 2018.</p>
    <p>[9] Pujol, E., O Hohlfeld, and A Feldmann. Annoyed users: Ads and ad-block usage in the wild. In Proceedings of the Internet Measurement Conference, pages 93106, 2015.</p>
    <p>Prior research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Effectiveness and usability of ad-blockers  Impact on ad content removal, battery life, CPU</p>
    <p>and memory usage, usability, etc.</p>
    <p>Effectiveness of advertising  Impact on business revenues and market</p>
    <p>structure (sales, prices, competition, market concentration, etc.) [10-13]</p>
    <p>[10] Chen, J., J Stallaert. An economic analysis of online advertising using behavioral targeting. MIS Quarterly , 38(2), 2014</p>
    <p>[11] Jeziorski, P., and I Segal. What makes them click: Empirical analysis of consumer demand for search advertising. American Econ. Journal: Microeconomics, 7(3):2453, 2015.</p>
    <p>[12] Datta, A., MCl Tschantz, and A Datta. Automated experiments on ad privacy settings. In Proceedings on Privacy Enhancing Technologies, volume 1, pages 92112, 2015.</p>
    <p>Prior research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research question: What is the effect of ad-blocking deployment on consumers product search and purchase behaviors and the resulting outcomes?</p>
    <p>Between-subject lab experiment  2 conditions: with and without an ad-blocker</p>
    <p>Our study</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>METHOD</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Variables</p>
    <p>Expenditures (prices of chosen products)</p>
    <p>Search time</p>
    <p>Satisfaction -- in short term -- immediately after purchasing</p>
    <p>browsing experience  product choice, price, and expected product quality</p>
    <p>-- in long term -- after the product has been delivered  product choice, price, and actual product quality</p>
    <p>If the role of advertising:</p>
    <p>persuasive informative</p>
    <p>H1</p>
    <p>Ad blockers</p>
    <p>increase decrease .. the price of chosen products</p>
    <p>H2 decrease increase .. searching time</p>
    <p>H3</p>
    <p>decrease increase .. consumer satisfaction in short term (with the product choice and browsing experience)</p>
    <p>H4 decrease decrease .. consumer satisfaction in long</p>
    <p>term (with the product choice)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental design</p>
    <p>Screening survey</p>
    <p>Lab experiment</p>
    <p>Order confirmation</p>
    <p>Expected delivery</p>
    <p>Follow-up survey</p>
    <p>Consent Instructions Choices Purchase Exit survey</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>O rg</p>
    <p>a n</p>
    <p>ic</p>
    <p>O rg</p>
    <p>a n</p>
    <p>ic</p>
    <p>Sp o</p>
    <p>n so</p>
    <p>re d</p>
    <p>G</p>
    <p>o o</p>
    <p>g le</p>
    <p>Sh</p>
    <p>o p</p>
    <p>p in</p>
    <p>g</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participants</p>
    <p>CMU participant pool, Craigslist, flyers  212 participants  52% female  Age: mean=26, min=18, max=72  Bachelors degree and higher 59%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RESULTS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attitudes to advertising</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PRICES</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prices</p>
    <p>No sig treatment effect on prices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prices</p>
    <p>No sig treatment effect on prices  Experienced (home) ad-blocker users chose products</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SEARCH TIME</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Search time</p>
    <p>No sig treatment effect on search time (t(1682)=0.85, p=.40) and number of inspected search results (t(1682)=.24, p=.81)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Search time</p>
    <p>No sig treatment effect on search time  Experienced (home) ad-blocker users did not spend</p>
    <p>less or more time on product searching</p>
    <p>(t(1682)=-.86, p=.39),</p>
    <p>but inspected more search results (t(1682)=2.34, p=.02) 19</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Search time</p>
    <p>Participants who chose the products from sponsored Google shopping listings spent less time on their searching than those, who chose the products following organic links (ANOVA: b=-1.64, p=0.00).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SATISFACTION - browsing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Browsing satisfaction</p>
    <p>Satisfaction with browsing:  overall pleasure from browsing experience,  speed of web page load,  relevance of the search results to the query,  selection of the products on the visited websites,  quality and professionalism of the visited</p>
    <p>websites,  ease of navigation on the visited websites,  technical functioning level (broken links, distorted</p>
    <p>elements).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Browsing satisfaction</p>
    <p>Satisfaction with web page loading speed was higher in the NoBlock condition (68% satisfied in the NoBlock vs. 46% satisfied in the Block; p=.00)</p>
    <p>Ad-blocker uses additional computational resources [13] (use of multiple ad-blockers may have amplified the effect) Slower webpage loading speed</p>
    <p>Reduced satisfaction, but not searching time</p>
    <p>[13] BBC News. Ad code slows down browsing speeds. 2019: https://www.bbc.com/news/technology-47252725 23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Browsing satisfaction</p>
    <p>Index of satisfaction with browsing (Cronbachs =.85)  No sig treatment effects  lower among experienced (home) ad-blocker users</p>
    <p>(p=0.01)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SATISFACTION - products</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Product satisfaction</p>
    <p>No sig treatment effect  Experienced (home) ad-blocker users are less satisfied</p>
    <p>with product choices</p>
    <p>short term</p>
    <p>long term</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Types of search ads</p>
    <p>Products chosen from sponsored Google shopping listings:  Lower prices (on 10% level of significance: b=-1.32, p=.06)  Shorter search time (b=-1.64, p=.00)</p>
    <p>BUT:</p>
    <p>Lower price satisfaction (b=-.33, p=.04)  Lower quality satisfaction (short term) (b=-.68, p=.00)</p>
    <p>Products chosen from top sponsored links:  Higher prices (b=2.84, p=.01), but no effect on satisfaction</p>
    <p>Products chosen from bottom sponsored links:  Lower product choice (b=-1.05, p=.049)  Lower quality satisfaction (short term) (b=-1.01, p=.03)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>The use of privacy- and security-enhancing ad-blockers do not harm consumers purchasing behaviors in terms of prices paid, product searching time, and satisfaction with products, their prices, and quality</p>
    <p>Ad-blockers may negatively affect satisfaction with web page loading speed, but not eventual searching time</p>
    <p>Experienced ad-blocker users tend to:  Choose cheaper products  Inspect more search results before making purchasing decision  Be less satisfied with browsing experience and product choices</p>
    <p>Alisa Frik: afrik@icsi.berkeley.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
