<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Spectral Analysis of Noise: A Comprehensive, Automated, Formal Analysis of Diffie-Hellman Protocols</p>
    <p>Guillaume Girol1 Lucca Hirschi2 Ralf Sasse3 Dennis Jackson4 Cas Cremers5 David Basin3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Noise family or protocols</p>
    <p>Noise:</p>
    <p>secure channel between Alice and Bob  based on Diffie-Hellman key exchange</p>
    <p>Noise is a large family (technically infinite)</p>
    <p>Ex: Wireguard, Lightning, Whatsapp use 3 distinct Noise protocols</p>
    <p>Meant to adapt to many use cases:</p>
    <p>Alice Bob Has long-term key Yes/No Yes/No</p>
    <p>Knows peers long-term key Yes/No Yes/No Shared symmetric key material Yes/No</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Noise family or protocols</p>
    <p>Noise:</p>
    <p>secure channel between Alice and Bob  based on Diffie-Hellman key exchange</p>
    <p>Noise is a large family (technically infinite)</p>
    <p>Ex: Wireguard, Lightning, Whatsapp use 3 distinct Noise protocols</p>
    <p>Meant to adapt to many use cases:</p>
    <p>Alice Bob Has long-term key Yes/No Yes/No</p>
    <p>Knows peers long-term key Yes/No Yes/No Shared symmetric key material Yes/No</p>
    <p>1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Choosing a Noise protocol</p>
    <p>In the Noise specification: 50+ examples with widely different security guarantees, and you can even build your own!</p>
    <p>Our goal Helping practitioners choose the Noise protocol with the best security guarantees given their requirements and threat model</p>
    <p>Manual comparison is impossible  do it automatically with formal methods!</p>
    <p>Analysis based on the Tamarin prover:</p>
    <p>symbolic verification  precise modelling of Diffie-Hellman operations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What we want to know</p>
    <p>Proof goals</p>
    <p>A Noise protocol+</p>
    <p>Secrecy Agreement Anonymity*</p>
    <p>+A threat model</p>
    <p>yes no</p>
    <p>timeout</p>
    <p>What threat models? Any combination (,) of adversary capabilities:</p>
    <p>be active</p>
    <p>impersonate Alice/Bob/the PKI</p>
    <p>compromise keys before the session</p>
    <p>compromise keys at any time</p>
    <p>more than 1012 threat models!</p>
    <p>*some limitations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What we want to know</p>
    <p>Proof goals</p>
    <p>A Noise protocol+</p>
    <p>Secrecy Agreement Anonymity*</p>
    <p>+A threat model</p>
    <p>yes no</p>
    <p>timeout</p>
    <p>What threat models? Any combination (,) of adversary capabilities:</p>
    <p>be active</p>
    <p>impersonate Alice/Bob/the PKI</p>
    <p>compromise keys before the session</p>
    <p>compromise keys at any time</p>
    <p>more than 1012 threat models! *some limitations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contribution 1: the Vacarme tool</p>
    <p>Vacarme automatically derives the security properties of any Noise protocol</p>
    <p>Challenge: not enumerating all possible proof goals using the structure of the problem: some proof goals subsume each other, the ones we</p>
    <p>prove are soundly, carefully selected preprocessing: Vacarme includes a light-weight incomplete prover for easy proofs</p>
    <p>Any Noise protocol</p>
    <p>syntax defined in the spec</p>
    <p>Vacarme</p>
    <p>Symbolic Model</p>
    <p>+ Tamarin</p>
    <p>proof goals   8000 on avg</p>
    <p>Tamarin prover</p>
    <p>Dedicated heuristic</p>
    <p>Proof results</p>
    <p>What property holds in what threat model   human readable  150-lines table</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contribution 2: results on the Noise specification</p>
    <p>We ran Vacarme on the 53 Noise protocols given as examples in the Noise specification. Gives new insight, e.g.</p>
    <p>The Noise specification claims informal security levels (secrecy: 0  5 )  Prior work (Noise Explorer) proved them  We show they hold only if ephemeral keys do not leak  Not monotonic: upgrading from level 3 to level 5 can break secrecy  Vacarme procedurally infers a formal meaning for secrecy &amp; agreement levels</p>
    <p>Session identifiers must remain private (leaks break anonymity)  Adding a dummy pre-shared key sometimes worsens guarantees</p>
    <p>partial results for anonymity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contribution 3: what Noise protocol should I choose?</p>
    <p>A partial order on Noise protocols A is better than B when for any property p and threat model t, if p holds in t in protocol B, then p also holds in t in protocol A.</p>
    <p>Identical properties must be studied in A and B. Requires special care in the formulation of agreement properties.</p>
    <p>I1K</p>
    <p>IK</p>
    <p>IKpsk2KK</p>
    <p>I1K1</p>
    <p>IK1 K1KK1K1</p>
    <p>KK1</p>
    <p>I1X</p>
    <p>IX</p>
    <p>IXpsk2</p>
    <p>I1X1</p>
    <p>IX1NK</p>
    <p>NKpsk2</p>
    <p>X1K</p>
    <p>NKpsk0</p>
    <p>XK</p>
    <p>NK1</p>
    <p>X1K1</p>
    <p>XK1</p>
    <p>NX</p>
    <p>NXpsk2</p>
    <p>K1X</p>
    <p>XX</p>
    <p>KX</p>
    <p>NX1</p>
    <p>K1X1</p>
    <p>XX1</p>
    <p>KX1</p>
    <p>KKpsk2</p>
    <p>KXpsk2</p>
    <p>KKpsk0</p>
    <p>K1N</p>
    <p>KN</p>
    <p>X1N</p>
    <p>XN</p>
    <p>XNpsk3</p>
    <p>XKpsk3</p>
    <p>KNpsk0</p>
    <p>arrows point to better guarantees</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contribution 3: what Noise protocol should I choose? Example</p>
    <p>Example If Alice and Bob both have a long-term key and Bob knows Alices: 4 candidates: KX, K1X, KX1, K1X1, in green</p>
    <p>Redundant Noise protocols KX has better guarantees than K1X, KX1, K1X1.</p>
    <p>No (cryptographic) reason to choose K1X, KX1, K1X1: they are redundant Noise protocols.</p>
    <p>We identify 20 redundant Noise protocols.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Vacarme: an automated tool to determine the security guarantees of Noise protocols that can compare them to help</p>
    <p>choose the best ones.</p>
    <p>Full results &amp; source code as artifacts to the paper</p>
    <p>Thank you for your attention</p>
    <p>Contact: guillaume.girol@cea.fr</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
