<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EPIC Every Packet Is Checked</p>
    <p>in the Data Plane of a Path-Aware Internet</p>
    <p>Markus Legner, Tobias Klenze, Marc Wyss, Christoph Sprenger, and Adrian Perrig</p>
    <p>USENIX Security Symposium 2020</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Imagine an Internet in which ...</p>
    <p>... source-address spoofing is no longer possible as each packets source can be verified by every router; Source Authentication</p>
    <p>... route hijacks are a problem of the past; Secure Routing</p>
    <p>... end hosts have control over the path of their packets; Path Control</p>
    <p>... end hosts can verify the actual path of their packets. Path Validation</p>
    <p>Legner et al. EPIC USENIX Security 20 2 / 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Such an Internet exists already.</p>
    <p>Under development since 2010, today offered by several ISPs and in production use for several critical applications. SCION has two core components:</p>
    <p>The control plane discovers paths; secured by signatures. The data plane forwards data traffic; secured by symmetric cryptography.</p>
    <p>SCION is path aware: end hosts select a path to use and embed it in the packet header.</p>
    <p>OPT extension provides source authentication and path validation.</p>
    <p>Legner et al. EPIC USENIX Security 20 3 / 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power needs to be balanced between end hosts and network operators.</p>
    <p>In path-aware networks, hosts embed their chosen path in each packet.</p>
    <p>New challenge: How can autonomous systems pre-select allowed paths?</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>E</p>
    <p>F</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>E</p>
    <p>F</p>
    <p>Path Authorization</p>
    <p>SCION and other path-aware network architectures achieve path authorization through cryptographic tokens.</p>
    <p>On todays hardware, cryptographic operations can be several times faster than memory lookups. With hardware acceleration, encrypting/decrypting one AES block only requires 10 ns on commodity CPUs.</p>
    <p>Legner et al. EPIC USENIX Security 20 4 / 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power needs to be balanced between end hosts and network operators.</p>
    <p>In path-aware networks, hosts embed their chosen path in each packet.</p>
    <p>New challenge: How can autonomous systems pre-select allowed paths? Path Authorization</p>
    <p>SCION and other path-aware network architectures achieve path authorization through cryptographic tokens.</p>
    <p>On todays hardware, cryptographic operations can be several times faster than memory lookups. With hardware acceleration, encrypting/decrypting one AES block only requires 10 ns on commodity CPUs.</p>
    <p>Legner et al. EPIC USENIX Security 20 4 / 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SCION computes tokens in its control plane and checks them in the data plane.</p>
    <p>Autonomous systems exchange signed routing messages and collect path information:</p>
    <p>local routing information (neighbors); a cryptographic token, calculated as a message authentication code (MAC).</p>
    <p>Routing information is used in the data plane to determine where to forward packets.</p>
    <p>Removes the need for huge forwarding tables. Routers no longer need to perform longest-prefix matching.</p>
    <p>Token is checked to enforce path authorization.</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>Neighbor: B</p>
    <p>Neighbors: A, C</p>
    <p>Neighbor: B</p>
    <p>Legner et al. EPIC USENIX Security 20 5 / 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The current approach suffers from a trade-off between overhead and security.</p>
    <p>Each hop of the path requires a token in the packet header.</p>
    <p>Each token must be long enough to withstand brute-force attacks.</p>
    <p>Core issue: even if the probability of forging a token is small, a once-forged token can be reused for sending many packets.</p>
    <p>Legner et al. EPIC USENIX Security 20 6 / 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EPIC resolves the dilemma between communication overhead and security.</p>
    <p>Observation: individual forged packets are no threat to autonomous systems.</p>
    <p>By replacing static tokens by longer keys to compute short per-packet MACs, EPIC prevents the reuse of forged tokens.</p>
    <p>An attacker still has a small chance of forging a MAC to traverse an unauthorized link but this is limited to a single packet.</p>
    <p>Destination can filter packets based on a separate, unforgeable MAC.</p>
    <p>Source authentication and path validation are enabled by the additional use of efficiently derivable symmetric keys.</p>
    <p>Previous systems (OPT, ICING) were too expensive to be used on every packet.</p>
    <p>Legner et al. EPIC USENIX Security 20 7 / 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EPIC enables path authorization, source authentication by every router, and path validation by the destination with very small computation, storage, and</p>
    <p>communication overhead.</p>
    <p>Legner et al. EPIC USENIX Security 20 8 / 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EPIC has low communication overhead.</p>
    <p>Path Length</p>
    <p>H ea</p>
    <p>de rS</p>
    <p>iz e [B</p>
    <p>]</p>
    <p>sec. SCION sec. SCION+OPT ICING PPV EPIC basic EPIC advanced</p>
    <p>average in current Internet</p>
    <p>Legner et al. EPIC USENIX Security 20 9 / 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EPIC is highly efficient and parallelizable.</p>
    <p>Payload [B]</p>
    <p>Fo rw</p>
    <p>ar di ng</p>
    <p>P er fo</p>
    <p>rm an</p>
    <p>ce [G</p>
    <p>bp s]</p>
    <p>link capacity</p>
    <p>Legner et al. EPIC USENIX Security 20 10 / 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EPIC is highly efficient and parallelizable.</p>
    <p>Number of Cores</p>
    <p>Fo rw</p>
    <p>ar di ng</p>
    <p>P er fo</p>
    <p>rm an</p>
    <p>ce [M</p>
    <p>pp s]</p>
    <p>Legner et al. EPIC USENIX Security 20 11 / 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EPIC achieves strong security properties while being highly efficient.</p>
    <p>Legner et al. EPIC USENIX Security 20 12 / 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you, and please get in touch.</p>
    <p>Email: markus.legner@inf.ethz.ch</p>
    <p>Legner et al. EPIC USENIX Security 20 13 / 13</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
