<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(Mostly) Exitless VM Protection from Untrusted Hypervisor through Disaggregated Nested Virtualization</p>
    <p>Zeyu Mi, Dingji Li, Haibo Chen, Binyu Zang, Haibing Guan</p>
    <p>Shanghai Jiao Tong University</p>
    <p>https://ipads.se.sjtu.edu.cn</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vulnerable Commercial Hypervisors</p>
    <p>Xen CVE is growing</p>
    <p>LoC: from 45K (v2.0) to 2,649K (v4.14.0)</p>
    <p>321 XSA</p>
    <p>KVM and VMware</p>
    <p>KVM: 110+ CVE</p>
    <p>VMware: 140+</p>
    <p>https://xenbits.xen.org/xsa/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analyzing 201 of Xens Vulnerabilities (XSA)</p>
    <p>10 are ignored144 are in the hypervisor E.g., Host DoS, privilege escalation, etc.</p>
    <p>Use hypervisor to attack VM</p>
    <p>47 are not in hypervisor Some are in Domain-0</p>
    <p>Some are in Qemu</p>
    <p>Shi L, Wu Y, Xia Y, et al. Deconstructing Xen. NDSS. 2017.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Existing Approaches  Software Method</p>
    <p>In-the-box: harden the hypervisor layer  Cannot eliminate the risks of exploiting hypervisor</p>
    <p>vulnerabilities  Out-of-the-box: nested virtualization</p>
    <p>Numerous VM exits bring performance overhead</p>
    <p>Hardware Method (Intel SGX)  Only available to run in user mode  Limited EPC memory incurs significant performance overhead</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CloudVisor (SOSP 11)  Observation: protection logics for VMs are mostly</p>
    <p>fixed</p>
    <p>Idea: Separate management from protection  Deprivilege the commercial hypervisor to non-root mode</p>
    <p>Result: Minimized TCB  VMM and CloudVisor separately designed and evolved</p>
    <p>VM</p>
    <p>CloudVisor</p>
    <p>HypervisorVM VM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Cost of Protection: Excessive VM Exits</p>
    <p>VM Xen Dom0</p>
    <p>CloudVisor</p>
    <p>Operation Times Hypercall &gt;= 2X</p>
    <p>EPT Violation 2  6 X</p>
    <p>DMA Operation &gt;= 2X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CloudVisor-D: No Compromise for Security &amp; Performance</p>
    <p>A secure and efficient design to shield VM in untrusted clouds  Do not trust the commercial hypervisor  Introduce negligible overheads compared to the Xen</p>
    <p>hypervisor</p>
    <p>Disaggregated nested virtualization  Deprivilege the hypervisor through nested virtualization  Disaggregate the nested hypervisor</p>
    <p>Offload VM operations and their protection work to the non-privileged mode</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Architecture of CloudVisor-D</p>
    <p>VM Guardian-VM</p>
    <p>RootVisorInitialization Isolation</p>
    <p>SubVisor</p>
    <p>A tiny nested hypervisor in root mode</p>
    <p>A Guardian-VM for each VM in non-root mode</p>
    <p>Most VM ops offloaded to Guardian-VM  Hypercalls  Memory virtualization  I/O operations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Threat Model</p>
    <p>TCB: RootVisor and each Guardian-VM</p>
    <p>Distrusing: SubVisor and all guest VMs</p>
    <p>Out of scope  physical attack  Side-channel attacks  DoS attacks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Secrets: VMFUNC  Switch EPT efficiently without VM Exits</p>
    <p>Faster than VM exit (134 vs. 301 cycles on Intel Skylake)</p>
    <p>EPTP 0 EPTP 1 EPTP 2 0</p>
    <p>EPTP 511</p>
    <p>EPT 0 EPT 1 EPT 2 EPT 511 EPT</p>
    <p>Pointer</p>
    <p>VM</p>
    <p>VM exit</p>
    <p>EPTP List</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CloudVisor-D as Reference Monitor</p>
    <p>CloudVisor-D satisfies two properties  Tamperproof: protect RootVisor and Guardian-VM from compromising</p>
    <p>Complete Mediation: interpose on all communication paths between SubVisor and VMs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Complete Mediation</p>
    <p>Two paths  RootVisor Path: VM-&gt;RootVisor-&gt;SubVisor  Guardian-VM Path: VM-&gt;Guardian-VM-&gt;SubVisor</p>
    <p>VM Guardian-VM</p>
    <p>RootVisor</p>
    <p>SubVisor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Faking VMFUNC Attacks</p>
    <p>Type-1: Bypass Guardian-VM  Access arbitrary memory region in VM or SubVisor</p>
    <p>Type-2: Attack Guardian-VM</p>
    <p>Bypass</p>
    <p>VM Guardian-VM</p>
    <p>RootVisor</p>
    <p>SubVisor</p>
    <p>SecretsVMFUNC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dynamic EPTP List Manipulation  An invalid EPTP entry triggers a VM exit</p>
    <p>Guardian-EPT 0</p>
    <p>Guest-EPT</p>
    <p>0</p>
    <p>VM Guardian-VM</p>
    <p>SubVisor</p>
    <p>RootVisor</p>
    <p>Guardian-EPT SubVisor-EPT</p>
    <p>0</p>
    <p>Error VMFUNC(1) VMFUNC(3)</p>
    <p>VMFUNC(2)</p>
    <p>EPTP List EPTP List</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other Techniques</p>
    <p>Isolated Guardian-VM Page Table</p>
    <p>Jump table</p>
    <p>Memory virtualization  Shadow EPT and virtualization exception</p>
    <p>I/O protection  Compatible with PV I/O model  Encryption and integrity guarantee</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Microbenchmark</p>
    <p>Operation Xen CloudVisor CloudVisor-D Speedup</p>
    <p>Hypercall 1758 4681 1810 61.3%</p>
    <p>EPT violation handling</p>
    <p>Virtual IPI 11214 21344 13331 37.5%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Applications</p>
    <p>#VM exits: 1,691,758 -&gt; 63,909</p>
    <p>UP VM SMP VM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>dbench: I/O Performance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Todays cloud tenants are facing severe security threats</p>
    <p>A secure and efficient system to shield VM in untrusted clouds  Disaggregated nested virtualization  Same level of security guarantee as nested virtualization  Introduce negligible overhead compared with the vanilla</p>
    <p>Xen</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
