<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Xudong Pan1, Mi Zhang1, Duocai Wu1, Qifan Xiao1, Shouling Ji2,3 and Min Yang1</p>
    <p>Justinians GAAvernor: Robust Distributed Learning with Gradient</p>
    <p>Aggregation Agent</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I want to train an Enemy Detector for my</p>
    <p>palace with Deep Learning techniques, yet I lack</p>
    <p>training data.</p>
    <p>G</p>
    <p>Take 1. Justinian, a Byzantine emperor with Deep Learning knowledge, ponders.</p>
    <p>Enemy Friend</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I send my 3 generals to each of my borderlands</p>
    <p>and train the enemy detector with local</p>
    <p>data.</p>
    <p>V0</p>
    <p>V2</p>
    <p>V1</p>
    <p>Take 2. Justinian seems know the paradigm of distributed learning.</p>
    <p>G</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Every 10 days, they 1report me with their latest</p>
    <p>local model updates. I 2aggregate the updates by</p>
    <p>average and 3update my palaces detector. They</p>
    <p>training.</p>
    <p>V0 V2V1</p>
    <p>Take 3-A: (Naive Technical Option). Gradient Aggregation by Average</p>
    <p>+ + G</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Finally, I get my palace an effective enemy</p>
    <p>detector, because of the ultimate loyalty of all my</p>
    <p>generals.</p>
    <p>Take 4-GE: Following the intuition ideally brings Justinian an effective enemy detector.</p>
    <p>V0</p>
    <p>V1</p>
    <p>+ + G</p>
    <p>V2</p>
    <p>EnemyEffective!</p>
    <p>Yes, you are an EMEMY!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Finally, my empire was under fire. One of my generals must have</p>
    <p>betrayed me and reported a malicious update :(</p>
    <p>V0 V2</p>
    <p>G</p>
    <p>= 3</p>
    <p>V1</p>
    <p>+ +</p>
    <p>Friendmisclassification</p>
    <p>but, Im an EMEMY!</p>
    <p>Take 4-BE: Byzantium was under fire.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I aggregate the updates by majority</p>
    <p>voting and update my palaces detector! It</p>
    <p>eliminates the malicious minority.</p>
    <p>V0 V2</p>
    <p>?G</p>
    <p>V1</p>
    <p>Take 3-B: (Mainstream Technical Options). Majority Voting</p>
    <p>Algorithmic Voting</p>
    <p>Vector-wise Voting (e.g., Krum, GeoMed) Eliminate the updates which are less close to the majority in vector distance.</p>
    <p>Coordinate-wise Voting (e.g., Bulyan, Coord-Med) Do elimination and aggregation respectively for each coordinate.</p>
    <p>Aggregate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Finally, I get my palace an effective enemy</p>
    <p>detector, even when I later knows one of my</p>
    <p>general is a traitor!</p>
    <p>Take 4-GE: Majority Voting usually brings me an effective enemy detector when I have no more than 49.9% traitors.</p>
    <p>V0 V2</p>
    <p>G</p>
    <p>V1</p>
    <p>Algorithmic Voting</p>
    <p>EnemyEffective!</p>
    <p>Yes, you are an EMEMY!</p>
    <p>V1/V2 Aggregate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Finally, my empire was under fire. A</p>
    <p>Majority of my generals all betrayed me and provided</p>
    <p>me with a malicious voting result :(</p>
    <p>Take 4-BE: Byzantium was under fire. V0 V2</p>
    <p>G</p>
    <p>V1</p>
    <p>Algorithmic Voting</p>
    <p>Friendmisclassification</p>
    <p>No, but Im an EMEMY!</p>
    <p>V0/V1 Aggregate</p>
    <p>Malicious Majority can happen in e.g., Federated Learning systems.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I hired a learnable GAAvernor to help</p>
    <p>me deal with the aggregation. He adjusts the credit on each general</p>
    <p>depending the situation.</p>
    <p>V0 V2G</p>
    <p>= V1</p>
    <p>+ +</p>
    <p>Take 3-C: (Our Contribution). Gradient Aggregation Agent (GAA)</p>
    <p>Initially, 0.33 0.34 0.33 x x x</p>
    <p>x x x Later on,</p>
    <p>V0 V2G</p>
    <p>= V1</p>
    <p>+ +</p>
    <p>How GAA becomes clever? Reinforcement Learning</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Emperors GAA Spec.: Action  Parametrize Linear GAR:</p>
    <p>(0,1,0)</p>
    <p>(1,0,0)</p>
    <p>(0,0,1)</p>
    <p>Action on Environment</p>
    <p>credit</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Emperors GAA Spec.: State &amp; Policy Network</p>
    <p>avg. pooling</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Emperors GAA Spec.: Quasi-Validation (QV) Set</p>
    <p>Definition: GAA has a small set of data samples, which respects a similar distribution to that of the generals (i.i.d.).</p>
    <p>A Quasi-Validation set can be</p>
    <p>A. An existing validation set or training set, for classical distributed learning systems (e.g., Train ResNet18 on ImageNet).</p>
    <p>B. A public dataset from similar application domains as that of the client (e.g., in an FL Sys. among hospitals, a QV set can be medical data published for research.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Emperors GAA Spec.: Reward</p>
    <p>Reward := the relative change of loss on the QV set (usually 10 samples)</p>
    <p>Cumulative Reward (as the learning objective):</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of the Byzantine Game</p>
    <p>The whole system is differentiable, and thus learns effectively with back-prop.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Take 4-GE: GAA brings me an effective enemy detector in more cases.  4 Benchmarks under static attacks</p>
    <p>GAA defends static attacks, where a  ratio of generals report random updates.</p>
    <p>Finally, I get my palace an effective enemy</p>
    <p>detector, even when I later know only one of my</p>
    <p>generals is loyal!</p>
    <p>Time Consumption for 100 Rounds</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More Applicable Scenarios</p>
    <p>Limitations: GAA may be limited when the QV set is fully known by the adversary.</p>
    <p>A. Randomized Attack: The role of all but one generals randomly reverses at a period.</p>
    <p>B. Pretense Attack: A  ratio of generals pretend to be loyal until the riot.</p>
    <p>C. Adaptive Attack: The traitors have partial knowledge about the QV set and report carefully-crafted malicious gradients.</p>
    <p>Random sampling, N-version scheme,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you for Audience! For more details, welcome to read our paper!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
