<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SAVIOR: Securing Autonomous Vehicles with Robust Physical Invariants</p>
    <p>Raul Quinonez1, Jairo Giraldo4, Luiz Salazar2, Erick Bauman1, Alvaro Cardenas2, Zhiqiang Lin3</p>
    <p>USENIX Security 2020</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Autonomous Vehicles</p>
    <p>Autonomous Vehicles (AVs) include aerial, sea, and ground vehicles</p>
    <p>Levels of automation range from 0 to 5</p>
    <p>AVs evaluate their environment with a variety of sensors</p>
    <p>[Gon17]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Problem</p>
    <p>[Mit19]</p>
    <p>[Goo19]</p>
    <p>[YC20]</p>
    <p>[Wei17]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AVs Are Vulnerable to Sensor Targeted Attacks</p>
    <p>Main Problem</p>
    <p>AVs rely on sensors to evaluate and interact with their environment</p>
    <p>Sensors are susceptible to GPS spoofing and transduction attacks that manipulate environmental physical signals</p>
    <p>Previous Research Has Exposed Sensor Vulnerabilities</p>
    <p>Camera [DWJ+16, PSFK15, YXL16]</p>
    <p>LiDAR [PSFK15, SKKK17, CXC+19]</p>
    <p>RADAR [YXL16]</p>
    <p>Inertial Measurement Unit (IMU) [SSK+15, TWX+17, TLLH18]</p>
    <p>GPS [NKS+19, HLP+08, TPRC11, ZLS+18]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transduction Attacks and GPS Attacks Cannot be Addressed with Classical Security</p>
    <p>Transduction Attacks</p>
    <p>Digital outputAnalog to digital converter</p>
    <p>Magnetic</p>
    <p>Acoustic</p>
    <p>Optical</p>
    <p>Attacker can inject out-of-band signals</p>
    <p>GPS Attacks</p>
    <p>Spoofer Actual position Spoofed position</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Insights of Our Work</p>
    <p>SAVIOR</p>
    <p>We introduce our SAVIOR (Securing Autonomous Vehicles wIth rObust physical invaRiants) framework contributing to the following:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sensors and Movement Variables</p>
    <p>Drones</p>
    <p>Sensors: accelerometer, gyroscope, magnetometer, and GPS (lat, lon, alt)</p>
    <p>Ground AV</p>
    <p>Sensors: line data (angle, position) and speed</p>
    <p>Pitch</p>
    <p>Roll</p>
    <p>Yaw</p>
    <p>Yaw</p>
    <p>a) Aerial vehicle movement</p>
    <p>b) Ground vehicle movement</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Nonlinear Models</p>
    <p>Dynamics of a Quadcopter [CFCH14, Luu11]</p>
    <p>=   =   =</p>
    <p>= U Ix</p>
    <p>+ ( Iy Iz Ix</p>
    <p>)</p>
    <p>= U Iy</p>
    <p>+ ( IzIx Iy</p>
    <p>)</p>
    <p>= U Iz</p>
    <p>+ ( IxIy Iz</p>
    <p>) x = vx y = vy z = vz vx =</p>
    <p>Ut m</p>
    <p>(cos  sin  cos  + sin  sin )</p>
    <p>vy = Ut m</p>
    <p>(cos  sin  sin   sin  cos ) vz =</p>
    <p>Ut m</p>
    <p>cos  cos  g</p>
    <p>Dynamics of a Car [KPSB15]</p>
    <p>= tan1( lr lr +lf</p>
    <p>tan()) x = v cos( + ) y = v sin( + )  = v</p>
    <p>lr sin()</p>
    <p>v = a</p>
    <p>v</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SAVIOR Design</p>
    <p>Online sensor pre-processing to convert raw data into usable form</p>
    <p>Offline pre-processing stage to learn physical invariants and a build model</p>
    <p>Online stage to predict measurements and compare observe values</p>
    <p>Anomaly detection will raise an alert if the anomaly is persistent</p>
    <p>IMU</p>
    <p>GPS</p>
    <p>Pre</p>
    <p>processing ()</p>
    <p>Y</p>
    <p>Inputs:</p>
    <p>Dataset</p>
    <p>Output:</p>
    <p>(, Y)</p>
    <p>IDS EKF</p>
    <p>Anomaly</p>
    <p>detection</p>
    <p>(, , , , , , ) Y ()</p>
    <p>()</p>
    <p>Offline</p>
    <p>Online</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Online Stage</p>
    <p>An Extended Kalman Filter (EKF) [RG14] is used to predict AVs physical behavior by estimating unknown parameters from noisy sensor input</p>
    <p>The algorithm is divided into two main routines: prediction and correction</p>
    <p>The prediction will be compared against the observed data to be analyzed for sensor tampering</p>
    <p>Prediction Predicted state estimate</p>
    <p>Predicted covariance estimate</p>
    <p>Correction Kalman gain</p>
    <p>State correction</p>
    <p>Updated covariance estimate</p>
    <p>!#$% &amp; =  !#,#</p>
    <p># &amp; = ##&amp;%#$%</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p># = # &amp;#</p>
    <p>[## &amp;# + ]&amp;%</p>
    <p>!#$% = !#$% &amp; + # #  (!#</p>
    <p>&amp;)</p>
    <p># = [  ##]# &amp;</p>
    <p>Initial estimates</p>
    <p>For !;&amp;, ;&amp;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anomaly Detection</p>
    <p>The residual associated with each sensor is calculated (1)</p>
    <p>A Cumulative Sum (CUSUM) algorithm is then used to detect persistent attacks (2)</p>
    <p>An alarm is raised if the residual difference is larger than a predefined threshold (3)</p>
    <p>CUSUM Algorithm</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p>EKF CUSUM =    Alert</p>
    <p>Residual Generation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation</p>
    <p>Controllers follow a publish-and-subscribe architecture to provide inter-process communication via topics</p>
    <p>We are interested in the following topics for aerial AVs: sensors combined, vehicle magnetometer, and vehicle gps position</p>
    <p>Anomaly detector is situated right before the control signals are being sent to the actuators</p>
    <p>The code runs in its own module in parallel with the controller</p>
    <p>Actuator module</p>
    <p>EKF</p>
    <p>Pre-processing</p>
    <p>ModulesModulesPX4 modulesPX4 modules vehicle_gps_position</p>
    <p>sensors_combined</p>
    <p>Reference monitor</p>
    <p>IMU Middleware</p>
    <p>Flight stack</p>
    <p>GPS</p>
    <p>vehicle_magnetometer</p>
    <p>actuator_outputs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>Aerial AV: Intel Ready-To-Fly drone using PX4 flight controller (v1.9.2)</p>
    <p>Ground AV: Custom build on top of a Traxxas Ford Fiesta ST Rally chassis using ROS Kinetic Kame controller</p>
    <p>Ground AV Top View</p>
    <p>Aerial AV Top View</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ground AV Camera Attack and Detection Video</p>
    <p>Videos available: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ljrbtfo0gvM&amp;list=PLmicm3IoL28eLU5v1FH3ZOFSn5NlOuQLG</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Aerial AV GPS Attack and Detection</p>
    <p>P o si</p>
    <p>tio n X</p>
    <p>-200</p>
    <p>-100</p>
    <p>P o si</p>
    <p>tio n Y</p>
    <p>D e te</p>
    <p>ct io</p>
    <p>n S</p>
    <p>ta tis</p>
    <p>tic</p>
    <p>D e te</p>
    <p>ct io</p>
    <p>n S</p>
    <p>ta tis</p>
    <p>tic</p>
    <p>Attack</p>
    <p>Attack</p>
    <p>Attack detected</p>
    <p>Attack detected</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparison of SAVIOR with Baseline</p>
    <p>SAVIOR uses a nonlinear model for predicting the observations, and a CUSUM algorithm for anomaly detection (NLC)</p>
    <p>We will use Choi et al.s [CLA+18] algorithm as a baseline since their anomaly detector was the current state-of-the-art</p>
    <p>Choi et al.s [CLA+18] algorithm uses linear models for predicting observations and a Time-Window algorithm for anomaly detection (LTW)</p>
    <p>Our results show that our algorithms outperform state-of-the-art detection tools for AVs by detecting more attacks, detecting attacks faster, and having less false alarms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Linear (LTW) vs Nonlinear (NLC) Prediction Comparison</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Window (LTW) vs CUSUM (NLC) Detection Time and ROC Curves</p>
    <p>Drone</p>
    <p>NLC detects attacks faster</p>
    <p>NLC has a better ROC curve than LTW</p>
    <p>P R</p>
    <p>ROC Curve</p>
    <p>NLC LTW</p>
    <p>T im</p>
    <p>e t o D</p>
    <p>e te</p>
    <p>ct</p>
    <p>LTW NLC</p>
    <p>Ground AV</p>
    <p>Detection is better for both, drones and ground vehicles</p>
    <p>TP R</p>
    <p>ROC Curve Ground Vehicle</p>
    <p>LTW NLC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Stealthy Attacks</p>
    <p>We want to maximize the value of sensor tampering without raising any alarms</p>
    <p>The goal is to maximize deviation without increasing the added discrepancies</p>
    <p>This stealthy attack allows us to consider the worst case scenario of our PBAD system, where an attacker is not detected while it persistently injects the maximum amount of false information in the system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Purely Stealthy Attacks Against NLC Have Less Impact Than LTW</p>
    <p>NLC (blue) is able to follow the signal closer while the attacker performed an stealthy attack on the gyroscope and GPS</p>
    <p>LTW (orange) allows more tampering which ends up deviating the final destination more than NLC (blue)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Overhead</p>
    <p>Drone</p>
    <p>On average, SAVIOR consumes 5.4332% of CPU resources on Intel Aero</p>
    <p>Module Armed Hovering RC</p>
    <p>Idle 30.1444% 29.4379% 30.6056% mavlink if1 16.0183% 15.6195% 15.8956%</p>
    <p>EKF2 14.3242% 14.3779% 14.3006% logger 6.8647% 7.1288% 6.8752%</p>
    <p>mc att control 5.4349% 5.4007% 5.3425% reference monitor 5.3572% 5.4332% 5.5093%</p>
    <p>tap esc 4.4742% 4.4357% 4.4285% sensors 4.2744% 4.4792% 4.5200% hpwork 2.5077% 2.4462% 2.4750%</p>
    <p>mavlink if0 2.3323% 2.1384% 2.2667% mc pos control 1.4911% 2.4727% 1.4693%</p>
    <p>commander 1.4824% 1.4478% 1.4448% gps 0.3662% 0.3323% 0.3077%</p>
    <p>Ground AV</p>
    <p>On average, SAVIOR consumes 2.2501% of CPU resources on Traxxas Ford Fiesta ST Rally</p>
    <p>Module Line Following CA</p>
    <p>lidar collision avoidance 12.6886% 13.0694% elp cam bridge 11.0179% 15.6009%</p>
    <p>process line 10.3861% 11.7353% image processing 6.0726% 7.8523% reference monitor 2.5192% 1.9809%</p>
    <p>arduino node 2.4150% 2.5133% line follower 1.0097% 1.0488%</p>
    <p>low level controller 0.7948% 0.4503% perot demo 0.6990% 0.6589% roslaunch 0.4541% 0.2678%</p>
    <p>rplidarNode 0.3074% 0.3020% rosmaster 0.2973% 0.1569%</p>
    <p>rosout 0.0658% 0.0250%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>The Key Elements of Our Proposal</p>
    <p>SAVIOR Source Code</p>
    <p>https://github.com/</p>
    <p>Cyphysecurity/SAVIOR.git</p>
    <p>Videos</p>
    <p>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ljrbtfo0gvM&amp;</p>
    <p>list=PLmicm3IoL28eLU5v1FH3ZOFSn5NlOuQLG</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You</p>
    <p>Contact</p>
    <p>Raul Quinonez rxq100020@utdallas.edu Jairo Giraldo jairo.giraldo@utah.edu Luiz Salazar luedsala@ucsc.edu Erick Bauman exb131030@utdallas.edu Alvaro Cardenas alacarde@ucsc.edu Zhiqiang Lin zlin@cse.ohio-state.edu</p>
    <p>Top view Front view</p>
    <p>Side view</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References I</p>
    <p>Anezka Chovancova, Tomas Fico, Lubos Chovanec, and Peter Hubinsk, Mathematical modelling and parameter identification of quadrotor (a survey), Procedia Engineering 96 (2014), 172181.</p>
    <p>Hongjun Choi, Wen-Chuan Lee, Yousra Aafer, Fan Fei, Zhan Tu, Xiangyu Zhang, Dongyan Xu, and Xinyan Xinyan, Detecting attacks against robotic vehicles: A control invariant approach, Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), ACM, 2018, pp. 801816.</p>
    <p>Yulong Cao, Chaowei Xiao, Benjamin Cyr, Yimeng Zhou, Won Park, Sara Rampazzi, Qi Alfred Chen, Kevin Fu, and Zhuoqing Morley Mao, Adversarial Sensor Attack on LiDAR-based Perception in Autonomous Driving, Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), 2019.</p>
    <p>Drew Davidson, Hao Wu, Robert Jellinek, Thomas Ristenpart, and Vikas Singh, Controlling UAVs with sensor input spoofing attacks, Workshop on Offensive Technologies (WOOT), USENIX Association, 2016, pp. 221231.</p>
    <p>Gloria Gonzalez, Autonomous vehicles, drones offer new insurer risks and opportunities, https://www.businessinsurance.com/article/20171207/NEWS06/912317799/Autonomous-vehicles,</p>
    <p>-drones-offer-new-insurer-risks-and-opportunities#, 2017.</p>
    <p>Dan Goodin, Researchers trick tesla autopilot into steering into oncoming traffic, https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2019/04/</p>
    <p>researchers-trick-tesla-autopilot-into-steering-into-oncoming-traffic/, 2019.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References II</p>
    <p>Todd E Humphreys, Brent M Ledvina, Mark L Psiaki, Brady W OHanlon, and Paul M Kintner, Assessing the spoofing threat: Development of a portable gps civilian spoofer, Radionavigation Laboratory Conference Proceedings, 2008.</p>
    <p>Jason Kong, Mark Pfeiffer, Georg Schildbach, and Francesco Borrelli, Kinematic and dynamic vehicle models for autonomous driving control design, Intelligent Vehicles Symposium (IV), IEEE, 2015, pp. 10941099.</p>
    <p>Teppo Luukkonen, Modelling and control of quadcopter, Independent research project in applied mathematics, Espoo 22 (2011).</p>
    <p>Roi Mit, Gps spoofing mystery affirms need for protection, https://www.wardsauto.com/industry-voices/gps-spoofing-mystery-affirms-need-protection, 2019.</p>
    <p>Juhwan Noh, Yujin Kwon, Yunmok Son, Hocheol Shin, Dohyun Kim, Jaeyeong Choi, and Yongdae Kim, Tractor beam: Safe-hijacking of consumer drones with adaptive gps spoofing, ACM Transactions on Privacy and Security (TOPS) 22 (2019), no. 2, 12.</p>
    <p>Jonathan Petit, Bas Stottelaar, Michael Feiri, and Frank Kargl, Remote attacks on automated vehicles sensors: Experiments on camera and lidar, Black Hat Europe 11 (2015).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References III</p>
    <p>S lawomir Romaniuk and Zdzis law Gosiewski, Kalman filter realization for orientation and position estimation on dedicated processor, acta mechanica et automatica 8 (2014), no. 2, 8894.</p>
    <p>Hocheol Shin, Dohyun Kim, Yujin Kwon, and Yongdae Kim, Illusion and dazzle: Adversarial optical channel exploits against lidars for automotive applications, International Conference on Cryptographic Hardware and Embedded Systems (CHES), Springer, 2017, pp. 445467.</p>
    <p>Yun Mok Son, Ho Cheol Shin, Dong Kwan Kim, Young Seok Park, Ju Hwan Noh, Ki Bum Choi, Jung Woo Choi, and Yong Dae Kim, Rocking drones with intentional sound noise on gyroscopic sensors, USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security), USENIX Association, 2015.</p>
    <p>Yazhou Tu, Zhiqiang Lin, Insup Lee, and Xiali Hei, Injected and delivered: fabricating implicit control over actuation systems by spoofing inertial sensors, USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security), USENIX Association, 2018, pp. 15451562.</p>
    <p>Nils Ole Tippenhauer, Christina Popper, Kasper Bonne Rasmussen, and Srdjan Capkun, On the requirements for successful gps spoofing attacks, Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), ACM, 2011, pp. 7586.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References IV</p>
    <p>Timothy Trippel, Ofir Weisse, Wenyuan Xu, Peter Honeyman, and Kevin Fu, Walnut: Waging doubt on the integrity of mems accelerometers with acoustic injection attacks, European Symposium on Security and Privacy (EuroS&amp;P), IEEE, 2017, pp. 318.</p>
    <p>Elizabeth Weise, Mysterious gps glitch telling ships theyre parked at airport may be anti-drone measure, https://www.usatoday.com/story/tech/news/2017/09/26/</p>
    <p>gps-spoofing-makes-ships-russian-waters-think-theyre-land/703476001/, 2017.</p>
    <p>Z. Morley Mao Yulong Cao, Autonomous vehicles can be fooled to see nonexistent obstacles, https://gcn.com/articles/2020/03/06/lidar-spoofs-autonomous-vehicle-hack.aspx, 2020.</p>
    <p>Chen Yan, Wenyuan Xu, and Jianhao Liu, Can you trust autonomous vehicles: Contactless attacks against sensors of self-driving vehicle, DEF CON 24 (2016).</p>
    <p>Kexiong Curtis Zeng, Shinan Liu, Yuanchao Shu, Dong Wang, Haoyu Li, Yanzhi Dou, Gang Wang, and Yaling Yang, All your GPS are belong to us: Towards stealthy manipulation of road navigation systems, USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security), USENIX Association, 2018, pp. 15271544.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
