<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Understanding South African Mobile Users Perceptions of Privacy and</p>
    <p>Current Behaviors on Facebook and WhatsApp</p>
    <p>Jake Reichel Fleming Peck Mikako Inaba Bisrat Moges Brahmnoor Chawla Marshini Chetty</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation Social media usage and device ownership rising in emerging markets [Poushter, 2018]</p>
    <p>Most studies on user privacy conducted in resource-rich nations, on student populations [Belanger, 2011]</p>
    <p>Few studies in resource-poor settings + most focus on Facebook only [Romanosky and Chetty, 2018] [Wyche et al, 2013] [Vashistha et al, 2018] [Nyoni and Velempini, 2015]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goals</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Design + Recruiting</p>
    <p>Online targeted advertisements, Twitter, and locally, via research assistant in Cape Town, South Africa</p>
    <p>Demographic + social media usage survey</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Setting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Setting (cont.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interview Format</p>
    <p>1 Hour, on-site interviews with 52 participants o Conducted in English and Xhosa o Example questions:</p>
    <p>- Is there anything you avoid doing on social media? What? Why? - Have you thought about who can see what youre sharing on social media? - Are you aware of privacy settings in any of the social media apps you use?</p>
    <p>o Compensation was gift card to Takealot.com o Analysis: Interviews were translated if needed, transcribed +</p>
    <p>underwent two rounds of qualitative data coding</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participant Demographics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings: Who can see what?</p>
    <p>Not a single mention of privacy from provider (i.e. ads)</p>
    <p>Privacy viewed as information control o Participant 35: A new girlfriend looking at pictures on Facebook of</p>
    <p>him with an ex-girlfriend was described as a breach of privacy</p>
    <p>Major privacy violations stemming from device sharing o Participant 3: My girlfriend changed my password, accessed my</p>
    <p>Facebook, and read my messages</p>
    <p>Presentation of self to community o Participant 18: I have too much respect for my elders and I do</p>
    <p>not want them to see pictures of me and my boyfriend all over social media</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings: Privacy settings</p>
    <p>58% either dont know of or how to use privacy settings</p>
    <p>vs</p>
    <p>Data costs limited the ability to change settings</p>
    <p>Heavy reliance on block feature</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings: Physical safety influence</p>
    <p>I ensure that I upload the pictures I would like to have even after my phone has gone missing - Participant 45</p>
    <p>Ive heard of people luring [people I know] with fake job opportunities and kidnapping or raping them - Participant 25</p>
    <p>Social media as data storage Concerns for physical safety</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations</p>
    <p>Who can see info: Add simple privacy settings o Implement post-level audience settings (Instagram &amp;</p>
    <p>WhatsApp)</p>
    <p>Lack of Knowledge: Make settings more accessible o Quickly review some important settings</p>
    <p>Connectivity: Challenge always-online assumptions o Bring settings forward o Configurable offline settings</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations (cont.)</p>
    <p>Physical safety: Accommodate usage in high-crime areas o Alternative to real-time posting o Alerts if identifying information is about to be posted</p>
    <p>Device sharing: Improve data compartmentalization on devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary  Findings</p>
    <p>o Users concern  Who can see what? o Unaware of existing controls + cannot access them (data costs) o Physical safety factors into privacy models</p>
    <p>Recommendations o Make settings more accessible, both online and offline o Improve data compartmentalization for phone sharing o Accommodate for areas of high crime</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Thank you to Research ICT Africa for generously opening their doors to us and allowing us to use their boardroom for interviews in Cape Town, to Minah Radebe for conducting interviews</p>
    <p>all over the city, and all our participants.</p>
    <p>Feel free to reach out Jake Reichel  jakereichel@gmail.com</p>
    <p>Marshini Chetty  marshini@uchicago.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
