<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Drift with Devil: Security of Multi-Sensor Fusion based Localization in High-Level Autonomous</p>
    <p>Driving under GPS Spoofing</p>
    <p>Junjie Shen, Jun Yeon Won, Zeyuan Chen, Qi Alfred Chen</p>
    <p>Autonomous System Guard Research GroupASGuard</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Autonomous Vehicles (AVs) are finally on public roads</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>High-Level Autonomous Driving (AD) System</p>
    <p>Perception</p>
    <p>Localization</p>
    <p>Planning</p>
    <p>Control</p>
    <p>Abundant sensors: LiDAR, GPS, IMU, Camera, Radar, etc.</p>
    <p>A typical Level-4 AV:</p>
    <p>Photo Credit: Baidu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Localization is critical to the safety of AV</p>
    <p>Localization Off-Road Wrong-Way</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GPS spoofing attack</p>
    <p>GPS is the de facto location input for AD localization  GPS spoofing attacks  Attacker sets arbitrary position by sending fake satellite</p>
    <p>signals  Still an open problem</p>
    <p>Demonstrated in cars, yachts, drones, smartphones, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GPS spoofing is pervasive!</p>
    <p>Source: Above Us Only Stars @ C4ADS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>However, production high-level AD systems widely adopt MSF-based localization design  Baidu Apollo, [ICRA18] [ITS16] [IV16] [Sensors15] [IROS13] [IJRR11], etc.  Leverage strengths &amp; compensate weaknesses of different sensors to</p>
    <p>generally improve accuracy &amp; robustness  Most popularly fuse from GPS, LiDAR, and IMU  Can achieve 5.4 cm accuracy</p>
    <p>In such a design, GPS alone cannot dictate the localization results</p>
    <p>Multi-Sensor Fusion (MSF) based AD localization</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MSF: Generally believed to have potential to defend against GPS spoofing</p>
    <p>[Cardenas, CyBOK 19]</p>
    <p>[Guvenc et al., IEEE Comm 18]</p>
    <p>[Davidson et al., WOOT 16]</p>
    <p>[Lee et al., SMC 17]</p>
    <p>[Zeng et al., USENIX Security 18]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Question:</p>
    <p>In AV settings, whether state-of-the-art MSF algorithms are indeed sufficiently secure under GPS spoofing?</p>
    <p>Short Answer: No, as long as the spoofing is done strategically!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>End-to-end attack demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem formulation and attack goals</p>
    <p>Problem formulation  Attacker spoofs GPS inputs with certain distances to victims physical positions  Aim to maximize lateral deviation in MSF output w.r.t. no attack</p>
    <p>Attack goals: cause victim to drive off-road or onto a wrong-way</p>
    <p>Physical position</p>
    <p>Off-Road Attack Wrong-Way Attack</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security analysis</p>
    <p>Aim to find maximum possible deviation achievable by spoofing  Target: Baidu Apollo MSF (representative in both design &amp; impl.)  MSF indeed improves security against GPS spoofing  Discovered an interesting take-over effect, causing an exponential</p>
    <p>growth trend of deviations  Spoofed GPS becomes dominating source to MSF</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security analysis</p>
    <p>Aim to find maximum possible deviation achievable by spoofing  Target: Baidu Apollo MSF (representative in both design &amp; impl.)  MSF indeed improves security against GPS spoofing  Discovered an interesting take-over effect, causing an exponential</p>
    <p>growth trend of deviations  Spoofed GPS becomes dominating source to MSF</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security analysis</p>
    <p>Aim to find maximum possible deviation achievable by spoofing  Target: Baidu Apollo MSF (representative in both design &amp; impl.)  MSF indeed improves security against GPS spoofing  Discovered an interesting take-over effect, causing an exponential</p>
    <p>growth trend of deviations  Spoofed GPS becomes dominating source to MSF</p>
    <p>Cause: Dynamic and non-deterministic factors  e.g., sensor noises, algorithm inaccuracies, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack design: FusionRipper</p>
    <p>Take-over vulnerability is hard to predict/control by attacker  Needs to exploit in an opportunistic way  FusionRipper: 2-stage attack  Vulnerability profiling + aggressive spoofing</p>
    <p>Stage 1: vulnerability profiling Stage 2: aggressive spoofing</p>
    <p>Vulnerable!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation result highlights</p>
    <p>Evaluate on 6 real-world AV sensor traces  Always exists &gt;= one attack parameter can achieve 98.6% &amp; 95.9% success</p>
    <p>rates to cause lane departure or wrong-way driving  Takes only ~30 sec to succeed</p>
    <p>Practical attack considerations  Robust to spoofing inaccuracies and AD control  Success rate only down by &lt;= 4%</p>
    <p>Also did ablation study, generality analysis (w/ 2 other MSF designs), comparison w/ naive attack, black-box attack design (profiling cost &lt;= half a day), etc.  More details in the paper</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Potential defenses</p>
    <p>Fundamental solutions are not immediately deployable  Prevent GPS spoofing; improve sensing and AD localization technologies</p>
    <p>Actionable mitigation: attack detection &amp; emergency stop  Based on GPS spoofing detection, or camera-based lane detection  Still can cause DoS, but better than directly causing safety damages</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Responsible vulnerability disclosure</p>
    <p>As of 7/20/20, informed 29 companies developing/testing Level-4 AVs  16 has replied so far and have started investigation  1 of them is working on a fix</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>First security analysis on MSF-based AD localization under GPS spoofing  Discover take-over vulnerability that fundamentally defeats MSF</p>
    <p>design principle  Design FusionRipper to opportunistically capture &amp; exploit the vuln.  Design offline profiling method to improve attack practicality  Informed 29 companies developing/testing Level-4 AVs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you! More details please visit our project website:</p>
    <p>https://sites.google.com/view/cav-sec/fusionripper Scan to visit our project website</p>
    <p>Autonomous System Guard Research GroupASGuard</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
