<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Ballot is Busted Before the Blockchain: A Security Analysis of Voatz, the First Internet</p>
    <p>Application used in U.S. Federal Elections</p>
    <p>specter@mit.edu Michael A. Specter, James Koppel, Danny Weitzner</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In February, the state of West Virginia abruptly abandoned plans to adopt an internet voting phone app called Voatz</p>
    <p>This research is why.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(https://www.cdc.gov/ncbddd/disabilityandhealth/impacts/west-virginia.html)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions</p>
    <p>Does Voatz provide the essential security requirements of voting?  Correctness: Counted as cast, cast as intended, usability  Privacy: An attacker cannot learn a voters selections  Receipt Freeness: No voter can prove the way they voted  Coercion Resistance: A voter cannot cooperate with an attacker to prove the way they voted</p>
    <p>Advertised use of cryptography:  Hardware-backed key storage!  Mixnets!  And, of course, the Blockchain!  Is this End to end verifiable (E2E-V)?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology  Challenge:</p>
    <p>Cant touch server infrastructure (legal &amp; ethical concerns)  Must make assumptions about the backend</p>
    <p>Solution:  Manually reverse engineer the Voatz Android app  Iteratively reimplement the server to understand protocol  For analysis, assume the best possible situation for the backend</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results  5 high-severity vulnerabilities &amp; a serious privacy issue  Many basic implementation failures, e.g.:</p>
    <p>Mandated use of weak passwords  Anti-tamper/AV solution was easily circumventable  Sends a photo of users ID, and location to a third party without alerting the user</p>
    <p>API Server has complete control  No proofs of inclusion (wheres the Blockchain?)  Weak receipt validation, not E2E-V</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Passive Network Attack</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Standard HTTPS</p>
    <p>Gen 100 ECDSA Key Pairs.</p>
    <p>Gen 100 ECDSA key pairs Key57  Key agreement with the senders 57th key AESGCMsk $ RECDSAEnc(Key57, AESGCMsk), 100 PubKeys</p>
    <p>All comms Enc(AESGCMsk, *)</p>
    <p>Perform key agreement &amp; decrypt AESGCMsk</p>
    <p>Discards all secret keys, except #57</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Short_Candidate = { &quot;choiceDetails&quot; : { &quot;imageUrl&quot;: short.com/img.jpg, &quot;webUrl&quot; : short.com/desc }, &quot;choiceId&quot;: &quot;1&quot;, &quot;description&quot;: &quot;Short&quot;, &quot;description 1&quot;: &quot;^&quot;, &quot;description 2&quot;: &quot;^&quot;, &quot;isWriteIn&quot;: False, &quot;nonSelectable&quot; : False }</p>
    <p>Long_Candidate = { &quot;choiceDetails&quot;: { &quot;imageUrl&quot;: www.LONG_IMG_URL.info/LONG_IMG_URL.jpg, &quot;webUrl&quot; : www.LONG_IMG_URL.info/Long_Candidate_Info }, &quot;choiceId&quot; : &quot;2&quot;, &quot;description&quot;: &quot;Long Description !&quot;, &quot;description 1&quot; : &quot;See? Its super long .REALLLY long.111111&quot;, &quot;description 2&quot; : &quot;EPICALLYLOOOOOOOOOOOOONG....&quot;, &quot;isWriteIn&quot;: False , &quot;nonSelectable&quot; : False }</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>When the user submits their ballot  Sends *all* metadata of the voters choice  But only that candidates metadata</p>
    <p>Short_Candidate = { &quot;choiceDetails&quot; : { &quot;imageUrl&quot;: short.com/img.jpg, &quot;webUrl&quot; : short.com/desc }, &quot;choiceId&quot;: &quot;1&quot;, &quot;description&quot;: &quot;Short&quot;, &quot;description 1&quot;: &quot;^&quot;, &quot;description 2&quot;: &quot;^&quot;, &quot;isWriteIn&quot;: False, &quot;nonSelectable&quot; : False }</p>
    <p>Long_Candidate = { &quot;choiceDetails&quot;: { &quot;imageUrl&quot;: www.LONG_IMG_URL.info/LONG_IMG_URL.jpg, &quot;webUrl&quot; : www.LONG_IMG_URL.info/Long_Candidate_Info }, &quot;choiceId&quot; : &quot;2&quot;, &quot;description&quot;: &quot;Long Description !&quot;, &quot;description 1&quot; : &quot;See? Its super long .REALLLY long.111111&quot;, &quot;description 2&quot; : &quot;EPICALLYLOOOOOOOOOOOOONG....&quot;, &quot;isWriteIn&quot;: False , &quot;nonSelectable&quot; : False }</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Textbook Side-channel attack Regular HTTPS:</p>
    <p>Ciphertext = AES(gzip(data))  len(ciphertext) ~= len(gzip(data))  Plaintext length is *somewhat* obfuscated</p>
    <p>Voatz Protocol:</p>
    <p>Ciphertext = AES(gzip(AES(data))  len(gzip(AES(data))) = len(data)  len(Ciphertext) ~= len(data)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How did this happen?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Obfuscation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Documentation  FAQ with a bunch of security claims (https://perma.cc/FBQ8-N875)</p>
    <p>No formal description of their system</p>
    <p>No security reviews made public  No list of fixed vulns  Unclear claims</p>
    <p>...doubly anonymized: first by the smartphone, and second by the blockchain server network.  ...end-to-end vote encryption and vetting the certificates represented by unique IDs stored on</p>
    <p>the smartphone   anonymized voter-verified digital receipts   voter-verified audit trail</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Code Obfuscation</p>
    <p>All code was obfuscated using Proguard  Protocol strings (e.g. AES_GCM) were obfuscated</p>
    <p>Used a string-encoding scheme that deobfuscated at run-time  Common in games, DRM kits, and malware</p>
    <p>Nonstandard 57th key protocol  Bug bounty version of the app also obfuscated  No concrete security benefit</p>
    <p>...but it does make independent analysis harder.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We fully support the West Virginia Secretary of States office and the law enforcement agencies in their investigations under the purview of the law. Given that our elections infrastructure is classified as critical infrastructure under the Department of Homeland Security, we will continue to report any such attempts in the future.</p>
    <p>- CEO Nimit Sawhney</p>
    <p>https://statescoop.com/voatz-voting-app-west-virginia-fbi-hacking-attempt/ 18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OK, then.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>&quot;...the researchers true aim is to deliberately disrupt the election process, to sow doubt in the security of our election infrastructure, and to spread fear and confusion.&quot;</p>
    <p>https://blog.voatz.com/?p=1243</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The unit has security software that was two generations old, and to our knowledge is not used anywhere in the country.</p>
    <p>https://freedom-to-tinker.com/2006/09/20/refuting-diebolds-response/</p>
    <p>By any standard  academic or common sense  the study is unrealistic and inaccurate.</p>
    <p>...the researchers were analyzing an Android version of the Voatz mobile voting app that was at least 27 versions old at the time of their disclosure and not used in an election.</p>
    <p>...the researchers fabricated an imagined version of the Voatz servers, hypothesized how they worked, and then made assumptions about the interactions between the system components that are simply false.</p>
    <p>https://blog.voatz.com/?p=1243</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voatzs own 3rd Party Security Analysis  Confirmed vulns in most recent version  Confirmed severity</p>
    <p>*Before Voatz spoke to the press*</p>
    <p>Validated our methodology  Found many server-side issues:</p>
    <p>AV wasnt running during past elections  +40 other issues</p>
    <p>...Still not an independent audit</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We partner with organizations that prioritize acting in good faith towards the security researcher community and providing adequate</p>
    <p>access to researchers for testing.</p>
    <p>Because the Voatz program did not adhere to either of those requirements, we terminated our partnership in March 2020.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>-Bradley Tusk, Voatz Backer &amp; Mobile Voting Project founder</p>
    <p>Its not that the cybersecurity people are bad people, per se.</p>
    <p>I think its that they are solving for one situation, and I am solving for another. They want zero technology risk in any way, shape, or form. [...] I am solving for the problem of turnout.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Argument: Solve a Policy Problem through</p>
    <p>Technology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem: Unanalyzed Risk.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Asymmetric Information</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hack on everything else.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>specter@mit.edu</p>
    <p>Michael A. Specter, James Koppel, Danny Weitzner</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
