<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Light Commands: Laser-Based Audio Injection on Voice-Controllable Systems</p>
    <p>Takeshi Sugawara, Benjamin Cyr, Sara Rampazzi, Daniel Genkin, Kevin Fu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voice Controllable Systems (VCSs)</p>
    <p>speech recognition</p>
    <p>system signal</p>
    <p>processing command execution</p>
    <p>voice command</p>
    <p>microphone</p>
    <p>[Source: pandaily.com] [Source: developers.google.com]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Concerns  Sacrifice of security to promote usability  Interfacing with 3rd Party Software  Blind trust in microphone readings</p>
    <p>123...</p>
    <p>124...</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>Incorrect Passcode, Try Again...</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>Incorrect Passcode, Try Again...</p>
    <p>125... Incorrect Passcode, Try Again...</p>
    <p>438 OK, Opening the front door</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problem</p>
    <p>Assumption:</p>
    <p>Microphones capture acoustic signals</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problem</p>
    <p>Reality:</p>
    <p>Microphones capture acoustic signals &amp; LIGHT signals</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problem</p>
    <p>Two Questions: 1. How does laser injection affect VCSs? 2. How can we protect VCSs against laser injection?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions</p>
    <p>Inject light commands via MEMS microphones  Analyze limits of light-based VCS vulnerabilities</p>
    <p>Success at 110m with 5mW laser pointer  Works through glass windows between buildings</p>
    <p>Demonstrate risks to smart speakers, phones, smart homes, and cars</p>
    <p>Suggest HW and SW countermeasures</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MEMS Microphones  Used in most Voice Controllable Systems  The diaphragm and backplate work as a capacitor  When diaphragm moves, causes a change in capacitance</p>
    <p>The ASIC converts the capacitive change to voltage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MEMS microphones exhibit light sensitivity  Output voltage affected by light irradiance  Inject signal by modulating optical power</p>
    <p>MEMS Microphones</p>
    <p>Laser beam</p>
    <p>Irradiance:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key ideas 1. Amplitude modulated light generates a voltage</p>
    <p>signal on microphone output 2. Higher amplitude light == higher amplitude voltage 3. Very little distortion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How is this Working? Combination of two physical effects:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Signal Injection via Laser</p>
    <p>Audio voltage signal from laptop  Laser current driver converts to current signal</p>
    <p>With DC Bias  Laser output power is proportional to current</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VCS Command Injection via Light</p>
    <p>Laptop Audio Laser Current Driver Amp</p>
    <p>OK Google, Open the Garage Door</p>
    <p>OK, Opening</p>
    <p>Voltage Signal Current Signal Light SignalDigital Signal</p>
    <p>Laser Diode</p>
    <p>Target</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measuring Vulnerability - Power</p>
    <p>Investigated 17 devices  Used scanning mirrors  Measured minimum</p>
    <p>optical power to recognize commands</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measuring Vulnerability - Range</p>
    <p>Measuring the maximum range of the attack</p>
    <p>Optics!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack Results</p>
    <p>Laser pointer power!</p>
    <p>Phones/Tablets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cross-Building Attack Scenario</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack Demonstration</p>
    <p>Demos available at lightcommands.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consequences</p>
    <p>Open garage doors Unlock car Start engine</p>
    <p>Brute force unlock door Unauthorized purchases</p>
    <p>Turn on/off Enable/Disable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations</p>
    <p>Dependence on Focusing, Aiming, Acoustic Noise, and Audio Quality</p>
    <p>Requires Line of Sight  Very little diffraction  Difficult to target top microphones</p>
    <p>Limited Feedback</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Countermeasures</p>
    <p>Software Approaches  Stronger Authentication  Liveness Tests  Sensor Fusion: Compare</p>
    <p>Multiple Microphones</p>
    <p>Please confirm by repeating the second digit of your passcode</p>
    <p>Hardware Approaches  Light-Blocking Covers</p>
    <p>On the VCS (fabric)  Inside the MEMS Mic</p>
    <p>Please give the passcode to unlock the garage door</p>
    <p>...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Deep exploration of physical causality - Lead to future defenses</p>
    <p>Other Vulnerabilities: - Non-MEMs Microphones - Other Motion Sensors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work Attacks on VCS Speech Recognition:</p>
    <p>- Vaidya et al., Cocaine noodles: exploiting the gap between human and machine speech recognition, USENIX WOOT, 2015. - Carlini et al., Hidden voice commands. in USENIX 2016. - Yuan et al., CommanderSong: A systematic approach for practical adversarial voice recognition, in USENIX 2018 - Kumar et al., Skill squatting attacks on Amazon Alexa, in USENIX 2018.</p>
    <p>Acoustic Injection on VCS via Ultrasound: - Roy et al., Backdoor: Making microphones hear inaudible sounds, in ACM MobiSys 2017. - L. Song and P. Mittal, Inaudible voice commands, arXiv preprint arXiv:1708.07238, 2017 - Zhang et al., DolphinAttack: Inaudible voice commands, in ACM CCS 2017. - Roy et al., Inaudible voice commands: The long-range attack and defense, in USENIX NSDI 2018.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Lasers can inject commands into VCSs  Long range with low optical power  Physical vulnerability in MEMS microphones  Highlights security flaws in VCSs  Blind trust of any input often</p>
    <p>points to vulnerabilities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You! Authors: Takeshi Sugawara, Benjamin Cyr, Sara Rampazzi, Daniel Genkin, Kevin Fu</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Website: lightcommands.com</p>
    <p>My Email: bencyr@umich.edu</p>
    <p>Team: LightCommandsTeam@gmail.com</p>
    <p>This research was funded by JSPS KAKENHI Grant #JP18K18047 and #JP18KK0312, by DARPA and AFRL under contracts FA8750-19-C-0531 and HR001120C0087, by NSF under grants CNS-1954712 and CNS-2031077, gifts from Intel, AMD, and Analog Devices, and an award from MCity at the University of Michigan.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
