<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>You Are What You Broadcast: Identification of Mobile and IoT Devices</p>
    <p>from (Public) WiFi</p>
    <p>Lingjing Yu, Bo Luo, Jun Ma, Zhaoyu Zhou, and Qingyun Liu</p>
    <p>USENIX Security Symposium, Boston, MA. August 2020</p>
    <p>THE UNIVERSITY OF KANSAS</p>
    <p>TSINGHUA UNIVERSITY</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device identification in communication and</p>
    <p>computing</p>
    <p>Device management</p>
    <p>Network measurement Cyber situational awareness</p>
    <p>Malicious device discovery</p>
    <p>Device Identification: Why?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OWL: Overhearing on WiFi for Device Identification</p>
    <p>When a mobile/IoT device connects to a WiFi network, we want to know that it is.</p>
    <p>To identify the manufacturer, type, model of mobile devices using public information.</p>
    <p>Task 1: Device Identification</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OWL: Overhearing on WiFi for Device Identification</p>
    <p>When a malicious device connects to a WiFi network, we want an alert.</p>
    <p>To detect the abnormal devices, whose BC/MC traffic deviates from benign patterns.</p>
    <p>Task 2: Malicious Device Detection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OWL: Overhearing on WiFi for Device Identification</p>
    <p>When a device is connected to a wireless network, it sends out broadcast or multicast packets: DHCP, mDNS, SSDP, etc</p>
    <p>Use these packets to fingerprint devices.</p>
    <p>Core Idea: Use Features from Broadcast/Multicast Packets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Data Collection</p>
    <p>Public WiFi with Captive Portals</p>
    <p>Encrypted WiFiOpen Public WiFi</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Data Collection</p>
    <p>Collected Broadcast/Multicast traffic from 176 WiFi Networks, 12 networks disabled BC/MC traffic</p>
    <p>Locations: coffee shops, restaurants, retail stores, airports, hotels, corporate guest networks, universities, authors own homes</p>
    <p>BC/MC packets from 31,850 unique devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Data Collection</p>
    <p>We collected data through a completely passive approach.</p>
    <p>We did not turn on promiscuous mode: we were the legitimate and intended receivers of these BC/MC packets. NO unicast traffic.</p>
    <p>No violation of Terms and Conditions to our best knowledge.</p>
    <p>Discussed with two Institutional Review Boards.</p>
    <p>Post-processing to remove any potential personal identifier.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Data Collection</p>
    <p>The ground truth dataset  The identity of each device is physically verified  423 devices with {manufacturer, type, model} labels  E.g., {D-link, camera, dcs-930lb}</p>
    <p>The annotated dataset  Labeled by annotators based on human-readable content  4064 devices with {manufacturer, type, model} labels  6519 devices with {manufacturer, type} labels  15895 devices with only {manufacturer} label</p>
    <p>The sanitized dataset  Removed all human interpretable textual features from</p>
    <p>the annotated dataset.  MAC prefixes are also removed.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Feature Extraction</p>
    <p>Identifiers. MAC prefix, HostName in DHCP, etc.  Informative, unique  not always available, may be tampered</p>
    <p>Main Features. Key-value pairs, pseudo natural language features  Not unique identifiers  Robust, available, provide good discriminatory power</p>
    <p>Auxiliary Features. SSDP notify  URL  device description file  Include identifiers (device names)  Need to actively retrieve the file, not always available</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Feature Extraction</p>
    <p>Identifiers. MAC prefix, HostName in DHCP, etc.  Informative, unique  not always available, may be tampered</p>
    <p>Main Features. Key-value pairs, pseudo natural language features  Not unique identifiers  Robust, available, provide good discriminatory power</p>
    <p>Auxiliary Features. SSDP notify  URL  device description file  Include identifiers (device names)  Need to actively retrieve the file, not always available</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Feature Extraction</p>
    <p>Identifiers. MAC prefix, HostName in DHCP, etc.  Informative, unique  not always available, may be tampered</p>
    <p>Main Features. Key-value pairs, pseudo natural language features  Not unique identifiers  Robust, available, provide good discriminatory power</p>
    <p>Auxiliary Features. SSDP notify  URL  device description file  Include identifiers (device names)  Need to actively retrieve the file, only used in evaluation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Feature Extraction</p>
    <p>Features from different protocols complement each other</p>
    <p>Each protocol generates an independent set of features</p>
    <p>Not all protocols are available in all devices</p>
    <p>Multi-view Classification</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Multi-view Wide and Deep Learning</p>
    <p>The deep component: early fusion; maximize the generalization performance</p>
    <p>The wide component: late fusion; improve the memorization of label-view interaction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Multi-view Wide and Deep Learning</p>
    <p>: best classification performance for device labels under input features</p>
    <p>: to optimize classification performance on each view</p>
    <p>+: view consistency: to maximize view agreement for benign samples</p>
    <p>+: to maximize the view inconsistency for malicious devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Multi-view Wide and Deep Learning</p>
    <p>: best classification performance for device labels under input features</p>
    <p>: to optimize classification performance on each view</p>
    <p>+: view consistency: to maximize view agreement for benign samples</p>
    <p>+: to maximize the view inconsistency for malicious devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Multi-view Wide and Deep Learning</p>
    <p>: best classification performance for device labels under input features</p>
    <p>: to optimize classification performance on each view</p>
    <p>+: view consistency: to maximize view agreement for benign samples</p>
    <p>: to maximize the view inconsistency for known malicious devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Experiments</p>
    <p>Coverage: the fraction of all devices that OWL could generate a label for.</p>
    <p>Accuracy: the fraction of labeled devices that are correctly labeled</p>
    <p>Overall Identification Rate: the faction of all devices that are correctly labeled.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Experiments</p>
    <p>[ARE] Xuan Feng, Qiang Li, Haining Wang, and Limin Sun. Acquisitional rule-based engine for discovering internet-of-things devices. In USENIX Security, 2018. [WDMTI] Lingjing Yu, Tao Liu, Zhaoyu Zhou, Yujia Zhu, Qingyun Liu, and Jianlong Tan. WDMTI: Wireless Device Manufacturer and Type Identification using Hierarchical Dirichlet Process. In IEEE MASS, 2018.</p>
    <p>Performance on Ground truth Data  OWL provides the best overall performance</p>
    <p>(OIR) at all granularity levels.  OWLs coverage is consistently the highest.  At finer granularity, OWL significantly</p>
    <p>outperforms both ARE and WDMTI in OIR.  ARE has the best accuracy but limited</p>
    <p>coverage, especially at fine granularity levels.</p>
    <p>WDMTIs coverage is always limited.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Experiments</p>
    <p>Performance on Annotated Data  Again, OWL provides the best overall</p>
    <p>performance (OIR) at all granularity levels.  Accuracy (A*) and OIR (OIR*) was only</p>
    <p>evaluated on partial data in {M, T} and {M, T, M} categories.</p>
    <p>A* and OIR* represent the upper-bound of the actual A and OIR.</p>
    <p>OIR* in the range of [0.95, 0.98]</p>
    <p>[ARE] Xuan Feng, Qiang Li, Haining Wang, and Limin Sun. Acquisitional rule-based engine for discovering internet-of-things devices. In USENIX Security, 2018. [WDMTI] Lingjing Yu, Tao Liu, Zhaoyu Zhou, Yujia Zhu, Qingyun Liu, and Jianlong Tan. WDMTI: Wireless Device Manufacturer and Type Identification using Hierarchical Dirichlet Process. In IEEE MASS, 2018.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Device Identification: Experiments</p>
    <p>Performance on Sanitized Data  All human-interpretable contents are</p>
    <p>removed from annotated dataset.  This is to evaluate OWLs performance in</p>
    <p>extreme conditions.  A and OIR represent the lower-bound of</p>
    <p>the actual A and OIR.  OWLs OIR is still high, in the range of [0.75,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Malicious Device Detection: Approach</p>
    <p>: best classification performance for device labels under input features</p>
    <p>: to memorize the interactions among features, views and labels</p>
    <p>+: view consistency: to maximize view agreement for benign samples</p>
    <p>: to maximize the view inconsistency for known malicious devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Malicious Device Detection: Case Study</p>
    <p>Spoofed Apple TV (31 devices)  mDNS view: AppleTV, high confidence  Other views: not AppleTV, high confidence  Labels: not AppleTV, some in ground truth dataset  AirPlay: Apples proprietary protocol suite for</p>
    <p>multimedia streaming over WiFi  mDNS packets of these devices were similar to</p>
    <p>AppleTV, so that others may AirPlay on them  They were all connected to a corporation named</p>
    <p>Lebo (or HappyCast)</p>
    <p>mDNS view other views</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OWL: Overhearing on WiFi for Device Identification</p>
    <p>OWL</p>
    <p>MvWDL</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>email:yulingjing@iie.ac.cn</p>
    <p>Thanks for listeningQ&amp;A</p>
    <p>Lingjing Yu, Zhaoyu Zhou, and Qingyun Liu were supported in part by the Youth Innovation Promotion Association of the Chinese Academy of Sciences, and the Key Technical Talents Project of CAS; Bo Luo was supported in part by US National Science Foundation, NSA Science of Security (SoS) Initiative, and the Ripple University Blockchain Research Initiative.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
