<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed, Patrick Shaffer, Kay Connelly, David Crandall, Apu Kapadia</p>
    <p>Addressing Physical Safety, Security, and Privacy for People with Visual</p>
    <p>Impairments</p>
    <p>Indiana University Bloomington</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Visual impairment is not total blindness It is sight loss that cannot be fully corrected using glasses or contact lenses.</p>
    <p>Macular degenerationRetinitis Pigmentosa Source: Wikipedia Source: Wikipedia</p>
    <p>Glaucoma Source: ACBVI</p>
    <p>Low Vision/Cataract Source: cs.utah.edu</p>
    <p>Diabetic Retinopathy Source: CNIB</p>
    <p>Hemianopia Source:visionsimulators</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sighted people can monitor their surroundings easily</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Previous studies revealed concerns about (physical) privacy</p>
    <p>Tousif Ahmed, Roberto Hoyle, Kay Connelly, David Crandall, and Apu Kapadia, Privacy Concerns and Behaviors of People with Visual Impairments In The Proceedings of ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 15)</p>
    <p>Device Privacy and Security Concerns</p>
    <p>Physical Privacy and Security Concerns</p>
    <p>Eavesdropping</p>
    <p>Shoulder Surfing Eavesdropping</p>
    <p>Kane et al (2009), Azenkot et al (2012), Ahmed et al (2015), Dosono et al (2015), Sauer et al (2010)</p>
    <p>Device Security Web Security</p>
    <p>Lack of Independence Home Security</p>
    <p>Ahmed et al (2015)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Previous studies revealed concerns about (physical) privacy</p>
    <p>Tousif Ahmed, Roberto Hoyle, Kay Connelly, David Crandall, and Apu Kapadia, Privacy Concerns and Behaviors of People with Visual Impairments In The Proceedings of ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 15)</p>
    <p>Device Privacy and Security Concerns</p>
    <p>Physical Privacy and Security Concerns</p>
    <p>Eavesdropping</p>
    <p>Shoulder Surfing Eavesdropping</p>
    <p>Kane et al (2009), Azenkot et al (2012), Ahmed et al (2015), Dosono et al (2015), Sauer et al (2010)</p>
    <p>Device Security Web Security</p>
    <p>Lack of Independence Home Security</p>
    <p>Count the number of people nearby</p>
    <p>Detect and specify specific faces nearby</p>
    <p>Detect shoulder surfing</p>
    <p>Read private documents</p>
    <p>Technology Ideas Life Logging Cameras</p>
    <p>getnarrative.com</p>
    <p>Wearable Glasses www.orcam.com</p>
    <p>Smart Watches www.fubiz.net</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Goal</p>
    <p>RQ: How can wearable devices address the privacy and security concerns of people with visual impairments?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We interviewed an urban population of people with visual impairments (N=19)</p>
    <p>Male, 9</p>
    <p>Female, 10</p>
    <p>Age Distribution</p>
    <p>T, 8</p>
    <p>L, 5</p>
    <p>X, 6</p>
    <p>T (Congenitally Total Blind)</p>
    <p>L (Congenitally Low Vision)</p>
    <p>X (Late Impaired)</p>
    <p>CRIME INDEX (U.S. AVERAGE=294.7)</p>
    <p>Crime Index Distribution</p>
    <p>P re</p>
    <p>vi ou</p>
    <p>s st</p>
    <p>ud y</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our interviews shed light on safety and security concerns and behaviors</p>
    <p>RQ1: How can wearable devices address privacy, safety, and security concerns of people with visual impairments?</p>
    <p>RQ1: What are the privacy, safety, and security concerns of people with visual impairments?</p>
    <p>RQ2: How do people with visual impairments manage their privacy, safety and security?</p>
    <p>RQ3: How can wearable devices address privacy, safety, and security concerns of people with visual impairments?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demographics and history age, level of visual impairment, history of impairments</p>
    <p>Privacy and Security Scenarios related to sharing health information, reading email and withdrawing money from ATM</p>
    <p>Design Considerations what types of information, which device, how to interact and how to provide feedback</p>
    <p>Structure of the interview</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two researchers identified key concepts</p>
    <p>Recorded and transcribed audio</p>
    <p>Coding procedure iterative process using open coding, created a codebook</p>
    <p>Seven groups of concepts e.g. safety concerns, privacy concerns, feelings, coping behavior, design attributes, desired information and feedback</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What are the physical safety and security concerns?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We identified four groups of safety and security concerns</p>
    <p>www.israelnationalnews.com</p>
    <p>Public Transit</p>
    <p>sanfrancisco.cbslocal.com</p>
    <p>On the Street</p>
    <p>www.freep.com</p>
    <p>magneetmedia.com</p>
    <p>Private Spaces</p>
    <p>www.smartfoxsecurity.com</p>
    <p>thehomeworksgroup.com</p>
    <p>ATM Booths</p>
    <p>newsblogs.chicagotribune.com</p>
    <p>www.bcliving.ca</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed 13</p>
    <p>www.israelnationalnews.com</p>
    <p>Public Transit</p>
    <p>sanfrancisco.cbslocal.com</p>
    <p>On the Street</p>
    <p>www.freep.com</p>
    <p>magneetmedia.com</p>
    <p>Private Spaces</p>
    <p>www.smartfoxsecurity.com</p>
    <p>thehomeworksgroup.com</p>
    <p>ATM Booths</p>
    <p>newsblogs.chicagotribune.com</p>
    <p>www.bcliving.ca</p>
    <p>It is not safe to walk on the streets</p>
    <p>When I go for walks, I have been followed. And so basically because of how society is today, I dont go for walks with my guide dog because I dont know who is around me and I think that is much more debilitating for me than anything that we have discussed. Not knowing my environment, not knowing who is around me and if something happened to me I would not be able to tell anyone.</p>
    <p>-T7 (Totally Blind)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed 14</p>
    <p>www.israelnationalnews.com</p>
    <p>Public Transit</p>
    <p>sanfrancisco.cbslocal.com</p>
    <p>On the Street</p>
    <p>www.freep.com</p>
    <p>magneetmedia.com</p>
    <p>Private Spaces</p>
    <p>www.smartfoxsecurity.com</p>
    <p>thehomeworksgroup.com</p>
    <p>ATM Booths</p>
    <p>newsblogs.chicagotribune.com</p>
    <p>www.bcliving.ca</p>
    <p>Taking public transit can be risky</p>
    <p>I was in a waiting spot to get a paratransit van, and somebody came into this area. I thought there was someone there but I wasnt sure, and then someone else came up and said: Did he do anything? And I was like What?! And so I was right and there was someone there.</p>
    <p>-T7 (Totally Blind)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed 15</p>
    <p>www.israelnationalnews.com</p>
    <p>Public Transit</p>
    <p>sanfrancisco.cbslocal.com</p>
    <p>On the Street</p>
    <p>www.freep.com</p>
    <p>magneetmedia.com</p>
    <p>Private Spaces</p>
    <p>www.smartfoxsecurity.com</p>
    <p>thehomeworksgroup.com</p>
    <p>ATM Booths</p>
    <p>newsblogs.chicagotribune.com</p>
    <p>www.bcliving.ca</p>
    <p>Attackers can easily shoulder-surf in ATM Booths</p>
    <p>I dont think it is safe to use ATM. We walk so I cant get into a car, so if I use an ATM to get $20, I could walk down the street and get mugged. So why should I go to an ATM showing everybody that I am getting money or if I am making a deposit?</p>
    <p>-L5 (Low Vision)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed 16</p>
    <p>How do people with visual impairments manage their privacy, safety and security?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed 17</p>
    <p>People with visual impairments adopted several coping strategies</p>
    <p>Avoidance</p>
    <p>Relocation</p>
    <p>Mitigation</p>
    <p>Help from others</p>
    <p>Adaptation</p>
    <p>Acceptance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed 18</p>
    <p>Avoidance I only use the devices when I feel safe... When I have reservations about the safety of my behaviors, my default choice is just turn the device off. That way no one can have access to it. Because I am not even really using it.</p>
    <p>-X6 (Late Impaired)</p>
    <p>Avoid certain situations or devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed 19</p>
    <p>Relocation</p>
    <p>Usually I talk and then stop and go to a corner by myself and send it. Before doing screen magnification I usually sit somewhere or wont take [the text] right away  I will wait until I am by myself and at the same time put myself back-against-the wall, so that I am holding my cell phone when I read the text.</p>
    <p>-L3 (Low Vision)</p>
    <p>Relocate to a different place</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed 20</p>
    <p>Acceptance</p>
    <p>Whenever we have difficulties we have to call someone in and that invades our privacy. We cant read my mail, dont even know who it is from. Most of the time [automatic scanning] doesnt work So our privacy... we dont have any privacy.</p>
    <p>-T7 (Totally Blind)</p>
    <p>I guess over my lifetime I have developed an assumption that someone is there. I kind of say to myself, if I walk out my front door someone can hear me.</p>
    <p>-T6 (Totally Blind)</p>
    <p>Accept the risks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed 21</p>
    <p>How can wearable devices address privacy, safety, and security concerns of people with</p>
    <p>visual impairments?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Monitor surroundings to provide privacy, safety and security feedback</p>
    <p>Extract Desired Information</p>
    <p>Compute Feedback</p>
    <p>Feedback</p>
    <p>Extracted Images</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Many options for monitoring surroundings</p>
    <p>Smartphone Cameras Surveillance Cameras Web Cameras</p>
    <p>OrCam Google Glass HoloLens</p>
    <p>Narrative Clip iON SnapCam YoCam</p>
    <p>Regular Cameras</p>
    <p>Head Mounted Cameras</p>
    <p>Life Logging Cameras</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed 24</p>
    <p>I like the idea of having something on your clothes because it is less noticeable... because people will start to wonder why is he wearing this weird eyeglass thing. If you want to do stuff low key, then you do it that way.</p>
    <p>-L2 (Low Vision)</p>
    <p>Clip on camera, something I could clip on my glasses or clip on to my cap or collar. Not too visible because it would make me an easy target to someone who might want to steal my camera. They might try to get my camera and knock me over.</p>
    <p>- X4 (Late Impaired)</p>
    <p>People prefer Wearable and Discreet cameras</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What information is desired?</p>
    <p>How many people are in my vicinity?</p>
    <p>How close are people to me?</p>
    <p>Who is in my vicinity?</p>
    <p>What are the people in my vicinity doing?</p>
    <p>Forensic capture: who was around me?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What information is desired?</p>
    <p>How close are people to me?</p>
    <p>What are the people in my vicinity doing?</p>
    <p>Forensic capture: who was around me?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Are people too close to me?</p>
    <p>Privacy Bubble</p>
    <p>Several participants used the term bubble to mark the territory of their private space.</p>
    <p>Radius of the Bubble</p>
    <p>Radius of the bubble varied between 5 -10 feet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What are the people in my vicinity doing?</p>
    <p>Maybe a lot of people arent paying attention to me at all. The device could say that you have a person two feet away from you watching TV or texting on their cell phone.</p>
    <p>- T4 (Totally Blind)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Forensic capture: who was around me?</p>
    <p>Id like a notification tone and at that point, maybe when it gives that tone, start taking thirty or 15 second interval pictures of who is around. When the police do decide to help, they ask oh well you didnt see them, we cant describe them. Wed have these pictures in every five, ten, fifteen or thirty seconds intervals of who was around at that point.</p>
    <p>-T5 (Totally blind)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Forensic capture: who was around me?</p>
    <p>I would like to know as a blind person, when other cameras (surveillance cameras) are about. I would like to know where those cameras are because, for example, if I thought I was in kind of an icky neighborhood and I need to make a phone call or do something on my phone, if I know there is a camera up ahead at the corner, I would do whatever I did by the camera so that a cop could  if I was robbed  have a chance of figuring out who that person was. I will use those cameras as my friend.</p>
    <p>- X2 (Late Impaired)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed 31</p>
    <p>Extract Desired Information</p>
    <p>Compute Feedback</p>
    <p>Feedback</p>
    <p>Extracted Images</p>
    <p>Monitor surroundings to provide privacy, safety and security feedback</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extract Desired Information</p>
    <p>How many people? How close are they? What are they doing? Who are they? Who was around me?</p>
    <p>Wearable</p>
    <p>Compute Feedback</p>
    <p>Feedback</p>
    <p>Extracted Images</p>
    <p>Monitor surroundings to provide privacy, safety and security feedback</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed 33</p>
    <p>Apu Kapadia kapadia@indiana.edu</p>
    <p>David Crandall djcran@indiana.edu</p>
    <p>Kay Connelly connelly@indiana.edu</p>
    <p>Tousif Ahmed touahmed@indiana.edu</p>
    <p>Patrick Shaffer patshaff@indiana.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tousif Ahmed 34</p>
    <p>This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation (NSF) under grants CNS-1408730 and</p>
    <p>IIS-1253549. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the</p>
    <p>author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In conclusion</p>
    <p>We found that people with visual impairments have significant concerns about their physical safety in the context of crime</p>
    <p>As a result they develop several coping mechanisms including the complete acceptance of risk</p>
    <p>We derive design suggestions for a camera based assistive tool for improving the safety, security, and privacy of people with visual impairments</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
