<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Inconvenient Trust: User Attitudes toward Security and Usability</p>
    <p>Tradeoffs for Key-Directory Encryption Systems</p>
    <p>Wei Bai, Doowon Kim, Moses Namara, Yichen Qian, Patrick Gage Kelley*, Michelle L. Mazurek</p>
    <p>University of Maryland, College Park *University of New Mexico</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is End-to-End Encryption? Hackers</p>
    <p>Governments Misbehaving Employees/Company Itself</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>End-to-End Encryption</p>
    <p>Integration</p>
    <p>(Auto) Encryption Decryption</p>
    <p>UI Design</p>
    <p>Key Management</p>
    <p>Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Easy to Use</p>
    <p>Secure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Easy to Use</p>
    <p>Secure</p>
    <p>System B</p>
    <p>Exchange (PGP-like) Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exchange Model: exchanging public locks[1] manually out of band</p>
    <p>[1] W. Tong, S. Gold, S. Gichohi, M. Roman, and J. Frankle. Why King George III can encrypt. 2014</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Easy to Use</p>
    <p>Secure</p>
    <p>System B</p>
    <p>Exchange (PGP-like) Model End users exchange public locks manually out of band. The usability has been improved, but still not popular.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Easy to Use</p>
    <p>Secure</p>
    <p>System A</p>
    <p>Registration (keydirectory-based) Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Registration Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Easy to Use</p>
    <p>Secure</p>
    <p>System A</p>
    <p>Registration Model A central server will be responsible for distributing public locks. Alarms some security experts.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Targeting General Users Security Experts General Public</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Targeting General Users Political Activists, Journalists, etc.</p>
    <p>General Public</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How do general users consider the security and usability tradeoffs between</p>
    <p>exchange and registration models?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>O U T L I N E</p>
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Participants</p>
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Participants</p>
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Participants  Email listservs  Online platforms, e.g. Craigslist  Flyers</p>
    <p>First Model</p>
    <p>High-level concepts  Complete email tasks, learn about security</p>
    <p>Feedback</p>
    <p>Second Model</p>
    <p>High-level concepts  Complete email tasks, learn about security</p>
    <p>Feedback</p>
    <p>Overall Feedback</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model Design</p>
    <p>Exchange Model Regist ration</p>
    <p>Model</p>
    <p>Mailvelope</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Email Tasks for Introducing Concepts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Email Tasks for Introducing Concepts</p>
    <p>*Participants dont need to exchange public locks in the registration model.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Email Tasks for Introducing Concepts</p>
    <p>*Participants dont need to exchange public locks in the registration model.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Email Tasks for Introducing Concepts</p>
    <p>*Participants dont need to exchange public locks in the registration model.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Email Tasks for Introducing Concepts</p>
    <p>a. Lose Alices public lock* b. Lose own private key c. Publicize own private key</p>
    <p>*There is no such task in registration model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>This threat doesnt happen usually, because it requires Mallet to have much power and resources to achieve this.</p>
    <p>Mallet</p>
    <p>Security Learning: Exchange Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>[In primary registration model] you need to trust the email provider</p>
    <p>Security Learning: Registration Model (Primary)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Learning: Registration Model (CaaS[1])</p>
    <p>Third-Party Service</p>
    <p>[In CaaS model] you need to trust the two parties dont collaborate.</p>
    <p>[1] S. Fahl, M. Harbach, T. Muders, and M. Smith. Confidentiality as a Service  usable security for the cloud. In Trust, Security and Privacy in Computing and Communications (TrustCom), 2012 IEEE 11th International Conference on, pages 153162, June 2012.</p>
    <p>Email Provider</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Learning: Registration Model (Auditing[1])</p>
    <p>[In auditing model] you need to trust the auditors and/or the software on your devices.</p>
    <p>[1] M. S. Melara, A. Blankstein, J. Bonneau, E. W. Felten, and M. J. Freedman. CONIKS: Bringing key transparency to end users. In 24th USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security 15), pages 383398. USENIX Association, Aug. 2015.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Participants</p>
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participants</p>
    <p>Gender: Male 60%</p>
    <p>Female: 40%</p>
    <p>Occupation: 40% reported</p>
    <p>jobs or majors in computing, math and engineering 52</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participants</p>
    <p>Security Expertise[1]: 2 out of 52 scored 3 or higher (out of 5.5)</p>
    <p>[1] L. J. Camp, T. Kelley, and P. Rajivan. Instrument for measuring computing and security expertise. Technical Report TR715, Indiana University, Feb. 2015.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis</p>
    <p>Quantitative Analysis  5-point Likert scale responses  Cumulative-link mixed regression model (CLMM)</p>
    <p>Qualitative Analysis  Open coding independently by two researchers  Met to resolve all differences</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Participants</p>
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Selected Results</p>
    <p>Usability Security Comparison</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Selected Results</p>
    <p>Usability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exchange, First</p>
    <p>Exchange, Second</p>
    <p>Registration, First</p>
    <p>Registration, Second</p>
    <p>Sending and receiving encrypted email to 10 people would be difficult (intellectually challenging)</p>
    <p>Number of Participants</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sending and receiving encrypted email to 10 people would be cumbersome (tedious)</p>
    <p>Exchange, First</p>
    <p>Exchange, Second</p>
    <p>Registration, First</p>
    <p>Registration, Second</p>
    <p>Number of Participants</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exchange model was dramatically more cumbersome and somewhat more difficult.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(The exchange model is) time consuming, especially sending urgent emails. I have no choice but to wait for (the correspondents public lock).</p>
    <p>ES9</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Selected Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Registration</p>
    <p>Exchange</p>
    <p>Security Comparison</p>
    <p>The Perceived Security Gap</p>
    <p>Manual effort may lead to vulnerability</p>
    <p>Some concern but generally trusted</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>This model effectively protected my privacy</p>
    <p>Exchange, First</p>
    <p>Exchange, Second</p>
    <p>Registration, First</p>
    <p>Registration, Second</p>
    <p>Number of Participants</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The order participants saw each model played a significant role:</p>
    <p>participants who saw registration model first were more comfortable with it.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exchange model: manual effort may lead to vulnerability</p>
    <p>More than half were concerned about the security of the medium used to exchange locks.</p>
    <p>There are too many exchanges between different people. Exchanging [locks] to many people may go wrong.</p>
    <p>RT7</p>
    <p>Concern 52%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(Primary) Registration model: some concern but generally trusted</p>
    <p>(Big companies like) Google and Yahoo! dont do such things [violate users privacy], unless the government forces them to do so. In general, its secure.&quot;</p>
    <p>RT10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CaaS and auditing models: some additional perceived security for registration</p>
    <p>(In Auditing Model) Obviously its extra secure. Other parties are verifying it.&quot;</p>
    <p>ET13</p>
    <p>(In CaaS Model) If one party is screwed up, you have another one to protect [your email]. You are still safe.</p>
    <p>ES8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CaaS and auditing models: still some concerns</p>
    <p>(In Auditing Model) I want to know who these auditors are, . . . Their reputations, and whether they are truly independent.</p>
    <p>(In CaaS Model) Involving more systems may complicate the system, so it is less trustful.</p>
    <p>RS9</p>
    <p>RS1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Selected Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rate your willingness to use this model in the future</p>
    <p>Exchange</p>
    <p>Registration</p>
    <p>No significant difference between two models for personal use.</p>
    <p>Number of Participants</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>When they would use the models Exchange model  high-security info only  at a small scale only</p>
    <p>Registration model  more broad use</p>
    <p>would use in general email or large scale</p>
    <p>would use in general email</p>
    <p>large scale</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Handling Misconfigurations</p>
    <p>All Correct</p>
    <p>Largely Correct</p>
    <p>Other</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Handling Misconfigurations</p>
    <p>I will send my email to a third person I trust, and ask that person to encrypt the email for me and send to my recipients. Similarly, he will decrypt the [response] email for me and forward it to me.</p>
    <p>One participant mentioned recovering keys from a backup (such as a USB drive) rather than generating a new key pair.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary  It is possible to explain the high level concepts</p>
    <p>and risks of encryption to users.</p>
    <p>Place users in the context, and trust their decisions.</p>
    <p>They can think about tradeoffs effectively.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary  The registration model is more convenient than the</p>
    <p>exchange model, BUT the perceived security gap between them is small.</p>
    <p>Show a near-best-case possibility of explaining</p>
    <p>encryption to users.</p>
    <p>Contact: Wei Bai, University of Maryland, College Park wbai@umd.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
