<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Productive Security: A scalable methodology for analysing employee security behaviours</p>
    <p>Adam Beautement, Ingolf Becker, Simon Parkin, Kat Krol, M. Angela Sasse University College London</p>
    <p>SOUPS 2016, 24th June 2016 Denver, CO</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Security managers declare central security policy  Based on expertise and experience</p>
    <p>Restrictive technology can hinder employees  Employee co-operation critical  Over-burden and misalignment impacts business</p>
    <p>Policies must consider employees  Daily working lives are not all security  other tasks  Employee populations are not all the same</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Goal: generate rich snapshot of security maturity and security behaviours within a large organisations employee population, for direct use in aligning security with business Aim:  Elicit realistic survey responses from employees  Consider both scalability and meaning of the survey  Support policy decision-making with data</p>
    <p>Represent operational reality of the organisation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  security culture</p>
    <p>Consider employees as members of a larger organisation</p>
    <p>Cultural theory predicts impact that organisation norms can have upon risk perception  Individualists rely on themselves for solutions  Egalitarians rely on group solutions to problems  Hierarchists rely on existing systems or technologies  Fatalists feel that their actions are not significant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  security maturity</p>
    <p>Model of behaviour maturity  Based on CMU maturity model</p>
    <p>Consider security competence relative to business  Competence supports secure working habits</p>
    <p>Five levels  Level 1: Is not engaged with security in any capacity  Level 2: Follows security policy when forced to  Level 3: Knows a policy exists and follows it by rote  Level 4: Has internalised policy, adopts secure practices  Level 5: Champions security, challenges breaches</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Survey  example attitude question</p>
    <p>Jessica is heading toward an unmanned turnstile and notices a man she does not recognise in front of her pass through the barrier by following close behind someone else unfamiliar. The two men are walking close together although they do not appear to obviously be in conversation. The second man is holding a cup of coffee in one hand and his laptop in the other. His ID badge is not immediately visible. Jessica decides to:</p>
    <p>A. Follow the man and ask to see his ID badge. B. Find a security guard at one of the manned turnstiles and tell them what</p>
    <p>happened. C. Return to her desk, she sees this sort of thing quite regularly and it is</p>
    <p>probably because his hands were full that he did not swipe through himself.</p>
    <p>D. Do nothing, if he is up to some mischief the security guards will catch him later on.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Survey results  statistical analysis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results overview  maturity levels</p>
    <p>Participants more likely to choose more acceptable options</p>
    <p>35-39 age group shows lower average level 5 rank than other groups  Also ranks level 4 higher than other age groups</p>
    <p>HQ rank maturity level 4 higher than level 5 + rank level 2 significantly higher than other locations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results overview  behaviour types</p>
    <p>Human resources a hotspot - employees choose options independent of assigned severity</p>
    <p>25-29 and 30-34 more Hierarchist than other age groups, 50-54 less Hierarchist  30-34 less Fatalist, 50-54 and 55 more so</p>
    <p>HQ and Homeworkers rank Individualist highest</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>High-level outcomes</p>
    <p>Organisation has very positive security posture  Employees pick more acceptable, less severe options  Good security practices adopted, even when not</p>
    <p>required to by technology or policy</p>
    <p>Where friction exists between business and security, approaches predominantly Individualist  Shadow security, relying on own skills and knowledge  Hierarchists abide by existing structures; Individualists</p>
    <p>may identify and solve new challenges 11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Areas to investigate</p>
    <p>Sales and Service have stronger maturity levels + able to assess severity of options</p>
    <p>HQ ranks maturity level 4 higher than level 5 + Individualist first + absence of Hierarchists  Hot-desking policy may factor here  HQ constantly reinvents itself with new advances</p>
    <p>25-34 more Hierarchist, 50+ more Fatalist  Younger employees mostly in Sales (fraud exposure)</p>
    <p>Reported to board; resources targeted to these areas</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Scalable surveys based on rich interview data  Multi-purpose questions provide multi-dimensional</p>
    <p>view of employee security  Organisation used results to target interventions  Scope to adapt scenarios across companies  Can explore potential for managers and</p>
    <p>employees to find collaborative solutions</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
