<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Do They Do What They Do? A Study of What Motivations Users to (Not) Follow</p>
    <p>Computer Security Advice Authored by: Michael Fagan and Mohammad Maifi Hasan Khan</p>
    <p>University of Connecticut</p>
    <p>Presented by: Michael Fagan</p>
    <p>SOUPS 2016  June 23rd 2016</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problem</p>
    <p>Users must navigate disparate and widespread threats  Malware, phishing, etc.</p>
    <p>Many tools and advice to stay safe</p>
    <p>BUT plenty of users still exhibit insecure behaviors  Bad passwords</p>
    <p>Ignoring updates</p>
    <p>These decisions have consequences on others</p>
    <p>What makes some users follow security advice while others do not?  What are the perceptions each group has of the decision and how do those</p>
    <p>perceptions compare?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Rational Choice Perspective (Herley 2009/2014)  Benefits vs. Cost  Common in related studies</p>
    <p>Significance of Risk (Howe 2012, Camp 2006, Asgharpour 2007)  Added to Benefits/Costs  Also a popular topic in usable security (for good reason)</p>
    <p>Social Motivations (Tyler 2010, Das et al. 2014)  Less studied than other concepts</p>
    <p>Good vs. Bad Actors (Ion et al. 2015, Kang et al. 2015)  Many have investigated from an expert vs. non-expert perspective</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Design and Execution</p>
    <p>Compare those who follow advice to those who dont  Use a rational decision framework to identify differences in perceptions</p>
    <p>Add risk and social variables to the basic framework</p>
    <p>Ask participants, why?</p>
    <p>Initial sample gathered from Mechanical Turk (N = 764)  Groups of 50 formed for 8 groups</p>
    <p>One group only had 47 eligible participants</p>
    <p>Groups contacted with full survey</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Variables</p>
    <p>Common Security Advice 1. Keeping your software up to date</p>
    <p>Decision Model  12 total variables</p>
    <p>3 components: benefit, risk, and cost</p>
    <p>2 effect target groups: you (individual), and users of other computers (social)</p>
    <p>2 behavior contexts: following (the advice), and not following (the advice)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Variables</p>
    <p>Common Security Advice 1. Keeping your software up to date</p>
    <p>Decision Model  12 total variables</p>
    <p>3 components: benefit, risk, and cost</p>
    <p>2 effect target groups: you (individual), and users of other computers (social)</p>
    <p>2 behavior contexts: following (the advice), and not following (the advice)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Variable Definitions</p>
    <p>Yes Groups A. How much would you say [you / users of other computers] are [benefited / cost or</p>
    <p>inconvenienced / put at risk] by you [following the advice]?</p>
    <p>B. How much would you say [you / users of other computers] would be [benefited / cost or inconvenienced / put at risk] if you did not [follow the advice]?</p>
    <p>No Groups A. How much would you say [you / users of other computers] are [benefited / cost or</p>
    <p>inconvenienced / put at risk] by you not [following the advice]?</p>
    <p>B. How much would you say [you / users of other computers] would be [benefited / cost or inconvenienced / put at risk] if you did [follow the advice]?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Variable Definitions</p>
    <p>Yes Groups A. How much would you say [you / users of other computers]</p>
    <p>are [benefited / cost or inconvenienced / put at risk] by you [following the advice]?</p>
    <p>B. How much would you say [you / users of other computers] would be [benefited / cost or inconvenienced / put at risk] if you did not [follow the advice]?</p>
    <p>No Groups A. How much would you say [you / users of other computers]</p>
    <p>are [benefited / cost or inconvenienced / put at risk] by you not [following the advice]?</p>
    <p>B. How much would you say [you / users of other computers] would be [benefited / cost or inconvenienced / put at risk] if you did [follow the advice]?</p>
    <p>Defines Following</p>
    <p>Defines Not Following</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hypotheses H-1a - For all decisions, the Benefits of Following will be seen as higher by the Yes groups compared to the No</p>
    <p>groups.</p>
    <p>H-1b - For all decisions, the Benefits of Not Following will be seen as higher by the No groups compared to the Yes groups.</p>
    <p>H-2a - For all decisions, the Risks of Not Following will be seen as higher by the Yes groups compared to the No groups.</p>
    <p>H-2b - For some decisions, the Risks of Following will be seen as higher by the No groups compared to the Yes groups.</p>
    <p>H-3a - For all decisions, the Costs of Not Following will be seen as higher by the Yes groups compared to the No groups.</p>
    <p>H-3b - For all decisions, the Costs of Following will be seen as higher by the No groups compared to the Yes groups.</p>
    <p>H-4a - Those who follow each advice will do so, generally, to increase their security and/or for convenience purposes.</p>
    <p>H-4b - Those who do not follow each advice will do so, generally, to avoid a cost/inconvenience or due to confidence in current behavior (i.e., they might know they should change, but don't want to).</p>
    <p>H-5 - Social considerations will be lower than Individual concerns for all decisions. 9</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sample and Group Descriptions</p>
    <p>Advice Group n Gender Age Comp. Expertise Sec. Expertise Often Use Comp</p>
    <p>Male Female Avg. St.D. Avg. St.D. Avg. St.D. Avg. St.D.</p>
    <p>Update Yes 39 20 19 38.4 14 4.15 0.7 3.56 0.8 4.79 0.4</p>
    <p>No 30 12 18 35.8 11 3.77 0.8 2.93 0.6 4.40 0.9</p>
    <p>Password Manager</p>
    <p>Yes 41 19 22 33.2 8.7 4.24 0.6 3.63 0.9 4.61 0.4</p>
    <p>No 38 16 22 34.0 9.7 4.30 0.7 3.50 0.7 4.79 0.4</p>
    <p>No 31 19 12 32.9 9 4.26 0.7 3.77 0.7 4.58 0.6</p>
    <p>Change Password</p>
    <p>Yes 37 20 17 36.0 10 4.22 0.6 3.78 0.8 4.73 0.6</p>
    <p>No 38 19 19 34.1 9.6 4.05 0.7 3.39 0.8 4.68 0.5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perceptions - Benefits</p>
    <p>Individual Benefit of Following Individual Benefit of Not Following</p>
    <p>H-1a - For all decisions, the Benefits of Following will be seen as higher by the Yes groups compared to the No groups. H-1b - For all decisions, the Benefits of Not Following will be seen as higher by the No groups compared to the Yes groups.</p>
    <p>Yes No M-W U-Test</p>
    <p>A(M) A(M) U p d</p>
    <p>Update 1.51(1) 2.13(2) 347.5 0.002 0.38</p>
    <p>Pass.Man. 1.68(1) 2.70(3) 302 &lt;0.001 0.49</p>
    <p>Chg.Pass. 1.70(2) 3.03(3) 176 &lt;0.001 0.66</p>
    <p>Yes No M-W U-Test</p>
    <p>A(M) A(M) U p d</p>
    <p>Update 3.77(4) 2.97(3) 274.5 &lt;0.001 0.51</p>
    <p>Pass.Man. 3.78(4) 2.5(2.5) 154.5 &lt;0.001 0.73</p>
    <p>Chg.Pass. 3.47(4) 2.53(3) 256 &lt;0.001 0.57</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perceptions - Risks</p>
    <p>Risk of Following Risk of Not Following</p>
    <p>H-2a - For all decisions, the Risks of Not Following will be seen as higher by the Yes groups compared to the No groups. H-2b - For some decisions, the Risks of Following will be seen as higher by the No groups compared to the Yes groups.</p>
    <p>Yes No M-W U-Test</p>
    <p>A(M) A(M) U p d</p>
    <p>In d</p>
    <p>iv id</p>
    <p>u a</p>
    <p>l Update 3.42(4) 2.77(3) 336.5 0.002 0.37</p>
    <p>Pass.Man. 2.88(3) 1.80(2) 302.5 &lt;0.001 0.52</p>
    <p>Chg.Pass. 3.14(3) 2.63(3) 440.5 0.003 0.34</p>
    <p>S o</p>
    <p>ci a</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>Update 2.67(3) 1.76(1) 262.5 &lt;0.001 0.44</p>
    <p>Pass.Man. 1.92(2) 1.29(1) 409 0.002 0.37</p>
    <p>Chg.Pass. 1.70(1) 1.29(1) 483 0.044 0.24</p>
    <p>*Change Passwords: U = 498.5, p = 0.014, d = 0.28</p>
    <p>U = 342.5 p &lt; 0.001 d = 0.49</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perceptions  Costs</p>
    <p>Cost of Following Cost of Not Following</p>
    <p>H-3a - For all decisions, the Costs of Not Following will be seen as higher by the Yes groups compared to the No groups. H-3b - For all decisions, the Costs of Following will be seen as higher by the No groups compared to the Yes groups.</p>
    <p>Yes No M-W U-Test</p>
    <p>A(M) A(M) U p d</p>
    <p>In d</p>
    <p>iv id</p>
    <p>u a</p>
    <p>l Update 2.95(3) 2.00(2) 247.5 &lt;0.001 0.48</p>
    <p>Pass.Man. 3.15(3) 1.75(1) 244.5 &lt;0.001 0.60</p>
    <p>Chg.Pass. 2.28(3) 1.61(1) 425.5 0.003 0.35</p>
    <p>S o</p>
    <p>ci a</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>Update 2.32(2) 1.59(1) 248 0.001 0.41</p>
    <p>Pass.Man. 1.84(1) 1.03(1) 354 &lt;0.001 0.49</p>
    <p>Chg.Pass. 1.50(1) 1.24(1) 525.5 0.174 0.16</p>
    <p>Yes No M-W U-Test</p>
    <p>A(M) A(M) U p d</p>
    <p>In d</p>
    <p>iv id</p>
    <p>u a</p>
    <p>l Update 2.03(2) 2.10(2) 527.5 0.444 0.09</p>
    <p>Pass.Man. 1.73(2) 2.18(2) 533 0.011 0.28</p>
    <p>Chg.Pass. 2.35(2) 2.97(3) 449.5 0.005 0.33</p>
    <p>S o</p>
    <p>ci a</p>
    <p>l</p>
    <p>Update 1.22(1) 1.29(1) 431 0.781 0.04</p>
    <p>Pass.Man. 1.28(1) 1.52(1) 565.5 0.213 0.15</p>
    <p>Chg.Pass. 1.28(1) 1.64(1) 491 0.073 0.21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perception Gaps</p>
    <p>Participants generally rated the benefits of their decision higher than the projected benefits from switching  Expected, but interesting</p>
    <p>For risk, Yes groups rated the risks avoided as higher than the risk reported by No groups  Both cant be right, but hard to tell who is</p>
    <p>Overall, participants ratings reflected a confidence in their decision, either to follow or not follow</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why they do what they do</p>
    <p>Updating  Yes: desire to increasing security and want to avoid bugs and/or issues  No: avoid inconvenience, say they dont need updates, or are too lazy</p>
    <p>Using a Password Manager  Yes: most like the convenience, but many also not the security benefits  No: many are avoiding a perceived security risk, centralization of passwords</p>
    <p>Using 2FA  Yes: most are using to increase security, with some (9/36) saying it feels better  No: some are confident in their current security and many are avoiding a cost</p>
    <p>Changing Passwords Frequently  Yes: added security and avoiding theft top reasons  No: many are avoiding an inconvenience and/or see no reason to change behavior</p>
    <p>H-4a - Those who follow each advice will do so, generally, to increase their security and/or for convenience purposes. H-4b - Those who do not follow each advice will do so, generally, to avoid a cost/inconvenience or due to confidence in</p>
    <p>current behavior.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Individual vs. Social Concerns H-5 - Social considerations will be lower than Individual concerns for all decisions.</p>
    <p>For all, a Sign test of these differences yielded: Z &lt; -5, p &lt; 0.001</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Key points:  Perception gaps found between Yes/No groups</p>
    <p>Added convenience can be powerful</p>
    <p>Low social motivations</p>
    <p>Limitations  Larger samples from different populations would help generalize</p>
    <p>Extended framework could give more insights</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You! Questions?</p>
    <p>michael.fagan@uconn.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
