<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Follow My Recommendations: A Personalized Privacy Assistant</p>
    <p>for Mobile Apps</p>
    <p>Bin Liu, Mads Schaarup Andersen, Florian Schaub, Hazim Almuhimedi, Shikun Zhang,</p>
    <p>Norman Sadeh, Alessandro Acquisti, Yuvraj Agarwal</p>
    <p>Carnegie Mellon University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Android Permissions: Better Control, More Burden?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Android Permissions: Better Control, More Burden?</p>
    <p>Too many settings to manage!</p>
    <p>On average: 95 apps per user 5 permissions per app</p>
    <p>And there will be more</p>
    <p>Health data, Smart home, Internet of Things,...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Helping User Configure Their Permission Settings: Recommendations</p>
    <p>Recommendations of permission settings  Majority Choice [Agarwal et al. MobiSys 2013]  Expert labeling [Rashidi et al. IM 2015]  One-size-fits-all solutions</p>
    <p>Users preferences are diverse  [Liu et al. WWW 2014]</p>
    <p>One-size-fits-all recommendations are limited</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Personalized Recommendations</p>
    <p>We can learn users privacy preferences and help users configure many of their settings  [Liu et al. WWW 2014, Lin et al. SOUPS 2014]</p>
    <p>Personalized Privacy Assistant (PPA) to help real users  In this paper we built such an assistant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline: Personalized Privacy Assistant (PPA)</p>
    <p>Capturing Users Preferences, Building Privacy Profiles</p>
    <p>84 participants, 2 weeks</p>
    <p>Generating Profile-based Recommendations for Users</p>
    <p>Field Study: Evaluation of PPA with real Android Users</p>
    <p>72 (different) participants, 9 days</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Capturing Users Preferences: Building Privacy Profiles</p>
    <p>How to capture and model real Android users preferences?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Collecting Data: Real Android Users</p>
    <p>We want to collect settings from real Android users using their phones as part of their regular everyday life.</p>
    <p>Tradeoffs:  Privacy Paradox  Self-reported preferences V.S. actual settings</p>
    <p>The settings should have to have real impact on their apps and their data.</p>
    <p>We built a permission manager of our own, and ran a field study with rooted Android users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Collecting Data: Better Engagement</p>
    <p>By default users are not actively engaging in permission settings  [Liu et al. WWW 2014]</p>
    <p>Privacy nudges can help motivate users to review their settings  [Almuhimedi et al. CHI 2015]</p>
    <p>Paying more attention  Better awareness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PPA App: Enhanced Permission Manager Awareness + Engagement</p>
    <p>Frequency of Use</p>
    <p>Likely Purpose(s) of Use</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PPA App: Enhanced Permission Manager Awareness + Engagement</p>
    <p>Frequency of Use</p>
    <p>Likely Purpose(s) of Use</p>
    <p>Periodic Nudge Notifications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dataset Collection</p>
    <p>We got 84 rooted Android users finished the study  We recruit from online communities where we can</p>
    <p>better reach rooted users: Google+, Facebook, Reddit, Android forums.</p>
    <p>Two-week data collection  Starting from week 2, the PPA app showed privacy</p>
    <p>nudges once a day</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dataset Statistics</p>
    <p>3559 Permission Settings  App ran in foreground or got configured by user</p>
    <p>(Android K &amp; L by default allow the permissions)</p>
    <p>2888(81.15%) allows and 671(18.85%) denies.  Significant factors: (random-effect logistics regression)</p>
    <p>App Categories  Permissions</p>
    <p>Purpose information  Importance reported by participants  But not frequently available to all the apps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Building Privacy Profiles: Group Like-minded Users</p>
    <p>Quantifying a users preference:</p>
    <p>Aggregated general preference on each specific triple (app category, permission, purpose)  Based on logistic regression analysis</p>
    <p>Apply weighted tensor factorization to impute the missing values (optimize only on known settings)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Building Privacy Profiles</p>
    <p>Clustering Algorithm</p>
    <p>Hierarchical Clustering  Performs good on unbalanced data  Adjustable with non-triangle distance metrics</p>
    <p>K=7, complete linkage, cosine distance  Silhouette Coefficient=0.2079</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Building Privacy Profiles</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Generating Profile-based Recommendations for Users</p>
    <p>For a new user, how can we capture their preferences and provide recommendations?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Capturing Users Preferences: Interactive Dialog to Assign Them to Profiles For each new user, the PPA app ask up to 5 questions to capture the users preference.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Capturing Users Preferences: Interactive Dialog to Assign Them to Profiles For each new user, the PPA app ask up to 5 questions to capture the users preference.</p>
    <p>Types of questions:</p>
    <p>(category, permission)  (permission, purpose)  (permission)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Capturing Users Preferences: Interactive Dialog to Assign Them to Profiles For each new user, the PPA app ask up to 5 questions to capture the users preference.</p>
    <p>Types of questions:  (category, permission) -&gt; allow/deny  (permission) -&gt; allow/deny  (permission, purpose) -&gt; allow/deny</p>
    <p>Context-specific:</p>
    <p>the questions are chosen by optimizing a decision tree dynamically according to what apps are installed on users device.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Generate Recommendations</p>
    <p>The recommendation task can be formalized as a classification problem  F: (user, app, permission) -&gt; {allow / deny}</p>
    <p>We train a SVM classifier that takes the following features into consideration:  Profile membership, App category, Permission  Purpose(s) of the permission request</p>
    <p>Only the recommended denies are shown to the user (Android K &amp; L)</p>
    <p>Model optimized on the collected dataset using 10-fold cross validation 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Showing Recommendations</p>
    <p>Revise  User can revise the</p>
    <p>recommendations and adjust them to match their preferences.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Showing Recommendations</p>
    <p>Explanations  User can click ? to check</p>
    <p>the explanations of each recommendation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Field Study: Evaluation of PPA</p>
    <p>Are we effective? Are we usable?</p>
    <p>Need evaluation by real Android users!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Field Study: Evaluation of PPA</p>
    <p>In this study, we would like know:</p>
    <p>Do users accept our recommendations?</p>
    <p>Do there find the recommendations useful?</p>
    <p>In addition, do they keep our recommendations and feel comfortable with them?</p>
    <p>Do our privacy profiles model their preference accurately?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Field Study: Evaluation of PPA</p>
    <p>We recruited a second set of 72 participants who also used rooted Android phones.</p>
    <p>We used Experience Sampling Method and Exit Survey to capture their satisfaction and feedback</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PPA: Recommendations  27 participants of 43 in treatment group are shown</p>
    <p>recommendations  Majority of the recommendations were accepted</p>
    <p>196 of 249 recommended items (78.7%)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PPA: Recommendations  Majority of the recommendations were accepted</p>
    <p>196 of 249 recommended items (78.7%)</p>
    <p>Participants kept most of the accepted recommendations  During the remaining 6 days after they are shown</p>
    <p>recommendations, we continue to show daily privacy nudges. Only 10 of the previously accepted recommendation (5.10%) were changed back to allow.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PPA: Recommendations  Recommendations helped users converge more quickly</p>
    <p>Permission Denies: the earlier, the better!</p>
    <p>The treatment group finished 82.51% of their settings in the day when they are shown recommendation, significantly more than 68.42% of control group.</p>
    <p>Most of the participants remained in the same profile they were assigned to. (35/49) 29</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of PPA: Recommendations</p>
    <p>Participants are comfortable with the recommendations.</p>
    <p>Recommendations are helpful</p>
    <p>It made what would have taken 10-20 clicks through menus looking to change these settings done in one click.</p>
    <p>It provides you with recommendations using your preferences so you can quickly change the settings without having to do much yourself.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations</p>
    <p>Sample population  In this study: Young, male, tech-savvy  Our methodology and results would extend to a more</p>
    <p>general population.</p>
    <p>Relatively short time length of the study  Daily privacy nudges are effective  Longer studies might be interesting to see how users</p>
    <p>preferences change over time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Existing Permissions Are Not Expressive Enough</p>
    <p>App behavior affects users choices</p>
    <p>Some apps need some permissions to function.  Some permissions are used for multiple purposes.</p>
    <p>Resource-centric control =&gt; Purpose-centric control  I want to allow location only for navigation  I want to deny contact access to third-parties</p>
    <p>I want to use a feature of the app that requires this permission</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other Considerations</p>
    <p>Degree of automation to permission settings configuration  Many different possible modes of interaction with the</p>
    <p>user - varying degrees of automation</p>
    <p>Better awareness  Frequency and purpose information are useful  Possible Improvement: Tell users how privacy and app</p>
    <p>functionality would be affected by permission change</p>
    <p>PPA could be applied to support privacy decision making in other domains as well  Web browser, Internet of Things, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary Personalized Privacy Assistant</p>
    <p>Privacy Profiles  Interactive Profile-Assigning Dialog  Recommendations</p>
    <p>Field study shows the effectiveness and the usability of our PPA app</p>
    <p>http://www.privacyassistant.org</p>
    <p>Enhanced version to be released this summer! Email us to get notified bliu1@cs.cmu.edu sadeh@cs.cmu.edu 34</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
