<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Attitudes Toward the Inspection of Encrypted</p>
    <p>Traffic Scott Ruoti, Mark ONeill, Daniel Zappala, Kent Seamons Brigham Young University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction  TLS Proxies</p>
    <p>SSL Inspection</p>
    <p>Used by organizations to protect their networks</p>
    <p>Used by governments to spy on citizens</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attitudes on Inspection of Encrypted Traffic  Security experts are actively trying to stop TLS proxies</p>
    <p>Certificate transparency  DANE</p>
    <p>Business and governments want them</p>
    <p>What do end-users think?  Might decide which side wins this argument  Should guide research  Unexplored</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TLS Proxies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Questions  Is the website who it says it is?</p>
    <p>Is the connection to the website secure?</p>
    <p>The lock icon is supposed to indicate a secure connection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TLS Authentication  Websites identify themselves using a X.509 certificate</p>
    <p>Browser validates this certificate to authenticate website</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Certificate Verification  X.509 certificates are signed by other X.509 certificates</p>
    <p>Browser checks that this chain ends at a trusted root certificate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TLS Proxy  Man-in-the-middle TLS communication</p>
    <p>Generate substitute certificates  Signed properly by the CA system  Signed by a locally installed trusted root</p>
    <p>No visual indication that the connection isnt secure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Uses</p>
    <p>MALICIOUS</p>
    <p>Stealing passwords</p>
    <p>Identity theft</p>
    <p>Tracking government dissidents</p>
    <p>Spying (for example the NSA)</p>
    <p>Censorship</p>
    <p>PROTECTIVE</p>
    <p>Blocking malware and viruses</p>
    <p>Protecting company secrets</p>
    <p>Blocking harmful websites</p>
    <p>Catching malicious individuals</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Teaching Users About TLS Proxies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dilemma  Goal: gather ordinary peoples opinions</p>
    <p>If we only survey those with pre-existing knowledge  Mostly security experts  Not our target demographic</p>
    <p>If we teach individuals about TLS proxies  Can survey are target demographic  Might influence participant responses</p>
    <p>Teaching about TLS proxies is not ideal, but is necessary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Creating the Description  Strived for neutrality</p>
    <p>Surveyed existing descriptions  Security experts  Businesses</p>
    <p>Established consensus</p>
    <p>Pilot studies  Convenience sample (6 participants)  MTurk (80 participants)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>First Survey</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology  Amazon Mechanical Turk (MTurk)</p>
    <p>1,049 responses  Skewed male (61%) and 25  34 years old (41%)  Participants mostly from the USA (87%) and India (12%)</p>
    <p>Instructed users regarding TLS proxies</p>
    <p>Asked participants about their opinions  Likert scale questions  Free response questions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attitudes Regarding TLS Proxies</p>
    <p>There Should Be Legislation Addressing TLS Proxies</p>
    <p>Browsers Should Notify Users of TLS Proxies</p>
    <p>Concerned TLS Proxies Could Be Used by Governments</p>
    <p>Concerned TLS Proxies Could Be Used by Hackers</p>
    <p>There Are Acceptable Uses of TLS Proxies</p>
    <p>TLS Proxies Are an Invasion of Privacy</p>
    <p>Strongly Agree Agree Neither Agree nor Disagree Disagree Strongly Disagree</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acceptable Uses  Protect organizations (51%)</p>
    <p>It is the companys hardware  Companies need to inspect internal traffic to prevent attacks</p>
    <p>Protect individuals (35%)  E.g., anti-virus</p>
    <p>Censor content (7%)  Some indicated it was never acceptable to censor content (3%)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Concerns  Hackers (76%)</p>
    <p>Government spying (71%)</p>
    <p>Privacy (55%)  Identity theft (10%)</p>
    <p>Performed without notification or consent (13%)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reactions</p>
    <p>PERCEPTION</p>
    <p>Negative (61%)</p>
    <p>Positive (5%)</p>
    <p>Depends (34%)</p>
    <p>BEHAVIOR</p>
    <p>Suspicious (26%)</p>
    <p>Discontinue use (17%)</p>
    <p>Change behavior (6%)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Personas  Pragmatic majority (76%)</p>
    <p>Privacy fundamentalist (17%)</p>
    <p>Unconcerned (1%)</p>
    <p>Jaded (5%)  Cares about security  Feels there is no hope</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Second Survey</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology  Amazon Mechanical Turk (MTurk)</p>
    <p>927 responses  Participants mostly from the USA (94%) and India (5%)</p>
    <p>Instructed users regarding TLS proxies</p>
    <p>Asked participants about specific use cases for TLS proxies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attitudes Regarding TLS Proxies</p>
    <p>Study 2  Acceptable Uses</p>
    <p>Study 1  Acceptable Uses</p>
    <p>Study 2  Invasion of Privacy</p>
    <p>Study 1  Invasion of Privacy</p>
    <p>Strongly Agree Agree Neither Agree nor Disagree Disagree Strongly Disagree</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acceptable Uses</p>
    <p>Your Government Monitoring Your Internet Traffic Your ISP Paid WiFi</p>
    <p>Your Employer When You Use Your Own Device Free WiFi -- Airport, Hotel, Cafe, Etc.</p>
    <p>Software You Installed to Protect Your Computer University</p>
    <p>Public Library Elementary School</p>
    <p>Your Employer When You Use a Company</p>
    <p>Yes Notified Consent No Unsure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participant Responses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Informed Participants  High level of engagement</p>
    <p>Good understanding of problem</p>
    <p>Recognize tradeoffs</p>
    <p>This is one of those doubled-edged swords  it can be used for your good and security and it can be used to harm and spy on</p>
    <p>you. Because of the distinct possibility of lost privacy, this type of proxy should [not be] used, except by your agreement, not by anyone else.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Notification and Risk  Nearly all participants want notification</p>
    <p>Most participants want consent to be required</p>
    <p>Well for some things it would be understandable, Id just like to be informed so I know the risk Im taking.</p>
    <p>If I encrypt something no one has the right to unencrypt it unless I give them the right to - simple as that.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  Gathered user attitudes towards TLS proxies</p>
    <p>Participants had nuanced views of trade-offs  TLS proxies are an invasion of privacy  See acceptable uses</p>
    <p>Users want notification and consent</p>
    <p>We need to engage end-users more often</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
