<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bram Bonn1, Sai Teja Peddinti2, Igor Bilogrevic2, Nina Taft2</p>
    <p>Exploring decision making with Androids runtime permission dialogs using in-context surveys</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>App lifecycle decisions</p>
    <p>Permission requestApp installation Altering permission App removal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research questions What are users rationales when making these decisions?</p>
    <p>Do they vary across:</p>
    <p>Permission groups?</p>
    <p>Demographics?</p>
    <p>Are users comfortable with their decisions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Context  Lack of user comprehension and attention [Felt 2012a, Kelley 2012], unpleasant</p>
    <p>surprises due to user expectation mismatch [Jung 2012, Thompson 2013], and user discomfort [Felt 2012b].</p>
    <p>Developers lack knowledge [Stevens 2013], make mistakes [Shklovski 2014, Smith 2016], and are overzealous [Wei 2012].</p>
    <p>High rates for users wanting to deny permissions [Wijesekera 2015, Wijesekera 2017]</p>
    <p>And much more... (over 50 publications on Android permissions!).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Context All of the previous studies:</p>
    <p>Install-time permissions model (pre-Android Marshmallow), or  Runtime request models</p>
    <p>Hypothetical scenarios  Ask questions some time after decisions had been made  Using modified Android devices</p>
    <p>Our approach:</p>
    <p>Runtime permissions model  Use participants personal Android devices  Ask in-situ, at the moment participants are making their decision</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology Experience Sampling Method: Survey participants right at the moment they made their choice.</p>
    <p>Extended open-source Android app called Paco.</p>
    <p>To launch in-situ surveys when apps are installed/removed and when permission decisions are made</p>
    <p>To collect information about installed apps and their permissions  To provide E2E encryption  Open source extensions available on https://github.com/google/paco</p>
    <p>Users install it on their personal phones.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In-situ survey  Asked on specific events</p>
    <p>App installation  App removal  Granting / denying permission via dialog  Granting / denying permission via settings</p>
    <p>Asks about rationale (Why did you allow ?)</p>
    <p>Multiple choice (randomized order), including other option  Options are based on a pre-study using Google Surveys with 4000 participants  Coded responses, grouped by topic, consolidated to 10 rationales per event</p>
    <p>Also measures reluctance: is the participant comfortable with their decision?</p>
    <p>Limited to 5 questions per day</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Paco User Experience</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exit survey  Identify participants privacy stance &amp; technology adoption</p>
    <p>Revisit comfort level with permissions granted in the past How comfortable would you be with &lt;app&gt; knowing your home and work address?</p>
    <p>Worded as hypothetical scenarios  Permission access made explicit</p>
    <p>Knowing your home and work address (Location)  Knowing the phone numbers of your friends</p>
    <p>and family (Contacts)  Knowing who is calling you (Phone)  Seeing the pictures taken with your camera (Storage)</p>
    <p>Includes pre-study permission grants</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participants  157 remote participants across the U.S., from</p>
    <p>different job categories</p>
    <p>6 weeks</p>
    <p>No interaction with researchers after set-up</p>
    <p>Experiment labeled as study on app interactions</p>
    <p>Incentives: $10 per week, $20 for exit survey</p>
    <p>Education</p>
    <p>Up to High School 15</p>
    <p>Some college (1-4 years, no degree)</p>
    <p>Associates degree 28</p>
    <p>Professional school degree 5</p>
    <p>Bachelors degree 51</p>
    <p>Graduate degree 18</p>
    <p>Age</p>
    <p>Gender</p>
    <p>Male 79</p>
    <p>Female 78</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Event Type Occurrences Surveyed</p>
    <p>App Installs 3118 1913</p>
    <p>App Removals 1944 775</p>
    <p>Permission Grants</p>
    <p>Permission Denials</p>
    <p>Total 7738 4565</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Factors influencing app installs</p>
    <p>(multiple responses per event are possible)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Factors influencing app installs</p>
    <p>(multiple responses per event are possible)</p>
    <p>Runtime permissions model: no permissions shown during installation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Permission decisions Dialogs vs Settings</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why do users grant permissions? Context helps!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why do users deny permissions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why do users deny permissions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why do users deny permissions?</p>
    <p>Users are aware about privacy controls (58% of users denying)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Denial rates across permission groups In absolute numbers Storage and Location are most requested, most denied</p>
    <p>In relative numbers Microphone has highest denial rate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reasons for denials across permission groups</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Permission denials in</p>
    <p>categories</p>
    <p>*numbers indicate total # decisions per category</p>
    <p>* * *</p>
    <p>* * *</p>
    <p>*</p>
    <p>*</p>
    <p>Difference in denial rate also per permission type</p>
    <p>E.g. Location permission  43% denial rate in</p>
    <p>Travel and Local  11% denial rate in</p>
    <p>Communication</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reluctance In-situ: I dont mind giving &lt;app&gt; access to my &lt;permission&gt;</p>
    <p>Participants disagree or strongly disagree with 10% of grants</p>
    <p>34% of participants disagreed at least once</p>
    <p>In hindsight: How comfortable would you be with the &lt;app&gt; knowing &lt;the pictures taken with your camera / who is calling you / ...&gt;?</p>
    <p>Not at all comfortable selected in 29% cases  64% of participants were uncomfortable at least once  Least comfortable about Phone and Storage permissions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Influence of demographics on denial rate</p>
    <p>Denial rate varies across age groups for men</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Insights (1) Permissions influence during app (un)installations:</p>
    <p>Small in terms of percentages, yet ...  affects millions of app per day in absolute numbers.</p>
    <p>Dominant reasons related to grants/denies are related to app functionality</p>
    <p>Users are reasoning about permissions well - based on context and functionality.</p>
    <p>Users understand their options/controls: 40% of the time, when participants denied a permission, they did so because they knew they could change it later</p>
    <p>Good news: Runtime dialogs help!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Insights (2) Users decision making is complex and varied! Theres no simple model:</p>
    <p>Often multiple reasons influence each decision  Rationales differ across app categories  Rationales differ across type of data (permission group)</p>
    <p>Users often think requests for CONTACTS shouldnt be necessary and they postpone granting</p>
    <p>Trust is more important for LOCATION and CAMERA than other permissions</p>
    <p>Findings hint at the existence of multiple &amp; multi-dimensional privacy personas</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Insights (3)  There is some reluctance (10%) when granting permissions, and discomfort</p>
    <p>grows in hindsight (29%).</p>
    <p>Desire to deny a permission affects many people at some point:  49% of participants deny permissions at least once.  34% of participants have at least one app they think asks for a permission it shouldnt need  34% of participants showed reluctance for at least one of the permissions they granted  64% of participants are uncomfortable in hindsight with at least one of the permissions they</p>
    <p>granted</p>
    <p>Demographics have some influence: women deny twice as often as men</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>bram.bonne@uhasselt.be {psaiteja,ibilogrevic,ninataft}@google.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Additional slides (not used during presentation)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ethical considerations  Participants were informed of all data types collected before joining the</p>
    <p>experiment</p>
    <p>Participant responses were anonymized, thus no PII used in data analysis</p>
    <p>Data from participants who quit early was discarded</p>
    <p>We implemented E2E encryption in Paco, so data gathered is only available to those participating and those doing data analysis (us).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reasons for installing an app</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reasons for installing an app Indicate limited choice</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reasons for removing an app Mostly reiterating other reasons, but also:</p>
    <p>Permission abuse  Negative publicity  Expectation mismatch</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participant employment data</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
