<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>New Me: Understanding Expert and Non-expert</p>
    <p>Perceptions and Usage of the Tor Anonymity Network</p>
    <p>Kevin Gallagher</p>
    <p>New York University</p>
    <p>Sameer Patil Indiana University</p>
    <p>New York University</p>
    <p>Nasir Memon</p>
    <p>New York University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tor is a decentralized anonymity network.</p>
    <p>= Tor Node</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Little is known about Tor users.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We utilized multiple recruitment strategies.</p>
    <p>*</p>
    <p>* Reddit was also used, but did not allow us to use their logo.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We recruited participants from all walks of life.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participants took part in an interview.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>There is not enough time to cover all findings.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experts treat Tor as a Complex Network.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experts treat Tor as a Complex Network.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>When I started off I understood [Tor] pretty crudely as just kind of a way to get past state firewalls and to hide your identity from Web sites you are visiting. As I continued to use it, its really good for NAT [Network Address Translation] traversal for example. Like, if you want to host a Web site from your home address</p>
    <p>and youre behind NAT, a Tor hidden service is a great way to give you that kind of access.</p>
    <p>(P8, Expert, Male)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experts understood the threat model.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Between the laptop and the entry I will write a little note that says ISP can see that Im using Tor. And then</p>
    <p>between the entry and the middle Im going to say encrypted traffic. And then between the middle and</p>
    <p>the exit Im going to say encrypted traffic and between the exit and the Web site Im going to say ISP</p>
    <p>can see requests, but not the originator. (P1, Expert, Male)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Nodes may be owned/0wned by governments. (P5, Expert, Unspecified gender)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Non-experts view Tor as a service.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>As far as Im aware the way it works is it bounces your signal around a lot . . . To various countries and</p>
    <p>such. (P3, Non-expert, Male)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>And then like IP address . . . I dont know . . . does Tor jumble up your IP? Maybe, perhaps it does,</p>
    <p>perhaps it doesnt. Perhaps it gives you a new IP. (P2, Non-expert, Female)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Non-experts misunderstand the threat model.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I know that Im not doing anything dangerous but they dont know that, so I can see why the government</p>
    <p>would want to have access to that kind of thing. Or maybe they can receive alerts from Tor saying hey this person is suspicious by your standards . . . but thats</p>
    <p>bad business, so... (P4, Non-expert, Female)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our findings have a few actionable implications.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our findings have a few actionable implications.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Kevin Gallagher New York University</p>
    <p>kevin.gallagher@nyu.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
