<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 1</p>
    <p>Privacy Expectations and Preferences in an IoT World Pardis Emami-Naeini, Sruti Bhagavatula, Martin Degeling, Hana Habib, Lujo Bauer, Lorrie Faith Cranor, Norman Sadeh</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 3</p>
    <p>Do you know:  What are they collecting?</p>
    <p>Who are they sharing your data with?</p>
    <p>For how long are they keeping your data?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 4</p>
    <p>Now imagine the future  What are they collecting?</p>
    <p>Who are they sharing my data with?</p>
    <p>For how long are they keeping my data?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 5</p>
    <p>Design questions  Informing people about data collections</p>
    <p>What should we notify people about?</p>
    <p>Giving some choices to control privacy  What factors make people comfortable?  What factors make people allow/deny a data</p>
    <p>collection?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 6</p>
    <p>Design questions  Making the system automated</p>
    <p>How well can we predict people preferences?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 7</p>
    <p>Vignette study  Capture wide range of scenarios</p>
    <p>Stories about individuals, situations and structures which can make reference to important points in the study of perceptions, beliefs and attitudes (Hughes 1998)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 8</p>
    <p>Scenarios varied by 8 factors  Type of data collected  Location of data collection  Device collecting data  Retention time  Purpose of data collection  Who benefits from data collection  Whether or not data is shared  Whether more info could be inferred</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 9</p>
    <p>Example scenario  You are at [work]. This building has [cameras]</p>
    <p>that are recording [video of the entire building]. The video is [shared with law enforcement] to [improve public safety] and they [will not delete it].</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 10</p>
    <p>Example scenario  You are at a [department store]. This store has</p>
    <p>an [iris scanner] that scans customers' irises automatically as they enter the store in order to [remotely identify returning customers]. Your iris scan will be kept for [one week].</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 11</p>
    <p>Studied 380 IoT scenarios</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 12</p>
    <p>Our participants  1007 Mechanical Turk participants</p>
    <p>From the United States</p>
    <p>Avg. age: 35.3</p>
    <p>~15 minutes to complete</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 13</p>
    <p>Questions per scenario  I would want my mobile phone to notify me [every time /</p>
    <p>only the first time / every once in a while] this data collection occurs.</p>
    <p>five point scale from strongly agree to strongly disagree</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 14</p>
    <p>Questions per scenario  How would you feel about the data collection in the</p>
    <p>situation described above if you were given no additional information about the scenario?  five point scale from very comfortable to very uncomfortable</p>
    <p>If you had the choice, would you allow or deny this data collection?  Choices: allow, deny</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 15</p>
    <p>Model selection  GLMM + random intercept</p>
    <p>Backward elimination</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 16</p>
    <p>Model: Every time notification  Most impactful explanatory factor:</p>
    <p>Biometrics for an unspecified purpose (coef: 0.88, 61%)  Presence for a not beneficial purpose (coef: -0.49, 27%)</p>
    <p>Least impactful explanatory factor:  data collected at a department store (coef: -0.69, 42%)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 17</p>
    <p>Model: Comfort level  Most impactful explanatory factor:</p>
    <p>Video collection happening today (coef: 1.39, 69%)  Biometrics (coef: -1.45, 28%)</p>
    <p>Least impactful explanatory factor:  Data being kept forever (coef: 0.10, 48%)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 18</p>
    <p>Model: Desire to Allow/Deny  Most impactful explanatory factor:</p>
    <p>Video collected at department store (coef: -0.9, 66%)  Presence collected at work (coef: 2.11, 36%)</p>
    <p>Least impactful explanatory factor:  Data being shared (coef: 0.52, 45%)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 19</p>
    <p>Prediction accuracy  Comfort level:</p>
    <p>~81%</p>
    <p>Desire to allow or deny:  ~79%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 20</p>
    <p>Preferences in a nutshell  Anonymous data types</p>
    <p>Id be fine with data that doesnt identify me.</p>
    <p>Public vs. private [I would be] comfortable with public spaces, absolutely not comfortable in my home.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 21</p>
    <p>Preferences in a nutshell  Ranked 1st = Type of data + X</p>
    <p>Notification X = user perceived benefit  comfort X = happening today  allow/deny X = location</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PERSONALIZED PRIVACY ASSISTANT PROJECT 22</p>
    <p>Our results design  Design personalized privacy systems</p>
    <p>In progress: experience sampling More info: www.privacyassistant.org</p>
    <p>Pardis Emami-Naeini, Sruti Bhagavatula, Martin Degeling, Hana Habib, Lujo Bauer, Lorrie Faith Cranor, Norman Sadeh</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
