<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Raise the Curtains: The Effect of Awareness about Targeting on Consumers Attitudes and</p>
    <p>Purchase Intentions Sonam Samat, Alessandro Acquisti and Linda Babcock</p>
    <p>Carnegie Mellon University</p>
    <p>This research has been supported by the National Science Foundation under grants 1012763, 1514192, and 1327992, and by a Google Focused Research Award.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>offline sources</p>
    <p>Targeted Advertising</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>offline sources</p>
    <p>Targeting happens behind the scenes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>offline sources</p>
    <p>Raise The Curtains</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Tools For Awareness FTC recommendation to the ad industry: Provide notice to consumers (FTC report, 2009)</p>
    <p>Leon et al., 2012: 53% believe that more ads would pop up 45% believe the AdChoices tagline was selling ad space</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contrasting Evidence From Literature Awareness may increase purchase intentions  Explanations help increase trust in recommendation</p>
    <p>systems (Herlocker et. al., 1999; Chen &amp; Pu 2005)  There may be a placebo effect (Cosley 2003, OkCupid, 2015)  Targeted Ads act as social labels (Summers et. al., 2016)</p>
    <p>Awareness may decrease purchase intentions  Personalization can be creepy (Malheiros, 2012)  Surveys suggest consumers do not like targeting (Turow et. al.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contrasting Evidence From Literature Awareness may increase purchase intentions  Explanations help increase trust in recommendation</p>
    <p>systems (Herlocker et. al., 1999; Chen &amp; Pu 2005)  There may be a placebo effect (Cosley 2003, OkCupid, 2015)  Targeted Ads act as social labels (Summers et. al., 2016)</p>
    <p>Awareness may decrease purchase intentions  Personalization can be creepy (Malheiros, 2012)  Surveys suggest consumers do not like targeting (Turow et. al.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contrasting Evidence From Literature Awareness may increase purchase intentions  Explanations help increase trust in recommendation</p>
    <p>systems (Herlocker et. al., 1999; Chen &amp; Pu 2005)  There may be a placebo effect (Cosley 2003, OkCupid, 2015)  Targeted Ads act as social labels (Summers et. al., 2016)</p>
    <p>Awareness may decrease purchase intentions  Personalization can be creepy (Malheiros, 2012)  Surveys suggest consumers do not like targeting (Turow et. al.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Hypothesis</p>
    <p>Awareness that the ad is targeted</p>
    <p>Attitudes &amp; Purchase intentions</p>
    <p>Opinions towards targeting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Studies  Study 1: Exploratory study  Build a scale to measure opinions about targeting  What are the different opinions people have towards targeting?</p>
    <p>How prevalent are each of those opinions?  Study 2: Validation study  Is the scale reliable?</p>
    <p>Study 3: Evaluation study  How does awareness about targeting impact attitudes and purchase</p>
    <p>intentions towards advertised product?  Does this effect depend on opinions about targeting?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study 1: Exploratory Study</p>
    <p>Participants recruited from Mechanical Turk  Shown hypothetical scenarios involving targeted ads  Asked how they would feel if they experienced this scenario (open</p>
    <p>ended)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Re-marketed Ad Scenario</p>
    <p>Imagine that you are looking to buy a new pair of shoes online. You look into a few different websites that sell shoes. You find a pair of shoes that you like, on a website that youve never visited before. You spend some time looking at this particular pair of shoes and then move on to doing something else. You havent decided whether or not you want to purchase this particular pair of shoes.</p>
    <p>A few days later, you are reading an article on the New York Times website. You notice that the advertisement next to the article is for the same pair of shoes that you were looking at the other day.</p>
    <p>You realize that your browsing history had been tracked and that it was being used to display an advertisement that has been specifically targeted to you.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study 1: Results</p>
    <p>Sample size N=111  Coding of open-ended responses  2 independent coders  Cohens kappa &gt; 0.70</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How would you feel if you experienced this scenario?</p>
    <p>Neutral Positive Mixed emotions Slightly annoyed</p>
    <p>Weird/Strange Dislike Angry/Upset Violated</p>
    <p>Pe rc</p>
    <p>en ta</p>
    <p>ge</p>
    <p>Opinions about targeting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A scale to measure for opinions about targeting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Studies  Study 1: Exploratory study  Build a scale to measure opinions about targeting  What are the different opinions people have towards targeting?</p>
    <p>How prevalent are each of those opinions?  Study 2: Validation study  Is the scale reliable?</p>
    <p>Study 3: Evaluation study  How does awareness about targeting impact attitudes and purchase</p>
    <p>intentions towards advertised product?  Does this effect depend on opinions about targeting?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study 2: Validation Study</p>
    <p>Study 2a: 14-items scale Consolidate scale Exploratory factor analysis</p>
    <p>Study 2b: 6-items scale Confirmatory factor analysis Convergent and divergent validity Test-retest reliability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Final Scale for Opinions about Targeted Ads</p>
    <p>Statement Category</p>
    <p>I would feel ok about this type of advertising Neutral</p>
    <p>I would not be bothered by this type of advertising Neutral</p>
    <p>I would be interested in products shown in this type of advertising Positive</p>
    <p>I would feel this type of advertising can be helpful to me Positive</p>
    <p>I would be annoyed by this type of advertising Negative</p>
    <p>I would not like this type of advertising Negative</p>
    <p>!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Studies  Study 1: Exploratory study  Build a scale to measure opinions about targeting  What are the different opinions people have towards targeting?</p>
    <p>How prevalent are each of those opinions?  Study 2: Validation study  Is the scale reliable?</p>
    <p>Study 3: Evaluation study  How does awareness about targeting impact attitudes and purchase</p>
    <p>intentions towards advertised product?  Does this effect depend on opinions about targeting?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study 3: Evaluation Study</p>
    <p>Phase 1:  Participants recruited from Mechanical Turk  Measured opinions about targeting using our 6-item scale</p>
    <p>Phase 2:  Same participants invited to a new study after a two weeks  Randomized into one of two conditions:  Awareness vs. No Awareness</p>
    <p>Measured attitudes and purchase intentions towards product</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Light bulbs  Laudry detergents  Notebooks  Air purifiers  Dish scrubbers  Water bottles</p>
    <p>Shopping Task</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Awareness Condition: Our software will customize an advertisement for you based on your responses from the shopping task you completed earlier</p>
    <p>Advertisement Evaluation Task</p>
    <p>No Awareness Condition:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measures</p>
    <p>Attitudes: How much do you like this product?  Purchase intentions: How likely are you to buy this product?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All Participants Positive and Neutral Opinions</p>
    <p>Negative Opinions</p>
    <p>M ea</p>
    <p>n V</p>
    <p>al ue</p>
    <p>Awareness No Awareness</p>
    <p>Attitudes Towards Product</p>
    <p>p-value = 0.045p-value &gt; 0.05p-value &gt; 0.05</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Purchase Intentions Towards Product</p>
    <p>All Participants Positive and Neutral Opinions</p>
    <p>Negative Opinions</p>
    <p>M ea</p>
    <p>n V</p>
    <p>al ue</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Awareness No Awareness</p>
    <p>p-value = 0.074p-value &gt; 0.10p-value &gt; 0.10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why is this important?</p>
    <p>Revenue from online advertising was $19.6 billion in the first quarter of 2017 (IAB Report, 2016)</p>
    <p>Several people have negative opinions about targeted advertising  Our research:  53% had negative opinions (Exploratory Study)</p>
    <p>Other researchers:  66% do not want targeted ads (Turow et al., 2009)  55% do not want targeted ads (McDonald &amp; Cranor 2010)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  The self-regulated ad industry is not incentivized to make</p>
    <p>consumers aware about which ads are targeted to them  Are FTC recommendations enough?  We need regulations to help consumers make informed</p>
    <p>decisions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You</p>
    <p>Contact: sonamsamat@gmail.com</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
