<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Format vs. Content: The Impact of Risk and Presentation</p>
    <p>on Disclosure Decisions Sonam Samat and Alessandro Acquisti</p>
    <p>Carnegie Mellon University</p>
    <p>This research has been supported by the National Science Foundation under grants 1012763, 1514192, and 1327992.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation: The Online Data Market</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation: The Online Data Market</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Provide notice about how data is used  Give consumers choice to opt-out</p>
    <p>Current Solution: Notice &amp; Choice</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FTC recommendations to ad industry</p>
    <p>Current Solution: Notice &amp; Choice</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two factors:  Content: Objective costs and benefits  Format: Not related to objective costs and benefits</p>
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tsai et al. (2011)</p>
    <p>Content-based Factors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adjerid et al. (2013), John et al. (2011)</p>
    <p>Format-based Factors</p>
    <p>PRIVACY SETTINGS</p>
    <p>a. Yes b. No</p>
    <p>a. Yes b. No</p>
    <p>SURVEY SETTINGS</p>
    <p>a. Yes b. No</p>
    <p>a. Yes b. No</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Compare the effect of content and format based factors on disclosure decisions</p>
    <p>Investigate whether the effect of format based factors varies as content is varied</p>
    <p>Our Research Objectives</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Studies</p>
    <p>On the next pages you will be asked questions aimed at exploring the extent to which individuals participate in a number of behaviors with ethical implications.</p>
    <p>Please note that some of the questions asked deal with adult or sensitive material, and that you may skip any questions you wish not to answer. An example of an intrusive question similar to those asked in this study is:</p>
    <p>&quot;Have you ever had a one-night stand?&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Studies</p>
    <p>Sharing Settings Before we ask you the ethical behavior questions, please answer the following question about your sharing settings.</p>
    <p>Allow my responses to the ethical behavior questions to be shared with the research assistants for this study.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Studies</p>
    <p>Sharing Settings Before we ask you the ethical behavior questions, please answer the following question about your sharing settings.</p>
    <p>Prohibit my responses to the ethical behavior questions from being shared with the research assistants for this study.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Studies</p>
    <p>Sharing Settings Before we ask you the ethical behavior questions, please answer the following question about your sharing settings.</p>
    <p>Prohibit my responses to the ethical behavior questions from being shared with marketing companies.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Format-based factor influences disclosure behavior</p>
    <p>Study 1 Study 2</p>
    <p>Pe rc</p>
    <p>en ta</p>
    <p>ge w</p>
    <p>ill in</p>
    <p>g to</p>
    <p>s ha</p>
    <p>re</p>
    <p>Allow Prohibit</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Assistants Marketing Companies</p>
    <p>Mechanical Turk Forums with MID</p>
    <p>Pe rc</p>
    <p>en ta</p>
    <p>ge w</p>
    <p>ill in</p>
    <p>g to</p>
    <p>s ha</p>
    <p>re</p>
    <p>Allow Prohibit</p>
    <p>Effect of format-based factor varies with content-based factor</p>
    <p>Effect size = 0.31</p>
    <p>Effect size = 0.47</p>
    <p>Effect size = 0.78</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Notice &amp; choice mechanism is not sufficient in protecting consumer privacy  Format of notices needs to be regulated</p>
    <p>Individuals susceptibility to format-based factors increases as risk associated with disclosure increases  Format regulations should take into account the level of risk put</p>
    <p>forward by different websites</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You</p>
    <p>Contact: sonamsamat@gmail.com</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
