<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TurtleGuard: Helping Android Users Apply Contextual Privacy Preferences</p>
    <p>Lynn Tsai UC Berkeley Primal Wijesekera University of British Columbia Joel Reardon UC Berkeley Irwin Reyes ICSI Jung-Wei (Jennifer) Chen Good Research Nathan Good Good Research Serge Egelman ICSI / UC Berkeley David Wagner UC Berkeley</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HOW TO SHOW PRIVACY NOTICES ON MOBILE DEVICES?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>comprehension study</p>
    <p>online study of 308 Android users  quantitative survey</p>
    <p>laboratory study with 24 users  think-aloud experiment  semi-structured interviews</p>
    <p>A. P. Felt, E. Ha, S. Egelman, A. Haney, E. Chin, and D. Wagner. Android Permissions: User Attention, Comprehension, and Behavior. In Proceedings of the 2012 Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security (SOUPS). Best Paper Award!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>suggestions</p>
    <p>many were habituatedtoo many requests  only show information when necessary</p>
    <p>many were unawaretoo late in the process  provide information prior to decision-making</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>this ignores context</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UNDER WHAT CIRCUMSTANCES? show privacy notices more than once, but</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>how often are resources accessed in practice?</p>
    <p>dynamic analysis  modified Android OS and gave phones to 40 people  hooked all API methods involving access to sensitive data</p>
    <p>what are users doing when data is accessed (context)?</p>
    <p>P. Wijesekera, A. Baokar, A. Hosseini, S. Egelman, D. Wagner, and K. Beznosov. Android Permissions Remystified: A Field Study on Contextual Integrity. Proceedings of the 24th USENIX Security Symposium, 2015.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>the results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>more runtime requests?</p>
    <p>asking each time is infeasible  but 80% of participants wanted to block at least 1 request  on average, they wanted to block 35% of all requests</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>lessons learned</p>
    <p>visibility of the application requesting permission is a strong contextual cue.</p>
    <p>frequency at which requests occur makes it impractical to prompt user on every case.</p>
    <p>ask-on-first-use can be extended to capture the context.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>privacy as contextual integrity</p>
    <p>inappropriate data flows violate contextual information norms</p>
    <p>contextual information norms are modeled using:  data subject (i.e., the user)  data sender  data recipient  information type  transmission principle (constraints)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>what does this mean for user-centered design?</p>
    <p>notice should be shown in context</p>
    <p>only provide notice when reasonable privacy expectations are likely to be violated</p>
    <p>dont bother the user about appropriate data flows to prevent habituation</p>
    <p>do bother the user about unknown or inappropriate flows to preserve contextual integrity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HOW CAN NOTICES BETTER ACCOUNT FOR CONTEXT?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>notice in context</p>
    <p>definitively determining context is impossible use proxies to approximate, and learn from mistakes</p>
    <p>can we use machine learning to detect when context has changed from expected data use to unexpected?</p>
    <p>P. Wijesekera, A. Baokar, L. Tsai, J. Reardon, S. Egelman, D. Wagner, and K. Beznosov. The Feasability of Dynamically Granted Permissions: Aligning Mobile Privacy with User Preferences. In Proceedings of the 2017 IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (Oakland 17).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>automatically regulating access</p>
    <p>Error Rate Average Prompts/User</p>
    <p>Ask-on-first-use (Android/iOS) 15.4% 12.34</p>
    <p>ML Model 3.2% 12.00</p>
    <p>ML Model (low-prompt) 7.4% 8.00</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WHERE CAN USERS GO TO CORRECT ERRORS?</p>
    <p>because the classifier isnt perfect,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>status quo problems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>privacy dashboard</p>
    <p>classifier reduces error rates five-fold  some errors will always occur  open question: acceptable error rate?</p>
    <p>users need to be able to:  understand automated decisions (auditing/error detection)  change incorrect decisions (retraining)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>dashboard user study</p>
    <p>prior work showed &lt;25% of users understand background applications have same abilities as foreground ones</p>
    <p>does the dashboard correct this mental model? does it help users regulate access based on context?</p>
    <p>C. Thompson, M. Johnson, S. Egelman, D. Wagner, and J. King. When Its Better to Ask Forgiveness than Get Permission: Designing Usable Auditing Mechanisms for Mobile Permissions. In Proceedings of the 2013 Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security (SOUPS 13).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TurtleGuard</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TurtleGuard</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TurtleGuard</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TurtleGuard</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>dashboard user study</p>
    <p>functioning prototype implemented in HTML5:  control (Android M settings panel)  study conducted online (n=400)</p>
    <p>tasks designed to test:  understanding resource usage  fixing misaligned settings</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>task 1</p>
    <p>what are the two most recent apps that accessed the devices location?</p>
    <p>open-ended response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>task 1: control</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>task 1: control</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>task 1: control</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>task 1: TurtleGuard</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>task 1: TurtleGuard</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>task 1</p>
    <p>results:  control: 84% correct (167/198)  TurtleGuard: 68% correct (132/194)</p>
    <p>observations:  confusion from presenting all data types together  a quarter never opened TurtleGuard</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>task 2</p>
    <p>currently, which of the following data types can be accessed by the ZvW app?  multiple choice</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>task 2: control</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>task 2: TurtleGuard</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>task 2</p>
    <p>results:  control: 70% correct (140/198)  TurtleGuard: 59% correct (116/194)</p>
    <p>observations:  several confounding factors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>tasks 3 &amp; 4</p>
    <p>is the ZvW app able to access location data even when it is not actively being used?  multiple choice</p>
    <p>prevent it from doing soor explain whether it is even possible  open-ended response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>tasks 3 &amp; 4: control</p>
    <p>answering question relies on knowledge of Android!</p>
    <p>not possible to regulate foreground vs. background data access!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>tasks 3 &amp; 4: control</p>
    <p>answering question relies on knowledge of Android!</p>
    <p>not possible to regulate foreground vs. background data access!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>tasks 3 &amp; 4: TurtleGuard</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>tasks 3 &amp; 4</p>
    <p>results:  control:  43% understood background access would occur  23% correctly understood they could not regulate it</p>
    <p>TurtleGuard:  78% understood background access would occur  75% were able to limit it</p>
    <p>observations:  strong effects (task 3=0.36, task 4=0.51)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ITERATIVE DESIGN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VALIDATION STUDY</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>methodology</p>
    <p>repeat of pilot study  same 4 tasks</p>
    <p>new Mechanical Turk participants (n=298) compared with Prolific Academic sample (n=300)</p>
    <p>no differences in behavior</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>validation study results</p>
    <p>task 1: understanding recent location access  control: 83% correct (of 287)  TurtleGuard: 83% correct (of 293)</p>
    <p>task 2: finding granted permissions  control: 77% correct (of 287)  TurtleGuard: 81% correct (of 293)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>validation study results</p>
    <p>task 3: understanding privacy settings (background access):  control: 38% correct (of 287)  TurtleGuard: 79% correct (of 293)  medium-to-large effect size: =0.41</p>
    <p>task 4: changing privacy settings (background access):  control: 28% said it was impossible (of 287)  TurtleGuard: 77% correctly did it (of 293)  large effect size: =0.49</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>conclusions</p>
    <p>demonstrated how to use iterative user-centered design to construct a new interface for managing app permissions:</p>
    <p>without prior training, performs as well as the permissions interfaces users are accustomed to</p>
    <p>performs significantly better at communicating foreground vs. background data access</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NEXT STEPS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>validation field study</p>
    <p>we have a working prototype</p>
    <p>how will real users use it?</p>
    <p>will users make the same decisions when permission are actually denied?</p>
    <p>will they rectify errors with the dashboard?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>validation field study</p>
    <p>methodology  recruit 40 local Android users  use our phones as their own for a week  measure decision-making and interactions  post-study interviews/tasks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
