<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>End User Security &amp; Privacy Concerns with Smart Homes Eric Zeng ericzeng@cs.washington.edu University of Washington</p>
    <p>In collaboration with: Shrirang Mare Franziska Roesner</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation  Interview  Results  Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Internet of Things - so hot right now</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Internet of Things - so hot right now</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Securing IoT: Related Technical Work</p>
    <p>Contextual permissions for smart home platforms ContexIoT: Towards Providing Contextual Integrity to Appified IoT Platforms [Jia et al. 2017]</p>
    <p>Information flow control for smart home platforms FlowFence: Practical Data Protection for Emerging IoT Application Frameworks [Fernandes et al. 2016]</p>
    <p>Centralizing security in the smart home hub Securing Vulnerable Home IoT Devices with an In-Hub Security Manager [Simpson et al. 2017]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What kinds of security and privacy concerns do end users of smart homes have?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation  Interview  Results  Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Questions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Semi-structured interviews  30-45 minutes  Phone interviews</p>
    <p>Participants  Convenience/snowball sampling: recruited from social media, mailing lists,</p>
    <p>smart home forums  Users of at least two smart home devices</p>
    <p>Analysis  Independently surfaced initial codes from the interview transcripts  Iterated on and collapsed codes into a common codebook  Each transcript was coded by two researchers using the codebook</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation  Interview  Results  Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participant Demographics</p>
    <p>15 total participants  4 female, 11 male  7 had a background in CS or IT  3 were not the primary users of the smart home  Average ownership time was 2.26 years (range 1 week - 9 years)</p>
    <p>Age 18-24 25-34 35-44 45-54 55+</p>
    <p># Participants 3 6 2 1 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General Smart Home Use</p>
    <p>Common types of devices  Lights and outlets  Intelligent personal assistants  Thermostats  Security cameras  Motion sensors  Door locks</p>
    <p>Common use cases  Enhancing physical security  Home automation (convenience)</p>
    <p>What devices do you own? What apps and automations do you have installed?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General Smart Home Use</p>
    <p>What devices do you own? What apps and automations do you have installed?</p>
    <p>Methods for automating devices  End user programming  Scripting and coding  Third party services</p>
    <p>(e.g. IFTTT, stringify)  Third party apps</p>
    <p>(e.g. SmartThings apps)</p>
    <p>End user programming 3rd party apps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mental Models</p>
    <p>Advanced Intermediate Limited</p>
    <p>Could you please draw a diagram of how all of your devices are connected together?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security and Privacy Concerns</p>
    <p>One type of concern were interested in is security or privacy concerns. Do you or did you have any concerns like that about your smart home? You might not have any such concerns -- thats fine, and wed like to hear about that too.</p>
    <p>Summary  Sparse set of concerns - diverse set of issues, but few</p>
    <p>concerns universally shared  Most were aware of potential security/privacy issues, but</p>
    <p>were explicitly not concerned 15</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Threat model: assets</p>
    <p>Primary assets mentioned were physical security  Concern about the security of smart locks  Using smart homes as security system</p>
    <p>Many mentioned privacy in general, but were not concerned</p>
    <p>Its not like I openly admit to anything ridiculous that would incriminate me. And even if I did, no ones going to hear it, because Amazon doesnt release audio logs... That doesnt bother me, I guess  some people, it freaks them out, but its not a big deal. Its just part of big data. (P5)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Threat model: adversaries</p>
    <p>Companies: frequently mentioned, but most trusted them</p>
    <p>...we are dealing with Amazon, we are dealing with big companies that are probably not totally irresponsible about privacy and security. (P11)</p>
    <p>Government: abstractly concerned, but not specific about motivations</p>
    <p>I havent changed any of my behavior in the house. If the FBI/CIA actually ever gets a recording of whats going into my Echo, theyll probably just think Im a weirdo. (P8)</p>
    <p>Third party developers: only mentioned by one participant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Threat model: threats and vulnerabilities</p>
    <p>More advanced mental models = more aware of smart home threats</p>
    <p>People are concerned that someone could check into their camera or their lights they cant do that if they dont get your password. (P3)</p>
    <p>Advanced mental models  Lack of TLS (HTTPS)  Re-pairing attacks on vulnerable</p>
    <p>device pairing protocols  Insecure/malicious devices</p>
    <p>Limited mental models  Weak passwords  Unsecured wifi networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why the lack of concern about security and privacy?</p>
    <p>Trust for companies that produce smart home devices  Didnt consider themselves to be worthwhile targets  Believed they took appropriate security measures  Explicitly mentioned a tradeoff between usability and</p>
    <p>security/privacy</p>
    <p>I read some stuff about Hue bulbs being hacked, but I live in a small town. No one is going to pull up to my house and do any of that stuff. (P7)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mitigation Strategies</p>
    <p>Varied ad-hoc technical mitigations  Separate WiFi networks for IoT devices, home computers  Only purchasing Z-Wave devices  Good passwords for accounts and WiFi</p>
    <p>Few behavioral mitigations  Didnt change behavior around smart home devices, like the Echo  Avoided putting cameras in sensitive locations</p>
    <p>Thinking specifically about security and privacy concerns, have those concerns caused you to change any of your behaviors?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multi-User Issues</p>
    <p>Smart homes have different classes of users  Primary user - set up home, has full access to</p>
    <p>accounts and devices  Incidental users - may or may not have full access, but</p>
    <p>are affected by the smart home system  Differences in power and control, could be problematic</p>
    <p>Have you ever had disagreements with people in your home about how your smart home is set up?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multi-User Issues: Restricted Device Access</p>
    <p>Does your wife have access to the devices in the home?</p>
    <p>She does not have any of the apps on her phone. The only thing she uses as a smart device would be the Echo, and that is to basically turn off the TV, like I do.</p>
    <p>I locked down my thermostat from her specifically, because she complains that it is hot all the time, and Im like just turn on the fan, just turn on the ceiling fan and stand under it, and youll be good, because it costs money.  (P5)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multi-User Issues: Audio and Video Surveillance</p>
    <p>One time we threw a party and didn't tell the woman who coordinates our house, and someone unplugged the NEST camera in the kitchen... and when it is unplugged, it automatically sends an email to whoevers account is associated with the camera, and it has a photo of the last thing the camera saw.</p>
    <p>...so the coordinator got the email and it was like Your camera was unplugged, this is the last thing the camera saw! And there was like 25 people that were in this little tiny area of the kitchen. She wasnt mad!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multi-User Issues: Behavioral Surveillance</p>
    <p>I have some automations that drive my wife nuts...</p>
    <p>I get push notifications on a private slack channel I have when my wife or daughter arrives home, based on the (inaudible) door lock...</p>
    <p>My wife hates the aspect that I know when her device comes or goes on the local LAN. Which obviously creates an audit log so to speak of when shes at home. Shes now chiming in, thats the reason her phone doesnt connect to the wifi anymore, so I cant track her. (P2)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation  Interview  Results  Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons</p>
    <p>Users have fewer concerns about privacy compared to physical security</p>
    <p>Users have gaps in their threat models, and no universal best practices for smart home security exist</p>
    <p>The design of smart home technology has created differences in power between users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations</p>
    <p>Help users make more informed security decisions  Design devices to improve users mental models (and</p>
    <p>threat models)  Develop standard best security practices for end users</p>
    <p>Design consciously for multiple users  Support multiple accounts, physical access</p>
    <p>Minimize tradeoffs for security and privacy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks!</p>
    <p>Collaborators</p>
    <p>Shrirang Mare</p>
    <p>Contact ericzeng@cs.washington.edu homes.cs.washington.edu/~ericzeng keybase.io/ericzeng</p>
    <p>Franzi Roesner</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Smart homes are becoming increasingly popular  We conducted interviews with end users of smart homes to learn about their</p>
    <p>security and privacy concerns  We found that current smart home users</p>
    <p>have incomplete mental models and threat models,  have limited personal concern about security and privacy</p>
    <p>We found that smart homes should better accommodate multi-user home environments</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
