<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Is that you, Alice? A Usability Study of the Authentication Ceremony of</p>
    <p>Secure Messaging Applications</p>
    <p>Elham Vaziripour, Justin Wu, Mark ONeill, Ray Clinton, Jordan Whitehead,</p>
    <p>Scott Heidbrink, Kent Seamons, Daniel Zappala</p>
    <p>Brigham Young University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why the Authentication Ceremony is Important</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why the Authentication Ceremony is Important</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why the Authentication Ceremony is Important</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Verifying the Identity Key</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Questions</p>
    <p>methods to they prefer?</p>
    <p>trust?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Three Popular Secure Messaging Applications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Facebook Messenger</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Facebook Messenger</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Viber</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>24 participants (first phase) and 48 (second phase) were recruited on campus</p>
    <p>Participants were recruited in pairs (with their friends)</p>
    <p>Each phase is within-subjects comparison of 3 applications</p>
    <p>Between-subjects comparison of the effect of instruction</p>
    <p>a. Phase 1: instruction on threats</p>
    <p>b. Phase 2: additional instruction on necessity of authentication ceremony</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phase 1 Instruction</p>
    <p>that nobody else (such as the service provider) can read your text</p>
    <p>messages.</p>
    <p>his/her credit card number, he left home, through the application.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phase 1: Most do not find/use the authentication ceremony  Only 4 of 24 participants had some success</p>
    <p>Security of voice vs text:</p>
    <p>a. Voice : Participants believed it is harder to be hacked in real-time</p>
    <p>b. Text : They believed it is easy to delete afterward</p>
    <p>Methods of authentication:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phase 2 Additional Instruction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phase 2: 78% Completed the Ceremony</p>
    <p>Success rate much higher with instruction  78% vs 14%</p>
    <p>Viber significantly better success rate  In-app phone call and instructions to compare keys on screen</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phase 2:  But it Takes too Long  Mean 3.2 minutes to find, 4.5 minutes to complete the authentication</p>
    <p>Finding the ceremony: No significant difference among the apps  Using the ceremony: Viber significantly faster than WhatsApp (3.6 vs 4.78 minutes)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phase 2: Successful Verification Methods</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Education Increased Trust in Viber</p>
    <p>First Phase Second Phase</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Common Difficulties</p>
    <p>Participants complained about the length of the encryption key  Its about eight years long!  R27A</p>
    <p>Please explain why you think you have (or have not) verified the identity of your friend.</p>
    <p>32 of 141 responses did not mention the ceremony  28 of these mention using features of their partner as the method of verifying</p>
    <p>identity (e.g. physical appearance in video, shared private knowledge, familiar</p>
    <p>voice)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Threat Model  Who do you think can read your message except you and your</p>
    <p>friend?</p>
    <p>Weak perception of active man-in-the-middle attack  just the two of us unless there were hackers  R36A  not WhatsApp or third parties! But probably people with skills  R28A</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Problem: Authentication ceremony does not match users mental model about authentication</p>
    <p>Solutions:  Use social authentication  post public keys to multiple social media</p>
    <p>accounts</p>
    <p>i. Verifying account authenticity matches what users expect when authenticating</p>
    <p>identity</p>
    <p>ii. Automate the ceremony</p>
    <p>Use key transparency (e.g. CONIKS) to monitor keys</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!</p>
    <p>Find study materials and data at: alice.internet.byu.edu</p>
    <p>Contact us at : elhamvaziripour@byu.edu</p>
    <p>Internet Research Lab</p>
    <p>Brigham Young University</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
