<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ethics Emerging: the Story of Privacy and Security</p>
    <p>Perceptions in Virtual Reality Devon Adams, Alseny Bah, Catherine Barwulor, Nureli Musabay, Kadeem Pitkin</p>
    <p>and Elissa M. Redmiles</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Virtual Reality</p>
    <p>Immersion</p>
    <p>Interactivity</p>
    <p>Sensory Feedback</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Early Adopters 3% of U.S. has adopted VR</p>
    <p>What VR Looks Like in 5 years</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Questions</p>
    <p>What are users privacy and security concerns with VR?  How are developers thinking about addressing security and privacy concerns?</p>
    <p>How are users coping with security and privacy issues?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Interview Results</p>
    <p>Privacy Policies</p>
    <p>Ethical Guidelines</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interview Study</p>
    <p>Participants</p>
    <p>Recruitment</p>
    <p>Screening</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interview Protocol</p>
    <p>Open Ended Questions</p>
    <p>VR Background What made you decide to buy / use a VR headset?</p>
    <p>Information Sources How did you learn to develop for VR?</p>
    <p>Concerns Do you foresee any privacy or security concerns with your product or with VR in general?</p>
    <p>Data Collection Do you think your VR system collects information about you? What information?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participant Demographics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Well-BeingSecurity Privacy</p>
    <p>Motion Sickness</p>
    <p>Psychological</p>
    <p>Vision DamageMalicious</p>
    <p>Applications</p>
    <p>Sensor Data Sniffing</p>
    <p>Company Reputation Distrust</p>
    <p>Data Collection Harassment</p>
    <p>Not There YetNot There Yet</p>
    <p>Always On Camera (IR), Microphone</p>
    <p>Concerns VR Background</p>
    <p>Community Goals Applications</p>
    <p>Developers: Supportive</p>
    <p>Users: Exclusive</p>
    <p>Influence</p>
    <p>Developers: Presence</p>
    <p>Users: Immersion VideosGames</p>
    <p>Art</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Concerns</p>
    <p>Security</p>
    <p>Not There Yet Sensors Data Sniffing</p>
    <p>Malicious Applications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Few Security Concerns Mentioned Little mention among developers (d=2, u=4)</p>
    <p>Developers mention an inclination to pass responsibility to others (d=2)</p>
    <p>Use of cloud data storage means that we dont have to deal with securing information ourselves. It makes it their problem and not ours.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Concerns</p>
    <p>Privacy Not There Yet Company Reputation Distrust</p>
    <p>Data Collection</p>
    <p>Always On Camera (IR) Microphone</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Greater Privacy Concerns</p>
    <p>The Rift actually has a microphone in it [so I realized] oh crap people can hear me. Ive [also] seen somebody</p>
    <p>post a picture of what the sensors actually picked up and it was a pretty clear view of the room.</p>
    <p>A majority of users (u=6, d=6) mentioned microphone and IR sensor data collection</p>
    <p>Privacy issues around the headset producers reputation (u=4, d=3)</p>
    <p>Considering that Oculus Rift is owned by Facebook, I [am] concerned you know Facebook has been in the</p>
    <p>news recently about just how much they picked up based on your habit, posting activities and things like that.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Image Captured from Oculus Sensors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Well-Being Concerns</p>
    <p>Well-Being</p>
    <p>Motion Sickness Psychological Harassment</p>
    <p>Vision Damage</p>
    <p>Physical Harm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Psychological Well-Being Concerns</p>
    <p>VR is a very personal intimate situation and when you wear a VR headset you really believe it, its really</p>
    <p>immersive. So if someone harms you in VR, you will also feel that after taking off the headset.</p>
    <p>Users felt those at psychological risk shouldnt use VR Some people might not be mentally developed enough to</p>
    <p>take something like that and not be messed up over it, you know?</p>
    <p>Developers mention concerns about the psychological well being of users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Developer Responsibility</p>
    <p>I think that its on the developer to try and limit the user to being able to only experience</p>
    <p>what the developer was intending for them experience in the first place.</p>
    <p>Developers feel responsible for users well-being and privacy Desire to use existing norms to ensure safety in VR</p>
    <p>Permissions (d=4) Privacy Policies (d=6)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Permissions</p>
    <p>Four developers suggested permission requests</p>
    <p>But, currently no such permissions on desktop VR</p>
    <p>And design is hard if you want to [request] some information</p>
    <p>from the player you cannot simply display it on the screen because it is not there.</p>
    <p>identical to current privacy methodologies requesting permission from the end user ahead of time.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Policies</p>
    <p>Have Privacy Policy</p>
    <p>App</p>
    <p>App</p>
    <p>App</p>
    <p>Mention VR / VR Data</p>
    <p>Have Privacy Policy</p>
    <p>App</p>
    <p>App App</p>
    <p>Mention VR / VR Data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>theres a quite a big list of unknowns right now in terms of whats best etiquette for a user and whats gonna keep the user the most [safe], comfortable, and satisfied</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Code of Ethics Co-Design</p>
    <p>Draft of guidelines</p>
    <p>Invited developers to edit &amp; add to guidelines</p>
    <p>Trace ethnographic analysis of edits</p>
    <p>Consensus reached on 10 principles for VR ethical development</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Code of Ethics Co-Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Three categories of concerns: Security, Privacy, Well-Being</p>
    <p>Developers feel responsible for Privacy &amp; Well-Being; Existing Practices May Not Work</p>
    <p>Co-design with developers may be useful in other security &amp; privacy areas</p>
    <p>Future work: secure libraries for VR development, what does policing look like in a Virtual World, how does well-being fit in as a security / privacy topic</p>
    <p>Contact: Alseny Bah (abah4@umbc.edu); Elissa Redmiles (eredmiles@cs.umd.edu) 24</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
