<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Its ScaryIts ConfusingIts Dull: How Cybersecurity Advocates</p>
    <p>Overcome Negative Perceptions of Security</p>
    <p>Julie Haney and Wayne Lutters University of Maryland, Baltimore County SOUPS 18, August 14, 2018</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Cyber attacks are on the rise, but people often fail to adopt and effectively use security best practices and technologies.</p>
    <p>From the audiences perspective, security can be characterized by three major factors: one , its scary; two, its confusing; three, its dull.</p>
    <p>--P08</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cybersecurity Advocates</p>
    <p>Cybersecurity advocates are security professionals who promote and encourage security adoption as a major component of their job  Examples:  Security awareness professionals  Secure development champions  Security consultants  Non-profit security advocacy staff</p>
    <p>Must be effective at communicating security risk, motivating behavior change, and overcoming negative perceptions of security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Questions</p>
    <p>What are the professional characteristics and skills that cybersecurity advocates employ in their work?</p>
    <p>What techniques do cybersecurity advocates use to encourage security adoption?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Interviewed 28 cybersecurity advocates  10 females, 18 males  Various job roles  e.g., consultants, security engineers, educators  Diverse educational backgrounds  14 with at least one non-tech degree  Experienced group  most &gt; 10 years experience in security  Multiple sectors - industry, government, higher ed, non-profits  Diverse audiences  internal and external</p>
    <p>Questions on work practices, professional motivations, challenges, characteristics of successful advocates</p>
    <p>Grounded Theory methods for data collection and analysis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Establishing Trust</p>
    <p>Trust is the most important thing that I have. -- P12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demonstrating Technical Knowledge</p>
    <p>You really do need to understand the</p>
    <p>technologyThis stuffs tricky, and you dont just guess your</p>
    <p>way out of it. -- P08</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Building Relationships</p>
    <p>I think people have to have a high emotional intelligence and especially empathy. Part of being successful in this is being able</p>
    <p>to have a conversation and put yourself in the place of the person that youre working with, and then be able to give</p>
    <p>effective advice that is not preaching, is trying to be helpful, and is letting them know that theyre not stupid because they may</p>
    <p>not know how to do certain things. --P18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overcoming Its Scary</p>
    <p>Were just really a fear-mongering industry. -- P21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Being Honest, Yet Discerning, About Risk</p>
    <p>You cant appreciate the importance of security</p>
    <p>without first understanding whats at</p>
    <p>stake, whats at risk. -- P14</p>
    <p>If I told everyone what I know, theyd freak out. I want to tell a smaller list of people I know so that</p>
    <p>we can quietly fix it. -- P11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Empowerment</p>
    <p>I love empowering people and seeing their lightbulbs go off in the moment that they understand why they are a target and what they can do about it. So, its not a place of fear. You have to</p>
    <p>start with fear to get them to understand that theres a problem,</p>
    <p>but then you also give them the tools. --P21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overcoming Its Confusing</p>
    <p>Security is mysterious to most people. -- P07</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bridging the Gap: Translation &amp; Context Awareness</p>
    <p>Being able to translate</p>
    <p>complicated things very simply is</p>
    <p>crucial -- P02</p>
    <p>You have to assimilate to and acclimate to the</p>
    <p>language and the beliefs and the</p>
    <p>culture that you are trying to affect.</p>
    <p>-- P11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Providing Practical Recommendations</p>
    <p>I think in the security area theres a lot of mythology and a lot of things we do because we heard its the</p>
    <p>right thing to do. And we have no idea why, but everybody else seems to be doing it, so we should do it, too. And so, trying to get people to stop and think it through, and figure out whats actually going to be</p>
    <p>effective. --P07</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overcoming Its Dull</p>
    <p>Nobody wants to spend their time doing security. -- P07</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Incentivizing - Selling Security</p>
    <p>I am trying to drive them to make themselves more secure by using</p>
    <p>various argumentative techniques. And, in some way, thats manipulating</p>
    <p>them. But if youre manipulating somebody for their own good, thats</p>
    <p>not wrong. --P10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Using Engaging Communication Techniques</p>
    <p>You can feel the energy that they</p>
    <p>believe in it. -- P14</p>
    <p>Personalizing the message is useful,</p>
    <p>seeing that this happens to real</p>
    <p>people. -- P07</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implications</p>
    <p>Advancing risk communication  Relationship to non-security risk domains  Strategies for communicating security risk</p>
    <p>Emerging cybersecurity advocate role  Establishment of an advocate work role  Continuing education efforts to support</p>
    <p>progression from other roles and disciplines</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Contribution Summary</p>
    <p>Identifies the cybersecurity advocate role</p>
    <p>Provides insight into security advocacy techniques in a variety of contexts, which can inform design of security resources</p>
    <p>Future: Validate interview findings with client interviews</p>
    <p>Contact me: jhaney1@umbc.edu</p>
    <p>Quotation box art credit: https://www.showeet.com</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
