<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introducing the Cybersurvival Task: Assessing and Addressing Staff Beliefs about Effective Cyber Protection James Nicholson, Lynne Coventry, Pam Briggs PaCT Lab, Northumbria University Newcastle, UK</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Kiahr, R., Shah, J.N., Sheriffs, P., Rossington, T., Pestell, G., Button, M. and Wang, V. Cyber Security Breaches Survey 2017.</p>
    <p>Security Breaches in 2017 (UK)</p>
    <p>Human Factors Technology</p>
    <p>-$3.5m Average cost of a cybersecurity breach:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Self-report measurement tools:  SeBIS (16 self-reported items)</p>
    <p>Device Securement, Password Generation, Proactive Awareness, Updating  e.g. I do not change my passwords unless I have to. (Never =&gt; Always)</p>
    <p>HAIS-Q (63 self-reported items)  Password management, Email use, Internet use, Social media use, Mobile devices,</p>
    <p>Information handling, Incident reporting  Knowledge / Attitude / Behaviour</p>
    <p>E.g. I share my work passwords with colleagues</p>
    <p>How do we assess an organisations security culture?</p>
    <p>Egelman, S., &amp; Peer, E. (2015). Scaling the security wall: Developing a security behavior intentions scale (sebis). In Proceedings of the 33rd Annual ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 2873-2882). ACM. Parsons, K., Calic, D., Pattinson, M., Butavicius, M., McCormac, A. and Zwaans, T. 2017. The Human Aspects of Information Security Questionnaire (HAIS-Q): Two further validation studies. Computers &amp; Security. 66, (May 2017), 4051.</p>
    <p>Wash, R., Rader, E. and Fennell, C. 2017. Can People Self-Report Security Accurately? Proceedings of the 2017 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems - CHI 17 (2017), 22282232.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Purpose: Highlight cybersecurity misconceptions amongst employees and serve as a reflective exercise to security experts in organisation</p>
    <p>Expert = those responsible for setting the security agenda in their organisation</p>
    <p>Rank the 20 behaviours in order of importance for staying safe online in [organisation]</p>
    <p>The Cybersurvival Task</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Stage Approximate Duration</p>
    <p>Generate List of Behaviours (Experts) 30 minutes</p>
    <p>Workshops (Employees) 60 minutes (each)</p>
    <p>Reflection (Experts) 45 minutes</p>
    <p>Overview of the Task</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workshop with organisations security experts  Initial list of behaviours pre-compiled from Ion et al. (2015) and</p>
    <p>organisations Information Security Policy  Experts tasked with adding, removing, and rephrasing behaviours</p>
    <p>to reflect their desired focus for their organisation  Experts asked to rank the final list of behaviours in order of</p>
    <p>importance for their staff to follow</p>
    <p>Generating the Behaviours</p>
    <p>Ion, L., Reeder, R. and Consolvo, S. 2015. ... no one can hack my mind: Comparing Expert and Non-Expert Security Practices. Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security (2015), 327346.</p>
    <p>Egelman, S., &amp; Peer, E. (2015). Scaling the security wall: Developing a security behavior intentions scale (sebis). In Proceedings of the 33rd Annual ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 2873-2882). ACM.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Activity Approximate Duration</p>
    <p>Introduction 2 minutes</p>
    <p>Individual ranking of Cybersurvival Sheet 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Reveal: top 3 and bottom 3 behaviours 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Group ranking of Cybersurvival Sheet 25 minutes</p>
    <p>Reveal of expert rankings 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Debrief 3 minutes</p>
    <p>Employee Workshops</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Activity Approximate Duration</p>
    <p>Introduction 2 minutes</p>
    <p>Individual ranking of Cybersurvival Sheet 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Reveal: top 3 and bottom 3 behaviours 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Group ranking of Cybersurvival Sheet 25 minutes</p>
    <p>Reveal of expert rankings 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Debrief 3 minutes</p>
    <p>Employee Workshops</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Activity Approximate Duration</p>
    <p>Introduction 2 minutes</p>
    <p>Individual ranking of Cybersurvival Sheet 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Reveal: top 3 and bottom 3 behaviours 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Group ranking of Cybersurvival Sheet 25 minutes</p>
    <p>Reveal of expert rankings 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Debrief 3 minutes</p>
    <p>Employee Workshops</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Activity Approximate Duration</p>
    <p>Introduction 2 minutes</p>
    <p>Individual ranking of Cybersurvival Sheet 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Reveal: top 3 and bottom 3 behaviours 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Group ranking of Cybersurvival Sheet 25 minutes</p>
    <p>Reveal of expert rankings 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Debrief 3 minutes</p>
    <p>Employee Workshops</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Activity Approximate Duration</p>
    <p>Introduction 2 minutes</p>
    <p>Individual ranking of Cybersurvival Sheet 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Reveal: top 3 and bottom 3 behaviours 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Group ranking of Cybersurvival Sheet 25 minutes</p>
    <p>Reveal of expert rankings 10 minutes</p>
    <p>Debrief 3 minutes</p>
    <p>Employee Workshops</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experts presented with report highlighting:  Their rankings  Average employee rankings (individual and group)</p>
    <p>Colour-coded highlighting of biggest shifts  Key reason for ranking of behaviour</p>
    <p>Experts alerted to biggest staff misconceptions</p>
    <p>Expert Reflection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Output: Discrepancies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Output: Discrepancies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Output: Discrepancies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Output: Discrepancies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Output: Discrepancies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Output: Discrepancies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Academic Group 2 (Female 1): But if you opened it, I wouldnt</p>
    <p>anyway, but open an attachment from someone I didnt know  I</p>
    <p>would just delete it  but if I did open it I would assume that</p>
    <p>unless I clicked on a link within that attachment then the</p>
    <p>attachment couldnt, unless, you know like a Word attachment, if</p>
    <p>they sent me some kind of attachment that could be actually</p>
    <p>downloading a virus.</p>
    <p>Example Output: Flawed Mental Models</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CISO: I have, based on years of experience, developed a prejudice towards certain desired behaviours that I now think, based on this, perhaps Ive allowed that prejudice to drive my</p>
    <p>own personal baseline. And I think this tool helps break that and forces me to re-evaluate my concept of desired behaviours.</p>
    <p>Feedback from Experts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ranking task, so less social desirability  Specific to each organisation  Provides cybersecurity insights for both employees and experts</p>
    <p>Overall duration (for deployment 2): 5 hours and 15 minutes  Needs evaluation in different industries</p>
    <p>Strengths and Weaknesses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Task where employees have to rank a list of (organisationspecific) behaviours in order of importance for staying safe online</p>
    <p>Allows for identification of disagreements between organisational security experts and employees  Identify misconceptions and shadow behaviours  Experts can tailor training or awareness programme to these</p>
    <p>behaviours  Experts can rethink their policies</p>
    <p>Summary: The Cybersurvival Task</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>e: james.nicholson@northumbria.ac.uk</p>
    <p>t: @jjnicholson</p>
    <p>w: www.jjnc.xyz</p>
    <p>You could ask me about:</p>
    <p>- What differences did you observe across job roles?</p>
    <p>- You mentioned interesting heated discussions. What were they fighting about?</p>
    <p>- What else were the experts surprised by?</p>
    <p>- What are your pearls of wisdom if I want to run this task?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
