<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>API Blindspots: Why Experienced Developers Write</p>
    <p>Vulnerable Code Electrical and Computer Engineering Department, University of Florida</p>
    <p>Daniela Seabra Oliveira, Tian Lin, Muhammad Sajidur Rahman, Rad Akefirad, Donovan Ellis, Eliany Perez, Rahul Bobhate, Lois A. DeLong, Justin Cappos, Yuriy Brun, Natalie C. Ebner</p>
    <p>@dseabraoliveira daniela@ece.ufl.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vulnerabilities keep increasing From Symantec Security Report 2018!</p>
    <p>Total number of vulnerabilities</p>
    <p>Zero-day vulnerabilities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The same old vulnerabilities again and again</p>
    <p>August 2018!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Community Response 1 Blame the developer for lack of security education</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Community Response 1 Blame the developer for lack of security education</p>
    <p>Nah</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Community Response 2 Security should be required from the beginning, developers</p>
    <p>can write secure code if provided with resources</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Community Response 2 Security should be required from the beginning, developers</p>
    <p>can write secure code if provided with resources</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Community Response 3 Developers need *usable* resources to write secure code</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Community Response 3 Developers need *usable* resources to write security code</p>
    <p>Yes!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ButVulnerabilities keep increasing From Symantec Security Report 2018!</p>
    <p>Total number of vulnerabilities</p>
    <p>Zero-day vulnerabilities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What if there is something else? Like some missing ingredient for the recipe of secure code?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hypothesis: Even with usable resources to write secure code, developers might still experience blindspots, especially when using APIs...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>API blindspot: a developer misunderstanding or oversight when using an API function, which can lead to a violation of the recommended API usage with possible introduction of vulnerabilities.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Donnie Brasco 1976-1981 (Joe Pistone)</p>
    <p>Source: FBI archives</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Donnie Brasco 1976-1981 (Joe Pistone)</p>
    <p>Source: FBI archives</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Donnie Brasco 1976-1981 (Joe Pistone)</p>
    <p>Impact:  200 indictments  100 convictions  Bonnano family almost destroyed  NY Mafia instituting new rules  $500,000 contract on his life forever</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Undetected Donnies Vulnerabilities</p>
    <p>Met with FBI contact agent twice a month</p>
    <p>Called contact agent every few days and even FBI headquarters</p>
    <p>Wore wires on several occasions</p>
    <p>Every 3 weeks he visited his wife and daughters.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Werent the Mafia guys experienced?</p>
    <p>When you talk on the phoneyou dont talk direct about whats going on  Because all the phones are tapped... Like most mobsters, he [Lefty] was paranoid. Theres agents everywhere.</p>
    <p>Because of their paranoia that there are bugs planted everywhere, mob guys, , always turn on the TV or radio to cover the conversation.</p>
    <p>Source: Donnie Brasco. My Undercover Life with the Mafia. Joseph D. Pistone</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Arent Mafia guys experts?</p>
    <p>Lefty was Mafia twenty-four hours a day. He would never let his guard down.</p>
    <p>Sonny [cappo] was good at what he did.</p>
    <p>Source: Donnie Brasco. My Undercover Life with the Mafia. Joseph D. Pistone</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What about developers blindspots?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Understand API blindspots from a developers perspective</p>
    <p>Pe rce pti on s</p>
    <p>Exp eri en ce/</p>
    <p>Exp ert ise</p>
    <p>Cognition</p>
    <p>Personality</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Goals</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part 2: Demographics</p>
    <p>Part 3: Professional Experience and</p>
    <p>Expertise</p>
    <p>Part 5: Personality Assessment (Big 5)</p>
    <p>Part 4: Cognitive Assessment</p>
    <p>Part 1: Programming Puzzles (Java)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part 1: Programming Puzzles</p>
    <p>*</p>
    <p>* **</p>
    <p>Set 1</p>
    <p>BS Non-BS</p>
    <p>Set 2 Set 3</p>
    <p>I/O String Crypto</p>
    <p>US Brazil</p>
    <p>India, Bangladesh</p>
    <p>Programming puzzles</p>
    <p>Set 4 Random assignment</p>
    <p>Source: http://www.techreviewer.club/why-hire-wordpress-developers/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part 1: Puzzles  BS on String API</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part 1: Puzzles - BS on String API</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part 1: Puzzles  BS on String API</p>
    <p>Which of the following statements would be correct if the setDate() method was invoked with an arbitrary String value as the new date:</p>
    <p>a. If the given String value does not conform to the dd-mm-yyyy format, an exception is thrown. b. The setDate() method cannot change the date. c. The setDate() method might do more than change the date. d. The return value of the waitFor() method is not interpreted correctly (lines 1417). e. The web application will crash.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part 1: Puzzles - BS on String API</p>
    <p>Which of the following statements would be correct if the setDate() method was invoked with an arbitrary String value as the new date:</p>
    <p>a. If the given String value does not conform to the dd-mm-yyyy format, an exception is thrown. b. The setDate() method cannot change the date. c. The setDate() method might do more than change the date. d. The return value of the waitFor() method is not interpreted correctly (lines 1417). e. The web application will crash.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part 2: Participants Demographics (n = 109)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part 3: Professional Experience and Expertise</p>
    <p>Programming languages:  Java, Python, C/C++, PHP, Visual Basic, .Net, and JavaScript</p>
    <p>Programming concepts and technologies:  SQL, Cryptography, File compression, Networking, HTTP/HTTPS,</p>
    <p>I/O operations, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BTACT (Brief Test of Adult Cognition by Telephone) and the NIH Toolbox</p>
    <p>Processing speed  Memory span  Verbal fluency  Short- and long-term episodic verbal memory  Inductive reasoning</p>
    <p>Part 4: Cognitive Assessment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BTACT Word list recall Processing speed and working memory</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part 5: Personality Assessment (Big 5)</p>
    <p>https://www.enkimd.com/big-five-personality-traits.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Analysis and Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>H1: Developers are less likely to solve puzzles with API</p>
    <p>functions containing BS than puzzles with innocuous</p>
    <p>functions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multilevel logistic regression. (Wald  2(2) = 20.60, p &lt; .001)</p>
    <p>Presence of blindspot had a significant effect on puzzle accuracy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>API Usage Type and Blindsposts</p>
    <p>Blindspot effect more pronounced for I/O API .(Wald  2(2) = 24.81, p &lt; .001)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cyclomatic Complexity and Blindposts</p>
    <p>Wald  2(2) = 24.81, p &lt; .001)</p>
    <p>Complexity</p>
    <p>Security accuracy in puzzles with BS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>H2a-d: Developers perceive puzzles with BS as more difficult, less clear, less familiar, and with less confidence than puzzles without BS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Developers perceptions did not differ as a function of presence of BS</p>
    <p>Multilevel modeling, all ps &gt; 0.1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>H3: Higher cognitive functioning in developers is associated with greater accuracy in solving puzzles with BS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Higher cognitive functioning did not predict higher ability in finding</p>
    <p>vulnerabilities in puzzles with BS</p>
    <p>Multilevel modeling, all ps &gt; 0.1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>H4: Higher levels of professional experience and expertise in developers are associated with greater accuracy in solving puzzles with BS.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More experience and expertise did not predict higher ability in finding</p>
    <p>vulnerabilities in puzzles with BS</p>
    <p>Multilevel modeling, all ps &gt; 0.1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>H5: Higher levels of openness and conscientiousness, and lower levels of neuroticism and agreeableness in developers are associated with greater accuracy in solving puzzles with BS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ability to detect</p>
    <p>vulnerabilities</p>
    <p>Multilevel modeling, all p &lt; 0.001 https://www.enkimd.com/big-five-personality-traits.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Developers experience blindspots while using certain API functions  Effect more pronounced for I/O APIs and complex code</p>
    <p>Characteristics NOT predicting higher ability in finding vulnerabilities:  Perceptions of code difficulty, clarity, familiarity, and</p>
    <p>confidence  Experience and expertise  Level of cognitive functioning</p>
    <p>Openness associated with developers ability in finding vulnerabilities.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Now what? Recommendations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>API Functions  Should be simple</p>
    <p>Functions should be designed assuming developers will NOT handle security issues  Especially I/O related</p>
    <p>Design of new functions should leverage developer studies</p>
    <p>Documentation of legacy functions should address blindspots</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Software Security Training and Awareness</p>
    <p>Even expert, experienced, and highly intelligent developers will experience blindspots when using APIs</p>
    <p>Perceptions and gut feelings might be misleading</p>
    <p>More reliance on diagnostics tools</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Software development process</p>
    <p>Fun ctio</p>
    <p>nali ty Security</p>
    <p>vs</p>
    <p>Functionality</p>
    <p>Security</p>
    <p>O penness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>daniela@ece.ufl.edu @dseabraoliveira</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
