<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cheul Young Park, Cori Faklaris, Siyan Zhao, Alex Sciuto, Laura Dabbish, and Jason Hong</p>
    <p>Aug. 13, 2018</p>
    <p>USENIX Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security (SOUPS 2018), Baltimore, Md., USA</p>
    <p>Share &amp; Share Alike? An Exploration of Secure Behaviors in Romantic Relationships</p>
    <p>Human-Computer Interaction Institute</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key takeaways from our study</p>
    <p>Ex: Who carries the thing you have for two-factor authentication of shared accounts?  Ex: Partner as insider threat to personal data in a breakup or domestic dispute.</p>
    <p>Household maintenance.  Trust.  Convenience.  Relationship maintenance (the novel finding of our study).</p>
    <p>Cori Faklaris - August 2018 - Carnegie Mellon University - Page 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Growing emphasis on social cybersecurity</p>
    <p>Previous studies have looked at sharing in such social contexts as households, companies, and indigenous communities.</p>
    <p>Our work is among the first to examine security behaviors in romantic relationships.</p>
    <p>Page 3</p>
    <p>Half of U.S. adults in 2016 were married,</p>
    <p>with 7% more cohabitating - Pew</p>
    <p>Research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related works in usable security research</p>
    <p>Trust &amp; convenience as drivers of sharing  Ex: Singh et al. Password sharing: implications for security design based on social</p>
    <p>practice. (CHI 2007)</p>
    <p>Taxonomy of sharing types  Ex: Matthews et al. &quot;She'll just grab any device that's closer: A Study of Everyday</p>
    <p>Device &amp; Account Sharing in Households.&quot; (CHI 2016)</p>
    <p>Social psychology lens for security behaviors  Ex: Das et al. &quot;The effect of social influence on security sensitivity.&quot; (SOUPS 2014)</p>
    <p>Intimate partner abuse  Ex: Muslukhov et al. &quot;Know your enemy: the risk of unauthorized access in</p>
    <p>smartphones by insiders.&quot; (International conference on Human-computer interaction with mobile devices and services. 2013.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research questions for our study</p>
    <p>RQ1: How do individual differences affect sharing behaviors  age, gender, income, education, relationship status, and relationship duration?</p>
    <p>RQ2: Do sharing behaviors differ with types of accounts and stages of a relationship  finance vs. entertainment accounts, early vs. late relationships?</p>
    <p>$$$ Cori Faklaris - August 2018 - Carnegie Mellon University - Page 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology: Participants recruited on MTurk</p>
    <p>We aimed to recruit workers on Amazon Mechanical Turk with</p>
    <p>an approval rating &gt;95% and  &gt;1000 tasks approved.</p>
    <p>The study was limited to  U.S. residents age 18 or older  who had ever experienced a romantic</p>
    <p>relationship for longer than one month or  had broken up less than one year ago.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology: Online questionnaire</p>
    <p>We deployed a Qualtrics survey between Aug. 30 and Sep. 6, 2017, covering these questions:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology: Data analysis</p>
    <p>Quantitative analysis to infer how demographic or relationship variables affected sharing for n=174 participants.</p>
    <p>Hypothesis 1: Those who are younger and more educated would report sharing less. Not supported.</p>
    <p>Hypothesis 2: Those who reported less income and were in a relationship or cohabiting for a longer time would report sharing more. Partly supported.</p>
    <p>Qualitative analysis to identify themes in open-ended responses to questions about sharing motivations and methods.</p>
    <p>Iterative coding of text responses conducted by 3 authors ( = 0.49-0.79).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trigger for sharing - romantic leap of faith?</p>
    <p>Statistically significant differences in account sharing were found for marital status, cohabitation status, relationship duration, and cohabitation duration, with positive effect sizes. (RQ1)</p>
    <p>Effects are more pronounced in male subgroups than females (although gender itself is not significant). (RQ1)</p>
    <p>Possibly reflecting that males traditionally are registered owners of properties used by couples?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>First comes Netflix, then comes Costco</p>
    <p>People in new relationships (&lt;7 months duration) share more entertainment accounts. (RQ2)</p>
    <p>Those in new relationships also share significantly fewer financial accounts. (RQ2)</p>
    <p>People who are in relationships that are not new (&gt;= 7 months in duration) share more jointly owned accounts. (RQ2)</p>
    <p>Proportion of accounts shared, by categories of accounts.</p>
    <p>Cori Faklaris - August 2018 - Carnegie Mellon University - Page 10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>People reported sharing accounts for reasons that fell into one of four general categories:  Convenience (63.8% of responses).  Household maintenance:</p>
    <p>Economics (60.1%).  Logistics (67.3%).</p>
    <p>Trust (45.3%).  Relationship maintenance:</p>
    <p>Relationship well-being (20.9%).  Support (5.6%).</p>
    <p>Account sharing is both functional &amp; emotional</p>
    <p>$</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Functional: Convenience, Household Maintenance</p>
    <p>These are common streaming accounts that we share. There is no need for us to have our own accounts when it comes to streaming.</p>
    <p>We have been married for 7 years so far and have 2 kids. We both need to know what we have in the accounts in order to make purchase and pay bills. It[']s important we have a working knowledge of the money we share.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Emotional: Trust, Relationship Maintenance</p>
    <p>I choose to share for utilities because I trust my partner, and believe both people should have access to them.</p>
    <p>[We share accounts] to discuss sports and see highlights of the night before. [We] use [it] for different content also.</p>
    <p>I already had a netflix account before we started dating. ... I gave her my password so she could watch when we weren't together.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Many usability challenges for couples sharing</p>
    <p>Some participants reported using less-secure practices or workarounds for accounts that didnt easily accommodate secure sharing.  Ex: The amazon account is automatically signed</p>
    <p>in. We both use it/share the Prime account to keep costs down and use our own credit cards attached to it.</p>
    <p>Some participants mentioned hiding accounts or keeping separate accounts to guard privacy or individuality, also for surprises or gifts.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alternative to 1 user-1 account architecture  We suggest designing a security architecture to support the</p>
    <p>multiple profile - 1 account model used by Netflix &amp; Hulu as a way to help romantic partners balance data intimacy and privacy.</p>
    <p>Secured Account</p>
    <p>Individual 1s data</p>
    <p>Individual 2s data</p>
    <p>Shared data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Many usability challenges for those breaking up</p>
    <p>Support easier separation and/or download of individual data that is held in shared accounts.</p>
    <p>For jointly owned accounts, incorporate programming to easily allow for the splitting of accounts when couples part ways.</p>
    <p>Help users to keep track of unauthorized usages of their accounts through such affordances as notifications and reminders.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Any questions? You can find me at</p>
    <p>Twitter: @heycori | Email: heycori @cmu.edu  Website: http://corifaklaris.com</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
