<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can Digital Face Morphs Influence Attitudes and Online Behaviors? EYAL PEER, SONAM SAMAT, AND ALESSANDRO ACQUISTI, SOUPS 2018</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Visceral targeting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From Targeted advertising to Visceral targeting  Increasingly, marketers target consumers with customized</p>
    <p>offers (targeted advertising), matching consumers to specific products or services</p>
    <p>However, explicit forms of targeting are perceived as invasive or creepy (McDonald &amp; Cranor, 2010). Consumers may even avoid ads they perceive as intrusive (White et. al., 2008)</p>
    <p>But what if individuals personal information was used in undetectable manners to customize the ad itself, and influence behavior?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Agenda  Broad: Can personal information about individuals</p>
    <p>be used in a subtle and implicit (visceral) fashion</p>
    <p>for customized, covert influence?</p>
    <p>Specific: Can digital self face morphs influence</p>
    <p>consumer behavior?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why would self face morphs work?  Face morphs: Images digitally created by combining</p>
    <p>facial pictures of different individuals  Self face morphs: morph created with a persons</p>
    <p>own face  Self face morphs are trusted more (DeBruine, 2002)  Self face morphs seem more attractive (DeBruine, 2004)  More prosocial towards self</p>
    <p>morph than identical twin morph (Bressan &amp; Zucchi, 2009)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From attitudes to behaviors  Familiar people are more persuasive (Bornstein et al., 1987; Weisbuch et al., 2003)</p>
    <p>Perceived trustworthiness increases purchase intentions (Priester &amp; Petty, 2003)</p>
    <p>Perceived attractiveness increases purchase intentions (Snyder &amp; Rothbart, 1971; Horai et al., 1974)</p>
    <p>Self face morphs &gt;&gt; Attitudes (e.g. trust)</p>
    <p>&gt;&gt; Behaviors (e.g. purchases)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach</p>
    <p>online social networks), and</p>
    <p>attitudes and behaviors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Studies 1) Study 1: Can self face morphs impact hiring/service</p>
    <p>purchase intentions?</p>
    <p>Spoiler Alert: Why did we end up with a replication study?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Design: Overview</p>
    <p>Phase IPhase I</p>
    <p>Collected participants photos</p>
    <p>Stimuli CreationStimuli Creation</p>
    <p>Created face morphs</p>
    <p>Phase IIPhase II</p>
    <p>Used face morphs to advertise a product/service, captured multiple DVs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phase 1 (Studies 1 &amp; 2) ~10K MTurk Ps asked to provide link to FB profile ~10K MTurk Ps asked to provide link to FB profile</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Stimuli creation (example)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study 1: Can selfmorphs impact hiring/purchase of services?  Online experiment with MTurk male participants (N = 188)</p>
    <p>Morphs based on publicly available Facebook photos</p>
    <p>Focus: Choosing and hiring a private music instructor online</p>
    <p>Primary DV: Hiring/service purchase intentions</p>
    <p>Secondary DVs: Other measures traditionally captured in face</p>
    <p>morph studies (e.g. perceived trustworthiness)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study 1: Design  Participants asked to imagine looking to hire an instructor to learn how to play an instrument of their choosing</p>
    <p>Shown two images of private instructors found in online searches</p>
    <p>Instructors reported to have similar experience and rates</p>
    <p>Participants asked to indicate which instructor they would personally choose to hire</p>
    <p>One of the instructors images was a self-morph (self photo + randomly selected stock photo), while the other was a morph of two unfamiliar persons (other participants photo + randomly selected stock photo)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study 1: Results</p>
    <p>Mean (SD)</p>
    <p>t Cohen's dDV Other Self p</p>
    <p>Trustworthy 5.07(1) 5.01(1.1) 0.47 0.64 0.09</p>
    <p>Attractive 5.44(1) 5.35(1.1) 0.93 0.36 0.17</p>
    <p>Knowledgeable 4.32(1.3) 4.55(1.2) 1.74 0.09 0.32</p>
    <p>Like 4.81(1) 4.70(1) 1.12 0.27 0.21</p>
    <p>Identify 4.12(1.3) 4.14(1.3) 0.18 0.86 0.03</p>
    <p>Similar 4.28(1.2) 4.19(1.3) 0.65 0.52 0.12</p>
    <p>Overall judgments* 4.66 (0.8) 4.67 (0.8) 0.21 0.83 0.04</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study 2: Can selfmorphs impact selfdisclosure?  Online experiment with female MTurk participants (N = 310)</p>
    <p>Morphs based on publicly available Facebook photos</p>
    <p>Focus: Willingness to disclose personal and sensitive information to a therapist presented as self-morph or control morph</p>
    <p>Primary DV: Affirmative Admission Rate (AAR) (John, Acquisti, and Loewenstein 2014)</p>
    <p>Secondary DVs: Other measures traditionally captured in face morph studies (e.g. perceived trustworthiness)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study 2: Results</p>
    <p>Mean (SD)</p>
    <p>t Cohen's dDV Other Self p Trustworthy 5.29(1.1) 5.25(1.2) 0.30 0.76 0.03 Attractive 5.27(1.2) 5.28(1.1) -0.10 0.92 -0.01 Knowledgeable 4.81(1.2) 4.69(1.1) 0.89 0.37 0.10 Like 5.28(1.2) 5.11(1.1) 1.31 0.19 0.15 Good 5.22(1.2) 5.04(1.3) 1.29 0.20 0.15 Identify 4.10(1.4) 4.10(1.4) -0.05 0.96 -0.01 Similar 4.20(1.3) 4.10(1.4) 0.61 0.54 0.07 Overall judgments* 4.88 (0.9) 4.80 (0.9) 0.77 0.44 0.09</p>
    <p>No statistically significant differences in AAR between self vs. other conditions (M = 2.91 vs. 3.08, p = 0.346)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study 3: Large Scale Replication  Lab experiment  Participants recruited via CBDR experiments list and CMU Data Truck</p>
    <p>Male and female participants (N = 495)</p>
    <p>Morphs based on high quality lab photos</p>
    <p>Focus: Replication (Study on images)</p>
    <p>DVs: Perceived trustworthiness (and other measures traditionally captured in morph studies)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study 3: Results</p>
    <p>Mean</p>
    <p>t Cohens dDV Other Self p Trustworthy 4.46 (1.2) 4.59 (1.2) 1.202 0.23 0.11</p>
    <p>Attractive 4.16 (1.3) 4.22 (1.4) 0.457 0.65 0.04</p>
    <p>Knowledgeable 4.40 (1.0) 4.46 (1) 0.650 0.52 0.06</p>
    <p>Like 3.96 (1.2) 4.17 (1.3) 1.972 0.05 0.18</p>
    <p>Identify 3.16 (1.4) 3.26 (1.5) 0.804 0.42 0.07</p>
    <p>Similar 3.41 (1.5) 3.51 (1.4) 0.835 0.41 0.08</p>
    <p>Overall judgments* 3.92 (1.0) 4.03 (1.0) 1.279 0.20 0.12</p>
    <p>No statistically significant differences between self vs. other conditions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why failed replication?</p>
    <p>Gender effects?</p>
    <p>Quality of images?</p>
    <p>Morphing procedure?</p>
    <p>Sample size?</p>
    <p>Choice of DVs?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings (and Implications) Self face morphs did not seem to affect attitudes or behaviors in our studies</p>
    <p>Research implication: Face morphs effects currently reported in the literature may be quite sensitive to experimental conditions, and possibly not robust</p>
    <p>Policy implication: Nevertheless, this research attempts to bring a potential form of visceral nudge to the attention of policy makers and the public</p>
    <p>Open question: Can the industry, with more resources and stronger incentives, find ways to use these (or other related) forms of visceral influence to secretly affect individuals behavior?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sometimes child abuse is only visible to the child</p>
    <p>suffering it</p>
    <p>If somebody hurts you, phone us and well help you</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you! Questions?</p>
    <p>This work was supported by NSF Grant Award Number 1012763 and NSF Grant Award Number 1327992</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
