<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Effectiveness of Fear Appeals in Increasing Smartphone Locking Behavior among Saudi Arabians</p>
    <p>College of Computing and Informatics Elham Al Qahtani Mohamed Shehab</p>
    <p>Abrar Aljohani</p>
    <p>Fourteenth Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security AUGUST 1214, 2018 BALTIMORE, MD, USA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>video designs customized for the Saudi population.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Motivation  Methodology  Evaluation  Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Smartphone Usage in Saudi  Saudi Arabia ranked</p>
    <p>third in the world for smartphone use [1]</p>
    <p>Saudi Arabia has 81% Mobile Banking penetration [2]</p>
    <p>[1] Saudi Arabia ranks 3rd globally for smartphone use http://www.arabnews.com/node/1075126/corporate-news [2] Consultancy.uk, https://bit.ly/2NPW8Qj</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Smartphone Usage in Saudi  Saudi Arabia ranked</p>
    <p>third in the world [1]</p>
    <p>Saudi Arabia has 81% Mobile Banking penetration [2]</p>
    <p>[1] Saudi Arabia ranks 3rd globally for smartphone use http://www.arabnews.com/node/1075126/corporate-news [2] Consultancy.uk, https://bit.ly/2NPW8Qj</p>
    <p>Emerging Asia</p>
    <p>Developed Asia</p>
    <p>UAE</p>
    <p>KSA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cybersecurity in Saudi Arabia  58% of Saudi population has experienced different forms</p>
    <p>of online cybercrime [3]</p>
    <p>One in four users had a mobile device stolen, potentially exposing sensitive information to cyber thieves [3]</p>
    <p>[3] Cybercrime hit 6.5m in kingdom last year. http: //www.arabnews.com/node/967966/saudi- arabia</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Study Saudi Arabia?  Lack of awareness of security behind users</p>
    <p>insecure behavior [4]</p>
    <p>The increase of online cybercrime in Saudi Arabia  Our study investigates the efficiency of</p>
    <p>communicating risk to the Saudi population by using different fear appeal videos</p>
    <p>[4] A. Alzahrani and K. Alomar. Information security issues and threats in Saudi Arabia: A research survey. International Journal of Computer Science Issues (IJCSI), 13(6):129, 2016</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fear Appeal  Fear Appeal: it is a persuasive message that describes the</p>
    <p>seriousness of the risks to motivate users to cope with recommended behavior</p>
    <p>Protection Motivation Theory:  Perceived severity</p>
    <p>(How serious a user rates a threat)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fear Appeal  Fear Appeal: it is a persuasive message that describes the</p>
    <p>seriousness of the risks to motivate users to cope with recommended behavior</p>
    <p>Protection Motivation Theory:  Perceived severity  Perceived vulnerability</p>
    <p>(A user feels susceptible to the threat)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fear Appeal  Fear Appeal: it is a persuasive message that describes the</p>
    <p>seriousness of the risks to motivate users to cope with recommended behavior</p>
    <p>Protection Motivation Theory:  Perceived severity  Perceived vulnerability  Self-efficacy</p>
    <p>(A confidence about performing the recommended action)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fear Appeal  Fear Appeal: it is a persuasive message that describes the</p>
    <p>seriousness of the risks to motivate users to cope with recommended behavior</p>
    <p>Protection Motivation Theory:  Perceived severity  Perceived vulnerability  Self-efficacy  Response efficacy</p>
    <p>(A users belief about taking the recommended action)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Replication Study  The original study (SOUPS 17) by Albayram et al. [5]  Effectiveness of risk communication for changing users</p>
    <p>risky behavior, rather than annoyance  A fear appeal video design  Amazons Mechanical Turk in USA</p>
    <p>[5] Y. Albayram, M. M. H. Khan, T. Jensen, and N. Nguyen. ... better to use a lock screen than to worry about saving a few seconds of time: Effect of fear appeal in the context of smartphone locking behavior. In Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security (SOUPS), 2017</p>
    <p>Groups Locked Screen</p>
    <p>Control group (No Video) 21%</p>
    <p>Treatment group (Video) 50%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conducting Similar Study in SA  Challenges</p>
    <p>Cultural and language Barrier  Social and relevance Barrier  In addition to IRB approval, we needed approval</p>
    <p>from the Saudi Government</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Motivation  Methodology  Evaluation  Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Groups  Control: No video  Original: The same video in the original study  Dubbed: The original video with Arabic dubbing  Subtitled: The original video with Arabic captions  Customized: A customized video for Saudis</p>
    <p>A frame from the original video</p>
    <p>A frame from the dubbed video</p>
    <p>A frame from the subtitled video</p>
    <p>A frame from the customized video</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Designing the Customized Video  The effectiveness of video media on communicating fear</p>
    <p>appeal to the Saudi population  The customization focuses on the following aspects</p>
    <p>Customized video</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Designing the Customized Video  Relevant Risks and Fears</p>
    <p>Risks and fears that are related to the target audience  A victim is being blackmailed via stored personal media in WhatsApp  The risks of reputation damage specially in a conservative society  A victims bank information was stolen by sending a 2FA code and</p>
    <p>accessing the bank password and username.</p>
    <p>Stolen bank information scenario from the customized video</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Designing the Customized Video  Relevant applications and attributes</p>
    <p>Information related to the top-ranking applications among Saudis</p>
    <p>For example: WhatsApp and ALRajhiBank rather than those used in the original video, such as PayPal, Netflix, and Bank of America app.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Designing the Customized Video  Cultural</p>
    <p>The video dialog used culturally relevant vocabulary delivered in Arabic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hypotheses  The customized group will have higher ratings for:</p>
    <p>Perceived sensitive data  Concerns about their smartphones security and</p>
    <p>privacy  Perceived severity and risk awareness  Response efficacy  Number of participants who enabled a screen lock</p>
    <p>The customized group will have lower ratings for:  Perceived response cost than other groups</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Design  We interviewed 200 Saudi participants (In-person study)</p>
    <p>&gt; 18 years old  No screen locking mechanism on their phone  Assigned randomly to one of the five groups</p>
    <p>The participants were recruited through flyers and faceto-face recruitment</p>
    <p>We collected participants cell phone numbers to follow up after the initial interview</p>
    <p>Same questions of the original study but in Arabic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Motivation  Methodology  Evaluation  Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>First Section of the Main Study  Participants Background  Smartphone usage behavior questions  Online security behavior questions  Initial reasons for not using a screen lock  Their opinions about people who use a lock</p>
    <p>screen on their smartphone</p>
    <p>No Significant Difference</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>First Section of the Main Study  Participants Background  Smartphone usage behavior questions  Online security behavior questions  Initial reasons for not using a screen</p>
    <p>lock  Their opinions about people who use a</p>
    <p>lock screen on their smartphone Mental burden</p>
    <p>No risk</p>
    <p>Nothing to hide</p>
    <p>Annoying to use</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>First Section of the Main Study  Participants Background  Smartphone usage behavior questions  Online security behavior questions  Initial reasons for not using a screen lock  Their opinions about people who use a</p>
    <p>lock screen on their smartphone</p>
    <p>Maybe they have bad photos on</p>
    <p>their phones and misfortunes to</p>
    <p>hide from others</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Second Section of the Main Study  Video evaluation for treatment groups  Persuasion, believability and effectiveness</p>
    <p>for each video  What are the aspects of the video they</p>
    <p>liked and did not like</p>
    <p>Original Subtitled Dubbed Customized</p>
    <p>Persuasion 17.5% 35% 72.5% 87.5%</p>
    <p>Believability 10% 47.5% 72% 90%</p>
    <p>Effectiveness 15% 40% 82.5% 92.5%</p>
    <p>Rating for each video</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Third Section of the Main Study  The value of stored data on their</p>
    <p>smartphone  Their concerns on Security and Privacy  The possibility of losing their smartphone or</p>
    <p>someone access it  The cost of using the screen lock if it is an</p>
    <p>inconvenience or hard to remember  Their confidence in performing the</p>
    <p>recommended behavior</p>
    <p>We found significant differences for all questions at p  .001 by performing the Kruskal-Wallis test and post hoc multiple</p>
    <p>comparison</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Follow-Up A week after the initial interview, we called participants to ask them  If they have enabled the screen lock or not  What was their motivation behind their</p>
    <p>decision  Significant difference(H(4) = 39.46, p  .001)</p>
    <p>Control Original Subtitled Dubbed Customized</p>
    <p>Percentages for participants who enabled the screen lock</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reasons Behind Their Decision  The highest-ranking reason for not</p>
    <p>enabling the screen lock changed to  Forgettable/Mental burden (28.9%)</p>
    <p>The highest reason for their motivation  The control group: the questionnaire  The treatment groups: the video</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reasons Behind Their Decision  Enabled:</p>
    <p>Not enabled:</p>
    <p>Previously, I saw no risk from not locking</p>
    <p>the screen because my mobile was with</p>
    <p>me all the time, but after watching the</p>
    <p>video I learned a lot</p>
    <p>I and my family use my phone as a</p>
    <p>personal hotspot for sharing Internet data,</p>
    <p>and it is annoying to put a screen lock on,</p>
    <p>especially when someone who trusts you</p>
    <p>shares your phone</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Motivation  Methodology  Evaluation  Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>Responses from the original group were very close to the control group</p>
    <p>Original video was only minimally effective in changing Saudis locking behavior</p>
    <p>Subtitled video was effective in a simple proportion</p>
    <p>Dubbed video had the second highest level impact Customized video had the most effect on participants perceptions</p>
    <p>Control</p>
    <p>Original</p>
    <p>Subtitled</p>
    <p>Dubbed</p>
    <p>Customized</p>
    <p>Enabled the screen lock</p>
    <p>Level of effectiveness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you</p>
    <p>Questions ?? Contact me at:</p>
    <p>ealqahta@uncc.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
