<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Comparative Usability Study of Key Management in Secure Email</p>
    <p>Scott Ruoti Jeff Andersen, Tyler Monson, Daniel Zappala, Kent Seamons</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  How does an IBE-based email system fare</p>
    <p>against a well implemented PGP-based email system?</p>
    <p>Two outcomes  Research results  A research platform</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MESSAGEGUARD: A RESEARCH PLATFORM FOR SECURING THE WEB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Web  Much of todays software is on</p>
    <p>the Web  Strong push for moving</p>
    <p>desktop software to the cloud  Software-as-a-Service (SaaS)</p>
    <p>Pros  Cheap  Scalable  Resilient</p>
    <p>Cons  Limited ability to configure  No control of own data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MessageGuard  Retrofit websites/SaaS</p>
    <p>products to add security  Add end-to-end encryption  Verify signatures of content</p>
    <p>Does not require cooperation by the website/SaaS product</p>
    <p>Strong isolation from the underlying application</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Overlays  Replace portions of the</p>
    <p>interface with overlays  iFrame</p>
    <p>Author and view secure content in the overlay</p>
    <p>Visually seamless</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Platform Framework  Easy-to-modify</p>
    <p>Pluggable  Universal</p>
    <p>Most websites  Desktop and mobile</p>
    <p>Fast</p>
    <p>Benefits  Accelerate the creation of</p>
    <p>functional prototypes  Simplifies creating prototypes</p>
    <p>for A/B testing  Provides an easy way to</p>
    <p>share research results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Systems  Private Facebook Chat</p>
    <p>Robinson et al., 2012  Pwm 2.0</p>
    <p>Ruoti et al., 2016  Short-lived keys</p>
    <p>Monson et al., 2018  This work</p>
    <p>Ruoti et al. Private Webmail 2.0: Simple and Easy-to-Use Secure Email. UIST 2016. Monson et al. A Usability Study of Secure Email Deletion. EuroUSEC 2018.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Opportunities  Security researchers</p>
    <p>Easily conduct usability studies  Key management  Messaging protocols</p>
    <p>Usability researchers  Test fully-implemented systems  Trustworthy interfaces  Avoiding mistakes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Available now at https://messageguard.io</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>COMPARING KEY MANAGEMENT IN SECURE EMAIL</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IBE vs. PGP  IBE consistently</p>
    <p>outperforms PGP  Reasons to questions</p>
    <p>this gap  Poorly designed PGP</p>
    <p>systems  Emergence of public key</p>
    <p>directories (PKD)  Prior work is insufficient</p>
    <p>to answer this question</p>
    <p>Escrow vs.</p>
    <p>Key Directory</p>
    <p>AliceBob</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Design  Use MessageGuard to create email prototypes</p>
    <p>that differ only in key management  IBE, PKD, and Passwords</p>
    <p>Leverage standard metrics  Use a two-person study methodology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two-Person Methodology  Two roles</p>
    <p>Johnnyinitiator  Janeinitiated</p>
    <p>Simple task  Helping with taxes</p>
    <p>Within-subject</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demographics  94 total participants</p>
    <p>Largest secure email study  50/50 gender split  Most were undergraduate students</p>
    <p>Attempted to recruit non-students, but failed  Not all were from our university</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ResultsPerceived Usasbility  IBE and PKD</p>
    <p>performed similarly  Passwords</p>
    <p>performed the worst  MessageGuard</p>
    <p>based systems outperformed other similar systems</p>
    <p>PKDPublic Key Directory Ruoti et al. Private Webmail 2.0: Simple and Easy-to-Use Secure Email. UIST 2016.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ResultsTime</p>
    <p>Passwords</p>
    <p>IBE</p>
    <p>PKD</p>
    <p>Stage 1</p>
    <p>Stage 2</p>
    <p>No difference in overall time  PKD takes longer to send</p>
    <p>first encrypted email  I am more motivated (i.e., I</p>
    <p>can more readily see the need) to install the app if the encrypted message is already sitting there in my inbox. Also, the fewer emails I have to send/receive the better.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ResultsOther  Understanding</p>
    <p>IBE and PKD performed poorly</p>
    <p>Passwords were intuitive  Favorite System</p>
    <p>Split between the three  Changed with understanding</p>
    <p>Passwords  Why not just use the out-of</p>
    <p>band channel for communication?</p>
    <p>It was way lame that I had to call him because I might as well have just given him the info that way. . . . If I'm gonna communicate with them through email, it's because I want to do it through email, not through a phone call.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations  Impossible to remove all confounding factors  Laboratory study  Focused on first-time use  Non-representative demographic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SUMMARY</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary  MessageGuard is a research platform for</p>
    <p>securing the Web and SaaS  Many interesting research questions to be explored</p>
    <p>Compared the usability of key management in secure email  Gap between IBE and PKD is minimal</p>
    <p>Data and code available at https://messageguard.io/</p>
    <p>IBEIdentity-Based Encryption PKDPublic Key Directory</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
