<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Action Needed! Helping Users Find and Complete the Authentication Ceremony in Signal</p>
    <p>Elham Vaziripour, Justin Wu, Mark ONeill, Daniel Metro, Josh Cockrell, Timothy Moffett, Jordan Whitehead, Nick Bonner, Kent Seamons, Daniel Zappala</p>
    <p>Brigham Young University</p>
    <p>Internet Research Lab</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Importance of Secure Messaging</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>End-to-End Encryption is a Solution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Verify the Identity Key</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Verify the Identity Key</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Last year at SOUPS...</p>
    <p>Users have a hard time finding and completing the authentication ceremony without</p>
    <p>instruction</p>
    <p>14% success rate with no instruction  78% success rate with instruction</p>
    <p>It takes too long to complete the ceremony even with instruction</p>
    <p>7 minutes, average time to find  11 minutes , average time to complete</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How Can We Help People To Quickly Find and Use the Authentication Ceremony in Secure Messaging Applications, Without Instruction?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach</p>
    <p>Opinionated design: Make more decisions and leave fewer options (1)  Encourage the user to be security minded</p>
    <p>Nudges (2)  Monetary incentive</p>
    <p>Comprehension and adherence. In Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), pages 28932902. ACM, 2015.</p>
    <p>Nudges for privacy and security: Understanding and assisting users choices online. ACM Computing Surveys (CSUR), 50(3):44,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach</p>
    <p>Follow design principles from Schroder et al. - EuroUSEC 2016</p>
    <p>(1) Awareness of the security status of conversations</p>
    <p>(2) Comprehensible instructions for recommended actions</p>
    <p>(3) Clear risk communication</p>
    <p>(4) Easily accessible verification</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Original Signal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current path to find and use the authentication ceremony in Signal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current path to find and use the authentication ceremony in Signal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current path to find and use the authentication ceremony in Signal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current path to find and use the authentication ceremony in Signal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modification 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modification 1</p>
    <p>(1) Awareness of security status</p>
    <p>(4) Easily accessible verification</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modification 1</p>
    <p>(1) Awareness of security status (4) Easily accessible verification</p>
    <p>(3) Comprehensible instructions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modification 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modification 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modification 2</p>
    <p>(3) Comprehensible instruction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modification 2 (Over a phone call)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modification 2 (In person)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lab User Studies to Evaluate the Modifications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Participants signed up in pairs (30 pairs total)  Versions cycled through in round robin manner  10 pairs for each version  During the study:</p>
    <p>One participant was told to send a credit card to the other  Participants were given $7 with a $3 bonus to make sure the credit</p>
    <p>card number is transferred safely</p>
    <p>Afterward, they filled out a survey and were asked questions about their comprehension</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Find and Complete Ceremony</p>
    <p>Completion Rate (Self-Reported)</p>
    <p>Found (Coordinator-Reported)</p>
    <p>Completion Rate (Coordinator-Reported)</p>
    <p>Original Signal 50% 25% 0%</p>
    <p>Modification 1 90% 100% 30%</p>
    <p>Modification 2 60% 95% 90%</p>
    <p>Half of the participants who used the original Signal, and the majority of participants who used the modified versions, believed that they completed</p>
    <p>the task safely</p>
    <p>Original: none successfully performed the authentication ceremony  Modification 1: majority clicked the toggle before verification</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Confusion Regarding the Original Authentication Ceremony</p>
    <p>I was a little confused at first and I wondered if we needed to be in the same room to scan the QR code to make sure our conversation was secure. At the bottom it just asked if I could switch the conversation to verified and so I did.</p>
    <p>I hit [the button] and then I was like, well that did nothing and so I hit it again and nothing happened...I hit verify and then it says that I just unhit it immediately afterwards...I was just like, verify what? What am I verifying? It didnt really tell me...Honestly it meant nothing.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>No Need for Instructions</p>
    <p>Prior Study WhatsApp Facebook Msgr (with instruction)</p>
    <p>Viber (with instruction)</p>
    <p>This Study Modification 1 (without instruction)</p>
    <p>Modification 2 (without instruction)</p>
    <p>Completion Rate 30% 70% 90%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Result: Timing</p>
    <p>Modification 1: time to locate ceremony drops to under a minute  Modification 2, time to complete the task drops in half  Between modification 2 and the previous study, time drops from 11 to</p>
    <p>Application Time to Find the Authentication Ceremony Completion Time</p>
    <p>Original 3.5 N/A</p>
    <p>Modification 1 &lt; 1 7</p>
    <p>Modification 2 &lt; 1 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Authentication using a Phone Call</p>
    <p>I liked that it came up on the middle of the phone call screen rather than being sent through a text message that I would have to pull up during the conversation. There were a lot of numbers, which could be hard to keep track of if you were reading them over the phone, but the amount of numbers ensures greater safety.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Result: Comprehension</p>
    <p>Participants were asked about the purpose of the authentication</p>
    <p>ceremony</p>
    <p>Even though some expressed understanding of authentication</p>
    <p>and confidentiality, many of these</p>
    <p>participants were still unsure of</p>
    <p>their answers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Result: Adoption</p>
    <p>Am I willing? Yes. Will I? No. Because here is the thing, I dont really care if my messages get intercepted because most of the time I am not sending my credit card number or social security numbers. Will I use it for things that are really important? For sure.</p>
    <p>Yes: 32  No: 4  For confidential information: 14  Certain contacts: 6</p>
    <p>Are you willing to use the authentication ceremony before you exchange messages</p>
    <p>with a friend the first time?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Finding and completing the authentication ceremony improves  Using opinionated design  Using nudges  Apply design principle  Encourage to be security minded</p>
    <p>Improvement made with no instructions  Time to find and complete the ceremony is significantly shorter</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Improve risk communication  Determine the importance of comprehension  Encourage people to be security-minded without monetary incentive  Apply lessons learned to attack scenarios  Find ways to automate the authentication ceremony</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
