<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>KOMPETENZZENTRUM FR ANGEWANDTE SICHERHEITSTECHNOLOGIE (KASTEL) FORSCHUNGSGRUPPE SECURITY  USABILITY  SOCIETY (SECUSO)</p>
    <p>www.kit.eduKIT  Die Forschungsuniversitt in der Helmholtz-Gemeinschaft</p>
    <p>Replication Study: A Cross-Country Field Observation Study of Real World PIN Usage at ATMs and in Various Electronic Payment Scenarios</p>
    <p>Towards Understanding Why People Do, or Do Not, Shield PIN Entry</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Replication Study: A Cross-Country Field Observation Study of Real World PIN Usage at ATMs and in Various Electronic Payment Scenarios</p>
    <p>What is this talk about?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Replication Study: A Cross-Country Field Observation Study of Real World PIN Usage at ATMs and in Various Electronic Payment Scenarios</p>
    <p>What is this talk about?</p>
    <p>SOUPS 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Replication Study: A Cross-Country Field Observation Study of Real World PIN Usage at ATMs and in Various Electronic Payment Scenarios</p>
    <p>What is this talk about?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Replication Study: A Cross-Country Field Observation Study of Real World PIN Usage at ATMs and in Various Electronic Payment Scenarios</p>
    <p>What is this talk about?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Replication Study: A Cross-Country Field Observation Study of Real World PIN Usage at ATMs and in Various Electronic Payment Scenarios</p>
    <p>What is this talk about?</p>
    <p>Towards Understanding Why People Do, or Do Not, Shield PIN Entry</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Field Observations</p>
    <p>SOUPS 2018 Talk by Research Group Security  Usability  Society (SECUSO)29.08.18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A variety of ATM / payment scenarios</p>
    <p>Each location was visited at least twice during different time periods</p>
    <p>Locations enabling non-intrusive observations</p>
    <p>Observation sessions were not prolonged</p>
    <p>Methodology  Observation Locations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Factors Country</p>
    <p>Scenario: Withdrawing vs. Paying</p>
    <p>Whether accompanied by other people (or not)</p>
    <p>Dependent Variable: Shielded (or not)</p>
    <p>Methodology  Study Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Study Factors Country Scenario: Withdrawing vs. Paying Whether accompanied by other people (or not)</p>
    <p>Dependent Variable: Shielded (or not)</p>
    <p>Notes taken in written form by one researcher Only those observations counted in which the observer was 100% sure</p>
    <p>Methodology  Study Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Payment: 34% Germany, 14% U.K., 0% Sweden ATMs</p>
    <p>Our results: 39% Germany, 29% U.K, 29% Sweden DeLuca et al.: 23%  no significant difference</p>
    <p>Regression Model and Post-hoc ANOVA comparison Country</p>
    <p>In Germany significantly more people shield compared to U.K. and Sweden For payment: In the U.K. significant more people shield compared to Sweden</p>
    <p>Scenario Germany: No significant difference between withdrawal and payment U.K. &amp; Sweden: Significant fewer people shield in payment scenarios</p>
    <p>Being accompanied or not Our results: No significant differences</p>
    <p>Findings for PIN shielding</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Follow-Up Interviews</p>
    <p>SOUPS 2018 Talk by Research Group Security  Usability  Society (SECUSO)29.08.18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Public interviews Not those that were observed / different places / same cities Interviews either in English or German Notes were taken in written form</p>
    <p>Procedure Asking for availability and consent Asked to be frank and honest Card usage to pay when paying / withdrawing Questions about when and how they / others shield Questions about why they think there is a difference between ATM/payment</p>
    <p>Methodology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presence of hard cash during withdrawals / different goals ATM environements considered more risky</p>
    <p>...at an ATM anyone could stand behind you. But people in a supermarket are there to buy something Youre not supposed to get robbed in stores Not something you usually think about in a store</p>
    <p>Lack of understanding of the actual attack scenarios: People versus cameras Habituation</p>
    <p>Payment happens so often (Sweden, the U.K.)  as fast as possible Actually according to the Statistical Office of the European Union payment with PIN happens 5 times more often in the U.K. compared to Germany and seven times more often in Sweden compared to Germany</p>
    <p>Lack of reminders to shield with payment scenarios</p>
    <p>Possible Explanations from Interviews: Payment versus ATM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations &amp; Conclusion</p>
    <p>SOUPS 2018 Talk by Research Group Security  Usability  Society (SECUSO)29.08.18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proper shields need to be provided</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proper shields need to be provided</p>
    <p>Just-in-time reminders</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proper shields need to be provided</p>
    <p>Just-in-time reminders</p>
    <p>Raising awareness in particular for the payment scenarios</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Field observation Observer objectivity More scenarios as we could observe</p>
    <p>Interviews Explanations provided by our interviewees were not directly provided by the observed subjects People may have falsely represented their usual PIN related actions during interviews</p>
    <p>Limitations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Replication Study: A Cross-Country Field Observation Study of Real World PIN Usage at ATMs and in Various Electronic Payment Scenarios</p>
    <p>Thanks! Questions?</p>
    <p>Habituation, lack of reminders, presence of hard cash, different goals, lack of understanding of the actual attack scenarios</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We got clearance from the ethics commision/IRB and legal teams</p>
    <p>Acquiring consent Would have influenced the measurement Muphy and Dingwall (2007): if people are in the public space they give implicit consent to be seen</p>
    <p>Deception Not really an issue: covert non-participant</p>
    <p>Privacy PIN entry is sensitive action All locations were chosen so the observer could not see the entered PIN</p>
    <p>Anonymity We did not collect any personal data on the observed subjects</p>
    <p>Ethical Considerations</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
