<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More than Smart Speakers: Security and Privacy Perceptions of Smart Home Personal Assistants</p>
    <p>Presenter: Noura Abdi| PhD student| noura.abdi@kcl.ac.uk</p>
    <p>Authored by:</p>
    <p>Noura Abdi- Department of Informatics, Kings College London</p>
    <p>Kopo Marvin Ramokapane- Bristol Cyber Security Group, University of Bristol</p>
    <p>Jose M. Such- Department of Informatics, Kings College London</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adoption of Smart Home Personal Assistants - SPAs</p>
    <p>Its estimated that 10% of global consumers own a smart home personal assistant</p>
    <p>Amazon Echo and Google Home are the most used SPAs.</p>
    <p>2018 (Q1): 3.2M Google Home and 2.5M Amazon Echo</p>
    <p>In the future, its estimated more users will adopt into using smart home personal assistants such as the ones we study.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>41% of voice assistant users</p>
    <p>have concerns about trust</p>
    <p>and privacy Forbes</p>
    <p>More homes are</p>
    <p>becoming smart</p>
    <p>increasing security and</p>
    <p>privacy risks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Not just SMART SPEAKERS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Smart Home Personal Assistant (SPA) Eco-system</p>
    <p>Smart Speaker (Amazon Echo, Google</p>
    <p>Home)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions  We investigate users understanding of the SPA eco-system (Data</p>
    <p>processing, sharing, storing and learning)</p>
    <p>Users particular lack of trust for one feature: shopping</p>
    <p>Identify SPA threats</p>
    <p>Discuss the coping strategies users implement to deal with threats</p>
    <p>We present design implications for better security and privacy mechanisms for SPAs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Screening Pilot Study Interviews Analysis</p>
    <p>We conducted semi-structured interviews with current SPA users until saturation was reached.</p>
    <p>Recruitment through Prolific and internally at KCL</p>
    <p>We conducted 5 pre-interviews to refine the script (not used during the analysis)</p>
    <p>We further interviewed 17 Amazon Echo and Google Home users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Analysis</p>
    <p>We analysed data following grounded theory method.</p>
    <p>Identifying patterns and relationships between the</p>
    <p>codes.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Usage Scenarios</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings</p>
    <p>Users setup experience</p>
    <p>What are users perceptions regarding SPA eco-system</p>
    <p>Users reasons for not trusting shopping</p>
    <p>SPA threats and coping strategies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SPA setup USERS USED AN EXISTING PERSONAL ACCOUNT TO SETUP</p>
    <p>THEIR SPA.</p>
    <p>SPA HAS ACCESS TO THEIR PERSONAL</p>
    <p>INFORMATION SUCH AS CALENDAR, ADDRESS,</p>
    <p>BANK DETAILS ETC.</p>
    <p>ONLY 2 OUT OF 10 AMAZON USERS</p>
    <p>REPORTED COMPLETING VOICE RECOGNITION SETUP WHILE ALL GOOGLE HOME USERS HAVE COMPLETED THIS..</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perceptions of SPA eco-system</p>
    <p>Data limited to the SPA provider only [data processing, data storing and data sharing].</p>
    <p>They perceive that their SPA does everything without considering the full eco-system.</p>
    <p>SPA is capable to learn personal information about users such as their usage patterns, routines.</p>
    <p>Overall SPA users have incomplete mental models of their SPA eco-system.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perceptions of SPA eco-system: Processing</p>
    <p>Data processed locally in the device</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perceptions of SPA eco-system: Storage</p>
    <p>Data stored includes, voice recordings, requests and history logs and shopping.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perceptions of SPA eco-system: Sharing</p>
    <p>Participants mental models about data sharing with other third-parties are</p>
    <p>influenced by stories of data misuse in other domains.</p>
    <p>No participant using third-party skills (uber) or smart devices (Philipps bulbs)</p>
    <p>mentioned data being accessible by them (Uber of Phillips), let alone with</p>
    <p>whom they might share the data they gather.</p>
    <p>Data Sharing.. P3 so data brokers they would try</p>
    <p>and influence users purchasing decisions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perceptions of SPA eco-system: Learning</p>
    <p>Users describe SPAs as a small brain and having a memory with AI</p>
    <p>Capable of learning things about the user i.e. shopping habits, routines, favourite music etc.</p>
    <p>SPA use what they learn about the user: serve them well, recommend things, tailor adds.</p>
    <p>Overall users have a mixed attitude towards learning.  Positive as it could simplify their life e.g. morning routines , favourite music, news updates  Negative e.g. being scary and sinister, not pleasant for sensitive things like health symptoms.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Shopping concerns</p>
    <p>Lack of product visibility i.e.</p>
    <p>buying wrong products</p>
    <p>Insecure connection</p>
    <p>including Payment</p>
    <p>People hearing orders and/or</p>
    <p>code</p>
    <p>Number and Trustworthiness</p>
    <p>of vendors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Threats Model</p>
    <p>Users concerns in using their devices:</p>
    <p>Threat Agents: Hackers, government and data brokers.</p>
    <p>Threat Types: Unwanted listening, network attacks such as hijacking.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Coping Strategies</p>
    <p>Coping Strategies</p>
    <p>Disable certain features</p>
    <p>Turn off or mute device</p>
    <p>Unable to protect</p>
    <p>themselves</p>
    <p>Use other devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Better awareness and transparency mechanisms for SPAs</p>
    <p>Usable Control Mechanisms for SPA:</p>
    <p>Personalized intelligent mechanisms</p>
    <p>Voice recognition</p>
    <p>Implications/ Future</p>
    <p>Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Shopping To increase users trust in shopping:</p>
    <p>Provide more information about the products and vendors</p>
    <p>Verbal information and exploring other modalities</p>
    <p>Voice recognition as initial setup for Amazon Echo to avoid repeating voice code when purchasing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you</p>
    <p>noura.abdi@kcl.ac.uk</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
