<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Typology of Perceived Triggers for End-User Security and Privacy Behaviors</p>
    <p>Sauvik Das, Georgia Tech Laura Dabbish, Carnegie Mellon University Jason Hong, Carnegie Mellon University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenge: Bridging the expert/end-user gap</p>
    <p>&lt;10% of Google account holders use two-factor (Milka, 2018)</p>
    <p>Img source: https://www.clinicalleader.com/2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Behavior Change Model (Fogg, 2009)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation and ability are better understood</p>
    <p>Security measures can block users goals in the moment (Dourish et al 2004, Sasse 2003)  Example: 2 factor delaying email</p>
    <p>access</p>
    <p>People dont believe they are at risk (Adams &amp; Sasse, 1999; Wash 2010)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation and ability are better understood</p>
    <p>People lack awareness of relevant threats and protection measures (Adams &amp; Sasse, 1999, Ion et al., 2005)</p>
    <p>People lack knowledge to use current tools (Norman &amp; Draper, ; Wash, 2010; Pew, 2017)  Example: URLs or email headers</p>
    <p>(Dhamija et al. 2006) 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theres less work on behavioral triggers</p>
    <p>Warning design has improved but they are just one trigger (Akhawe &amp; Felt, 2005; Bravo-Lillo et al 2013; )</p>
    <p>Some qualitative work describes momentary triggers (Das, Kim, Dabbish &amp; Hong, 2014; Das, Kramer, Dabbish &amp; Hong, 2014; Rader, Wash Brooks, 2012; Redmiles et al, 2016)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How are triggers associated with behavior?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Triggers for security &amp; privacy behaviors</p>
    <p>Synthesized from (Das, Kim, Dabbish &amp; Hong, 2014; Das, Kramer, Dabbish &amp; Hong, 2014; Rader, Wash Brooks, 2012; Redmiles et al, 2016)</p>
    <p>Social - direct social interactions (e.g. observing a friend providing advice or observing others security behaviors)</p>
    <p>Forced - non-social, external stimuli or situations (e.g. experiencing a personal data breach, or employer requiring password update)</p>
    <p>Proactive - non-social, internal processes - routines, habits (e.g. enabling lock screen or routine password updates)</p>
    <p>Source: flaticon</p>
    <p>Source: noun project</p>
    <p>Source: shutterstock</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our focus: Understand behavior triggers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Questions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method: Online survey about recent behavior</p>
    <p>Participants were asked if they did any of the following in the last 6 months:</p>
    <p>Mobile Auth: enabling or changing ones method of authenticating into a mobile device (e.g., smartphone, laptop, tablet or other portable electronic device)</p>
    <p>App Uninstallation: uninstalling a smartphone application, specifically for privacy or security reasons</p>
    <p>Password Update: changing or updating a password for an online account  Facebook Privacy: updating ones Facebook account privacy settings</p>
    <p>We then asked about behavioral triggers for each change, whether they shared the change with others and why.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method: Online survey about recent behavior</p>
    <p>Participants were also asked:</p>
    <p>Demographics: gender, age, nationality, professional background  Security Behavior Intentions (Egelman &amp; Peer, 2015)</p>
    <p>Identify users who have low to medium security behavioral intention</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sample</p>
    <p>807 (95%) reported doing at least one behavior in the past 6 months  Reported on 1947 behavior changes and 2954 triggers leading up to those</p>
    <p>behaviors</p>
    <p>Demographics</p>
    <p>Age - Mean = 33 years (Standard dev: 10, Range: 18-74)  Gender - 63% Male, 36% Female  Nationality - 53% from US, 47% from India  Tech expertise - 47% had technology background</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RQ1: How frequent are different triggers leading to security and privacy behaviors?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Social triggers were most prevalent</p>
    <p>Social - 39% (1153) of reported triggers</p>
    <p>Forced - 26% (773)</p>
    <p>Proactive - 34% (1005) Source: flaticon</p>
    <p>Source: noun project</p>
    <p>Source: shutterstock</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trigger likelihood varied by system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RQ2: How does the frequency of triggers differ across levels of security behavioral intentions (SBI)?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RQ2: How does trigger frequency vary across levels of security behavioral intentions?</p>
    <p>Collapsed 16-item SeBIS scale into Security Behavioral Intention (SBI) construct capturing 17% of the variance based on a factor analysis</p>
    <p>Conducted a series of logistic regressions on behavioral trigger likelihood as a function of behavior type, age, gender, nationality and SBI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>People with low-medium SBI were more likely to report social triggers</p>
    <p>People with higher SBI were more likely to report proactive triggers (sbi = 0.36, p&lt;0.001)</p>
    <p>People with lower SBI were more likely to report more social triggers (sbi=0.12, p&lt;0.05) and forced triggers (sbi=-0.25, p&lt;0.001)</p>
    <p>Gaussian additive model accounting for non-linearities in the data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RQ3: How often and why do people share their security and privacy behaviors with others?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Socially triggered behaviors were four times more likely to be shared with others</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>People were generally concerned for the security and privacy welfare of others The most prevalent motivations for discussing a security change (aside from desire to socialize) were:</p>
    <p>- Noticing people were being insecure</p>
    <p>- Feeling obligated to protect them</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Social triggers were most frequent especially among those with low to medium security behavioral intention</p>
    <p>People were four times more likely to share socially triggered security and privacy behaviors with others</p>
    <p>People frequently shared security and privacy behaviors with others out of concern for their welfare (observing insecure behavior or a sense of obligation)</p>
    <p>Source: shutterstock</p>
    <p>Source: Icons8.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design implications</p>
    <p>Encourage social interaction - design for sharing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Explore the trigger design space</p>
    <p>Sparks - motivating triggers (advertising, social proof notifications)</p>
    <p>Facilitators - make the action easier (or seem easier)</p>
    <p>Signals - reminders of something we can and want to do</p>
    <p>Akhawe &amp; Porter Felt, 2013</p>
    <p>Das et al., 2014</p>
    <p>Social Proof</p>
    <p>SSL warning</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design implications</p>
    <p>Encourage social interaction - design for sharing</p>
    <p>Explore broader trigger design space</p>
    <p>Personalize behavioral triggers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you! @scyrusk, @dabbish, @jas0nh0ng</p>
    <p>Socialcybersecurity.org</p>
    <p>Key findings</p>
    <p>This work was funded by NSF grant no. CNS-1704087.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
