<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Personal Information Leakage by Abusing the GDPR Right of Access</p>
    <p>Mariano Di Martino, Pieter Robyns, Winnie Weyts, Peter Quax, Wim Lamotte, Ken Andries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) and Right of Access</p>
    <p>GDPR - European framework, in effect since May 2018. - European consumers and businesses. - Generated a lot of startups. - Substantial monetary penalties (20 000 000 euros or 4%</p>
    <p>of turnover).</p>
    <p>Right of Access - Permits subjects to request all their personal information. - For free and within a month (max. 2 months) - Subject Access Request or Data Request (in our paper).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research questions: Data Requests under Right of Access</p>
    <p>- What information is requested by the organization to verify the identity of the consumer ?</p>
    <p>- How is the requested information verified by the organization ?</p>
    <p>- Can the requested information be forged by an adversary or can the organization be persuaded through social engineering to obtain personal information from someone else ?</p>
    <p>- How can we improve the identity verification?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Setting up experiment</p>
    <p>- Impersonating 2 targeted individuals as an adversary to obtain their personal information by forging data requests.</p>
    <p>- Targeted individuals = 2 authors.</p>
    <p>- Contacted 55 organizations, primarily based on Alexa top 50. Independently from each other.</p>
    <p>- Classified each organization in categories: Financial, Retail, News Outlet, Entertainment, Transport &amp; Logistics and others.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What credentials are requested or verified by the organization ?</p>
    <p>Combinations of the following: - Login credentials - Email address ownership - ID card - Home address - Calling subject - Specific user data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can we forge or extract the requested credentials ?</p>
    <p>Email address: Forgeable - Create similar looking email. Old concept in phishing.</p>
    <p>mariano.dimartino@yahoo.com mariano.dlmartino@yahoo.com</p>
    <p>mariano.dimartino@gmail.com mariano.dimartino@gmal.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can we forge or extract the requested credentials ?</p>
    <p>Home address: Forgeable - Apply some OSINT: Found for both individuals.</p>
    <p>- Sometimes, only the city is required: social media.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can we forge or extract the requested credentials ?</p>
    <p>ID card - Take picture of own ID card and photoshop name, date of</p>
    <p>birth and portrait photo of the targeted individual.</p>
    <p>- Censor everything else.</p>
    <p>- National Register Number and Passport ID number are rarely required, so censor it.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can we forge the requested credentials ?</p>
    <p>ID card: Photoshopped</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can we persuade the organizations ?</p>
    <p>Org: Please send a request with an email address that is known to us. Adversary: Sorry, lost access to my account due to hackers. This is the reason why I am sending a data request. Trying to get a view of all personal information that may be leaked... Success: 1 / 5</p>
    <p>Org: We sent your personal data to an email address known to us. Adversary: Wait until a few days before deadline -&gt; Didnt receive response to data request. Deadline has almost passed. Success: 1 / 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can we persuade the organizations ?</p>
    <p>Org: Please send proof A,B and C to verify your identity. Adversary: Wait until a few days before deadline -&gt; Okay, here is proof A and C. Success: 2 / 2</p>
    <p>Overall strategy: pressure and legal talk.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results:</p>
    <p>- From 55 organizations: - 37 accepted manual data requests - 14 provided an online platform to request data. - 4 didnt answer at all.</p>
    <p>- 12 out of 37 organizations leaked the personal data of the targeted individual. Falsified credentials were never questioned.</p>
    <p>- 3 out of 37 organizations leaked the personal data of someone else.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results:</p>
    <p>- Leaked data consists of: - Financial: Timestamped financial transactions, account numbers, services bought, ... - Retail: serial numbers of products, delivery dates, products bought,  - Entertainment: profile preferences, products bought,  - T&amp;L: Timestamped GPS locations, saved routes, purchased tickets, customer ID,  - News outlets: browsing history, profile preferences,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations:</p>
    <p>- Consumers: - Basic hygiene</p>
    <p>- Organizations: - Require login credentials: significantly reduces risk (also,</p>
    <p>suggested by GDPR). - Strictly verifying ownership of email address. - Call subject and request specific user data. - Dont ask for IDs!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ethics:</p>
    <p>- Prior written permission of University Ethical Research Committee and targeted individuals.</p>
    <p>- Vulnerable organizations were notified of research and recommendations.</p>
    <p>- Organizations are anonymized.</p>
    <p>- All organizations responded positively. 3 organizations requested a meeting to discuss the recommendations.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you.</p>
    <p>Questions ?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References:</p>
    <p>Related work Type of credentials: Boniface et al. (https://hal.inria.fr/hal-02072302/document) Risks of SARs: Amber Welch (https://youtu.be/FAYGZ9COrto)</p>
    <p>Future work Cagnazzo et al. (https://www.syssec.ruhr-uni-bochum.de/media/emma/veroeffentlichungen/20 19/08/05/ESORICS19-GDPiRated.pdf)</p>
    <p>Urban et al. (https://www.ei.ruhr-uni-bochum.de/media/emma/veroeffentlichungen/2019/0 8/05/DPM19-SAR-Study.pdf)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interesting cases (1)</p>
    <p>We requested personal information of our targeted individual:</p>
    <p>Ley Johnson</p>
    <p>We received the data of another individual: Name: Lesley John Address: Sonarstreet nr.15</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
