<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Self-Report Measure of End-User Security Attitudes (SA-6) Cori Faklaris, Laura Dabbish and Jason I. Hong</p>
    <p>Human-Computer Interaction Institute</p>
    <p>Usenix Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security (SOUPS 2019), Aug. 12, 2019, Santa Clara, CA, USA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key takeaways</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SA-6 is a lightweight tool to quantify and compare security attitudes</p>
    <p>Generally, I diligently follow a routine about security practices.  I always pay attention to experts advice about the steps I need to take</p>
    <p>to keep my online data and accounts safe.  I am extremely knowledgeable about all the steps needed to keep my</p>
    <p>online data and accounts safe.  I am extremely motivated to take all the steps needed to keep my online</p>
    <p>data and accounts safe.  I often am interested in articles about security threats.  I seek out opportunities to learn about security measures that are</p>
    <p>relevant to me.</p>
    <p>On a scale of 1=Strongly Disagree to 5=Strongly Agree, rate your level of agreement with the following:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SA-6 may help to improve predictive modeling of security adoption</p>
    <p>Attitude toward security behavior</p>
    <p>Security behavior intention</p>
    <p>Security behavior</p>
    <p>SA-6</p>
    <p>SeBIS</p>
    <p>Recalled actions</p>
    <p>Better predictive modeling = better targeting of interventions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Much usability research employs in-depth interviews and observations.</p>
    <p>But this is not always feasible or desirable.</p>
    <p>Our field needs reliable and validated psychometric scales</p>
    <p>https://giphy.com/gifs/heyarnold-hey-arnold-nicksplat-xT1R9EbolF7trQnIyI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our field needs reliable and validated psychometric scales</p>
    <p>For large-scale, longitudinal or time-sensitive research, we need an online survey form that can be given with other scales or questionnaires.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Knowing users attitudes, intentions and behaviors helps us craft security tools that are:  Useful  Easy to use  Satisfying to users</p>
    <p>https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/topics/usability</p>
    <p>Our field needs reliable and validated psychometric scales</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our field needs reliable and validated psychometric scales</p>
    <p>An attitude scale helps answer research questions such as:  How attentive to security</p>
    <p>advice is a certain user group likely to be?</p>
    <p>Does a new tool help or hurt a users attitude toward security compliance?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current state of the art is SeBIS (Egelman &amp; Peer 2015)  16-item self-report inventory in four areas:</p>
    <p>Password generation  Proactive awareness  Software updates  Device securement</p>
    <p>But it has limitations:  Specific to behavior intentions, not to attitudes.  Tech-specific wording may become outdated.</p>
    <p>The Security Behavior Intentions Scale (SeBIS) isnt enough</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theory of Reasoned Action  Technology Acceptance Model  Diffusion of Innovation Theory</p>
    <p>Elaboration Likelihood Model  Self-Determination Theory  Protection Motivation Theory</p>
    <p>An additional scale is needed to conduct theory-motivated research</p>
    <p>Behavior</p>
    <p>Intention</p>
    <p>Attitude</p>
    <p>Fishbein &amp; Azjen 1967, 2010; Davis et al. 1989; Rogers 2010; Petty &amp; Cacioppo 1980; Ryan &amp; Deci 2000; Rogers 1975</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Generate candidate items from prior work (Das et al. 2017)</p>
    <p>Awareness Motivation Knowledge</p>
    <p>Security Sensitivity</p>
    <p>to engage in expert-recommended security practices</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
    <p>Attitude</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A security breach, if one occurs, is not likely to cause significant harm to my online identity or accounts.</p>
    <p>Generally, I am aware of existing security threats.  Generally, I am willing to spend money to use security measures that</p>
    <p>counteract the threats that are relevant to me.  Generally, I care about security and privacy threats.  Generally, I diligently follow a routine about security practices.  Generally, I know how to figure out if an email was sent by a scam</p>
    <p>artist.  Generally, I know how to use security measures to counteract the</p>
    <p>threats that are relevant to me.  Generally, I know which security threats are relevant to me.  Generally, I want to use measures that can counteract security and</p>
    <p>privacy threats.  I always pay attention to experts' advice about the steps I need to take</p>
    <p>to keep my online data and accounts safe.  I always trust experts recommendations about security measures</p>
    <p>(such as using unique passwords or a password manager, installing recommended software updates, etc.).</p>
    <p>I am confident that I am taking the necessary steps to keep my online data and accounts safe.</p>
    <p>I am confident that I can change my security behaviors, if needed, to protect myself against threats (such as phishing, computer viruses, identity theft, password hacking) that are a danger to my online data and accounts.</p>
    <p>I am confident that I could change my security behaviors if I decided to.  I am extremely knowledgeable about all the steps needed to keep my</p>
    <p>online data and accounts safe.  I am extremely knowledgeable about how to take the necessary steps</p>
    <p>to keep my online data and accounts safe.  I am extremely knowledgeable about which security threats (such as</p>
    <p>phishing, computer viruses, malware, password hacking) are a danger to my online data and accounts.</p>
    <p>I am extremely motivated to take all the steps needed to keep my online data and accounts safe.</p>
    <p>I am extremely well aware of existing security threats (such as phishing, computer viruses, identity theft, password hacking).</p>
    <p>I am extremely well aware of the necessary steps that I can take to counteract security threats (such as phishing, computer viruses, identity theft, password hacking).</p>
    <p>I am too busy to put in the effort needed to change my security behaviors.</p>
    <p>I care very much about the issue of security threats (such as phishing, computer viruses, identity theft, password hacking).</p>
    <p>I dread that using recommended security measures will backfire on me (such as forgetting a needed password, updated software becoming unusable, etc.).</p>
    <p>I feel guilty when I do not use recommended security measures (such as by reusing passwords, putting off software updates, etc.).</p>
    <p>I generally am aware of existing security measures that I can use to counteract security threats.</p>
    <p>I generally am aware of methods to send email or text messages that can't be spied on.</p>
    <p>I have much bigger problems than my risk of a security breach.  I need to change my security behaviors to improve my protection</p>
    <p>against security threats (such as phishing, computer viruses, identity theft, password hacking).</p>
    <p>I often am interested in articles about security threats.  I seek out opportunities to learn about security measures that are</p>
    <p>relevant to me.  I usually will not use security measures if they are inconvenient.  I usually will not use security measures unless I am forced to.  I want to change my security behaviors in order to keep my online data</p>
    <p>and accounts safe.  I want to change my security behaviors to improve my protection</p>
    <p>against threats (such as phishing, computer viruses, identity theft, password hacking) that are a danger to my online data and accounts.</p>
    <p>I worry that Im not doing enough to protect myself against threats (such as phishing, computer viruses, identity theft, password hacking) that are a danger to my online data and accounts.</p>
    <p>It is a lost cause to take all the steps needed to keep my online data and accounts safe.</p>
    <p>It is important for me to change my security behaviors to improve my protection against security threats (such as phishing, computer viruses, identity theft, password hacking).</p>
    <p>It is not possible for me to do more than I already am to counteract security threats (such as phishing, computer viruses, identity theft, password hacking) that are a danger to my online data and accounts.</p>
    <p>It's a sign of paranoia to use numerous security measures to protect against threats.</p>
    <p>It's a sign of paranoia to use recommended security measures (such as using unique passwords or a password manager, installing recommended software updates, etc.).</p>
    <p>My current lapses in using security measures are harmless.  My own actions can make a significant difference in keeping my online</p>
    <p>data and accounts safe.  Oftentimes, as soon as I discover a security problem, I report it to</p>
    <p>someone who can fix it.  Oftentimes, I am running on &quot;automatic pilot&quot; when I sift through my</p>
    <p>email and text messages.</p>
    <p>Best practice: Test many different item variations for SA-6 (60+ to start)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SeBIS scale, 16 items  Internet Know-How, 9 items  Technical Know-How, 9 items  Internet Users Information Privacy Concerns scale, 10 items  Frequency of falling victim to a security breach, 2 items  Amount heard or seen about security breaches, 1 item  Barratt Impulsiveness Scale, 30 items  Privacy Concerns Scale, 16 items  Ten-Item Personality Inventory, 10 items  General Self-Efficacy scale, 11 items  Social Self-Efficacy scale, 5 items  Confidence in Using Computers, 12 items  Web-Oriented Digital Literacy, 25 items  Need for Cognition scale, 18 items  GDMS Avoidance and Dependence subscales, 10 items  DoSpeRT Health/Safety subscales, 12 items  Consideration of Future Consequences scale, 12 items  Age range, 1 item  Gender, 1 item  Level of formal education, 1 item  Household income level, 1 item  Employment status, 1 item</p>
    <p>Best practice: Collect measures theorized to relate with SA-6</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Collect measures theorized to relate with SA-6</p>
    <p>Test convergent validity  RQ1a: Is SA-6 positively</p>
    <p>correlated with SeBIS?  RQ1b: Do other measures</p>
    <p>thought to relate with security attitude correlate with SA-6?</p>
    <p>Test discriminant validity  RQ2a: Does SA-6 vary with</p>
    <p>respect to background social factors (e.g. age, gender)?</p>
    <p>RQ2b: Does SA-6 vary with past experiences of security breaches?</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Samples not significantly different by age [overall X^2(4,</p>
    <p>N=475)=11.42, p = n.s.]</p>
    <p>or gender [X^2(1, N = 475) =2.95,</p>
    <p>p = n.s.]</p>
    <p>Amazon Mechanical Turk sample</p>
    <p>Best practice: Use a large, diverse sample for finalizing scale items</p>
    <p>Meets recommended ratio (5:1 to 10:1) of responses to scale items</p>
    <p>N = 475</p>
    <p>University-run study pool sample</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Repeat study in a representative sample to validate scale</p>
    <p>N = 209</p>
    <p>Qualtrics-filled panel with age, gender &amp; income tailored to U.S. population</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Iterative analyses to zero in on the items for the scale</p>
    <p>Factor tests  Exploratory</p>
    <p>Factor Analysis to check item correlations (SPSS)</p>
    <p>Reliability Analysis (alpha) to confirm internal consistency</p>
    <p>Model tests  Confirmatory</p>
    <p>Factor Analysis to check goodness of fit (MPlus)</p>
    <p>Run several CFA models to make sure we specified the best model</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SA-6 scale items (SPSS Principal Components Analysis) Factor loading</p>
    <p>I seek out opportunities to learn about security measures that are relevant to me. 0.81</p>
    <p>I am extremely motivated to take all the steps needed to keep my online data and accounts safe. 0.78</p>
    <p>Generally, I diligently follow a routine about security practices. 0.77</p>
    <p>I often am interested in articles about security threats. 0.72</p>
    <p>I always pay attention to experts' advice about the steps I need to take to keep my online data and accounts safe. 0.71</p>
    <p>I am extremely knowledgeable about all the steps needed to keep my online data and accounts safe. 0.71</p>
    <p>SA-6 demonstrates desired consistency + fit for a psychometric scale</p>
    <p>=.84</p>
    <p>CFI=.91</p>
    <p>SRMR =.05</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SA-6 scale items (SPSS Principal Components Analysis) Factor loading</p>
    <p>I seek out opportunities to learn about security measures that are relevant to me. 0.81</p>
    <p>I am extremely motivated to take all the steps needed to keep my online data and accounts safe. 0.78</p>
    <p>Generally, I diligently follow a routine about security practices. 0.77</p>
    <p>I often am interested in articles about security threats. 0.72</p>
    <p>I always pay attention to experts' advice about the steps I need to take to keep my online data and accounts safe. 0.71</p>
    <p>I am extremely knowledgeable about all the steps needed to keep my online data and accounts safe. 0.71</p>
    <p>SA-6 = attentiveness to and engagement with cybersecurity measures</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Statistical testing of SA-6 as a valid attitude measure</p>
    <p>Factor tests  Exploratory</p>
    <p>Factor Analysis to check item correlations (SPSS)</p>
    <p>Reliability Analysis (alpha) to confirm internal consistency</p>
    <p>Model tests  Confirmatory</p>
    <p>Factor Analysis to check goodness of fit (MPlus)</p>
    <p>Run several CFA models to make sure we specified the best model</p>
    <p>Validity tests  Test relationships +</p>
    <p>differences with other variables (SPSS)</p>
    <p>Also tested for ability to predict participants recalled security actions in past week</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Test for expected associations with SA-6</p>
    <p>Attitude toward security behavior</p>
    <p>Security behavior intention</p>
    <p>SA-6 SeBIS</p>
    <p>r=.540, p&lt;.01</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
    <p>Faklaris et al. 2019</p>
    <p>Egelman &amp; Peer 2015</p>
    <p>RQ1a: Is SA-6 positively correlated with SeBIS?</p>
    <p>Yes.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Test for expected associations with SA-6</p>
    <p>RQ1a: Is SA-6 positively correlated with SeBIS?</p>
    <p>Yes.</p>
    <p>Attitude toward security behavior</p>
    <p>Security behavior intention</p>
    <p>SA-6 SeBIS</p>
    <p>R2=.280, p&lt;.001</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
    <p>Faklaris et al. 2019</p>
    <p>Egelman &amp; Peer 2015</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Test for expected associations with SA-6</p>
    <p>- With the Internet Users Informational Privacy Concerns (IUIPC) scale</p>
    <p>- With the Privacy Concerns Scale (PCS)</p>
    <p>r=.390, p&lt;.01</p>
    <p>r=.382, p&lt;.01</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
    <p>Malhotra et al. 2004</p>
    <p>Buchanan et al. 2007</p>
    <p>RQ1b: Do other measures thought to relate with security attitude correlate with SA-6?</p>
    <p>Yes.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Test for expected associations with SA-6</p>
    <p>- With the Barratt Impulsiveness Scale</p>
    <p>- With the General Self-Efficacy scale</p>
    <p>- With the Social Self-Efficacy scale</p>
    <p>r=.180, p&lt;.01</p>
    <p>r=.208, p&lt;.01 r=.363, p&lt;.01</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
    <p>Stanford et al. 2009 (update)</p>
    <p>Zimmerman et al. 2000</p>
    <p>Zimmerman et al. 2000</p>
    <p>RQ1b: Do other measures thought to relate with security attitude correlate with SA-6?</p>
    <p>Yes.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Test for expected associations with SA-6</p>
    <p>RQ1b: Do other measures thought to relate with security attitude correlate with SA-6?</p>
    <p>Yes.</p>
    <p>- With the Kang Internet Know-How scale</p>
    <p>- w/Confidence in using computers</p>
    <p>- w/Web-oriented digital literacy</p>
    <p>r=.542, p&lt;.01</p>
    <p>r=.280, p&lt;.05 r=.503, p&lt;.05</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
    <p>Kang et al. 2015</p>
    <p>Fogarty et al. 2001 (adapted)</p>
    <p>Hargittai 2005</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Test for expected differences in SA-6 by subgroup</p>
    <p>RQ2a: Does SA-6 vary with background factors? Yes.</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
    <p>SA-6 Mean (SD) t(df ), p</p>
    <p>Age group 18-39</p>
    <p>Gender Male</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Test for expected differences in SA-6 by subgroup</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
    <p>SA-6 Mean (SD) t(df ), p</p>
    <p>College attendance No college 3.42 (.79)</p>
    <p>Attended college 3.73 (.76)</p>
    <p>t(207)=-2.76, p&lt;.01</p>
    <p>Income level Below $25K</p>
    <p>RQ2a: Does SA-6 vary with background factors? Yes.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RQ2b: Does SA-6 vary with past breach experiences? Yes. SA-6 Mean (SD) t(df ), p</p>
    <p>Low High</p>
    <p>Themselves falling victim to a security breach 3.56 (.78) 4.13 (.58) t(41.46) = -4.54, p&lt;.001</p>
    <p>Close friends or relatives falling victim 3.57 (.76) 4.10 (.74) t(207)= -3.40, p&lt;.005</p>
    <p>Heard about security breaches in the past year 3.35 (.80) 3.77 (.74) t(207)=-3.77, p&lt;.001</p>
    <p>Best practice: Test for expected differences in SA-6 by subgroup</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test support for predictive validity  RQ3: Does a persons SA-6 score positively associate with a measure</p>
    <p>of self-reported security behaviors within the past week?  Collected 10 items based on SeBIS, 5-level agreement scale (RSec)</p>
    <p>Best practice: Collect measures theorized to relate with SA-6</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
    <p>Ex: In the past week, I have verified at least once that my antivirus software is up to date.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Test for SA-6s influence on outcome variables</p>
    <p>Attitude toward security behavior</p>
    <p>Security behavior</p>
    <p>SA-6 RSec</p>
    <p>r=.398, p&lt;.001</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
    <p>Faklaris et al. 2019</p>
    <p>RQ3: Does SA-6 positively associate with a measure of self-reported security behaviors within the past week (RSec)?</p>
    <p>Yes. Faklaris et</p>
    <p>al. 2019</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Test for SA-6s influence on outcome variables</p>
    <p>Attitude toward security behavior</p>
    <p>Security behavior intention</p>
    <p>Security behavior</p>
    <p>SA-6</p>
    <p>SeBIS</p>
    <p>RSec</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
    <p>Faklaris et al. 2019</p>
    <p>Faklaris et al. 2019</p>
    <p>Egelman &amp; Peer 2015</p>
    <p>R2=.280, p&lt;.001</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Test for SA-6s influence on outcome variables</p>
    <p>Attitude toward security behavior</p>
    <p>Security behavior intention</p>
    <p>Security behavior</p>
    <p>SA-6</p>
    <p>SeBIS</p>
    <p>RSec</p>
    <p>R2=.235, p&lt;.001</p>
    <p>R2=.280, p&lt;.001</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
    <p>Faklaris et al. 2019</p>
    <p>Faklaris et al. 2019</p>
    <p>Egelman &amp; Peer 2015</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best practice: Test for SA-6s influence on outcome variables</p>
    <p>Attitude toward security behavior</p>
    <p>Security behavior intention</p>
    <p>Security behavior</p>
    <p>SA-6</p>
    <p>SeBIS</p>
    <p>RSec</p>
    <p>R2=.158, p&lt;.001</p>
    <p>Introduction | Study Motivation | Scale Development | Scale Validation | Conclusion</p>
    <p>Faklaris et al. 2019</p>
    <p>Faklaris et al. 2019</p>
    <p>Egelman &amp; Peer 2015</p>
    <p>R2=.235, p&lt;.001</p>
    <p>R2=.280, p&lt;.001</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SA-6 can improve predictive modeling + targeting of interventions</p>
    <p>Attitude toward security behavior</p>
    <p>Security behavior intention</p>
    <p>Security behavior</p>
    <p>SA-6</p>
    <p>SeBIS</p>
    <p>RSec</p>
    <p>Low SA-6  boost awareness/motivation; High SA-6  boost skill/ability</p>
    <p>Faklaris et al. 2019</p>
    <p>Faklaris et al. 2019</p>
    <p>Egelman &amp; Peer 2015</p>
    <p>R2=.158, p&lt;.001</p>
    <p>R2=.235, p&lt;.001</p>
    <p>R2=.280, p&lt;.001</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SA-6 can be helpful in your own usable security research</p>
    <p>Easily administer SA-6 via online survey form with other scales or questionnaires.</p>
    <p>Answer research questions such as  How attentive to security advice is a</p>
    <p>certain user group likely to be?  Does a new tool help or hurt a users</p>
    <p>attitude toward security compliance?</p>
    <p>https://socialcybersecurity.org/sa6.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SA-6 can be helpful in your own usable security research</p>
    <p>Test hypotheses &amp; models motivated by:</p>
    <p>Theory of Reasoned Action,  Elaboration Likelihood Model,  Self-Determination Theory,  Protection Motivation Theory,  Other theories and frameworks.</p>
    <p>https://socialcybersecurity.org/sa6.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Take the Security Attitude quiz at SocialCybersecurity.org/sa6quiz</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Get the SA-6 scale &amp; follow our work:</p>
    <p>Twitter: @heycori | Email: heycori @cmu.edu  https://socialcybersecurity.org/sa6.html</p>
    <p>Key takeaways</p>
    <p>Thank you to</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
