<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Youve Got Your Nice List of Bugs, Now What? Vulnerability Discovery and Management</p>
    <p>Processes in the Wild Noura Alomar, Primal Wijesekera, Edward Qiu, and Serge Egelman</p>
    <p>University of California (Berkeley) and ICSI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Many testing strategies  Penetration testing  Blue/ red and purple teams  Bug bounty programs  Quality assurance teams</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Many testing strategies  Penetration testing  Blue/ red and purple teams  Bug bounty programs  Quality assurance teams</p>
    <p>Many advanced vulnerability detection techniques  Standards: ISO/IEC 29147 and ISO/IEC 30111</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What decision makers expect from the various testing strategies?</p>
    <p>How do different teams fit in vulnerability discovery processes?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Interviews with 53 security practitioners  Roles</p>
    <p>CISOs, CTOs, security managers  Pen testers, bug bounty hunters, red/blue/purple teamers, internal security testers</p>
    <p>Countries  Bangladesh, Canada, Germany, India, Israel, Serbia, Singapore, Brazil, UK and US</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vulnerability Management Pipeline</p>
    <p>Strategic Decision Making</p>
    <p>Vulnerability Discovery</p>
    <p>Vulnerability Remediation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vulnerability Management Pipeline</p>
    <p>Strategic Decision Making</p>
    <p>Vulnerability Discovery</p>
    <p>Vulnerability Remediation</p>
    <p>When to create a bug bounty program?</p>
    <p>When to employ what testing strategy?</p>
    <p>When to create an internal team vs hire a testing firm?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vulnerability Management Pipeline</p>
    <p>Strategic Decision Making</p>
    <p>Vulnerability Discovery</p>
    <p>Vulnerability Remediation</p>
    <p>What are the activities of each team? What managers expect from each team?</p>
    <p>Strategic Decision Making</p>
    <p>Vulnerability Discovery</p>
    <p>When to create a bug bounty program?</p>
    <p>When to employ what testing strategy?</p>
    <p>When to create an internal team vs hire a testing firm?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vulnerability Management Pipeline</p>
    <p>Strategic Decision Making</p>
    <p>Vulnerability Discovery</p>
    <p>Vulnerability Remediation</p>
    <p>What are the activities of each team? What managers expect from each team?</p>
    <p>When to create a bug bounty program?</p>
    <p>When to employ what testing strategy?</p>
    <p>When to create an internal team vs hire a testing firm?</p>
    <p>How to fix uncovered vulnerabilities?</p>
    <p>How to prioritize remediation tasks?</p>
    <p>How to triage vulnerability reports received from external researchers?</p>
    <p>Vulnerability Remediation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main themes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main themes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main themes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main themes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Strategic Decision Making</p>
    <p>Uncertainty around what to expect from each team</p>
    <p>I have had clients that have suffered a breach in the past and immediately they are like, Hey, we want to get a penetration test or a red team to figure out how the attacker broke in (P37)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Strategic Decision Making</p>
    <p>Uncertainty around what to expect from each team</p>
    <p>I have had clients that have suffered a breach in the past and immediately they are like, Hey, we want to get a penetration test or a red team to figure out how the attacker broke in (P37)</p>
    <p>Bug bounty programs might be used as replacement to internal testing</p>
    <p>My CISO likes to be able to tell customers we have a bug bounty program; therefore we are very secure (P41)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pen testing</p>
    <p>Compliance requirements</p>
    <p>Pen tests are kind of a reproducible formula for getting the engagement done whether it is to get that compliance checkbox checked or they are just kind of going through the motions to make sure that basic security structures are in place (P10)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pen testing</p>
    <p>Compliance requirements</p>
    <p>Pen tests are kind of a reproducible formula for getting the engagement done whether it is to get that compliance checkbox checked or they are just kind of going through the motions to make sure that basic security structures are in place (P10)</p>
    <p>Accountability</p>
    <p>..the quality of that report you get from pen testing companies is much much higher. It can also hold people who did the pen test accountable (P32)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Red teaming</p>
    <p>Exposure to legal liability</p>
    <p>You dont know when someone is in the network, you dont know what he is reading. I know that there are NDAs, but sometimes there is a code of ethic, that says if you find something illegal during a penetration test, you have to report it. And in red teaming, lets be honest not many companies are in regulations with the law (P24).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bug Bounty Programs</p>
    <p>Sensitivity of data stored in organizations systems</p>
    <p>...trying to convince any government agency to try to offer people a reward to try to break into their financial data, I think we would have a very bad reaction to that, whereas saying, its an audit would be a much easier sell (P44)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trust</p>
    <p>Organizations  scoping decisions</p>
    <p>..everybody is talking about they want a red team, they want a red team, but at the end of the day, they want to put a bunch of rules around it, just like regular penetration tests&quot; (P38)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trust</p>
    <p>Organizations  scoping decisions</p>
    <p>..everybody is talking about they want a red team, they want a red team, but at the end of the day, they want to put a bunch of rules around it, just like regular penetration tests&quot; (P38)</p>
    <p>Bug bounty hunters  legal concerns</p>
    <p>I was looking around and I saw this, what looked like financial data and I started freaking out because it was a public company. But that was kind of scary that I had even looked at it and what if they saw that I looked at it (P25)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Compliance vs. Security</p>
    <p>External pen testers are asked to:  downplay severity ratings  take some vulnerabilities out of reports</p>
    <p>Weve been told we dont want you to actually solve this problem, we just want you to make the check box go away (P9)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Issues impacting effective vulnerability management:  Trust  Communication  Staffing &amp; funding  Misalignment between business &amp; security priorities</p>
    <p>Need to pay more attention to vulnerability remediation!</p>
    <p>Thank you! nnalomar@berkeley.edu</p>
    <p>@Noura_7N</p>
    <p>Youve Got Your Nice List of Bugs, Now What? Vulnerability Discovery and Management Processes in the Wild Noura Alomar, Primal Wijesekera, Edward Qiu, and Serge Egelman</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
