<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SOUPS 2020</p>
    <p>Sarah Bird, Mozilla Ilana Segall, Mozilla Martin Lopatka, Mozilla</p>
    <p>Replication: Why We Still Can't Browse in Peace: On the Uniqueness and Reidentifiability of Web Browsing Histories</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Johnny Can't Browse in Peace: On the Uniqueness of</p>
    <p>Web Browsing History Patterns</p>
    <p>Olejnik, Castelluccia, and Janc</p>
    <p>Technologies (Hot-PETS 2012)</p>
    <p>Browsing history - the set of domains you have visited - is highly unique and could be used as a tracking vector.</p>
    <p>Why replicate:  The web and browsing has evolved:</p>
    <p>user generated content and core platforms</p>
    <p>Tracking ecosystem has grown and consolidated</p>
    <p>We can collect more detailed data to answer questions about reidentifiability raised by original paper</p>
    <p>Original Paper</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Types of profile  All observed domains  Predefined list of domains - Trexa (Tranco + Alexa)  Categories</p>
    <p>Profile - a list of x that a user visited  Profile size - how many x did a user have in total?  Length of subvector - how many x are we considering?</p>
    <p>Background &amp; Definitions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We replicate the core findings of Olejnik et al.</p>
    <p>A large proportion of profiles are unique.</p>
    <p>This holds even for small profiles e.g. 50 domains.</p>
    <p>Replication</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We move beyond profile stability to measure a</p>
    <p>reidentification rate.</p>
    <p>Jaccard distance - degree of overlap between two sets.</p>
    <p>(a) For each wk1 profile compute the Jaccard distance to all wk2 profiles (b) pick the profile with the lowest Jaccard distance (c) If wk1 and wk2 users are the same, it is a match.</p>
    <p>Reidentifiability metric: % of users correctly matched</p>
    <p>Extension</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>n = 19,263 users with profile size &gt; 50</p>
    <p>Baseline reidentifiability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A 10x reduction in the number of users increases</p>
    <p>reidentification rate by 10%.</p>
    <p>Monte Carlo simulation on users with profile &gt;50,</p>
    <p>sampling between 1 and 19,263 users,</p>
    <p>Scalability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Compute reidentifiability rates for equally sized</p>
    <p>groups of users (n=1,766) with different profile sizes.</p>
    <p>Reidentifiability does not change dramatically</p>
    <p>between all domains and Trexa list.</p>
    <p>Profile Size ~80% for profile size &gt;150</p>
    <p>~50% for profile size ~50</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Use complete request-response data to</p>
    <p>identify actual exposure to third parties (grouped</p>
    <p>by entity e.g. Alphabet parent company of</p>
    <p>Google and others).</p>
    <p>Third-parties Alphabet and Facebook have close to maximum theoretical reidentifiability rates.</p>
    <p>A large number of third parties have sufficient presence for meaningful reidentification rates</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SOUPS 2020</p>
    <p>Sarah Bird, Mozilla* Ilana Segall, Mozilla Martin Lopatka, Mozilla</p>
    <p>* Corresponding author - sbird@mozilla.com</p>
    <p>Discussion!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
