<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Usable Sexurity:</p>
    <p>Studying Peoples Concerns and Strategies When Sexting</p>
    <p>Usable Sexurity Studying Peoples Concerns and Strategies When Sexting</p>
    <p>Christine Geeng, Jevan Hutson, Franziska Roesner</p>
    <p>Presented at SOUPS 2020 SPRL</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Consensual sexting is normal, not deviant</p>
    <p>About 26% of American adults have sent nude or semi-nude photos of themselves to someone else (Herbenick et al. 2017)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>However it can come with risks</p>
    <p>Coercion to sext in relationships  Unsolicited sexts  Revenge Porn</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>These risks are higher for younger women and queer individuals.</p>
    <p>Amanda Lenhart, Michele Ybarra, and Myeshia Price-Feeney. Nonconsensual image sharing, 2016. https://datasociety:net/output/nonconsensual-image-sharing/.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How can platforms better support sexual privacy?</p>
    <p>Protecting sexual privacy (as conceptualized by Citron) requires:</p>
    <p>Securing autonomy  Enabling intimacy  Protecting equality</p>
    <p>Danielle Keats Citron. Sexual privacy. 128 Yale Law Journal 1870 (2019); U of Maryland Legal Studies Research Paper No. 2018-25, 2019.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Questions</p>
    <p>For adults who have sexted, what are their:</p>
    <p>Experiences With</p>
    <p>Sexting Concerns Mitigation Strategies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methods</p>
    <p>Mixed-methods anonymous online survey (N=247)  Recruited adults who sext or have sexted before  IRB approved</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We describe sexting frequency, platform usage, sharing, storage, concerns, and strategies.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We describe sexting frequency, platform usage, sharing, storage, concerns, and strategies.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Concerns</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Top Concerns About Sexting (out of 20)</p>
    <p>get out 5. Shoulder surfing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Top Concerns About Sexting (out of 20)</p>
    <p>get out 5. Shoulder surfing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Women and non-binary people significantly more likely to receive unsolicited sexts and be concerned about this than men.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Strategies Technical and Non-technical</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technical Management Strategies</p>
    <p>Disappearing messages, password-protecting stored sexts, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Non-Technical Strategies</p>
    <p>Getting to know the person first, communicating rules and boundaries, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I sext with my partner whom I trust and we had several conversations about sexting before we started (when to delete photos, if we were at risk of revenge porning each other (were not)), from there we talked about several different platforms and ultimately chose an encrypted platform. Its not completely safe but its a calculated</p>
    <p>risk. Female, bi/pan, 25-34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How can platforms support sexual privacy?</p>
    <p>Policy Community Moderation Interface Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Policy</p>
    <p>Community guidelines can:</p>
    <p>Encourage asking for consent before saving images  Not allow harassment such as unsolicited sexts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Community Moderation</p>
    <p>Enforcing policy  Automatically detect and blur unsolicited nudes</p>
    <p>https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2019/sep/19/its-a-violation-the-war-on-unwanted-dick-pics-has-begun</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interface Design</p>
    <p>Not allowing photos to be sent unless both people in a conversation enable the feature.</p>
    <p>Or profile disclosure like Grindr:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our results cover sexting frequency, platform usage, sharing, storage, concerns, and strategies.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Platforms can support sexual privacy by considering consent through policy, moderation, and design.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Usable Sexurity:</p>
    <p>Studying Peoples Concerns and Strategies When Sexting</p>
    <p>Usable Sexurity Studying Peoples Concerns and Strategies When Sexting</p>
    <p>Christine Geeng, Jevan Hutson, Franziska Roesner</p>
    <p>Presented at SOUPS 2020</p>
    <p>@christinegeeng, @jevanhutson, @franziroesner</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
