<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Enhancing Privacy through the Visual Design of Privacy Notices: Exploring the Interplay of Curiosity, Control and Affect</p>
    <p>Agnieszka Kitkowska, Mark Warner, Yefim Shulman, Erik Wstlund, Leonardo A. Martucci</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Notice</p>
    <p>Must be acknowledged</p>
    <p>Provide no choice</p>
    <p>Difficult to understand</p>
    <p>Lengthy</p>
    <p>People &amp; Decisions</p>
    <p>Behavioral outcomes influenced by many factors (e.g., individual characteristics, privacy concerns, beliefs; external factors  exposure to stimuli)</p>
    <p>Problem</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>About visual design (framing and control) and its influence on:</p>
    <p>a) Affective state (positive vs negative)</p>
    <p>b) Privacy comprehension</p>
    <p>c) Intention to disclose information</p>
    <p>Research questions</p>
    <p>About psychological factors: a) Curiosity and its effect on comprehension</p>
    <p>b) Affective state and its role in the attitude-behavior relationship</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Online experiment with 620 participants</p>
    <p>Between-subject design  Independent variables:</p>
    <p>Manipulated: framing, control; Curiosity.</p>
    <p>Dependent variables:  Affect (valence), disclosure, comprehension</p>
    <p>Covariates  Concerns, trust, time spent on the policy page</p>
    <p>Statistical analysis  Univariate analysis of covariance</p>
    <p>(comprehension)  Multivariate analysis of covariance</p>
    <p>(disclosure and valence)  Mediation &amp; moderated mediation (the role</p>
    <p>of affect on the relationship between trust, concerns and disclosure)</p>
    <p>Positive framing, no control</p>
    <p>Negative framing, control</p>
    <p>Method</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Control  Valence significantly differed between control groups,</p>
    <p>F(1, 608)=5.8, p=.01, p 2&lt;.01</p>
    <p>Interaction effect: valence higher among participants provided control and scoring higher in curiosity, F(1, 608)=7.2, p&lt;.01, p</p>
    <p>Ability to change settings increases comprehension , F(1, 306)=11.1, p&lt;.01, p</p>
    <p>Ability to change settings influences intention to disclose, F(1, 306)=12.7, p&lt;.01, p</p>
    <p>Framing did not affect participants</p>
    <p>Time is important! (largest effect size)</p>
    <p>Results: visual design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Curiosity has a significant influence on privacy comprehension, F(1, 608)=8.5, p&lt;0.01, p</p>
    <p>Significant role of covariates: privacy concerns, trust implying that stable factors are better predictors of behavioral outcomes</p>
    <p>Moderated-mediation:</p>
    <p>Privacy concerns mediate the relationship between trust and information disclosure, b=.97, t(618)=8.06, p&lt;0.01, CI[.06, .20]</p>
    <p>Valence moderates the relationship between trust and concerns (scores on valence lower than 2.71 result in more negative relationship between trust and concerns)</p>
    <p>Results: psychological factors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Limitations &amp; Future work</p>
    <p>Effect sizes</p>
    <p>Use methods different than self-reports to measure affect (e.g., EEG)</p>
    <p>Test different contexts</p>
    <p>We learned that:</p>
    <p>Affording control perceived positively  potential for usability</p>
    <p>Valence moderates attitudes  affecting disclosure</p>
    <p>Privacy UIs: enhance curiosity and extend engagement time to improve comprehension</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>This project has received funding from the European Unions Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme under the Marie Skodowska-Curie grant agreement No 675730</p>
    <p>Thank you</p>
    <p>Enhancing Privacy through the Visual Design of Privacy Notices: Exploring the Interplay of Curiosity, Control and Affect</p>
    <p>Agnieszka Kitkowska, Mark Warner, Yefim Shulman,</p>
    <p>Erik Wstlund, Leonardo A. Martucci</p>
    <p>agnieszka.kitkowska@kau.se</p>
    <p>www.akitkowska.com</p>
    <p>@agakitkowska</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
