<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Empirical Study of Wireless Carrier Authentication for SIM Swaps Kevin Lee kvnl@cs.princeton.edu Graduate Researcher Princeton University Joint work with Ben Kaiser, Jonathan Mayer, Arvind Narayanan Special thanks to Mihir Kshirsagar</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What are SIM swap attacks?</p>
    <p>Victim</p>
    <p>Hi, Im Victim and I need to move my cell service over to a new SIM card.</p>
    <p>Sure, Victim. Lets confirm its you. Please provide the answer to challenge Y.</p>
    <p>The answer to that challenge is Z.</p>
    <p>Thats correct. Your service has been moved to the new SIM card.</p>
    <p>SMS</p>
    <p>Victims Carrier</p>
    <p>Adversary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What are SIM swap attacks?</p>
    <p>Victim</p>
    <p>Hi, Im Victim and I need to move my cell service over to a new SIM card.</p>
    <p>Sure, Victim. Lets confirm its you. Please provide the answer to challenge Y.</p>
    <p>The answer to that challenge is Z.</p>
    <p>Thats correct. Your service has been moved to the new SIM card.</p>
    <p>SMS</p>
    <p>Victims Carrier</p>
    <p>Adversary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>September 5, 2019</p>
    <p>Attackers can intercept messages and calls</p>
    <p>Leads to financial loss, account hijacking, impersonation, and denial of service</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All five carriers had flawed policies</p>
    <p>Attack 100% successful on major carriers, 40% success on virtual carriers</p>
    <p>Insecure authentication challenges across all carriers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key vulnerability: Manipulable information</p>
    <p>Date/amount of last payment (2 carriers)</p>
    <p>No authentication when making payments, so an attacker can make a payment, then use</p>
    <p>that information to authenticate</p>
    <p>Recently called numbers (incoming and outgoing) (3 carriers)</p>
    <p>Attackers can trick victims into placing or receiving calls</p>
    <p>Reponse: After reviewing our research, T-Mobile informed us that they no longer</p>
    <p>uses call logs for customer authentication (January 2020)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key vulnerability: Customer service reps</p>
    <p>Allowed SIM swaps without authentication</p>
    <p>Forgot to authenticate</p>
    <p>Proceeded despite failed attempts</p>
    <p>Disclosed information without authentication</p>
    <p>Guided our guesses</p>
    <p>Leaked billing address</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why does this matter?</p>
    <p>We reverse-engineered the authentication policies of 145 websites that support</p>
    <p>phone-based authentication.</p>
    <p>We examined the MFA schemes and recovery option pairs</p>
    <p>Limitation: accounts were not linked to assets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Most sites dont stand up well to SIM swaps</p>
    <p>Eighty three (a majority) websites default to insecure configurations</p>
    <p>Seventeen websites allow SMS recovery allowed alongside SMS 2FA</p>
    <p>We notified these vulnerable websites (January 2020)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you! Full findings, recommendations, carrier/website responses: issms2fasecure.com Email: kvnl@cs.princeton.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
