<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Industry Responses to the European Directive on Security</p>
    <p>of Network and Information Systems (NIS)</p>
    <p>Image credit: Terrence J Sullivan. CC Licensed. https://www.flickr.com/photos/25116523@N07/2612501905</p>
    <p>Dr Ola Michalec, Dr Sveta Milyaeva, Dr Dirk van der Linden, Prof Awais Rashid</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Operational Technologies (OT): engineering equipment used in critical infrastructure sectors (e.g. water, energy, transport). Traditionally built for safety and resilience</p>
    <p>Now OT are becoming digitised and connected to the Internet. This creates new avenues for cyber security attacks: blackouts in power stations, pollution of water supply, hacked traffic signals.</p>
    <p>The Network and Information Systems Security (NIS) directive aims to improve the baseline level of security across critical infrastructures. Since 2018, the European Union member states and the UK have been working on implementing it.</p>
    <p>Many questions arising: How to define the scope of the policy? How will NIS impact digital innovation? How to evidence OT are secure enough? How to ensure NIS wont become a tick-box exercise?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research design Semi-structured interviews with 30 cyber security professionals in</p>
    <p>CNIs, consultancies, law firms, public sector (October 2019-January 2020)</p>
    <p>Research questions 1. How is the knowledge of OT security created?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings: how OT security expertise is created</p>
    <p>practitioners skilled in both engineering and computer sciences.  The quality and expertise of OT professionals is inconsistent due to the</p>
    <p>varied routes into the career. Without recognised qualifications, employers face a challenge to identify capable candidates.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings: OT security tropes (example)</p>
    <p>Trope: IIoT is inevitable</p>
    <p>Analysis: The discourse of &quot;inevitability&quot; of innovation is consciously perpetuated by the IIoT manufacturers.</p>
    <p>CNI operators and regulators play an active role in deciding on the future of IIoT and other innovative</p>
    <p>technologies.</p>
    <p>Risk to NIS: Regulations becoming a vehicle for implementing IIoT for its own sake, without</p>
    <p>concerning security and other public values.</p>
    <p>NIS Recommendations for regulators: align the timescales of innovation funding, regular upgrades and NIS improvement plans. Seek robust evidence for the</p>
    <p>claims on the operational benefits of IIoT before approving funding.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key messages</p>
    <p>disagree?</p>
    <p>place before key decisions are made.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Teaser: Four types of NIS implementation practices</p>
    <p>Compliance Workaround Going above and beyond policy remit</p>
    <p>Negotiation</p>
    <p>Security Example</p>
    <p>Completing asset discovery as an essential basis for further cyber improvements</p>
    <p>OT experts implementing their own security measures, using policy as a sanity check</p>
    <p>Intelligence sharing through a working group set based on trust and shared terms of reference</p>
    <p>Operators giving feedback to regulators: asking to improve IT security-biased language of policy documents</p>
    <p>Insecurity example</p>
    <p>Interpreting the scope of NIS to own advantage, while excluding key OT assets</p>
    <p>Senior executives ignoring the need for improvements, based on their own interpretations of appropriate and proportionate clause in NIS</p>
    <p>Overreliance on the latest buzzword technologies when basic knowledge about them is missing</p>
    <p>Prioritizing business values over public values in policy interpretation (considering securing assets at the expense of customers privacy)</p>
    <p>* Please see our full paper for more details!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommended reading: Frey, S., Rashid, A., Zanutto, A., Busby, J. and Follis, K. (2016) On the Role of Latent Design Conditions in Cyber-Physical Systems Security. 2nd International</p>
    <p>Workshop on Software Engineering for Cyber Physical Systems</p>
    <p>Hallet, J., Larson, R. and Rashid, A. (2018) Mirror, Mirror, On the Wall: What are we Teaching Them All? Characterising the Focus of Cybersecurity Curricular</p>
    <p>Frameworks. USENIX Workshop on Advances in Security Education.</p>
    <p>Rashid, A., Gardiner, J., Green, B. and Craggs, B (2019) Everything is Awesome! Or is it? Cyber Security Risks in Critical Infrastructure, CRITIS</p>
    <p>Slayton, R. and Ginsberg, A. (2018) Beyond regulatory capture: Coproducing expertise for critical infrastructure protection. Regulation and Governance. 12</p>
    <p>(1), pp. 115-130</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you for your attention. Any questions?</p>
    <p>Email: ola.michalec@bristol.ac.uk</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
