<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Ethnographic Understanding of Software (In)Security and a Co-Creation Model to Improve Secure Software Development</p>
    <p>* Both are first authors</p>
    <p>Hernan Palombo*, Armin Ziaie Tabari*, Daniel Lende, Jay Ligatti, Xinming Ou University of South Florida, Tampa, FL, USA</p>
    <p>This research is supported by the U.S. National Science Foundation under Grant No. 1801633 and 1801545.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Are Developers to Blame?</p>
    <p>Hala Assal Sonia Chiasson</p>
    <p>Our work highlights the need to look beyond the individual and take a holistic approach to investigate organizational issues influencing software security.</p>
    <p>Rather than blaming developers, our analysis shows that the problem extends up in company hierarchies.</p>
    <p>Security in the software development life cycle, SOUPS 2018</p>
    <p>Think secure from the beginning: A survey with software developers, CHI 2019</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Do the Research as an Anthropologist  Studying the problem within the</p>
    <p>context of where the process happens</p>
    <p>Studying developers in their native habitat</p>
    <p>From the Native's Point of View: On the Nature of Anthropological Understanding, Clifford Geertz, Bulletin of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Methods Data analysis through coding the fieldnotes</p>
    <p>Two embedded researchers</p>
    <p>Regular discussion with a larger research team</p>
    <p>Co-creating interventions</p>
    <p>Security knowledge</p>
    <p>Participant Observation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Tale of Two Stories</p>
    <p>First researcher spent one year.</p>
    <p>Second researcher spent 6 months.</p>
    <p>One and a half years data in total</p>
    <p>performed the same tasks as a regular developer. uncovered several vulnerabilities in the companys product. provided advices on how to fix them.</p>
    <p>The researchers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main Findings</p>
    <p>Security researchers need to understand the competing business demands under which developers work</p>
    <p>Security can be integrated into software development through a co-creation model</p>
    <p>Co-creation is more effective when it happens in the moment, and when security experts understand the competing demands the software development team faces in a business environment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You For Your Attention</p>
    <p>Hernan Palombo hpalombo@usf.edu Armin Ziaie Tabari aziaietabari@usf.edu Daniel Lende dlende@usf.edu Jay Ligatti ligatti@usf.edu Xinming Ou xou@usf.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
