<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I Have a Narrow Thought Process: Constraints on Explanations Connecting Inferences and Self-Perceptions Emilee Rader, Samantha Hautea, and Anjali Munasinghe emilee@msu.edu, hauteasa@msu.edu, amunasinghe1620@gmail.com Department of Media and Information, Michigan State University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>https://www.flickr.com/photos/newspaperclub/20905735770/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/internet-noise.jpg</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Google Ad SettingsFacebook Ad Preferences</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach...</p>
    <p>Show people the inferences Facebook or Google had made about them  Elicit participants' explanations for the connection (or lack thereof) between</p>
    <p>themselves and the inferences</p>
    <p>Focus on why some inferences may be easier for them to relate to themselves than others</p>
    <p>Understand what makes inferences make sense to people  Identify implications for informed consent to inferences</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Step 1: Survey to rate inferences 95 respondents, 44 Facebook and 51 Google</p>
    <p>sensible: It makes sense that [inference] is associated with me.  relevant: [inference] is relevant to who I am as a person.  accurate: [inference] is an accurate description of my everyday activities.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Number of Mean ID Gender Age Aware? Inferences Accuracy</p>
    <p>Fa ce</p>
    <p>bo ok</p>
    <p>Pa rt</p>
    <p>ic ip</p>
    <p>an ts P01 Woman 62 No 20 5.05</p>
    <p>P02 Woman 28 No 26 5.44 P10 Man 44 Unsure 25 4.48 P11 Man 63 No 24 5.62 P13 Woman 28 No 33 4.39 P15 Woman 44 Yes 14 4.00 P16 Woman 34 No 25 4.84 P20 Man 38 Unsure 26 4.42</p>
    <p>G oo</p>
    <p>gl e</p>
    <p>Pa rt</p>
    <p>ic ip</p>
    <p>an ts</p>
    <p>P03 Man 38 No 59 4.05 P04 Woman 32 No 98 4.76 P05 Man 29 Yes 63 2.32 P07 Man 71 No 62 4.44 P08 Woman 59 Unsure 83 4.49 P09 Woman 63 No 40 4.78 P12 Man 31 No 48 3.77 P14 Man 30 No 94 4.68 P17 Woman 48 No 65 3.54 P18 Woman 30 No 104 3.87 P19 Man 38 No 44 3.05 P21 Woman 40 No 46 4.00 P22 Woman 43 No 109 3.07</p>
    <p>Table 2: Characteristics of the interview participants. Aware indicates whether the participant had previously seen the platforms inferences web page. Mean Accuracy is the average of each participants responses to the accuracy survey question about each inference. Higher means greater perceived accuracy on a scale of 17.</p>
    <p>For respondents with a very large number of inferences assigned to them, our code randomly selected 85 to ask about, because our pilot testing indicated that any more than this would result in an excessively long survey. The last question in the survey asked if respondents would be interested in participating in a follow-up interview, and 57% said yes and provided their contact information. On average, it took 32.5 minutes (SD=91) to complete the survey. Ninety-five respondents completed the survey (44 Facebook, 51 Google; 28 men, 66 women, 1 did not disclose gender). Eighty-seven percent of respondents were white, 7% were Asian, and the remaining respondents reported multiple ethnicities. Further demographics are presented in Table 1. Respondents who completed the survey received a $5 USD Amazon gift card. The survey questions are included in Appendix A.</p>
    <p>3DUWLFLSDQW1DPH)DFHERRN,QIRUPDWLRQ )LSV^PZ[OLPUMVYTH[PVU`V\HUZ^LYLKX\LZ[PVUZHIV\[^OLU`V\SSLKV\[[OLZ\Y]L @V\HUZ^LYLK [OYLLX\LZ[PVUZMVYLHJOWPLJLVMPUMVYTH[PVU!</p>
    <p>B?DPZYLSL]HU[[V^OV0HTHZHWLYZVU B?DPZHUHJJ\YH[LKLZJYPW[PVUVMT`L]LY`KH`HJ[P]P[PLZ 0[THRLZZLUZL[OH[B?DPZHZZVJPH[LK^P[OTL</p>
    <p>;OLJVSVYZPULHJO[HISLILSV^YLWYLZLU[[OLH]LYHNLVM`V\YYLZWVUZLZ[V[OL[OYLLX\LZ[PVUZMVYLHJO WPLJLVMPUMVYTH[PVU;OLSLNLUKPSS\Z[YH[LZ^OH[[OLJVSVYZTLHU!</p>
    <p>Figure 1: Example excerpt from a Facebook inferences report generated from data about one of the authors.</p>
    <p>about this in the Findings section). At that point we decided to conduct more of the remaining interviews with Google participants than Facebook participants. We conducted 22 interviews, but excluded P06 before analysis due to a high proportion of low quality, off-topic answers to questions. Of the 21 remaining interviews, 9 were with men and 12 with women, and 8 focused on Facebook inferences while 13 focused on Google inferences. Interview participants ranged in age from 28 to 71 (Mean=43). Most participants were currently or formerly employed as knowledge workers (e.g., staff or instructors at the university; teachers; working in local government; retired). See Table 2 for further information about the interview participants.</p>
    <p>Each interview began by showing the participant a report that we generated which included the inferences they had answered questions about in the survey, and the average of the ratings of the three questions asked about each inference, rounded to the nearest whole number and then color-coded according to the position of the average on the 7-point disagreeagree Likert scale. The report was designed to be a simple artifact that enabled us to elicit participants reactions to the inferences, independent of the jargon and branding on the platforms own pages. The last page of the report also showed inferences that were unique to each participant among the survey respondents who had been assigned the same platform, and inferences that all survey respondents asked about that platform had been assigned. See Figure 1 for an excerpt of a report generated using the inferences of one of the authors. The interview protocol and example Facebook and Google inference reports are included in Appendix C.</p>
    <p>The semi-structured interview protocol included questions designed to investigate participants beliefs about why and how the inferences had been assigned to them, and about what the inferences are used for by Facebook and Google. Care was taken to elicit participants thoughts and reactions in their own words and to ask non-leading follow-up questions, so that the interviewers did not impart a sense that technical correctness or incorrectness was an important framework for thinking about the inferences or prime their answers in other ways. We also avoided using the word privacy in the interviews unless the participant mentioned it first, to avoid influencing their reactions to the inferences. Interviews lasted 30-40 minutes,</p>
    <p>$UWV (QWHUWDLQPHQW</p>
    <p>$XWRV 9HKLFOHV</p>
    <p>&amp;RPSXWHUV (OHFWURQLFV</p>
    <p>Step 2: Interviews about reactions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Types of reactions Plausible, Implausible, and No Connection</p>
    <p>Plausible reactions: were believable, with specific evidence for why it made sense</p>
    <p>Example: [Parents (All)] Because I have three kids, well, a lot of my posts are about my kids.  P13, Woman, Facebook</p>
    <p>Implausible reactions: were initially not believable, but then rationalized</p>
    <p>Example: [Coffee &amp; Tea] I dont drink coffee. My husband does though. So again maybe, you know? P18, Woman, Google</p>
    <p>No Connection reactions: did not make sense, and participants were certain it did not apply to them</p>
    <p>Example: [Golf Equipment] I dont know why thats on there... golf equipment? I dont golf. Thats weird. P04, Woman, Google</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acceptance and Discomfort Coexist</p>
    <p>I mean, theres a level of acceptance that it happens, but then the more you think about it, it kind of starts to disturb you a little bit more... some of the things that they make connections for, it takes you a while in your head to get to how they got to that. And its a little bit, I dont know, disconcerting or something. Its just a little bit uncomfortable. P22, Woman, Google</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Platforms which place a priority on obtaining truly informed consent should restrict the inferences they make about users to those which provoke plausible reactions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Emilee Rader, Samantha Hautea, and Anjali Munasinghe emilee@msu.edu, hauteasa@msu.edu, amunasinghe1620@gmail.com Department of Media and Information, Michigan State University</p>
    <p>Thank You! I Have a Narrow Thought Process: Constraints on Explanations Connecting Inferences and Self-Perceptions</p>
    <p>This presentation is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under Grant No. CNS-1524296.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
