<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From Intent to Action: Nudging Users Towards Secure Mobile</p>
    <p>Payments Peter Story, Daniel Smullen, Alessandro Acquisti, Lorrie Faith Cranor,</p>
    <p>Norman Sadeh, Florian Schaub</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experts Advice  Users Behavior</p>
    <p>Hloom via Flickr / CC BY-SA, 401(K) 2013</p>
    <p>Mybloodtypeiscoffee via Wikimedia Commons</p>
    <p>Low adoption of secure mobile payments in the United States</p>
    <p>We investigated interventions with the potential to increase adoption</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Nudges</p>
    <p>Nudges help people act as they say they want to</p>
    <p>In our study:</p>
    <p>Protection Motivation Theory (PMT) nudge</p>
    <p>Implementation Intentions (II) nudge</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Longitudinal interviews (n=20)</p>
    <p>Longitudinal experiment (n=411)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Design</p>
    <p>Recruitment</p>
    <p>ControlPMT+IIPMT</p>
    <p>Follow-up: Used Apple Pay?</p>
    <p>One week later</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protection Motivation Theory Nudge</p>
    <p>Threat susceptibility</p>
    <p>Threat severity</p>
    <p>Response efficacy</p>
    <p>Self-efficacy</p>
    <p>S. Milne, P. Sheeran, and S. Orbell, Prediction and Intervention in HealthRelated Behavior: A MetaAnalytic Review of Protection</p>
    <p>Motivation Theory, Journal of Applied Social Psychology, vol. 30, no. 1, pp. 106143, Jan. 2000.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Threat Susceptibility: Recent Cases of Card Information Theft</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Threat Severity: The Consequences of Card Fraud</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Response Efficacy: The Security Protections of Mobile Payments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Self-efficacy: Instructions for Using Mobile Payments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation Intentions Nudge</p>
    <p>A concrete, contextually activated plan to achieve a goal</p>
    <p>Designed to help people remember to take an action</p>
    <p>P. M. Gollwitzer, Implementation intentions: strong effects of simple plans, American Psychologist, vol. 54, no. 7, 1999.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation Intention Template</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation Intention Template</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation Intention Template</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation Intention Template</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Treatments Made Participants More Likely To Use Apple Pay</p>
    <p>Use of Apple Pay was significantly more likely in the PMT and PMT+II groups than in the control</p>
    <p>Difference between PMT and PMT+II was not statistically significant</p>
    <p>Percent that used Apple Pay</p>
    <p>Control PMT PMT+II</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Treatments Made Participants More Likely To Agree That Apple Pay Would Protect Them</p>
    <p>If I were to start using Apple Pay regularly, I would be less likely to be a victim of card fraud.</p>
    <p>Strongly agree Agree Disagree Strongly disagree</p>
    <p>Control PMT PMT+II</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Our PMT nudge corrected misconceptions about mobile payments and our II nudge helped people plan to use mobile payments</p>
    <p>Both PMT and PMT+II treatments increased adoption of Apple Pay</p>
    <p>PMT and II nudges may help increase adoption of other tools and practices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Peter Story PhD Student, Carnegie Mellon University pstory@andrew.cmu.edu https://peterstory.me</p>
    <p>From Intent to Action: Nudging Users Towards Secure Mobile Payments</p>
    <p>Peter Story, Daniel Smullen, Alessandro Acquisti, Lorrie Faith Cranor, Norman Sadeh, Florian Schaub</p>
    <p>This research was supported in part by grants from the National Science Foundations Secure and Trustworthy Computing program (CNS-1330596, SES-1513957, CNS-1801316).</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
