<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Secure, Archival Storage With POTSHARDS</p>
    <p>Mark W. Storer Kevin M. Greenan Ethan L. Miller Kaladhar Voruganti</p>
    <p>FAST WIP Session February 14, 2007</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem: Long-Term Encryption  Keys may be lost</p>
    <p>Effectively short-term data deletion  Not long-term deletion</p>
    <p>Keys may be compromised  Affects the secrecy of every file encrypted with that key</p>
    <p>Even in the best case, is encryption ideal for long-term data?  Key management is complicated by long data lifetimes  Encryption is only computationally secure</p>
    <p>- Hard to predict the future of cryptanalysis - Future advances may compromise a lot of data in a short time</p>
    <p>Difficult to re-encrypt petabytes of data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Possible Solution: Secret Splitting  Create n pieces of data, m of which are required to recovery</p>
    <p>the original data  XOR based (fast by typically n out of n)  Linear interpolation based (Shamir)</p>
    <p>Provably secure  Any less than m pieces reveals no information  Encryption is only computational secure</p>
    <p>Reconstruction not dependent on a single key  Encryption keys are a single point of failure  No secret share is more important than the others</p>
    <p>=SR1 Rn-1 S...R2 A simple n of n secret sharing algorithm using XOR</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>POTSHARDS: Overview</p>
    <p>Archive 0 Archive 1 Archive 2 Archive 3</p>
    <p>Shard</p>
    <p>Shard</p>
    <p>Parity</p>
    <p>Shard</p>
    <p>Shard Y</p>
    <p>Shard</p>
    <p>Shard X</p>
    <p>User</p>
    <p>Redundancy Group</p>
    <p>Fragment Fragment Fragment</p>
    <p>Object</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>POTSHARDS: Data Recovery  Need to hide relationship between shards from intruders  Need to provide sufficient hints to allow reconstruction</p>
    <p>from just the shards  Solution: approximate pointers</p>
    <p>Point to a range of shards rather than just one  No way to verify correctness of a tuple until all the shards</p>
    <p>have been gathered</p>
    <p>Shard 00</p>
    <p>Shard 01</p>
    <p>Shard</p>
    <p>Shard 02</p>
    <p>Shard</p>
    <p>Shard 03</p>
    <p>Shard Shard</p>
    <p>Shard</p>
    <p>Shard</p>
    <p>Shard</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions</p>
    <p>Thanks to our sponsors:  SSRC industrial sponsors  Los Alamos National Laboratory /</p>
    <p>Institute for Scalable Scientific Data Management</p>
    <p>Petascale Data Storage Institute  Thanks to POTSHARDS team members</p>
    <p>Kevin M. Greenan  Professor Ethan L. Miller  Kaladhar Voruganti (IBM Almaden Research Lab)</p>
    <p>http://www.ssrc.ucsc.edu/proj/archive.html</p>
    <p>The great secret that all old people share is that you really haven't changed in seventy or eighty years. Your body changes, but you don't change at all. And that, of course, causes great confusion.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
