<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Using Provenance for Repeatability</p>
    <p>Quan Pham1, Tanu Malik2, Ian Foster1,2 Department of Computer Science1, and Computation Institute2,</p>
    <p>University of Chicago, and Argonne National Laboratory TaPP 2013</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Publication Process</p>
    <p>Submit paper  Review ideas &amp;experiments</p>
    <p>Learn novel methods.</p>
    <p>Traditional academic publication process</p>
    <p>Emerging academic publication process</p>
    <p>Submit paper  Review ideas &amp;experiments</p>
    <p>Validate software</p>
    <p>Are we reading something that is repeatable and reproducible?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Repeatability Testing</p>
    <p>Scientific progress relies on novel claims and verifiable results</p>
    <p>Scientific paper reviewers  Validate announced results  Validate for different</p>
    <p>data and parameters  Validate under different</p>
    <p>conditions and environments</p>
    <p>Challenge: Work under time &amp; budget constraints</p>
    <p>Image: from http://catsandtheirmews.blogspot.com/2012/05/update-on-computer-crash.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Repeatability Testing Challenges &amp; Constraints</p>
    <p>Repeatability requirements  Hardware : Single machine/Clusters  Software  Operating System : Which operating system was used? (Ubuntu/RedHat/Debian)  Environment: How to capture all environment variables?  Tools &amp; libraries installation: How to precisely know all the dependencies?</p>
    <p>Knowledge constraints  Experiment setup: how to setup the experiment?  Experiment usage: how the experiment is run?</p>
    <p>Resource constraints  Requires massive processing power.  Operates on large amounts of data.  Performs significant network communication.  Is long-running.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Approach to Repeatability Testing</p>
    <p>Challenges &amp; Constraints Possible Solutions</p>
    <p>Repeatability requirements  Hardware requirement  Software requirement</p>
    <p>Provide a virtual machine</p>
    <p>Provide a portable software</p>
    <p>Knowledge constraints  Experiment setup  Experiment usage</p>
    <p>Provide a reference execution</p>
    <p>Resource constraints Provide selective replay</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PTU  Provenance-To-Use</p>
    <p>PTU  Minimizes computation time during repeatability testing  Guarantees that events are processed in the same order using</p>
    <p>the same data</p>
    <p>Authors build a package that includes:  Software program  Input data  Provenance trace</p>
    <p>Testers may select a subset of the packages processes for a partial deterministic replay</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PTU Functionalities</p>
    <p>ptu-audit tool  Build a package of authors source code, data, and</p>
    <p>environment variables  Record process- and file-level details about a reference</p>
    <p>execution</p>
    <p>PTU package  Display the provenance graph and accompanying run-time</p>
    <p>details</p>
    <p>ptu-exec tool  Re-execute specified part of the provenance graph</p>
    <p>% ptu-audit java TextAnalyzer news.txt</p>
    <p>% ptu-exec java TextAnalyzer news.txt</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ptu-audit</p>
    <p>Uses ptrace to monitor system calls  execve, sys_fork  read, write, sys_io  bind, connect, socket</p>
    <p>Collects provenance</p>
    <p>Collects runtime information</p>
    <p>Makes package</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ptu-audit</p>
    <p>Use ptrace to monitor system calls  execve, sys_fork  read, write, sys_io  bind, connect, socket</p>
    <p>Collect provenance</p>
    <p>Collect runtime info</p>
    <p>Make package</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PTU Package</p>
    <p>[Figure 2. The PTU package. The tester chooses to run the sub-graph rooted at /bin/calculate ]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ptu-exec</p>
    <p>[Figure 3. ptu-exec re-runs part of the application from /bin/calculate. It uses CDE to re-route file dependencies]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current PTU Components</p>
    <p>Uses CDE (Code-Data-Environment) tool to create a package  CDE is a tool to package code, data, and environment</p>
    <p>required to deploy and run your Linux programs on other machines without any installation or configuration</p>
    <p>Uses ptrace to create a provenance graph representing a reference run-time execution</p>
    <p>Uses SQLite to store the provenance graph</p>
    <p>Uses graphviz for graph presentation</p>
    <p>Enhances CDE to run the package</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PEEL0</p>
    <p>Best, N., et. al., Synthesis of a Complete Land Use/ Land Cover Dataset for the Conterminous United States. RDCEP Working Paper, 2012. 12(08).</p>
    <p>Wget  Bash</p>
    <p>script</p>
    <p>R  Raster  Rgdal  Reclassify</p>
    <p>R  Geo</p>
    <p>algorithm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PEEL0</p>
    <p>[Figure 4: Time reduction in testing PEEL0 using PTU]</p>
    <p>Or use the actual execution graph??</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TextAnalyzer</p>
    <p>Murphy, J., et. al., Textual Hydraulics: Mining Online Newspapers to Detect Physical, Social, and Institutional Water Management Infrastructure, 2013, Technical Report, Argonne National Lab.</p>
    <p>runs a named-entity recognition analysis program using several data dictionaries</p>
    <p>splits the input file into multiple input files on which it runs a parallel analysis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TextAnalyzer</p>
    <p>[Figure 5. Time reduction in testing TextAnalyzer using PTU]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>PTU is a step toward testing software programs that are submitted to conference proceedings and journals to conduct repeatability tests</p>
    <p>Easy and attractive for authors</p>
    <p>Fine control, efficient way for testers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Works</p>
    <p>Other workflow type  Distributed workflows.</p>
    <p>Improve performance  Decide how to store provenance compactly in a</p>
    <p>package.</p>
    <p>Presentation  Improve graphic-user-interface and presentation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgements</p>
    <p>Neil Best</p>
    <p>Jonathan Ozik</p>
    <p>Center for Robust Decision making on Climate and Energy Policy (NSF grant number 0951576)</p>
    <p>Contractors of the US Government under contract number DEAC02-06CH11357</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
