<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cybercasing the Joint: On the Privacy Implications of Geo-Tagging</p>
    <p>Gerald Friedland, Robin Sommer International Computer Science Institute Berkeley, CA fractor,robin@icsi.berkeley.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is Geotagging?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Geo-Tagging?</p>
    <p>Allows easier clustering of photo and video series as well as additional services.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Geo-Tagging?</p>
    <p>Part of location-based service hype:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Support for Geo-Tags</p>
    <p>Allows easy search, retrieval, and ad placement.</p>
    <p>Social media portals provide APIs to connect geo-tags with metadata, accounts, and web content.</p>
    <p>Portal % Total YouTube (estimate) 3.0 3M Flickr 4.5 180M</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problems</p>
    <p>People are unaware of</p>
    <p>a. high resolution of sensors b. large amount of geo-tagged data c. easy-to-use APIs allow fast retrieval</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Be careful when using social location sharing services, such as FourSquare.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Mayhemic Labs, June 2010: Are you aware that Tweets are geo-tagged?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can you do real harm?</p>
    <p>Cybercasing: Using online (location-based) data and services to mount real-world attacks.</p>
    <p>Three Case Studies:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study 1: Twitter</p>
    <p>Pictures in Tweets can be geo-located  From an undisclosed celebrity we found:</p>
    <p>Home location (several pics)  Where the kids go to school  The place where he/she walks the dog  Secret office</p>
    <p>Systematic search: picfog.com 10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Celebs unaware of GeoTagging</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Celebs unaware of Geotagging</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Google Maps shows Address...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study 2: Craigslist</p>
    <p>Many ads with geo-location otherwise anonymized</p>
    <p>Sometimes selling high-valued goods, e.g. cars, diamonds</p>
    <p>Sometimes call Sunday after 6pm Multiple photos allow interpolation of</p>
    <p>coordinates for higher accuracy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Craigslist: Real Example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Geo-Tagging Resolution</p>
    <p>Measured accuracy: +/- 1m Figure 1: Photo of a bike taken with an iPhone 3G and a corresponding Google Street View image based on the stored geocoordinates. The accuracy of the camera location (marked) in front of the garage is about +/!1 m. Many classified advertisement sites contain photos describing objects for sale taken at home that automatically contain geo-tagging.</p>
    <p>tion would make it easy to increase the confidence in the results further. Geo-location can also be exploited for the taking the</p>
    <p>opposite route: findingacelebritysnon-advertisedTwitter feed intended only for private purposes (e.g., for exchanging messages with their personal friends5). Doing so becomes possible by sites such as Picfog, which allows anybody to search all images appearing on Twitter by keyword and geo-location in real-time. Having a rough idea of where a person lives thus allows to tailor queries accordingly until the right photo shows up. As an experiment,we succeeded to find a non-advertised butpublicly-accessibleTwitter-feedofacelebrityhaving a residence in Beverly Hills, CA.6 Note that while our scenario focused on celebrities,</p>
    <p>similar strategies obviously apply to tracking any person publishing geo-locations in similar ways. YouTube. In our final setup, we examined whether</p>
    <p>one can semi-automatically identify the home addresses of people who normally live in a certain area but are currently on vacation. Such knowledge offers opportunities for burglars to break into their unoccupied houses. We wrote a script using the YouTube API that, given a home location, a radius, and a keyword,findsa set of matching videos. For all the videos found, the script then gathers the associated YouTube user names and downloads all videos that are a certain vacation distance away and have been uploaded the same week. In our first experiment, we set the home location to be</p>
    <p>in Berkeley,CA, downtownand the radius to 100km. As the keyword to search for we picked kids since many people publish home videos of their children. The vacationdistance was1000miles. Our script reported1000 hits (themaximumamount)for the initial setofmatching videos. These thenexpandedtoabout50,000totalvideos</p>
    <p>Angela Taylor. We are currently also contacting her.</p>
    <p>in the second step identifying all other videos from the correspondingusers. 106of these turnedout tohavebeen taken more than1000miles away anduploaded the same week. Sifting quickly through the titles of these videos, we found about a dozen that looked promising for successful cybercasing. However, we stopped after the first real hit: a video uploaded by a user who was currently traveling in the Caribbean, as could clearly be seen by content, geo-tagging, and the date displayed in the video (one day before our search). The title of the video was first day on the beach. Also, comments posted along with the video on YouTube indicated that the user had posted multiple vacation videos and is usually timely in doing so. When he is not on vacation, he seemed to live with hiskidsnearAlbany,CA (close to Berkeley)as several videos were posted from his home, with the kids playing. Although the geo-locationof each of the videos seemednot todirectlypoint to a single housedue to GPS inaccuracies indoors, the user had posted his real name in the YouTube profile, which would likely make it easy to find the exact locationusing social engineering. In addition, averaging GPS locations across all of his home videos seemed to converge to one particular house.</p>
    <p>We also performed a second search with the same parameters, except for the keyword which we now set to home. This time, we found a person who seemed to have moved from San Francisco to New Jersey. Many of that persons videoshad been geo-taggedwith coordinates at a specific address inSan Francisco. Themost recentvideowasataplace inNewJersey forwhichGoogle Maps offered a real-estate ad that included a price of $399,999. The person had specified age and real name in his YouTube entry.</p>
    <p>Finally, we note that using our 204-line Python script we were able to gather all the data for these two experiments within about 15 minutes each.</p>
    <p>iPhone 3G pictureFigure 1: Photo of a bike taken with an iPhone 3G and a corresponding Google Street View image based on the stored geocoordinates. The accuracy of the camera location (marked) in front of the garage is about +/!1 m. Many classified advertisement sites contain photos describing objects for sale taken at home that automatically contain geo-tagging.</p>
    <p>tion would make it easy to increase the confidence in the results further. Geo-location can also be exploited for the taking the</p>
    <p>opposite route: findingacelebritysnon-advertisedTwitter feed intended only for private purposes (e.g., for exchanging messages with their personal friends5). Doing so becomes possible by sites such as Picfog, which allows anybody to search all images appearing on Twitter by keyword and geo-location in real-time. Having a rough idea of where a person lives thus allows to tailor queries accordingly until the right photo shows up. As an experiment,we succeeded to find a non-advertised butpublicly-accessibleTwitter-feedofacelebrityhaving a residence in Beverly Hills, CA.6 Note that while our scenario focused on celebrities,</p>
    <p>similar strategies obviously apply to tracking any person publishing geo-locations in similar ways. YouTube. In our final setup, we examined whether</p>
    <p>one can semi-automatically identify the home addresses of people who normally live in a certain area but are currently on vacation. Such knowledge offers opportunities for burglars to break into their unoccupied houses. We wrote a script using the YouTube API that, given a home location, a radius, and a keyword,findsa set of matching videos. For all the videos found, the script then gathers the associated YouTube user names and downloads all videos that are a certain vacation distance away and have been uploaded the same week. In our first experiment, we set the home location to be</p>
    <p>in Berkeley,CA, downtownand the radius to 100km. As the keyword to search for we picked kids since many people publish home videos of their children. The vacationdistance was1000miles. Our script reported1000 hits (themaximumamount)for the initial setofmatching videos. These thenexpandedtoabout50,000totalvideos</p>
    <p>Angela Taylor. We are currently also contacting her.</p>
    <p>in the second step identifying all other videos from the correspondingusers. 106of these turnedout tohavebeen taken more than1000miles away anduploaded the same week. Sifting quickly through the titles of these videos, we found about a dozen that looked promising for successful cybercasing. However, we stopped after the first real hit: a video uploaded by a user who was currently traveling in the Caribbean, as could clearly be seen by content, geo-tagging, and the date displayed in the video (one day before our search). The title of the video was first day on the beach. Also, comments posted along with the video on YouTube indicated that the user had posted multiple vacation videos and is usually timely in doing so. When he is not on vacation, he seemed to live with hiskidsnearAlbany,CA (close to Berkeley)as several videos were posted from his home, with the kids playing. Although the geo-locationof each of the videos seemednot todirectlypoint to a single housedue to GPS inaccuracies indoors, the user had posted his real name in the YouTube profile, which would likely make it easy to find the exact locationusing social engineering. In addition, averaging GPS locations across all of his home videos seemed to converge to one particular house.</p>
    <p>We also performed a second search with the same parameters, except for the keyword which we now set to home. This time, we found a person who seemed to have moved from San Francisco to New Jersey. Many of that persons videoshad been geo-taggedwith coordinates at a specific address inSan Francisco. Themost recentvideowasataplace inNewJersey forwhichGoogle Maps offered a real-estate ad that included a price of $399,999. The person had specified age and real name in his YouTube entry.</p>
    <p>Finally, we note that using our 204-line Python script we were able to gather all the data for these two experiments within about 15 minutes each.</p>
    <p>Google Street View</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>People are Unaware of Geo-Tagging</p>
    <p># Model # Model 414 iPhone 3G 6 Canon PowerShot SD780 287 iPhone 3GS 3 MB200 98 iPhone 2 LG LOTUS 32 Droid 2 HERO200 26 SGH-T929 2 BlackBerry 9530 20 Nexus One 1 RAPH800 9 SPH-M900 1 N96 9 RDC-i700 1 DMC-ZS7 6 T-Mobile G1 1 BlackBerry 9630</p>
    <p>Table 1: Devices geo-tagging photos found on Craigslist.</p>
    <p>Craigslist, we examined all postings to the San Franscisco Bay Areas For Sale section over a period of four days (including a weekend). While Craigslist does not provide a dedicated query API, it offers RSS feeds that include the postings full content. Consequently, during our measurement interval, we queried a suitably customized RSS feed every 10 minutes for the most recent 500 postings having images, each time downloading all linked JPEGs that we had not yet seen. In total, we collected 68,729 images, of which about 48% had EXIF information. 914 images were tagged with GPS coordinates, i.e., about 1.3% of the total.3 We presume that this number is lower than what we found for Flickr and YouTube because many photos on Craigslist are edited before posting. Still, already with a cursory look we found several cases where precise locations had the potential to compromise privacy, as we discuss in  4. We also examined the camera models used to take the</p>
    <p>In this section we take the perspective of a potential attacker to investigate examples of cybercasing. We focus on four different scenarios: one on Craigslist, one on Twitter and two on YouTube. Craigslist. In our first scenario, we manually in</p>
    <p>spected a random sample of Craigslist postings containing geo-located images, collected as described in  3. One typical situationwefoundwascarsbeingofferedfor sale with images showing them mostly parked in private parking lots. Most of the time it was straight-forward for us to verify a photos geo-location by comparing the image with what we saw on Google Street View. A fair amount of postings with geo-located images</p>
    <p>also offered other high-valued goods, such as diamonds, obviouslyphotographedat home; making them potential</p>
    <p>targets for burglars. In addition, many offered specifics about when and how the owner wants to be contacted (please call Sunday after 3pm), which allows for speculation about when somebody might be at home. Since manypostingspublishedmore thanone image,andsome locations were the origin of more than one offer, a more accurate estimation of the postal address would have been possible through averaging the geo-tags. While we did not further verify addresses, we set</p>
    <p>up an experiment to assess GPS accuracy in a typical Craigslist setting: We first photographed a bike in front of a garage with an iPhone 3G, as if we wanted to offer it for sale (see Figure 1). When we then entered the geocoordinatesthat thephoneembeddedinto thepicture into Street View, Google was able to locate the photos positionwithin +/!1 m. Suchaccuracy ismuchhigher than what we believe most people would expect. Among the Craigslist postings with geo-information</p>
    <p>we also found a significant number where the poster chose to not specify a home address, phone number, or e-mail account but opted for Craigslists anonymous emailing option. We take this as an indication that many posterswerenotaware that their imagesweregeo-tagged and thus leaked their location. We note that while we only performed experiments</p>
    <p>with Craigslists For Sale category, it is not hard to imagine what consequences unintended geo-tagging might have in Personals or Adult Services. Twitter. Blogging has become a common tool for</p>
    <p>celebrities to provide their fans with updates on their lives, and most of such blogs contain images. Likewise, many celebrities now also use public Twitter feeds that, besides potentially being geo-tagged themselves, may also link to external images they took. Our second scenario therefore involved tracking one of the co-authors favorite reality-show host who is currently very active on Twitter. 4 The celebritys show is broadcast on US national TV and has been exported into various foreign countries. In the latest episodes, the TV channel even started advertising that the host is maintaining a Twitter feed. It turns out that most images posted to that feedincluding photos taken at the hosts studio, places wherehewalkshisdog,andofhishomeweretakenwith an iPhone 3GS and are hosted on TwitPic, which conserves EXIF data. In addition, we noticed that the host is also commonly tweeting while he is on travel or meeting other well-known people away from home. Using the Firefox plug-in Exif Viewer, a right-click on any of the Twitter images suffices to reveal these locationsusing an Internet map service of ones choice. Again, averaging geo-tags from multiple images taken at the same loca</p>
    <p>For Sale section of Bay Area Craigslist.com: 4 days: 68729 pictures total,1.3% geo-tagged</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study 3: YouTube</p>
    <p>Once data is published, the Internet keeps it (in potentially many copies).  APIs are easy to use and allow quick retrieval of large amounts of data  Even simple inference algorithms (across different websites) allow for cybercasing.</p>
    <p>Can we find people on vacation in YouTube?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cybercasing on YouTube Experiment: Cybercasing using the YouTube API (240 lines in Python)</p>
    <p>Location Radius</p>
    <p>Keywords</p>
    <p>YouTube</p>
    <p>Users?</p>
    <p>Query</p>
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Query</p>
    <p>Results Time-Frame</p>
    <p>Distance</p>
    <p>Filter</p>
    <p>Cybercasing Candidates</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cybercasing on YouTube</p>
    <p>Input parameters</p>
    <p>Location: 37.869885,-122.270539 Radius: 100km Keywords: kids Distance: 1000km Time-frame: this_week</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cybercasing on YouTube</p>
    <p>Output Initial videos: 1000 (max_res) User hull: ~50k videos Vacation hits: 106 Cybercasing targets: &gt;12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cybercasing on YouTube</p>
    <p>Output Initial videos: 1000 (max_res) User hull: ~50k videos Vacation hits: 106 Cybercasing targets: &gt;12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solutions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solutions?</p>
    <p>Better Education  More secure default values  Blurring  Scrubbing  Privacy-preserving APIs and policies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The key to avoid wide-spread misuse of location information is clearly educating users about its misuse potential. However, it is our experience that currently even many tech-savvy users find it difficult to accurately assess the risk they face. We thus believe that the security and privacy community needs to take a more active role in shaping the deploymentof this rapidly emerging technology. We deemit crucial to ensure that users (i) are put into a position where they can make informed decisions; and (ii) are sufficiently protected unless they explicitly opt-in to potentially risky exposure. In the following,we frame preliminary suggestions towards this end. On a general level, we encourage our community to</p>
    <p>aim for a consensus on what constitutes an acceptable privacy policy for location-based services. As we discuss, currentapproachesdifferwidelyacrossdevicesand services, and we believe that establishing a unified strategyacrossproviderswouldgoa longway towardsavoiding user confusionand thus unnecessaryexposure. More specifically, we claim that a global opt-out approach to sharing high accuracy location-information is almost always inappropriate. Rather, users should need to acknowledge usage at least on a per-application basis. Apples iPhone takes a step into the right direction by requesting permission each time a new application wants to access the GPS sensor. However, its user interface still has two short-comings: (i) it doesnot apply that policy to photos/videos taken with the internal camera; and (ii) for each application, it is an all-or-nothing decision. Regarding the latter, it seems that often simply reducing a locations resolution might already be a suitable tradeoff. As an experiment on how such an approach could be supported, Figure 2 shows a mockup we did for extending the iPhones standard permission request dialog with a slider allowing to choose an acceptable resolution in intuitive terms. According to the choice, the device would then strip off a correspondingnumberof the leastsignificant digits of any coordinates. 7 Not only would this give users more control, but it would also explicitly point out that house-level accuracy is in the cards. From a research perspective, it is stimulating to think</p>
    <p>about how APIs such as offered by Flickr and YouTube could be redesigned to offer a higher level of privacy without restricting the benefits of geo-technology. One straight-forwardwaywouldbefor them to reducethe resolution; that however would limit some services significantly. Conceptually more interesting is to leverage approaches from related fields such as privacy-preserving data mining. As discussed  2, researchers have started to examinesuch approaches,yet we are not aware of any</p>
    <p>Figure 2: Our mockup of a mobile-phone dialog to give users more control over the geo-location embedded in their photos.</p>
    <p>real-world API that incorporates these ideas.</p>
    <p>This article makes a case for the emerging privacy issue caused by wide-spread adaptation of location-enabled photoand video capturingdevices, allowing potential attackers to easily case out joints in cyberspace. Several factors aggravate the problem. First, many people are either unaware of the fact that photos and videos taken with their cell phones contain geo-location, especially with such accuracy; or what consequences publishing the information may have. Second, even experts tend to neglect the easy search capabilities of todays online APIs and the resulting inference possibilities. Third, the fact that only a small percentage of all data is currently geo-tagged must not mislead us to ignore the problem because (i) with all the commercial pressure, the number seems poised to rise; and (ii) our preliminary experiments demonstrate that even a seemingly small fraction like 1% can already translate into several hundred relevant cases within just a small geographical area. Finally, we want to emphasize that we are not advo</p>
    <p>cating a ban of geo-location in general or geo-tagging specifically. It is a wonderful technology that drives innovation in manyareas. However,we feel there is a clear need foreducationaswell as for researchhowto best design systems to be location-awarewhile at the same time offer maximum protection against privacy infringement.</p>
    <p>References</p>
    <p>[1] David Crandall, Lars Backstrom, Dan Huttenlocher, and Jon Kleinberg. Mapping the Worlds PhotosMapping the Worlds Photos. In Proc. WWW, 2009.</p>
    <p>[2] EFF. On Locational Privacy, and How to Avoid Losing it Forever. http://www.eff.org/wp/locational-privacy.</p>
    <p>[3] Ian Goldberg Ge Zhong and Urs Hengartner. Louis, Lester and Pierre: Three Protocols for Location Privacy. In Proc. Privacy Enhancing Technologies Symposium, 2007.</p>
    <p>[4] John Krumm. A Survey of Computational Location Privacy. Personal and Ubiquitous Computing, 13(6):391399, 2009.</p>
    <p>Proposal: Opt-In with Choice of Accuracy</p>
    <p>Mockup of a privacy-improved iPhone dialog</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Geo-location offers great opportunities and we should continue to explore them</p>
    <p>However it can pose real-world risks</p>
    <p>Therefore, we should:  Raise the awareness on privacy issues  Discuss policies and interfaces</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Are you concerned?</p>
    <p>What is a good trade-off between privacy and utility?</p>
    <p>How can we design policies and APIs to implement the trade-off?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
