<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SRCMap: Energy Proportional Storage using</p>
    <p>Dynamic Consolidation</p>
    <p>Akshat Verma1 Ricardo Koller2 Luis Useche2</p>
    <p>Raju Rangaswami2</p>
    <p>FAST Conference, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current power density of data centers is 100 W/sq.ft &amp; increasing 15-20% per year.</p>
    <p>Storage consume 10-25% of computing equipment.</p>
    <p>Storage load low (10-30%), but still peak power consumed.</p>
    <p>CPUs are more energy proportionality than storage.</p>
    <p>Consolidation is a well known technique for energy proportionality in virtualized servers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Storage Consolidation?</p>
    <p>Can we use a storage virtualization layer to design a practical energy proportional storage system?</p>
    <p>Storage virtualization I/O indirection useful for consolidation.</p>
    <p>Challenge</p>
    <p>Moving logical volumes from one device to another is prohibitively expensive.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background: Storage Virtualization</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workloads</p>
    <p>mail Our department mail server.</p>
    <p>web-vm Virtual machine hosting two web-servers: CS web-mail &amp; online course management.</p>
    <p>homes NFS server that serves the home directories for our research group.</p>
    <p>Block traces collected downstream of an active page cache for three weeks.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observations</p>
    <p>Observation 1</p>
    <p>The active data set is only a small fraction of total storage used. (about 1.5-6.5%)</p>
    <p>Observation 2</p>
    <p>There is a significant variability in I/O load. (5-6 orders of magnitude)</p>
    <p>Observation 3</p>
    <p>More that 99% of the working set consist of really popular &amp; recently accessed data.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach</p>
    <p>Sample Characterize the logical volume to find the working set.</p>
    <p>Replicate Create multiple working-set replicas in various physical volumes scratch space.</p>
    <p>Consolidate Based on I/O workload intensity, activate a sub-set of physical volumes and serve workloads either from original copies or working set replicas on these active disks.</p>
    <p>Initialization</p>
    <p>Every H hours</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goals  Solutions</p>
    <p>Goal Solution</p>
    <p>Fine grained proportionality Multiple replica targets.</p>
    <p>Low space overhead Instead of entire volumes, only working-sets are replicated.</p>
    <p>Reliability Coarse-grained consolidation intervals. (hours)</p>
    <p>Workload Adaptation Update working set replicas</p>
    <p>with new data that lead to read misses.</p>
    <p>Heterogeneity support Performance-power ratio accounted for in the replica placement benefit function.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SRCMap work-flow</p>
    <p>Event Response</p>
    <p>Initialization Detect working-sets of logical volumes &amp; create replicas.</p>
    <p>Every H hours Identify what volumes and replicas to activate the next H hours.</p>
    <p>Change in workload Same as initialization.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Replica Placement</p>
    <p>Replication benefit based on:</p>
    <p>Assign space with priorities based on benefit.</p>
    <p>Update replica creation benefit as additional replicas are created.</p>
    <p>Algorithm executes until scratch spaces are full.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Active Replica Identification</p>
    <p>Calculate predicted aggregate workload IOPS.</p>
    <p>Compute minimum number of volumes to serve the aggregate IOPS.</p>
    <p>Identify replicas for inactive volumes.</p>
    <p>The number of active disks is incremented by one in case no active replica has been identified for some inactive volume.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workloads &amp; Configuration</p>
    <p>8 workloads to independent data volumes.</p>
    <p>Mix of web-servers of our CS department, and file server, SVN, and WiKi for our research group.</p>
    <p>H = 2. Change active replicas every 2 hours.</p>
    <p>Two minute disk time-outs.</p>
    <p>Working sets &amp; replicas based on three week workload history.</p>
    <p>We report results of replaying the next 8 most active hours in the traces.</p>
    <p>We assume an oracle for estimation of load during each consolidation interval.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Storage test-bed</p>
    <p>One machine with 8 SATA ports.</p>
    <p>Intel P4 HT 3GHz, 1GB memory.</p>
    <p>Trace played back using btreplay.</p>
    <p>Dedicated power supply for disks connected to power meter.</p>
    <p>Watts up? PRO power meter: measures power every second with resolution of 0.1W.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power</p>
    <p>W a tt s</p>
    <p>Baseline - On</p>
    <p>SRCMap</p>
    <p># D</p>
    <p>is ks</p>
    <p>O n</p>
    <p>Hour</p>
    <p>Power consumption measured every second &amp; active disks every 5 seconds.</p>
    <p>Disks off Power Saved</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Response time</p>
    <p>e sp</p>
    <p>o n se</p>
    <p>T im</p>
    <p>e &lt;</p>
    <p>x )</p>
    <p>Response Time (msec)</p>
    <p>SRCMap Baseline - On</p>
    <p>P (R</p>
    <p>e sp</p>
    <p>o n se</p>
    <p>T im</p>
    <p>e &lt;</p>
    <p>x )</p>
    <p>After 1ms, Baseline - On demonstrate better performance.</p>
    <p>8% of requests with latencies  10ms.</p>
    <p>2% of requests with latencies  100ms.</p>
    <p>Synchronization I/Os issued at beginning of each interval.</p>
    <p>Replaying without sync I/Os follows Baseline-On more closely.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Energy proportionality</p>
    <p>P o</p>
    <p>w e</p>
    <p>r (W</p>
    <p>a tt</p>
    <p>s)</p>
    <p>Load factor (%)</p>
    <p>interval in 24-hour duration.</p>
    <p>Load Factor: Load relative to the assumed volume maximum load capacity.</p>
    <p>SRCMap is able to achieve close to N-level proportionality for a system with N physical volumes.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>We proposed and evaluate SRCMap, a storage virtualization solution for energy proportional storage.</p>
    <p>SRCMap establishes the feasibility of energy proportional storage systems.</p>
    <p>SRCMap meets all goals we set out to achieve energy proportional storage:</p>
    <p>X Low space overhead X Reliability X Workload adaptation X Heterogeneity support X Fine grain energy proportionality</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Models to predict I/O workload intensity.</p>
    <p>Models that estimate the performance impact of storage consolidation.</p>
    <p>Investigate the presence of workload correlation for better workload estimation and consolidation decision.</p>
    <p>Optimizing the scheduling of synchronization I/Os to minimize impact on foreground requests.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>http://dsrl.cs.fiu.edu/projects/srcmap/</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Singly redundant schemes: Spin down volumes with redundant data during low load.</p>
    <p>Geared RAIDs: Redundancy on several disks and each disk spun down represents a gear shift.</p>
    <p>Caching systems: Cache of popular data on additional storage.</p>
    <p>Write Offloading: Increase disk idle periods by redirecting writes to alternate locations.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other Methods</p>
    <p>L o a d</p>
    <p>Hour</p>
    <p>R e m</p>
    <p>a p s</p>
    <p>P o w</p>
    <p>e r</p>
    <p>(W a tt s) SRCMap(L0)</p>
    <p>Replication Caching-1 Caching-2</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
