<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Confidential | Date | Other information, if necessary</p>
    <p>Server Workload Analysis for Power Minimization using Consolidation</p>
    <p>Akshat Verma, Gargi Dasgupta, Tapan Nayak, Pradipta De, Ravi Kothari</p>
    <p>IBM India Research Lab</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Consolidation for Power Minimization</p>
    <p>Phases in a Typical Consolidation Scenario  Workload Profiling  Workload Sizing  Server Selection  Placement</p>
    <p>Important Considerations &amp; Questions  A consolidation plan remains active for long durations.  Workload intensity may vary greatly with time.</p>
    <p>How are workloads sized (Peak, Average, any other)??  Which workloads are co-located on the same server?</p>
    <p>The servers may be heterogeneous with different power and performance limits.</p>
    <p>Which servers are selected?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>Details of the workload studied</p>
    <p>Workload Characteristics</p>
    <p>Implications for the Design of Consolidation Algorithms</p>
    <p>Peak Clustering Based Placement</p>
    <p>Validation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Workload Details</p>
    <p>Production data center of Fortune Global 500 company</p>
    <p>Monitored using MDMS framework  5 min granularity  90 day period in 2007</p>
    <p>Selected 4 application suites with 10, 18, 13 and 16 servers  AppSuite1, 2 and 4 are 2-tiered applications  AppSuite3 is 3 tiered</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Workload Characteristics</p>
    <p>Single Workload Characteristic  Peak load is typically close to 100%  If consolidation is</p>
    <p>performed by reserving the maximum utilization for each application, the application may require capacity equal to the size of its current entitlement.</p>
    <p>90 percentile is much less than Peak  If we could size an application based on 90-percentile CPU utilization instead of maximum CPU utilization, it could lead to significant savings.</p>
    <p>The tail does not decay exponentially  If a statistical measure that ignores the tail of the distribution is used for sizing an application, the consolidated server may observe a large number of SLA capacity violations.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Workload Characteristics</p>
    <p>Correlation between workloads 4. There are both positively correlated and uncorrelated applications in a typical</p>
    <p>server cluster  Hence, correlation needs to be considered during placement to avoid SLA capacity violations.</p>
    <p>Stability of statistical parameters</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Core Dump!!!!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Implications for Placement</p>
    <p>Peak based sizing wastes resources  Sizing based on parameters like mean may have high</p>
    <p>performance risk  Correlation between the applications may increase the</p>
    <p>risk further.</p>
    <p>Correlation-based Placement (CBP): Separate out positively correlated applications. Assumes that the peak of one workload can be handled by borrowing resources from other workloads.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Implications for Placement</p>
    <p>Problems with CBP  Correlation is a global metric and may not accurately</p>
    <p>capture correlated peaks.</p>
    <p>Single Parameter based sizing can not capture both the tail and the body of the distribution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>What next? Some complicated technique that nobody will ever use!!!!!!!</p>
    <p>Well, it is really very simple!!!!!</p>
    <p>Use two parameters to size a workload</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Implications for Placement</p>
    <p>Peak Clustering Based Placement  Use two metrics for sizing: (i) a body based metric</p>
    <p>when placing with workloads which do not peak together and (ii) a tail based metric when placing with workloads that peak together</p>
    <p>Cluster workloads that peak together and ensure we proportionally allocate workloads to a server from each cluster.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Peak Clustering Based Placement</p>
    <p>a p a c it y U</p>
    <p>s e d</p>
    <p>Time</p>
    <p>CB</p>
    <p>Cmax</p>
    <p>Original Time Series Envelop at PB = 0.67</p>
    <p>P Capacity Used</p>
    <p>P D</p>
    <p>F</p>
    <p>C B</p>
    <p>C max</p>
    <p>B</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>PCP (Contd..)</p>
    <p>Peak2</p>
    <p>CLUSTER 1</p>
    <p>RESERVATION FOR</p>
    <p>RESERVATION FOR</p>
    <p>CLUSTER 2</p>
    <p>RESERVATION FOR</p>
    <p>CLUSTER 3</p>
    <p>Server Capacity</p>
    <p>Time</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>U</p>
    <p>P ea</p>
    <p>k B</p>
    <p>uf fe</p>
    <p>r Largest PeakPeak1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>PCP (Cont ..)</p>
    <p>!&quot;#$%&amp;#'&amp;#</p>
    <p>()$*&amp;#'&amp;#$*&amp;+&amp;,-.&quot;/</p>
    <p>*&amp;#'&amp;#%</p>
    <p>:)$8+;%-&amp;#</p>
    <p>&lt;#=/%!&quot;#&gt;&amp;?</p>
    <p>@</p>
    <p>!&quot;#$/&amp;B-$%&amp;#'&amp;# C)$7&amp;#!8+;%-&amp;#$56$*D&quot;#-+.%-./E</p>
    <p>F)$56$7+=,&amp;&gt;&amp;/-$!&quot;#$%&amp;#'&amp;#</p>
    <p>*&amp;+&amp;,-&amp;?</p>
    <p>Create an envelop for each workload based on two parameters  Cluster workloads based on their peaks  Select the most power-efficient server  Allocate workloads from each cluster to the server in a proportional manner.  Keep a buffer for the peak.  Use FFD to minimize fragmentation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Experimental Setup</p>
    <p>Implemented in IBM Emerald 2.0 Consolidation Planning Tool</p>
    <p>Training Period of 5 days  Evaluation Period of 1 day (the day following the</p>
    <p>training)  Compared with best known methodology with Peak</p>
    <p>based and mode-based sizing  Metrics for Evaluation</p>
    <p>Power Consumed  Capacity Violations  Workload Imbalance across servers (difference between the</p>
    <p>most highly loaded server and the average)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>!&quot;&quot;#$%&amp;'!( !&quot;&quot;#$%&amp;'!) !&quot;&quot;#$%&amp;'!* !&quot;&quot;#$%&amp;'!+ ,</p>
    <p>,-)</p>
    <p>,-+</p>
    <p>,-.</p>
    <p>,-/</p>
    <p>(</p>
    <p>B17'&lt;=&gt;%?&amp;%@A</p>
    <p>CD9</p>
    <p>!&quot;&quot;#$%&amp;'!( !&quot;&quot;#$%&amp;'!) !&quot;&quot;#$%&amp;'!* !&quot;&quot;#$%&amp;'!+ ,</p>
    <p>-,</p>
    <p>(,,</p>
    <p>(-,</p>
    <p>),,</p>
    <p>)-,</p>
    <p>*,,</p>
    <p>. %/ 01 &amp;%/ 2 34 54 6 1 7</p>
    <p>&gt;/?':;&lt;%3&amp;%2=</p>
    <p>@A8</p>
    <p>Results Summary</p>
    <p>Power  Consolidation based on</p>
    <p>peak sizes may not even save any power</p>
    <p>PCP saves almost the same amount of power as mode.</p>
    <p>Violations  Mode has the most</p>
    <p>violations.  CBP may have violations</p>
    <p>depending on the correlation threshold cutoff</p>
    <p>The capacity violations for Mode may be as large as the capacity of the server.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>CPU utilization of workloads exhibit a high degree of variance</p>
    <p>Most servers peak close to 100% utilization.  The average utilization is usually much lower but</p>
    <p>consolidation based on average utilization has high consolidation risk.</p>
    <p>The statistical parameters are more stable than the workload itself.</p>
    <p>Placement based on two parameters for sizing may lead to aggressive consolidation with low risk of capacity violations.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>India Research Lab</p>
    <p>Thanks</p>
    <p>Questions?????</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
