<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BanalBanal</p>
    <p>Because Format Checking Because Format Checking is So Triteis So Trite</p>
    <p>Geoffrey M. VoelkerGeoffrey M. Voelker University of California, San DiegoUniversity of California, San Diego</p>
    <p>Workshop on Organizing Workshops, Conferences, and Workshop on Organizing Workshops, Conferences, and Symposia for Computer Systems (WOWCS08)Symposia for Computer Systems (WOWCS08)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>This Talk is This Talk is Not Very InterestingNot Very Interesting</p>
    <p>Banal is a format checker for PDF documents</p>
    <p>Deduces how a document was formatted  Optionally compares it with a specification</p>
    <p>Intended for conference management systems  Now being used in HotCRP and EDAS  Seemed timely to document its genesis and implementation</p>
    <p>April 15, 2008 WOWCS08 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why?Why?  Preserving reviewer anonymity</p>
    <p>Acrobat javascript that calls home when pdf is loaded</p>
    <p>Assisting conference management tasks  Ensuring anonymity rules  Possibly helping do initial assignments by mining the bib</p>
    <p>Fairness  Everyone else obeyed the rules</p>
    <p>Time  Already enough time spent on reviewing  Frustrated that abuse meant taking even more of my time</p>
    <p>April 15, 2008 WOWCS08 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How?How?  Convert PDF</p>
    <p>To XML (with pdftohtml)</p>
    <p>Track the locations of all segments of text, essentially form bounding boxes</p>
    <p>Compute margins, columns, body font, etc.  Heuristics for page #s, headers, footers, etc.</p>
    <p>April 15, 2008 WOWCS08 4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Where?Where?  A handful of SIGOPS/SIGCOMM conferences</p>
    <p>OSDI06, SIGCOMM07, SIGCOMM08  Eddie Kohler has integrated it into HotCRP</p>
    <p>Henning Schulzrinne also integrated banal with EDAS  Since 2006, used for over 800 events</p>
    <p>April 15, 2008 WOWCS08 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>So?So?  What are our community goals for having formatting</p>
    <p>requirements?  Evil: Annoying trifles that negatively impact our ability to</p>
    <p>communicate our results and ideas?  Helpful: Reflect practicalities of publishing costs and</p>
    <p>community time?</p>
    <p>Not surprisingly, Im in the practical camp</p>
    <p>April 15, 2008 WOWCS08 6</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
