<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>O tt itti th T ittOuttwitting the Twitterers  Predicting InformationPredicting Information Cascades in Microblogs</p>
    <p>Wojciech Galuba Karl AbererWojciech Galuba, Karl Aberer EPFL, Switzerland Dipanjan ChakrabortyDipanjan Chakraborty IBM Research India Zoran Despotovic, Wolfgang Kellerer D E L b M i h GDocomo Euro-Labs, Munich, Germany</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why study information flows in OSNs?</p>
    <p>casual link sharing</p>
    <p>breaking news M d li</p>
    <p>improve how information flows</p>
    <p>viral marketing activism Modeling  new applications</p>
    <p>insights into</p>
    <p>PR campaigns</p>
    <p>emergencies g</p>
    <p>underlying sociology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Information overload?</p>
    <p>Full-time job (reading tweets 40h</p>
    <p>k t 150WPM) Median: 23 tw/h, 552 tw/day</p>
    <p>a week at 150WPM)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OSN information spread modeling  Related work:  generative models</p>
    <p>reproduce statistical properties of info spread reproduce statistical properties of info spread predict coarse-grained aggregates</p>
    <p># of nodes reached by spread etc.</p>
    <p>Our approach: Our approach: Look at URL diffusion on Twitter Can we predict which user will mention which</p>
    <p>URL with what probability? 4</p>
    <p>URL with what probability?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why predict URL tweets?</p>
    <p>Protect from information overload Protect from information overload Sort incoming URLs by probability of</p>
    <p>t tiretweeting  Viral marketing Viral marketing Select a subset of users that ensure</p>
    <p>f l URL tisuccessful URL propagation  Spam detection Spam detection Mispredictions are a sign of anomalous</p>
    <p>ti it 5</p>
    <p>activity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data  300 hour window in Sep09  22M tweets  2.7M unique users  15M unique URLs 15M unique URLs  700M connections in the follower graphg p  Approx. 1/15th of the Twitter traffic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Follower graph*</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>F ll h*Follower graph*</p>
    <p>Mean (directed):Mean (directed): 3.61</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>U ti itUser activity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Per-URL activity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Information cascades</p>
    <p>Nodes: users thatNodes: users that mentioned a given URL A i f ti fl</p>
    <p>Arcs: information flow</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Re-tweeting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RT-cascade @alice: http://url.com</p>
    <p>@bob: RT @alice http://url.com@ p p</p>
    <p>@charlie: http://url.com</p>
    <p>Arcs: who retweets whom  Irrespective of wheter users follow one another</p>
    <p>Single parent 14</p>
    <p>g p  only the user name immediately after RT taken into account</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>F-cascade @alice: http://url.com @bob: http://url.com</p>
    <p>@charlie: http://url.com</p>
    <p>Arc @a@b exists if:  user @a mentioned URL before user @b user @a mentioned URL before user @b  user @b follows user @a</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RT-cascades vs. F-cascades</p>
    <p>RT cascades are trees RT-cascades are trees  F-cascades are DAGs  33% of the retweets credit a source that</p>
    <p>th d t di tl f llthe user does not directly follow</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>cascade</p>
    <p>subcascade</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Subcascade size</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cascade fragmentation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cascade depth</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Influence of the root</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Information diffusion rate</p>
    <p>Median: 50mins</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>URL tweeting prediction</p>
    <p>Based on the past URL retweets by users Based on the past URL retweets by users, predict the future ones</p>
    <p>Find probability that user i mentions URL u</p>
    <p>u =uipip 23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Influence</p>
    <p>ij</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>External influence</p>
    <p>i</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>URL virality</p>
    <p>u http://cnn com/http://cnn.com/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Per-user diffusion delay</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model ij</p>
    <p>ii</p>
    <p>http://cnn.com/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>At-Least-One (ALO) model</p>
    <p>u juij p jj</p>
    <p>P(at least one * Temporal component=uip</p>
    <p>( event happens) *</p>
    <p>component 2, ii</p>
    <p>ip ui</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Linear threshold (LT) model</p>
    <p>u juij p</p>
    <p>* Temporal component=uip</p>
    <p>* component2, ii</p>
    <p>ip  ui Thresholding</p>
    <p>function (sigmoid)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance metrics</p>
    <p>Recall: fraction of tweets predicted Recall: fraction of tweets predicted out of all tweets that happened</p>
    <p>Precision: fraction of true positives t f ll t t di t dout of all tweets predicted</p>
    <p>F-score: harmonic mean of recall and F score: harmonic mean of recall and precision</p>
    <p>F-score is the optimization goal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Learning</p>
    <p>Input: a time window of tweets Input: a time window of tweets  Computation: gradient ascent methodp g Parameter space:</p>
    <p>G l i i F</p>
    <p>Output: u ip Output: ip</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lineup</p>
    <p>LT Linear Threshold model LT  Linear Threshold model  LTr  Linear Threshold model with j</p>
    <p>instead of ALO At L t O d l</p>
    <p>j ji</p>
    <p>ALO  At-Least-One model  RND  baseline makes random guesses RND  baseline, makes random guesses</p>
    <p>about uip</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Log-normal degree distribution Log normal degree distribution  Small-world: 3.6 hops from user to user  Power-laws in the user activity and URL</p>
    <p>mentionse o s  Cascades are shallow: exponential depth falloff</p>
    <p>ff Log-normally distributed diffusion delay  The LT model:The LT model:</p>
    <p>predicts more than half of the URL tweets  with less than 15% false positive rate</p>
    <p>with less than 15% false positive rate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ongoing work</p>
    <p>Investigating mispredictions Investigating mispredictions  URLs  users</p>
    <p>Scaling up the real-time data miningg p g  continous MapReduce  crawler farm crawler farm</p>
    <p>Website: personalized URL rankings for Twitter users</p>
    <p>Apply to other systems 36</p>
    <p>pp y to ot e syste s</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
