<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Standard Metrics and Scenarios for Usable Authentication</p>
    <p>SCOTT RUOTI AND KENT SEAMONS BRIGHAM YOUNG UNIVERSITY</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our experience</p>
    <p>S. Ruoti, B. Roberts, and K. Seamons. Authentication melee: A usability analysis of seven web authentication systems. Proceedings of the 24th International Conference on World Wide Web. International World Wide Web Conferences Steering Committee, 2015.</p>
    <p>Reviewed numerous authentication papers</p>
    <p>Empirically evaluated seven web-authentication proposals</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem</p>
    <p>Unclear whether any real progress is being made  Steady stream of authentication proposals, but  Most lack empirical analysis  Few are compared against existing password-based authentication  Fewer still are compared against competing proposals</p>
    <p>We need a more scientific approach to this research area</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Head-to-head Comparisons</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Direct Comparisons</p>
    <p>Evaluate whether new proposals are making tangible progress  As compared to passwords  As compared to alternative proposals</p>
    <p>Within subject or between subject  Within subject can be preferable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Standard Metrics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Usability Scale (SUS)</p>
    <p>Simple and effective evaluation of usability  10 questions  Single usability score from [0, 100]</p>
    <p>Reliable  Across studies  Across populations  More accurate than mean time-to-authenticate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other Potential Metrics</p>
    <p>J. Sauro and J. Lewis. Quantifying the user experience: Practical statistics for user research. Elsevier, 2012.  Post study questionnaire  PSSUQ  Post-task questionnaire  SMEQ, SEQ</p>
    <p>User Burden Scale (UBS)  New scale introduced at CHI 2016</p>
    <p>Mean time-to-authenticate  Less reliable than SUS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Standard Scenarios</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Real-World Scenarios</p>
    <p>Allows for more rigorous comparisons  Systems evaluated against same criteria  Reduces confounding factors</p>
    <p>Real-world scenarios with relatable tasks  More accurately evaluates a proposals usability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Scenarios</p>
    <p>Banking  High security environment  Occasional usage</p>
    <p>Discussion board  Lower security environment  High usage</p>
    <p>Available for download</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recommendations</p>
    <p>Direct Comparisons  Within subject or between subject  Measure against baseline</p>
    <p>Standard usability metrics  SUS</p>
    <p>Standard scenarios  Banking  Discussion board</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>Standard usability metrics  Alternatives  Is SUS a good fit for usable security?</p>
    <p>Scenarios  Other compelling scenarios  Scenarios for emerging forms of authentication</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SUS Questions 1. I think that I would like to use</p>
    <p>this system frequently.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
