<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exploring Games for Improved Touchscreen Authentication on</p>
    <p>Mobile Devices</p>
    <p>Padmaja Scindia Jonathan Voris</p>
    <p>p s c i n d i a @ ny i t . e d u j v o r i s @ ny i t . e d u</p>
    <p>N e w Yo r k I n s t i t u t e o f Te c h n o l o g y</p>
    <p>D e p a r t m e n t o f C o m p u t e r S c i e n c e</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mobile Devices Need Strong Authentication</p>
    <p>Mobile devices increasingly responsible for sensitive information</p>
    <p>Their form factor makes them easily stolen  3.1 million devices stolen in 2013 [8]</p>
    <p>Data loss from mobile devices ranked the largest threat to mobile computing [4]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mobile User Authentication is Not Easy</p>
    <p>Mobile authentication is vulnerable to observation attacks [6]</p>
    <p>Usability concerns prevent adoption of existing methods</p>
    <p>47% of smartphone owners dont use a PIN, password, or unlock pattern [8]</p>
    <p>34% take no security precautions with their mobile devices [8]</p>
    <p>Solutions must be resource efficient</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Biometrics to the Rescue?</p>
    <p>Devices can verify user identity by measuring distinctive characteristics</p>
    <p>Traditional biometrics measure physical traits</p>
    <p>Advantages:  Not vulnerable to observation</p>
    <p>Harder to lose</p>
    <p>Disadvantages:  Requires specialized hardware</p>
    <p>Usability issues</p>
    <p>Only performed at session start</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Behavioral Biometrics</p>
    <p>Can users be authenticated based on the manner in which they use a device?</p>
    <p>Improves usability  Natural device usage</p>
    <p>Active authentication for improved security  Verify identity throughout a session</p>
    <p>Potential modalities:  Stylometry [1]  Application usage [5]  Device movement [7]  Touchscreen dynamics [9]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Behavioral Biometrics</p>
    <p>Challenges:</p>
    <p>Small resource footprint</p>
    <p>Privacy consciousness</p>
    <p>Detection time</p>
    <p>Modality relevance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Idea: Use Gameplay for Authentication</p>
    <p>Can users be authenticated by how they play a game?</p>
    <p>Are a persons gameplay habits consistent?</p>
    <p>Degree of variation between users?</p>
    <p>Why games?</p>
    <p>Natural usability benefits [2][3]</p>
    <p>Widespread popularity</p>
    <p>Privacy friendly</p>
    <p>Encourage rapid and distinct input</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A (Very) Preliminary Evaluation</p>
    <p>Developed a touchscreen input sensor for Android</p>
    <p>Installed on a Samsung Galaxy along with 3 popular games:  Angry Birds</p>
    <p>Flow Free</p>
    <p>Fruit Ninja</p>
    <p>Conducted IRB approved study with 12 participants  Played each game for 5 minutes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Gameplay Analysis</p>
    <p>Randomly selected 300 distinct gestures per user per game</p>
    <p>Derived 17 properties of touchscreen interactions:</p>
    <p>Applied a Support Vector Machine to gesture features per game  Trained with Sequential Minimal Optimization</p>
    <p>Tested with 10-fold cross validation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Game TP Rate FP Rate Precision AUC</p>
    <p>Angry Birds</p>
    <p>Flow Free 98.86% 0.10% 98.87% 0.996</p>
    <p>Fruit Ninja 99.45% 0.05% 99.46% 0.998</p>
    <p>Area Under the ROC Curve for each Combination of User and Game</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Behavioral biometrics are a promising approach to mobile authentication</p>
    <p>Users can potentially be authenticated by how they play touchscreen games</p>
    <p>Further research planned into how games impact authentication usability and speed</p>
    <p>Future work:  More comprehensive study</p>
    <p>Comparison of a wider variety of application usage</p>
    <p>Susceptibility of gameplay to attack (observation, mimicry, etc.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References [1] L. Fridman, S. Weber, R. Greenstadt, and M. Kam. Active Authentication on Mobile Devices via Stylometry, Application Usage, Web Browsing, and GPS Location IEEE Systems Journal, 2015.</p>
    <p>[2] A. Gallego, N. Saxena, and J. Voris. Exploring Extrinsic Motivation for Better Security: A Usability Study of Scoring-Enhanced Device Pairing. In Financial Cryptography and Data Security, 2013.</p>
    <p>[3] R. Halprin and M. Naor. Games for Extracting Randomness. In Proceedings of the 5th Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security, 2009.</p>
    <p>[4] P. Ruggiero and J. Foote. Cyber Threats to Mobile Phones. United States Computer Emergency Readiness Team Report. Available at: https://www.uscert.gov/sites/default/files/publications/cyber_threats-to_mobile_phones.pdf, 2011.</p>
    <p>[5] M. B. Salem, J. Voris, and S. Stolfo. Decoy Applications for Continuous Authentication on Mobile Devices. In 1st Who Are You?! Adventures in Authentication Workshop (WAY) co-located with the 10th Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security (SOUPS), 2014.</p>
    <p>[6] F. Schaub, R. Deyhle, and M. Weber. Password entry usability and shoulder surfing susceptibility on different smartphone platforms. In Proceedings of the 11th International Conference on Mobile and Ubiquitous Multimedia, 2012.</p>
    <p>[7] Z. Sitova, J. Sedenka, Q. Yang, G. Peng, G. Zhou, P. Gasti, and K. Balagani. HMOG: New Behavioral Biometric Features for Continuous Authentication of Smartphone Users. IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security, 2016.</p>
    <p>[8] D. Tapellini. Smart Phone Thefts Rose to 3.1 Million Last Year, Consumer Reports Finds. Available at: http://www.consumerreports.org/cro/news/2014/04/smart-phone-thefts-rose-to-3-1-million-last-year/index.htm, 2014.</p>
    <p>[9] H. Xu, Y. Zhou, and M. R. Lyu. Towards Continuous and Passive Authentication via Touch Biometrics: An Experimental Study on Smartphones. In Symposium On Usable Privacy and Security (SOUPS), 2014.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
