<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hakim Weatherspoon</p>
    <p>Joint with Lakshmi Ganesh, Tudor Marian, Mahesh Balakrishnan, and Ken Birman</p>
    <p>File and Storage Technologies (FAST)</p>
    <p>San Francisco, California</p>
    <p>February 26th, 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>U.S. Department of Treasury Study  Financial Sector vulnerable to significant data loss in disaster  Need new technical options</p>
    <p>Risks are real, technology available, Why is problem not solved?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Want asynchronous performance to local data center</p>
    <p>And want synchronous guarantee</p>
    <p>Primary site Remote mirror</p>
    <p>async</p>
    <p>sync</p>
    <p>Conundrum: there is no middle ground</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Want asynchronous performance to local data center</p>
    <p>And want synchronous guarantee</p>
    <p>Primary site Remote mirror</p>
    <p>sync</p>
    <p>Conundrum: there is no middle ground</p>
    <p>Local-sync Remote-sync</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How can we increase reliability of local-sync protocols?  Given many enterprises use local-sync mirroring anyways</p>
    <p>Different levels of local-sync reliability  Send update to mirror immediately  Delay sending update to mirror  deduplication reduces BW</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction  Enterprise Continuity</p>
    <p>How data loss occurs  How we prevent it  A possible solution</p>
    <p>Evaluation  Discussion and Future Work  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Primary site Remote mirror</p>
    <p>Rather, where do failures occur?</p>
    <p>Rolling disasters</p>
    <p>Packet loss Partition</p>
    <p>Site Failure</p>
    <p>Power Outage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Local-sync Network-sync Remote-sync</p>
    <p>Wide-area network Primary site Remote mirror</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Use network level redundancy and exposure  reduces probability data lost due to network failure</p>
    <p>Primary site Remote mirror Data Packet Repair Packet Network-level Ack Storage-level Ack</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network-sync increases data reliability  reduces data loss failure modes, can prevent data loss if  At the same time primary site fail network drops packet  And ensure data not lost in send buffers and local queues</p>
    <p>Data loss can still occur  Split second(s) before/after primary site fails  Network partitions  Disk controller fails at mirror  Power outage at mirror</p>
    <p>Existing mirroring solutions can use network-sync</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A file system constructed over network-sync  Transparently mirrors files over wide-area  Embraces concept: file is in transit (in the WAN link) but with enough</p>
    <p>recovery data to ensure that loss rates are as low as for the remote disk case!</p>
    <p>Group mirroring consistency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>B2 B1 append(B1,B2)</p>
    <p>V1 R1 I2 B4 B3 I1 append(V1..)</p>
    <p>V1</p>
    <p>R1</p>
    <p>I2 I1</p>
    <p>B2 B1 B3 B4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction  Enterprise Continuity  Evaluation  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demonstrate SMFS performance over Maelstrom  In the event of disaster, how much data is lost?  What is system and app throughput as link loss increases?  How much are the primary and mirror sites allowed to diverge?</p>
    <p>Emulab setup  1 Gbps, 25ms to 100ms link connects two data centers  Eight primary and eight mirror storage nodes  64 testers submit 512kB appends to separate logs</p>
    <p>Each tester submits only one append at a time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Local-sync unable to recover data dropped by network  Local-sync+FEC lost data not in transit  Network-sync did not lose any data</p>
    <p>Represents a new tradeoff in design space</p>
    <p>Primary site Remote mirror</p>
    <p>- 50 ms one-way latency - FEC(r,c) = (8,3)</p>
    <p>Localsync</p>
    <p>Networksync</p>
    <p>Remotesync</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>c = 0, No recovery packets: data loss due to packet loss  c = 1, not sufficient to mask packet loss either  c &gt; 2, can mask most packet loss  Network-sync can prevent loss in local buffers</p>
    <p>Primary site Remote mirror</p>
    <p>- 50 ms one-way latency - FEC(r,c) = (8,varies) - 1% link loss</p>
    <p>Localsync</p>
    <p>Networksync</p>
    <p>Remotesync</p>
    <p># M</p>
    <p>e s s a</p>
    <p>g e</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Value of C</p>
    <p>Local-sync+FEC total msgs sent Network-sync total msgs sent Unrecoverable lost msgs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>App throughput measures application perceived performance  Network and Local-sync+FEC tput significantly greater than</p>
    <p>Remote-sync(+FEC)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction  Enterprise Continuity  Evaluation  Discussion and Future Work  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Do (semi-)private lambda networks drop packets?  E.g. Teragrid</p>
    <p>Cornell National Lambda Rail (NLR) Rings testbed  Up to 0.5% loss</p>
    <p>Scale network-sync solution to 10Gbps and beyond  Commodity (multi-core) hardware</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Do (semi-)private lambda networks drop packets?  E.g. Teragrid</p>
    <p>Cornell National Lambda Rail (NLR) Rings testbed  Up to 0.5% loss</p>
    <p>Scale network-sync solution to 10Gbps and beyond  Commodity (multi-core) hardware</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction  Enterprise Continuity  Evaluation  Discussion and Future Work  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technology response to critical infrastructure needs  When does the filesystem return to the application?</p>
    <p>Fast  return after sending to mirror  Safe  return after ACK from mirror</p>
    <p>SMFS  return to user after sending enough FEC  Network-sync:</p>
    <p>Lossy NetworkLossless NetworkDisk!  Result: Fast, Safe Mirroring independent of link length!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Email: hweather@cs.cornell.edu</p>
    <p>Network-sync code available: http://fireless.cs.cornell.edu/~tudorm/maelstrom</p>
    <p>Cornell National Lambda Rail (NLR) Rings testbesb http://www.cs.cornell.edu/~hweather/nlr</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
