<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>&lt;Insert Picture Here&gt;</p>
    <p>Fine Grain Provenance Using Temporal Databases</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline of the talk</p>
    <p>Use case: Classic management of patient data  Data types, queries  History  Security and context information</p>
    <p>Fine grain provenance  I  Smart management of patient data</p>
    <p>Facts, knowledge, and information  The model  Classification and customization</p>
    <p>Fine grain provenance - II  Implementation details  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Use Case</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Classic Management of Patient Data</p>
    <p>Data Types</p>
    <p>Structured Data  SQL  Semi structured data  XML</p>
    <p>HL7 - Health Level-7  DICOM - Digital Imaging</p>
    <p>and Communications in Medicine</p>
    <p>Text  Any mix</p>
    <p>Data Manipulation and (continuous) queries</p>
    <p>SQL 92 and 99  XQuery</p>
    <p>HL/7 verbs  DICOM verbs</p>
    <p>Text processing verbs  Mixed use of languages</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>History</p>
    <p>Data management for patient history  No extended data model</p>
    <p>Simplifies programming significantly  Standard update, insert, delete</p>
    <p>Queries  The current values  The values/images at a specific time  The values/images as seen at a specific time  The evolution of values/images</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security and Context Information</p>
    <p>All queries and temporal queries support (fine grain) security  A doctor/nurse can only access data from patients s/he is</p>
    <p>currently treating</p>
    <p>Additional information recorded by the data base  The transactional context of any change or query  The transactional context includes host, database/OS user,</p>
    <p>program</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fine Grain Provenance - I</p>
    <p>The database is able to answer the following questions  What was a single or set of values at a given time  from the</p>
    <p>current perspective?  What was a single or set of values at a given time from an</p>
    <p>earlier perspective  imported to deal with corrections  What is the history of a single or a set of values</p>
    <p>Was a value ever corrected?  What is the history of correction?</p>
    <p>Who was responsible for providing/deleting a value?  Which program created the value?  Who looked at specific values?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Smart Management of Patient Data</p>
    <p>The issue:  Rapidly increasing amount and complexity of data  Rapidly increasing amount and complexity domain knowledge  Data and knowledge have grown way beyond the capacity of a</p>
    <p>human cognitive system  A solution</p>
    <p>Capture knowledge and personal preferences  Vocabularies, rules/models, classifications, customizations</p>
    <p>Capture facts  as done in classic support  Transform data (facts) into information using captured knowledge</p>
    <p>Alert medical personnel about time critical adverse conditions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Model</p>
    <p>Raw data - indiscriminate Quantitative</p>
    <p>Information - selective Qualitative*</p>
    <p>Online Protocols</p>
    <p>Online</p>
    <p>Alerts</p>
    <p>Near real time inference</p>
    <p>Protocols</p>
    <p>Patient Care Applications**</p>
    <p>Based on</p>
    <p>* Qualitative information is preferred by the human cognitive system</p>
    <p>** The application is as declarative as possible</p>
    <p>Facts Knowledge Information</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Use Case - Updated</p>
    <p>New functions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Information and Incidents</p>
    <p>Information is created as soon as new data/facts or new knowledge become available  The information is a compact and qualitative representation of important</p>
    <p>facts  The temperature is critical  The blood chemistry indicates a high probability of a cardiac arrest  The information has a high uncertainty, additional tests are</p>
    <p>recommended  Information is bundled as incidents</p>
    <p>Alert is issued for time critical information  Doctors can review the status of the patient on a qualitative level</p>
    <p>What is important; i.e., show incidents with certain characteristics  Show the history of selected incidents</p>
    <p>Is the patient improving as expected?  If needed the doctor can also look at the quantitative data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fine Grain Provenance - II</p>
    <p>Full auditing and tracking of facts  Implies full auditing and tracking of information</p>
    <p>Full Description and versioning of  Knowledge  rules, queries, model, programs, ..</p>
    <p>Who developed/tested/deployed/changed the knowledge elements and when</p>
    <p>Classifications  Who developed/tested/deployed/changed the classification and when</p>
    <p>Customizations  Who deployed/changed the customization</p>
    <p>The evolution of the information is now visible  What are the facts and knowledge behind information and incidents?  Do I accept the information?  Why did a colleague come to a (different) conclusion?  Why was the information (diagnosis) changed?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Databases support management of and access to a wide variety of data</p>
    <p>Temporal databases provide full support for auditing and tracking  no user programming required</p>
    <p>Adding knowledge management to data management provides full support for provenance - no user programming is required</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Read Consistency - Oracles Flashback</p>
    <p>One of the main features of Oracle is consistent read  No read locks are taken  Instead data is read as of a point in time in the past before all</p>
    <p>uncommitted changes (using undo)</p>
    <p>Flashback extends CR to be able to read data as of a point in time in the recent past (using undo)</p>
    <p>Total Recall extends flashback to go back far in the past</p>
    <p>Using flashback, it is possible to see data/information/ knowledge as it was at any point in time, providing the main building block for provenance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Temporal Database Support  Oracles Total Recall</p>
    <p>Total recall provides a way to enable transaction time history on a table for a specified retention</p>
    <p>Using total recall it is possible to do flashback queries  As of queries enable the user to read a row/table as</p>
    <p>of a point in time  Versions enable the user to get all committed</p>
    <p>versions of a row/table between a range of time  Provides the transaction start/end time of version, transaction</p>
    <p>context of creator of version</p>
    <p>Audit used for tracking queries  Valid time support can also be added in future</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Classification Model</p>
    <p>Value: Normal, guarded, serious, critical  Urgency: Stat, ASAP, none</p>
    <p>Uniform classification of</p>
    <p>data</p>
    <p>Type: deteriorating, improving  Rate: rapid, slow</p>
    <p>Uniform classification of</p>
    <p>change</p>
    <p>Patient is not improving as expected by model M1</p>
    <p>Statistical temporal change model</p>
    <p>Find all patients with critical condition lasting more than 2 hrs in the last 5 years</p>
    <p>Identify important incidences/adverse conditions</p>
    <p>Uniform classification</p>
    <p>simplifies queries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Classification - Design Principles</p>
    <p>Simplifies aggregating elementary quantitative information into highly compact representation</p>
    <p>Reduces the number of queries, rules, and models significantly</p>
    <p>Uniform classification</p>
    <p>Adjust to the preferences of a group, a doctor, or specific condition of a patient</p>
    <p>Adjusts to the specific situation of a patient</p>
    <p>Personalized classification</p>
    <p>rules</p>
    <p>Decision tables, rules, models, manual Classification</p>
    <p>Methods</p>
    <p>A vital is deteriorating fast  The patient does not improve as expected</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Classification With a Decision Table Lower Range Upper Range</p>
    <p>Cri/cal Serious Guarded Normal Normal Guarded Serious Cri/cal</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>TEMPERATURE 34.5 36 37 37.0 38.4 38.4 40 42</p>
    <p>HEART_RATE 40 50 60 60 100 100 125 150</p>
    <p>SYSTOLIC_BP 70 80 90 90 140 140 160 190</p>
    <p>DIASTOLIC_BP 40 50 60 60 90 90 100 110</p>
    <p>MEAN_ARTERIAL_PRESSURE 60 65 70 70 105 105 110 115</p>
    <p>RESPIRATORY_RATE 8 10 14 14 26 26 30 35</p>
    <p>OXYGEN_SATURATION 80 85 90 90 100</p>
    <p>WEIGHT</p>
    <p>EKG</p>
    <p>CO 3 4 4.0 6.0 6 8</p>
    <p>CI 2.2 2.6 2.6 4.2 4.2 6</p>
    <p>SVR 600 700 800 800 1200 1200 1400 1600</p>
    <p>CWP 4 12</p>
    <p>INTRA_ABD_PRESSURE 5 15 15 20 30</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>Note: Columns Guarded and Normal contain intentionally the same information</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
