<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Te-Yuan Huang, Kuan-Ta Chen, Polly Huang</p>
    <p>Network and Systems Laboratory National Taiwan University</p>
    <p>Institute of Information Science Academia Sinica, Taiwan</p>
    <p>INFOCOM, 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation Voice traffic is sensitive to network impairment Why VoIP sending rate is important? Most important factors on user satisfaction</p>
    <p>Sending Rate and its Variation High and Stable voice quality</p>
    <p>Why adapting sending rate is difficult? Aggressively? Conservatively?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  Cont. Skype  one of the most popular VoIP</p>
    <p>software</p>
    <p>Q1: How Skype adapts its voice traffic?</p>
    <p>Q2: Is their mechanism good enough?</p>
    <p>Q3: How can Skypes policy be improved?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work Skypes voice traffic is governed by: [Bonfiglio et al.]</p>
    <p>Bit Rate Framing Time Redundant Data</p>
    <p>PC-PSTN calls G.729</p>
    <p>PC-PC calls iSAC</p>
    <p>Only Redundant Data is controlled by Skype</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline Motivation Related Work How does Skype adapt the redundancy ratio? Is Skypes mechanism good enough? How can we do better? Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline Motivation Related Work How does Skype adapt its redundant data? Is Skypes mechanism good enough? How can we do better? Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment Setup</p>
    <p>PC-PC(iSAC)</p>
    <p>PC-PSTN(G.729)</p>
    <p>Only observing UDP sessions Voice Input : American English Speech Samples from Open Speech Repository</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observation G.729 (PC-PSTN)</p>
    <p>Constant bit rate Constant framing</p>
    <p>time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Redundancy Ratio Definition</p>
    <p>The percentage of packets that carry redundant voice data</p>
    <p>Redundancy Ratio = 2/4 = 0.5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Estimate Redundancy Ratio of G.729</p>
    <p>the latter is used in Taiwan and Hong Kong, and the former is used more often in Mainland</p>
    <p>Set Threshold at 40 bytes</p>
    <p>G.729 (PC-PSTN) Constant bit rate Constant framing</p>
    <p>time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Identify Redundancy Ratio Redundancy Ratio of G.729 (PC-PSTN Calls)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Identify Redundancy Ratio Redundancy Ratio of iSAC (PC-PC Calls)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline Motivation Related Work How does Skype adapt its redundancy ratio? Is Skypes mechanism good enough? How can we do better? Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Skypes Redundancy Control Algorithm</p>
    <p>Adapt to network loss rate Adapt to other factors?</p>
    <p>Codec Network Loss Burstiness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Effect of Codec</p>
    <p>iSAC</p>
    <p>G.729</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Effect of Network Loss Burstiness G.729 (PC-PSTN)</p>
    <p>BR=1</p>
    <p>BR=1.5</p>
    <p>BR=2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline Motivation Related Work How does Skype adapt its redundancy ratio? Is Skypes mechanism good enough? How can we do better? Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimal Redundancy Control Policy Whats the Optimal Policy?</p>
    <p>Minimum amount of redundancy data we need to sustain the same audio quality under different network conditions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Emulation Flow</p>
    <p>G.729</p>
    <p>Optimal Redundancy Ratio</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Skype vs. Optimal  G.729</p>
    <p>Burst Ratio = 1</p>
    <p>Skype</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimal Redundancy for the Burst Ratio</p>
    <p>G.729, MOS=3.5</p>
    <p>BR=1</p>
    <p>BR=1.5BR=2</p>
    <p>Skype</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modeling Optimal Redundancy Ratio Based on the targeted voice quality Take codec and burstiness into</p>
    <p>consideration Optimal Policy for G.729, targeted MOS=3.5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion Explore how Skype adapts its voice traffic</p>
    <p>Redundancy Ratio Skypes policy does not factor in the individual</p>
    <p>codec and loss patterns in to consideration Propose a general model for optimal policy</p>
    <p>Consistent user satisfaction Extensible to general VoIP software</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
