<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Case for Enterprise Ready Virtual Private</p>
    <p>Clouds</p>
    <p>Timothy Wood, Alexandre Gerber*, K.K. Ramakrishnan*, Jacobus van der Merwe*, and Prashant Shenoy</p>
    <p>University of Massachusetts Amherst *AT&amp;T Research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud Computing</p>
    <p>Rent computation and storage resources on demand  Accessed by multiple enterprise sites</p>
    <p>Cloud Platform types:  Software as a Service</p>
    <p>Hotmail, Google Docs</p>
    <p>Platform as a Service  Google App Engine, Microsoft Azure</p>
    <p>Infrastructure as a Service  Amazon EC2, VMware vCloud</p>
    <p>Cloud Platform</p>
    <p>Enterprise Sites</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Enterprise Cloud Challenges</p>
    <p>Existing platforms do not meet the needs of enterprise customers</p>
    <p>Insufficient security controls  Need isolation at server and network level</p>
    <p>Deployment is difficult  Cloud resources are completely separate from local ones  Cant make VMs look like part of existing LAN</p>
    <p>Limited control over network resources  Cannot specify network topology or IP addresses  Cannot reserve bandwidth or request QoS guarantees for</p>
    <p>network links</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud Platform</p>
    <p>Moving to the Cloud</p>
    <p>Acme wants to move part of its payroll app into the cloud</p>
    <p>Should be easy, right?</p>
    <p>Front End Reports</p>
    <p>Data Store Processing</p>
    <p>Tier</p>
    <p>Processing Tier</p>
    <p>Acme LAN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud Platform</p>
    <p>Acme LAN</p>
    <p>Problem #1: Transparency Application may have been written for LAN environment</p>
    <p>Might utilize broadcast or LAN service discovery</p>
    <p>Must add Internet gateways for apps previously only on LAN</p>
    <p>Now must communicate via public IPs or configure DNS</p>
    <p>Front End</p>
    <p>Data Store</p>
    <p>Processing proc.cloud.com</p>
    <p>Lack of transparency causes application modifications and infrastructure reconfigurations</p>
    <p>GW</p>
    <p>GW</p>
    <p>front.acme.com</p>
    <p>data.acme.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud Platform</p>
    <p>Acme LAN</p>
    <p>Problem #2: Security Acmes servers are now accessible from the public internet!</p>
    <p>Servers formerly on secure LAN now exposed to malicious users</p>
    <p>Must configure firewall rules to limit access  Fine grain rules are difficult to manage in dynamic environments</p>
    <p>Front End front.acme.com</p>
    <p>Data Store data.acme.com</p>
    <p>Processing proc.cloud.com</p>
    <p>Hacker123 hax.cloud.com</p>
    <p>Lack of secure cloud connections exposes enterprise to threats from</p>
    <p>both in and out of the cloud</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud Platform</p>
    <p>Acme LAN</p>
    <p>Problem #3: Flexible Resource Mgmt Benefit of cloud computing: ability to easily adjust resource capacities and add new VMs</p>
    <p>After a change must deal with transparency and security issues all over again!</p>
    <p>Current platforms do not support network resource reservation (Bandwidth/QoS guarantees)</p>
    <p>Front End front.acme.com</p>
    <p>Data Store data.acme.com</p>
    <p>Processing proc.cloud.com</p>
    <p>Processing #2 proc2.cloud.com</p>
    <p>Enterprises want control over network resources. Cloud must</p>
    <p>support dynamic changes</p>
    <p>+1</p>
    <p>+1</p>
    <p>+1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Observation Existing cloud platforms only cover</p>
    <p>storage and computation</p>
    <p>Enterprise Clouds need control over the network as well</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p>Cloud Platform</p>
    <p>Enterprise Sites</p>
    <p>VMDisk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Virtual Private Clouds A Virtual Private Cloud is</p>
    <p>A secure collection of server, storage, and network resources spanning one or more cloud data centers</p>
    <p>That is seamlessly connected to one or more enterprise sites</p>
    <p>Virtual Private Networks (VPNs)  Layer 2 and 3 MPLS based VPNs  Created by network provider with no end host configuration  Already used by many businesses!</p>
    <p>VMVM</p>
    <p>VMVM Enterprise</p>
    <p>Sites</p>
    <p>Cloud Sites</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VPC Benefits For the customer:</p>
    <p>Isolates network &amp; compute resources  Cloud resources are only accessible through VPN</p>
    <p>Simplifies deployment since cloud looks same as local resources</p>
    <p>For the service provider:  Provides mechanism for control over resource reservation</p>
    <p>within provider network  Simplifies management of multiple data centers by</p>
    <p>combining them into large resource pools</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VPC Challenges &amp; Solutions Existing cloud platforms do not integrate with network service providers</p>
    <p>Must coordinate with ISP to create VPN endpoints</p>
    <p>VPN endpoints must be linked to VLANs within the cloud data center</p>
    <p>VPN endpoints are traditionally static</p>
    <p>Utilize virtual routers with programmable interfaces to rapidly create and reconfigure routers</p>
    <p>Use BGP signaling to dynamically adjust VPN topology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud ManagerNetwork Manager</p>
    <p>CloudNet Cloud Manager</p>
    <p>Allocates computation and storage resources</p>
    <p>Manages VLAN assignment within cloud network</p>
    <p>Network Manager</p>
    <p>Creates and configure VPN endpoints</p>
    <p>Reserves network resources</p>
    <p>VM VMVLANVPN</p>
    <p>VM VMVPN VLAN</p>
    <p>Provider Edge</p>
    <p>Customer Edge Routers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WAN Migration Layer 2 VPNs make WAN act like a LAN</p>
    <p>Can use existing LAN migration techniques to move across WAN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PE</p>
    <p>WAN Migration</p>
    <p>PE</p>
    <p>Customer Site PE A</p>
    <p>Cloud Site 1</p>
    <p>Layer 2 VPN (VPLS)</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>ARP!</p>
    <p>ARP!</p>
    <p>Can use existing LAN migration techniques to move across WAN</p>
    <p>VPN endpoint</p>
    <p>Router</p>
    <p>Cloud Site 2 Switch</p>
    <p>VLAN</p>
    <p>VLAN</p>
    <p>CE</p>
    <p>CE</p>
    <p>Layer 2 VPNs make WAN act like a LAN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary Cloud Computing for enterprises requires:  Security</p>
    <p>Transparency</p>
    <p>Flexibility</p>
    <p>CloudNet can help provide these features  Defines interface between cloud platform and network provider</p>
    <p>Uses VPNs for secure, seamless connections</p>
    <p>Employs virtualization at server, router, and network levels to improve agility and efficiency</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Network optimizations to reduce latency of WAN migration</p>
    <p>Utilize VPLS to simplify deployment of high availability services across WAN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>twood@cs.umass.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extra slides</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WAN Migration LAN migration already supported by Xen, VMware, etc</p>
    <p>Transparently move a VM between two hosts</p>
    <p>Useful for load balancing, maintenance, etc</p>
    <p>Only works on LAN because of need for network reconfiguration</p>
    <p>Layer 2 VPNs make WAN act like a LAN</p>
    <p>Lets VPN endpoints across WAN act as a single LAN segment</p>
    <p>Allows for WAN migration without modifying VM platform!</p>
    <p>Storage migration still must be handled by other means</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
