<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Statistical Analysis and Distortion Modeling of MPEG-4 FGS</p>
    <p>Min DaiMin Dai Electrical Engineering Texas A&amp;M University, TX 77843</p>
    <p>Dmitri LoguinovDmitri Loguinov Computer Science Texas A&amp;M University, TX 77843</p>
    <p>Hayder RadhaHayder Radha Electrical and Computer Engineering Michigan State University, MI 48824</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rate-distortion (R-D) theory  The fundamental tradeoff in the design of any lossy</p>
    <p>compression system</p>
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>A typical R-D curve</p>
    <p>R</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>R-D function:  A bound on achievable (or theoretically possible)</p>
    <p>distortion for a given coding rate  A powerful tool in Internet streaming</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background (cont.)  Scalable coding is widely applied in Internet</p>
    <p>streaming  Provides the capability of recovering video information</p>
    <p>by partially decoding the compressed bitstream  Fine Granular Scalability (FGS) has been chosen in the</p>
    <p>MPEG-4 standard</p>
    <p>Fine granular scalability (FGS):  One low-bitrate base layer (BL) to provide a low, but</p>
    <p>guaranteed quality  One high-bitrate enhancement layer (EL) to provide fine</p>
    <p>quality improvement  EL can be truncated at any codeword</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Current status:  No current closed-form R-D model can capture all the</p>
    <p>complexities of a real encoder</p>
    <p>No specific work has been done on R-D modeling of scalable video coding for Internet streaming</p>
    <p>Goals in this paper:  Understand the statistical properties of FGS input and</p>
    <p>propose a more accurate statistical model for it</p>
    <p>Study the bitplane coding process in FGS and derive a closed-form distortion model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related work on Statistical Models  Input to FGS EL:</p>
    <p>DCT residue between the original image and the reconstructed image from BL</p>
    <p>The two most popular models of DCT residue:  Zero-mean Gaussian distribution:</p>
    <p>||</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>)(</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>exf</p>
    <p>Laplacian distribution (double exponential):</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related work on Statistical Models</p>
    <p>-15 -10 -5 0 5 10 15 DCT residue</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>ba bi</p>
    <p>lit y</p>
    <p>real PMF Gaussian Laplacian</p>
    <p>DCT residue P</p>
    <p>ro ba</p>
    <p>bi lit</p>
    <p>y</p>
    <p>real PMF Gaussian Laplacian</p>
    <p>The PMF of DCT residue with Gaussian and Laplacian estimations in frame 0 of the Foreman CIF sequence (left). Logarithmic scale of PMFs for the positive residue (right).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proposed Statistical Model  Mixture Laplacian model:</p>
    <p>||1||0 10</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>We use the Expectation-Maximization (EM) algorithm to obtain Maximum-likelihood (ML) estimation for parameters { p, 0, 1 }</p>
    <p>where 0 denotes the small variance Laplacian distribution and 1 denotes the large variance Laplacian distribution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results of Proposed Model</p>
    <p>-20 -10 0 10 20 DCT residue</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>ba bi</p>
    <p>lit y</p>
    <p>real PMF mixture</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>ba bi</p>
    <p>lit y</p>
    <p>real PMF mixture</p>
    <p>The real PMF and mixture Laplacian (left) and the logarithmic scale of the positive part (right)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More Results</p>
    <p>er ro</p>
    <p>r</p>
    <p>Gaussian Laplacian mixture</p>
    <p>er ro</p>
    <p>r</p>
    <p>Gaussian Laplacian mixture</p>
    <p>The weighted absolute error of estimation in Foreman CIF (left) and Coastguard CIF (right)</p>
    <p>All test sequences are coded at 10fps and 128 kb/s in the base layer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Classical model:</p>
    <p>A variation of the classical model (proposed by Chiang et al. in 1997):</p>
    <p>R XD</p>
    <p>where 2 is a signal-dependent constant, X2 denotes the signal variance and R is the bitrate</p>
    <p>where parameters a, b are obtained empirically</p>
    <p>Current Distortion Models</p>
    <p>Distortion model for Uniform Quantizer (UQ): 2( )D  =</p>
    <p>where  is quantization step and equals 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance of Current Models</p>
    <p>FGS EL bits</p>
    <p>P S</p>
    <p>N R</p>
    <p>(d B</p>
    <p>)</p>
    <p>Chiang et al. real PSNR UQ classical</p>
    <p>FGS EL bits</p>
    <p>P S</p>
    <p>N R</p>
    <p>(d B</p>
    <p>)</p>
    <p>Chiang et al. real PSNR UQ classical</p>
    <p>Performances of current models in frame 0 (left) and frame 252 of Foreman CIF (right)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A more Accurate Distortion Model</p>
    <p>For each component in the mixture-Laplacian model, the distortion is:</p>
    <p>where  is the quantization step of each bitplane in the FGS EL and p is the probability of Laplacian component 0</p>
    <p>(1 ) i</p>
    <p>ii i i i</p>
    <p>D e i e</p>
    <p>=  + +  =</p>
    <p>)()1()()( 10 += DpDpD  Final version:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
    <p>av g</p>
    <p>ab s</p>
    <p>er ro</p>
    <p>r (d</p>
    <p>B )</p>
    <p>classical UQ model our model</p>
    <p>av eg</p>
    <p>a bs</p>
    <p>e rr</p>
    <p>or (d</p>
    <p>B )</p>
    <p>classical UQ model our model</p>
    <p>The average absolute errors in Foreman CIF (left) and Coastguard CIF (right)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>This paper proposed an accurate statistical model for DCT residue</p>
    <p>Based on this statistical model, we derived a closed-form distortion function for FGS EL</p>
    <p>In summary, this paper provides a good starting point for further research on FGS streaming</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
