<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PacketPacket--Pair Bandwidth Pair Bandwidth Estimation: Stochastic Estimation: Stochastic Analysis of a Single Analysis of a Single Congested NodeCongested Node</p>
    <p>SeongSeong--ryongryong Kang, Xiliang Liu,Kang, Xiliang Liu, Min Dai, and Dmitri LoguinovMin Dai, and Dmitri Loguinov</p>
    <p>Texas A&amp;M UniversityTexas A&amp;M University</p>
    <p>City University of New YorkCity University of New York</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Definitions of Bandwidth</p>
    <p>Packet-pair bandwidth sampling</p>
    <p>Renewal cross-traffic</p>
    <p>Arbitrary cross-traffic</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  Bandwidth estimation is an important area of</p>
    <p>Internet research  To understand the characteristics of network paths</p>
    <p>Helps various Internet applications</p>
    <p>Majority of existing work is based on empirical studies  Assume no cross-traffic and/or</p>
    <p>Based on fluid model</p>
    <p>Our work aims to provide stochastic insights on this field</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation 2  Our purpose is not to offer another measurement</p>
    <p>tool</p>
    <p>Instead, we show that  Single-link case is completely tractable</p>
    <p>Some of the existing methods cannot estimate bandwidth under heavy cross-traffic</p>
    <p>We also prove the existence of convergence for arbitrary cross-traffic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bottleneck Bandwidth</p>
    <p>The capacity of the slowest link of an end-to-end path</p>
    <p>R1 R2 50 R3 R4</p>
    <p>Bottleneck capacity: C = 20</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Available Bandwidth</p>
    <p>The smallest average unused bandwidth along the end-to-end path</p>
    <p>Available bandwidth: A = 12</p>
    <p>R1 R2 50</p>
    <p>R3 R4 4020</p>
    <p>S D</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Available Bandwidth 2</p>
    <p>Multi-link case with arbitrary cross-traffic appears intractable at this stage  In this work, we restrict our analysis to a single link</p>
    <p>For an arbitrary cross-traffic arrival process r(t), define the average rate of cross-traffic at a link</p>
    <p>Then, available bandwidth is defined as</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-Pair Sampling</p>
    <p>Goal: measure both C and A over a single link with any cross-traffic arrival process</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-Pair Sampling 2</p>
    <p>Basic idea  Send back-to-back probe packets faster than C</p>
    <p>Then, the probe packets are queued directly behind each other at the bottleneck link</p>
    <p>The packet spacing between two probe packets are expanded due to transmission delay of the second packet at the bottleneck router</p>
    <p>At the receiver, measure the inter-packet arrival spacing to estimate the capacity C</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-Pair Sampling 3</p>
    <p>Without cross-traffic, inter-packet arrival spacing is the same as the transmission delay  of the second packet over the link</p>
    <p>y =x</p>
    <p>Estimate C as q/y , (q is probe packet size)</p>
    <p>However, cross-traffic can lead to y ?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-Pair Sampling 4</p>
    <p>If cross-traffic packets arrive between two probe packets, inter-arrival spacing is expanded</p>
    <p>y = + x</p>
    <p>This leads to inaccurate estimation of C</p>
    <p>Thus, filtering out the effects of cross-traffic noise is key for accurate estimation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-Pair Sampling 5</p>
    <p>For bottleneck bandwidth estimation  Many existing studies apply various histogram-based</p>
    <p>methods</p>
    <p>Assume no cross-traffic along the path</p>
    <p>For available bandwidth estimation  Cross-traffic is considered in the analysis</p>
    <p>However, predominantly assumes fluid model for all flows</p>
    <p>In this work, a stochastic queuing model is used to analyze the random noise without fluid assumption</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Stochastic Queuing Model</p>
    <p>Random process x(n) is the initial spacing between n-th and (n-1)-th probe packets</p>
    <p>R1 R2S D xn yn</p>
    <p>n nn-1 n-1  Inter-departure delay y(n)</p>
    <p>n is random delay noise</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Stochastic Queuing Model 2  The distribution of y(n) becomes fairly</p>
    <p>complicate without making prior assumption about cross-traffic</p>
    <p>Derive asymptotic results about process y(n)</p>
    <p>Note that y(n) itself does not lead to any tractable results  Observation period of the process is very small</p>
    <p>Thus, define a time-average process Wn to be the average of {yi} up to time n:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-Pair Analysis</p>
    <p>Assume ergodic renewal cross-traffic  Delays between cross-traffic packets are i.i.d.</p>
    <p>arrival rate of cross-traffic</p>
    <p>size of cross-traffic packets</p>
    <p>random delay noise</p>
    <p>Claim 1: Time-average process Wn converges to:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-Pair Analysis 2</p>
    <p>Histogram of measured inter-arrival times yn</p>
    <p>values of y(n) (ms)</p>
    <p>fr e</p>
    <p>q u</p>
    <p>e n</p>
    <p>cy</p>
    <p>CBR cross-traffic TCP cross-traffic</p>
    <p>values of y(n) (ms) fr</p>
    <p>e q</p>
    <p>u e</p>
    <p>n cy</p>
    <p>None of CBR samples are located at</p>
    <p>Mean of sampled signal Wn is shifted from</p>
    <p>C = 1.5 mb/s ( = 8 ms), mb/s</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-Train Analysis</p>
    <p>What is a packet-train?  Bursts of probe packets sent back-to-back</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>k+1</p>
    <p>n=1n=2</p>
    <p>n is burst number</p>
    <p>k is the size of packet-train, which is the number of packets sent at a single burst n</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-Train Analysis 2  Some studies suggested that packet-train</p>
    <p>measurements converge to the available bandwidth  By Carter et al. (1996) and Ahlgren et al. (1999)</p>
    <p>No analytical evidence to this effect has been presented so far</p>
    <p>Is this really true?</p>
    <p>Other studies used packet-train estimates to increase the measurement accuracy  Dovrolis et al. (INFOCOM 2001)</p>
    <p>Not clear how these samples benefit estimation process</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-Train Analysis 3</p>
    <p>Next, we examine packet-train methods</p>
    <p>Provide statistical insights on this technique</p>
    <p>Define packet-train samples as the average of inter-packet arrival delays within each burst n</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-Train Analysis 4</p>
    <p>Claim 2: For sufficiently large k, constant xn=x, and regenerative arrival process of cross-traffic, packet-train samples converge to Gaussian distribution for large n:</p>
    <p>Next assume renewal cross-traffic</p>
    <p>mean = E[yn]</p>
    <p>tends to zero for large k as long as Var[Xi] is finite</p>
    <p>variance Inter-arrival time of cross-traffic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-Train Analysis 5</p>
    <p>Histograms of measured inter-arrival times based on packet-trains with burst lengths k</p>
    <p>k = 5 k = 10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Packet-Train Analysis 6  Our results in Claim 2 offer statistical explanation</p>
    <p>for prior findings (e.g., Dovrolis et al. INFOCOM 2001) :  The histogram of packet-train samples becomes</p>
    <p>unimodal with increased k</p>
    <p>The distribution of packet-train samples exhibits lower variance as packet-train size k increase</p>
    <p>Packet-train histograms for large k tend to a single mode whose location is independent of burst size k</p>
    <p>However, there is no evidence that packet-train samples measure the available bandwidth</p>
    <p>Deeper analysis is in our IMC 2004 paper</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Arbitrary Cross-Traffic</p>
    <p>Observe that neither the i.i.d. assumption nor stationarity holds for regular Internet traffic</p>
    <p>Thus, we build another model using PASTA principles  Restricts sampling process, but works with arbitrary</p>
    <p>cross-traffic</p>
    <p>Only assumption we impose on cross-traffic is the existence of its finite time-average</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Arbitrary Cross-Traffic 2</p>
    <p>PASTA is based on Poisson sampling</p>
    <p>Sample with i.i.d. exponential random delays</p>
    <p>time</p>
    <p>r(t)</p>
    <p>t1 t2 t3 tn</p>
    <p>The average of r(ti) converges to</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Arbitrary Cross-Traffic 3</p>
    <p>In actual probing, Poisson sampling is achieved by sending packet-pairs with exponential intervals</p>
    <p>V1V2</p>
    <p>Metric Vi is an exponential random variable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Arbitrary Cross-Traffic 4</p>
    <p>It can be shown that time-average process Wn converges to:</p>
    <p>Notice that the above equation is a linear function of x   is the intercept and is the slope</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Arbitrary Cross-Traffic 4</p>
    <p>Claim 4: For a single congested bottleneck with finite time-average rate, the estimate of  at time n converges to :</p>
    <p>from  We next separate</p>
    <p>two different spacings xa and xb</p>
    <p>Use two sets of measurements and with</p>
    <p>time-average of</p>
    <p>time-average of</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Arbitrary Cross-Traffic 5</p>
    <p>Also, the following estimates of available bandwidth converge to A:</p>
    <p>From claim 4, estimated capacity converges to C:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Arbitrary Cross-Traffic 6</p>
    <p>Evolution of estimation errors with C=1.5 mb/s and 85% link utilization</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Arbitrary Cross-Traffic 7</p>
    <p>Compare available bandwidth estimation errors</p>
    <p>Relative error</p>
    <p>Ours Pathload Spruce IGI</p>
    <p>Bottleneck capacity</p>
    <p>C (mb/s)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Arbitrary Cross-Traffic 8</p>
    <p>Relative estimation errors produced by Spruce and IGI with C=1.5 mb/s and 85% link utilization</p>
    <p>Spruce IGI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More on Spruce and IGI</p>
    <p>Notice that Spruce/IGI require prior knowledge about bottleneck capacity C</p>
    <p>Pathrate IGI/Spruce</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Single-node case is tractable with stationary renewal cross-traffic and arbitrary sampling  It is also tractable under arbitrary cross-traffic and</p>
    <p>Poisson sampling</p>
    <p>Both C and A can be estimated simultaneously</p>
    <p>Multi-link appears difficult</p>
    <p>Low-rate sampling and deeper stochastic analysis of existing methods are in our IMC 2004 paper</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
