<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From an IP Address to a Street Address: Using Wireless Signals to Locate a Target!</p>
    <p>Craig A. Shue (WPI), Nathanael Paul (USF)! And Curtis R. Taylor (WPI)!</p>
    <p>! !</p>
    <p>WOOT 13! August 12, 2013! Washington, D.C.!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline!  Motivation and Goals!  Current Approaches!  Our Approach!</p>
    <p>Covert Wireless Signaling!  Experiments!  Countermeasures!  Summary!  Future Development!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation!  Online criminals must be apprehended!</p>
    <p>Child predators, online assailants!  Current work is not accurate or fast</p>
    <p>enough for many law enforcement purposes!  ISP subpoenas are slow.!</p>
    <p>Most US homes use wireless networks (61% - 80% in recent studies [1])!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goals!  Fast localization!</p>
    <p>Under an hour would be excellent!  Precise localization!</p>
    <p>Street address or exact triangulation!  Avoid the need for ISP subpoenas!</p>
    <p>Best to avoid any special law enforcement power!  Universally applicable!</p>
    <p>Works on targeted computers, smartphones, tablets, etc.!  Use only commodity hardware and software!</p>
    <p>Keep approach inexpensive!  Minimally invasive/noticeable!</p>
    <p>Avoid alerts to all but most sophisticated targets!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Approaches!  Wang et al. [2] used latency</p>
    <p>measurements to get within 690m radius circle.!  US census: up to 33,000 people near NYC!  Depends on many servers as landmarks for</p>
    <p>better accuracy!  Chen et al. [3] linked activity behind NATs.!  Area approximation based on IP prefix!</p>
    <p>Not reliable!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach!  Bridges gap between Wang and Chen.!  Assumes Wangs localization of 690m!  Uses covert wireless signals!  Consists of 3 components: the Observer,</p>
    <p>Signaler, and Target!  Signaler sends communication to Target!  Observer physically searches for signal!</p>
    <p>Code name: Marco Polo!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Layout of Components!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Covert Wireless Signals!  Concerned only with packet sizes!</p>
    <p>Packet length field is not encrypted!  We found [750-1500] byte packets to be</p>
    <p>relatively uncommon.!  Shared packet sizes and timestamps in</p>
    <p>advance!  Sharing the database allows signaling and</p>
    <p>observing to be separated without requiring the parties to communicate.!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Signaling Requirements!  Access points (APs) do not require</p>
    <p>connections.!  They send directly to the Target.!  Used in many cases, including universities!</p>
    <p>Network Address Translation (NAT) requires a connection!  Lure Target through honeypots (FBI)</p>
    <p>purporting to offer contraband!  Peer-to-Peer NAT traversal!  Hidden iFrames!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Signaling Mechanisms!  Must traverse NAT device, but</p>
    <p>prevent it from reaching user applications!</p>
    <p>Signal can be sent out-of-band.!  Use out-of-window TCP packets!</p>
    <p>Traverses NAT using existing mapping!  Inconspicuously discarded by Targets kernel!</p>
    <p>Out-of-band signals allow applicationagnostic signaling.!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Manipulating NAT Devices!  Connection termination does not necessarily</p>
    <p>stop the packet flow!</p>
    <p>In fact, the routers terminating transmissions violate RFCs 2663 and 5382 !</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>Router Model Forwards Out-ofWindow Packets</p>
    <p>Forwards After Termination</p>
    <p>Belkin F5D8235-4 yes yes</p>
    <p>D-Link DIR-655 yes yes</p>
    <p>Linksys E900 yes no</p>
    <p>Linksys WRT54G yes yes</p>
    <p>Netgear WNDR3700 yes yes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments!  Conducted two real-world experiments!</p>
    <p>Apartment setting!  Residential neighborhood!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Residential Neighborhood!  Target connected to HTTP server</p>
    <p>(Signaler) on WPI campus from home wireless network!</p>
    <p>Target stayed connected for the duration of the experiment!  Approximately 40 minutes!</p>
    <p>Observer physically traversed search region with laptop and wireless adapter!  Also had pre-shared packet sizes and</p>
    <p>timestamps ahead of time.!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Residential Neighborhood (continued)!</p>
    <p>Figure 1: Approximate 690m radius target was located in. Blue depicts path traveled.</p>
    <p>Figure 2: True positives and false positives seen in outlined region.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Residential Study!  Narrowed to three houses!  Target signals blocked by obstacles!</p>
    <p>Wireless router between fireplace and TV!  Target didnt want to bias the experiment by</p>
    <p>moving the router!  Experiment did not use enhancements!</p>
    <p>Directional antennas!  Use of RSSI to determine signal power!</p>
    <p>Potential for better results!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Countermeasures!  Hardwire !  Proxy server!  Router packet size obfuscation!</p>
    <p>However, doesnt protect burst patterns!  Anomaly detection!</p>
    <p>E.g., out-of-window packets!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implications!  Internet users are clearly not anonymous!  Anyone can do such tracking!  Legality !</p>
    <p>US federal judge ruled unencrypted data as being, readily available to the general public, and thus is legal to record under an exception of the Wiretap Act [4].!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary!  Ability to quickly locate wireless target!  Approach uses three components!</p>
    <p>Signaler, observer, and target!  Uses existing software and hardware!</p>
    <p>Cost effective!  Works on encrypted networks!  Uses covert wireless signals!  Works in different environments!  Raises privacy concerns!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Directions!  More experiments!  Specialized equipment!</p>
    <p>Directional antenna!  Transition to practical setting!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?!  Citations!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WiFi Police!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
