<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inaudible Sound as a Covert Channel in Mobile Devices</p>
    <p>Luke Deshotels</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Gist</p>
    <p>Leaking Data</p>
    <p>Oblivious Humans</p>
    <p>Malicious Receiver</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two Types of Inaudible Sound</p>
    <p>Isolated Sound  Vibrator and Accelerometer  Felt but not heard  Discussed in paper</p>
    <p>Ultrasonic Sound  Speaker to Microphone  Dog Whistle  Focus of Presentation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sound vs. Radio</p>
    <p>Radio (4G, Wi-Fi, Bluetooth, etc.)  Requires permissions  Security extensions monitor network connections  Often disabled by careful users</p>
    <p>Sound (Speakers)  No permissions  Often ignored by security extensions and users  Preventing detection is non-trivial</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ultrasonic Sound Assumptions</p>
    <p>Victim cannot hear 18khz or higher  Only intended frequencies are produced</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ultrasonic Sound Proof of Concept FrequenSee App on AndroidDog Whistle Free App on iOS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prior Knowledge Frequency Shift Keying</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Questions</p>
    <p>Transmission speed?  Recorder/attacker proximity?  Pockets?  Practical Attacks?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Constants  Low Frequency 0: 18khz  High Frequency 1: 19khz  Device: Nexus 7 2013 Edition</p>
    <p>Variables  Bitrate  Distance  Fabric</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimization</p>
    <p>Audible Clicks on Phase Shifts  Amplitude Bias Against Phase Shifts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bitrate Results*</p>
    <p>Bitrate Limit ~345 bits/sec *Plots are for illustration, but are not real data</p>
    <p>bitrate x 1</p>
    <p>bitrate x 2</p>
    <p>bitrate x 8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Error Rate Evaluation</p>
    <p>Multiple Decoding Scheme  Parity Numbers  Transmission: 0s1t2r3a4w5b6e7r8r9y  Received: 0t1t2r3a4w5b6e7r8r9y</p>
    <p>rs6tzaya4w5b6e7r8r9y *&amp;(lasfn20981hn4029x</p>
    <p>Error Rate: 3.75% (3 bit errors out of 80)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distance Results</p>
    <p>Distance Limit  ~100 feet</p>
    <p>Device in pocket still leaks data at 20 feet. *How did we get a Nexus 7 in a pocket?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Abuses</p>
    <p>Used to bypass information flow security.  PasswordManager leaks data to other app  PasswordManager leaks data to other</p>
    <p>device</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Large Scale Abuse Scenario</p>
    <p>Devices emit unique identifiers  Recorders in entrances forward IDs to</p>
    <p>tracking systems  Tracks devices with disabled networking</p>
    <p>(GPS, 4G, Wi-Fi, etc.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solutions</p>
    <p>Hardware solutions  Embed limits or use physical filters  Indicator light</p>
    <p>Software solutions  App to detect or log ultrasonic activity</p>
    <p>Train dogs to destroy ultrasonic devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Higher frequencies on other devices  Alternatives to frequency shift keying  More sophisticated recording devices  Implement solutions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions? Source code available:</p>
    <p>https://bitbucket.org/ladeshot/ultrasonicfsk</p>
    <p>alecdeshotels@gmail.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Speaker Frequency Limits</p>
    <p>Source: http://www.avsforum.com/forum/113-subwoofers-bass-transducers/1487271-spectrum-labsdifferent-slope-than-room-subwoofer-frequency-sweeps.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Accelerometer Attacks</p>
    <p>Tapprints</p>
    <p>(Sp)iPhone</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Isolated Sound Proof of Concept VibrationX App Accelerometer Monitor App on Touching Device</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quiet Sound Assumptions</p>
    <p>No drum-like surfaces  Not touching user  Not near users ear  No animals</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inspiration</p>
    <p>Covert Channels  Forbidden communication between processes  For example: bank app talking to game app</p>
    <p>Limits of Human Perception  Mobile Devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demonstrations</p>
    <p>Follow along:  FrequenSee for Android  Dog Whistle Free for iOS Demos  Clicks  Without Clicks</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
