<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs</p>
    <p>A Case-Study on Twitter</p>
    <p>Saptarshi Ghosh Gautam Korlam Niloy Ganguly</p>
    <p>Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur, India</p>
    <p>June 22, 2010</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 1/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Restrictions in OSNs</p>
    <p>Most popular OSNs impose restrictions on the number of friends / connections that a member can have</p>
    <p>First line of defence against spam: prevent establishing friendship links with indiscriminately large number of legitimate users</p>
    <p>Reduce strain on the system: most OSNs allow real-time communication from a user to all her friends</p>
    <p>Soft cut-off imposed by Twitter in contrast to fixed or hard limits applied by most OSNs</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 2/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation of analyzing restrictions</p>
    <p>Restrictions often criticised as encroachment on the freedom of users to have more friends</p>
    <p>Required to design effective restrictions: analysis of the effects of different forms of restrictions on the link-creation dynamics in OSNs</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 3/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Restriction in Twitter</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 4/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Twitter social network</p>
    <p>Twitter users communicate through the exchange of tweets: tweets posted by a user made available to all her followers</p>
    <p>Twitter users form a directed social network: user u follows user v if u is interested in tweets posted by v</p>
    <p>Nodes: Twitter users Edges: u  v if member u follows member v Out-degree of u  us social activity or her interest to collect information from other members In-degree of u  popularity of u in the Twitter social network</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 5/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Follow Spam in Twitter</p>
    <p>Growing popularity of Twitter since 2008 has attracted the attention of spammers</p>
    <p>Many Twitter users engage in Aggressive Following or Follow spam</p>
    <p>Follow spam is the act of following mass numbers of people, not because youre actually interested in their tweets, but simply to gain attention, get views of your profile (and possibly clicks on URLs therein), or (ideally) to get followed back. [2]</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 6/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Twitter Follow-limit</p>
    <p>August 2008: Twitter restricted the number of users that a user can follow (i.e. out-degree) to curb follow-spam and reduce strain on the website [1]</p>
    <p>Every user is allowed to follow up to 2000 others, but Once youve followed 2000 users, there are limits to the number of additional users you can follow: this limit is different for every user and is based on your ratio of followers to following.</p>
    <p>Limits improve site performance by ensuring that when we send a persons message to all of their followers, the sending of that message is meaningful.&quot;</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 7/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Twitter Follow-limit (contd.)</p>
    <p>Twitter does not specify the restriction fully in public</p>
    <p>We dont reveal exact limits, because its somewhat complicated and, more importantly, if you were to tell spammers exactly what the filtering rules are on your email or, say, Googles PageRank, theyd just engineer their way around them much more easily. [2]</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 8/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conjectures on Twitter Follow-limit</p>
    <p>uin: number of followers (in-degree) of user u</p>
    <p>umaxout : maximum number of members whom u can herself follow (maximum possible out-degree)</p>
    <p>version 1: umaxout = max{2000, 1.1  uin}</p>
    <p>version 2: umaxout =</p>
    <p>{</p>
    <p>Basically, if a user wants to follow (out-degree) more than 2000, she needs to have at least a certain number of followers (in-degree) herself</p>
    <p>Version 1 much more stringent compared to version 2</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 9/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments on Twitter and Observations</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 10/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Collection using Twitter API Challenges</p>
    <p>Twitter social network has grown too large to collect the entire network Twitter allows at most 150 API calls per hour</p>
    <p>Breadth-first search used to collect 1 million nodes during October 23 - November 8, 2009.</p>
    <p>Information collected for each user: #friends, #followers, #tweets posted, date of creation of the account, geographical location, ...</p>
    <p>Several smaller crawls starting from randomly selected nodes, during different dates; degree distributions of samples found to be stable irrespective of starting point and time</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 11/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scatter plot of followers / friends spread</p>
    <p>Number of friends (following)</p>
    <p>N u</p>
    <p>m b</p>
    <p>e r</p>
    <p>o f</p>
    <p>fo llo</p>
    <p>w e</p>
    <p>rs</p>
    <p>(left) In Jan-Feb 2008, reproduced from [4]</p>
    <p>(right) In Oct-Nov, 2009 (after restriction imposed)</p>
    <p>very few users have &gt; 2000 friends (about 6.68%)</p>
    <p>most users having &gt; 2000 friends lie left of the x = 1.1  y</p>
    <p>line: #friends  1.1  #followers</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 12/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Degree Distributions</p>
    <p>p k</p>
    <p>number of followers (in-degree), k</p>
    <p>Twitter data power-law fit</p>
    <p>p k</p>
    <p>number of friends (out-degree), k</p>
    <p>Twitter data power-law fit</p>
    <p>(left) in-degree distribution (right) out-degree distribution</p>
    <p>both show power-law fits pk  k 1.0 for k &lt; 2000</p>
    <p>sharp spike in out-degree distributon around 2000  a significant fraction of members unable to increase their number of friends beyond a certain limit near 2000</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 13/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation of analyzing restrictions</p>
    <p>Restrictions often criticised as an encroachment on the freedom of users to have more friends</p>
    <p>Requirements to design effective restrictions: Analysis of the effects of different forms of restrictions on the link-creation dynamics in OSNs</p>
    <p>Topological properties of OSNs can change significantly due to imposed restrictions on node-degree</p>
    <p>Formulate an analytical framework to study the effects of such restrictions on the degree-distribution of a network</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 14/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modeling restricted growth dynamics of OSNs</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 15/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Preferentiality in link dynamics</p>
    <p>Preferential creation of links</p>
    <p>Members create new links in proportion to their current</p>
    <p>out-degree</p>
    <p>A member already having many out-links (friends) is socially</p>
    <p>more active, hence more likely to create more out-links</p>
    <p>Preferential reception of links</p>
    <p>Members receive new links in proportion to their current</p>
    <p>in-degree</p>
    <p>A member who already has many in-links (followers) is a</p>
    <p>popular member, hence more likely to get new followers</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 16/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model by Krapivsky et. al.</p>
    <p>We customize a growth model [3] for directed networks by incorporating restrictions on degree</p>
    <p>At each time step, one of the following events occurs:</p>
    <p>Event 1: with probability p, a new node introduced</p>
    <p>Event 2: with probability q = 1  p, a new directed edge u  v created between two existing nodes</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 17/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model (contd.)</p>
    <p>Event 1: with probability p, a new node u introduced</p>
    <p>u forms a directed out-edge to an existing node v</p>
    <p>Probability of a particular v being selected  (vin + )</p>
    <p>New member u is more likely to follow a popular member v</p>
    <p>Event 2: with probability q = 1  p, a new directed edge u  v created between two existing nodes</p>
    <p>Probability of a particular u  v edge  (uout + )(vin + )</p>
    <p>A socially active member u is more likely to follow another</p>
    <p>member v, especially if v is popular herself</p>
    <p>, : model parameters that introduce randomness in preferential rules</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 18/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model (contd.)</p>
    <p>Nij(t): average number of nodes with in-degree i, out-degree j at time t</p>
    <p>Rate of change in Nij(t) due to change in in-degree of nodes:</p>
    <p>dNij dt in</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>[</p>
    <p>(i  1 + )Ni1, j  (i + )Nij I + N</p>
    <p>]</p>
    <p>Rate of change in Nij(t) due to change in out-degree of nodes:</p>
    <p>dNij dt out</p>
    <p>= q</p>
    <p>[</p>
    <p>(j  1 + )Ni,j1ij  (j + )Niji,j+1 J + N</p>
    <p>]</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 19/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How does Nij change with time? (contd.)</p>
    <p>The total rate of change in the number Nij of (i, j)-nodes is</p>
    <p>dNij dt</p>
    <p>= dNij dt in</p>
    <p>+ dNij dt out</p>
    <p>+ pi0j1</p>
    <p>Last term accounts for introduction of new nodes with in-degree 0 and out-degree 1</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 20/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Incorporating restrictions in the model</p>
    <p>Restrictions  only a fraction of the existing nodes can create new out-links</p>
    <p>ij = 1 iff members having in-degree i are allowed to have out-degree j</p>
    <p>Can be defined to model a variety of restrictions</p>
    <p>Notations used to specify different generalized restrictions:</p>
    <p>kc: out-degree at which the restriction starts (2000 in Twitter) -percent rule ( = 10 in Twitter)</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 21/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Twitter Follow-limit (recap)</p>
    <p>uin: number of followers (in-degree) of user u</p>
    <p>umaxout : maximum number of members whom u can herself follow (maximum possible out-degree)</p>
    <p>version 1 (known as the 10% rule):</p>
    <p>umaxout = max{2000, 1.1  uin}</p>
    <p>version 2:</p>
    <p>umaxout =</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 22/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modeling different restrictions For version 1:</p>
    <p>ij =</p>
    <p>)i }, i</p>
    <p>For version 2:</p>
    <p>ij =</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>)i</p>
    <p>For a hard cut-off at out-degree kc:</p>
    <p>ij =</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 23/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Significance of the model parameters</p>
    <p>p: controls the relative number of nodes and edges (network density)</p>
    <p>the average in-degree and average out-degree are both 1/p density of OSNs known to vary over time [5]</p>
    <p>, : how closely the dynamics of link-formation follow preferential attachment</p>
    <p>preferential attachment may increase due to recommendation of popular members to new members (as done in Twitter)</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 24/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results from the model</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 25/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Validating the model</p>
    <p>Proposed theoretical model validated by stochastic simulation</p>
    <p>Parameters: p = 0.01,  =  = 1.0, kc = 50,  = 10</p>
    <p>Exact agreement of the simulation results with theory</p>
    <p>p (k</p>
    <p>)</p>
    <p>in-degree k</p>
    <p>simulation theory</p>
    <p>p (k</p>
    <p>)</p>
    <p>out-degree k</p>
    <p>simulation theory</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 26/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Different Types of Restrictions</p>
    <p>No Cutoff power-law fit</p>
    <p>No restriction</p>
    <p>Hard Cutoff power-law fit</p>
    <p>Hard cutoff</p>
    <p>Twitter cutoff v1 power-law fit</p>
    <p>Twitter restriction version 1</p>
    <p>Twitter cutoff v2 power-law fit</p>
    <p>Twitter restriction version 2</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 27/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Different Types of Restrictions (contd.)</p>
    <p>Both hard and soft restrictions reduce the absolute value of the power-law exponent</p>
    <p>Smaller || indicates a more homogeneous structure of the network w.r.t. degrees  reduces strain on hubs</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 28/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Effects of the network dynamics</p>
    <p>Fraction of nodes that cross the restriction (out of all nodes) measured for different  =  and p</p>
    <p>Increases rapidly with  (= ) for their lower values, but</p>
    <p>stabilizes for higher values of  (= )</p>
    <p>Reduces sharply with increase in p signifying lesser activity</p>
    <p>and more growth</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>p</p>
    <p>=  = 1.0  =  = 5.0</p>
    <p>=  = 15.0  =  = 30.0</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 29/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Choice of cut-off parameters</p>
    <p>=  = 1.0  =  = 5.0</p>
    <p>=  = 15.0  =  = 30.0</p>
    <p>=  = 1.0  =  = 5.0</p>
    <p>=  = 15.0  =  = 30.0</p>
    <p>Number of nodes which cross Twitter cut-off (version 1),</p>
    <p>measured as a fraction of total number of nodes</p>
    <p>Different values of  =  in the range 1.0 to 30.0</p>
    <p>Does not change appreciably with</p>
    <p>Falls rapidly with increase in kc, for more random dynamics</p>
    <p>(relatively higher values of  = )</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 30/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Choice of cut-off parameters (contd.)</p>
    <p>=  = 1.0  =  = 5.0</p>
    <p>=  = 15.0  =  = 30.0 0</p>
    <p>=  = 1.0  =  = 5.0</p>
    <p>=  = 15.0  =  = 30.0</p>
    <p>Number of nodes which cross Twitter cut-off (version 1),</p>
    <p>measured as a fraction of the number of nodes which approach</p>
    <p>the cut-off</p>
    <p>Different values of  =  in the range 1.0 to 30.0</p>
    <p>relatively invariant with kc</p>
    <p>reduces with the increase in , especially in the range</p>
    <p>&lt; 10 The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 31/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions drawn from the model</p>
    <p>Preferentiality hinders users from crossing the restriction</p>
    <p>Role of different restriction parameters Importance of kc: to limit the fraction of members in the whole network, that are able to cross an imposed cut-off Importance of : more effective in deciding what fraction of the members who approach the cut-off are able to overcome it</p>
    <p>Proposed model can also be used to design restrictions with varying levels of difficulty in overcoming them</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 32/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References [1] Twitter support: Following limits and best practices.</p>
    <p>http://help.twitter.com/forums/10711/entries/68916.</p>
    <p>[2] Twitter blog: Making progress on spam. http://blog.twitter.com/2008/08/making-progress-on-spam.html, August 2008.</p>
    <p>[3] KRAPIVSKY, P. L., RODGERS, G. J., AND REDNER, S. Degree distributions of growing networks. Phys. Rev. Lett. 86, 23 (Jun 2001), 54015404.</p>
    <p>[4] KRISHNAMURTHY, B., GILL, P., AND ARLITT, M. A few chirps about twitter. In WOSN 08 (2008), ACM, pp. 1924.</p>
    <p>[5] KUMAR, R., NOVAK, J., AND TOMKINS, A. Structure and evolution of online social networks. In KDD (2006), ACM, pp. 611617.</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 33/34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You</p>
    <p>Complex Network Research Group Department of CSE, IIT Kharagpur, India http://www.cse-web.iitkgp.ernet.in/~cnerg/</p>
    <p>The Effects of Restrictions on Number of Connections in OSNs  p. 34/34</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
