<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to Phone Home with Someone Elses Phone</p>
    <p>INFORMATION EXFILTRATION USING INTENTIONAL SOUND NOISE ON GYROSCOPIC SENSORS</p>
    <p>Benyamin Farshteindiker Nir Hassidim Asaf Grosz Yossi Oren</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Poster Session on Thursday</p>
    <p>Come and watch a live attack on Thursday at 18:30.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Introduction Gyroscopes On Personal Devices The Attack Results Countermeasures Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implant Architecture  Secret Collection  Microphone, camera, side-channel probe.  Secret Exfiltration  RF backscatter, acoustical coupling, this work.</p>
    <p>Power Supply  Passive power, battery.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline Introduction</p>
    <p>Gyroscopes On Personal Devices The Attack Results Countermeasures Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Gyroscopes On Personal Devices</p>
    <p>MEMS gyroscopes sense the angular rate of rotation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline Introduction Gyroscopes On Personal Devices</p>
    <p>The Attack Results Countermeasures Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Attack  Attack model Base assumptions:  The adversary manages to place the implant near the victims</p>
    <p>mobile device.  The implant has some secret it wishes to exfiltrate.  The attacker has the ability to make the victims mobile device</p>
    <p>display a website or run some unprivileged application.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Attack  Evaluation Setup</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Attack  PRBS example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Attack  Advantages Advantages of our exfiltration scheme over traditional methods:  Gyro access requires zero permissions or notifications  Sensitivity of the sensor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline Introduction Gyroscopes On Personal Devices The Attack</p>
    <p>Results Countermeasures Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results  Error rate  Increasing amount of samples per data bit improve the results.</p>
    <p>Audio signal cant be heard by the human ear or detected as motion.</p>
    <p>Consumes less than 10 microwatt of power.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results  Activity profiles</p>
    <p>Samsung S5 results tested on different user activities running a native application.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results  Capacity and power bounds</p>
    <p>Theoretical capacity of the channel is 1 Kbps with 60 Hz sampling rate.</p>
    <p>Can grow over 4 Kbps when increasing the sampling rate.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline Introduction Gyroscopes On Personal Devices The Attack Results</p>
    <p>Countermeasures Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Countermeasures  Require permission to the gyroscope.  Lower the sampling rate.  Physical modification.  Sensor fusion.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline Introduction Gyroscopes On Personal Devices The Attack Results Countermeasures</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions  Low cost implants  No exposure risk  Undetectable bugs  Allow monitoring many implants simultaneously</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions  Two factor authentication</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Benyamin Farshteindiker farshben@post.bgu.ac.il</p>
    <p>https://iss.oy.ne.ro/PhoneHome</p>
    <p>* Dont forget to come to our poster session on Thursday.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
