<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>dr0wned Cyber-Physical Attack with Additive Manufacturing</p>
    <p>Sofia Belikovetsky Ben-Gurion University of the Negev</p>
    <p>Mark Yampolskiy University of South Alabama</p>
    <p>Jinghui Toh Singapore University of Technology and Design</p>
    <p>Jacob Gatlin University of South Alabama</p>
    <p>Yuval Elovici Ben-Gurion University of the Negev,</p>
    <p>Singapore University of Technology and Design</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Agenda o Introduction oManufacturing process oThe attack  Goal of attack  Methodology  Results</p>
    <p>oScale up</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is Additive Manufacturing?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Its already everywhere</p>
    <p>Entrepreneur Magazine 3D Printer Times</p>
    <p>metalocus.es http://3d-print.today/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation The FAA Cleared The First 3D Printed Part To Fly In A Commercial Jet Engine From GE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Manufacturing Process</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Manufacturing Process</p>
    <p>Additive Manufacturing Technologies - Gibson et al 8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AM Cyber Threats</p>
    <p>Violation of Intellectual property</p>
    <p>Sabotage attacks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Attack</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reducing the fatigue life of a 3D printed object Motivation: Create delayed damage, so that the object breaks after integration into critical system</p>
    <p>Goals:</p>
    <p>o Demonstration of a NEW sabotage attack that targets the fatigue life of a manufactured part in order to damage the system the integrates the part.</p>
    <p>o Present and experimentally validate the attack</p>
    <p>o Generalize the attack</p>
    <p>Evaluation Methods:</p>
    <p>o Experimental lab and field testing to assess the introduced damage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Use Case: Sabotage of Replacement Propeller via a fatigue attack</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>STL/AMF Propeller Design</p>
    <p>Personal Computer</p>
    <p>Source and Auxiliary Material Suppliers</p>
    <p>Replacement Propeller</p>
    <p>Quadcopter UAV</p>
    <p>Use Case: Sabotage of Replacement Propeller via a fatigue attack</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Systematic Analysis of attack chains</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Manipulation The Location of the Defect: Joint connection of the blades to the cap</p>
    <p>Iteration through Defects: 0.1 mm gaps  best for the time restrains</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lab tests Testing setup:</p>
    <p>o Installed a benign and sabotaged propellers on a drone in a lab</p>
    <p>o Examined the maximal RPM and time of each</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Field Trials Testing setup:</p>
    <p>o Replacing the propellers of a drone with AM printed copies.</p>
    <p>o 3 benign and 1 sabotaged</p>
    <p>o Operating the drone under regular conditions</p>
    <p>Results:</p>
    <p>oBreakage after 1:42 minutes of normal operation</p>
    <p>oWhen the drone was mid-flight</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The selected attack chain</p>
    <p>Phishing attack  Controller PC  STL files  Insertion of Gaps  Faster development of Fatigue time =&gt; Destruction of the drone</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Video</p>
    <p>Link: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zUnSpT6jSys</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Yes but Isnt it easy to detect? o The change in weight is less than 3%</p>
    <p>o The change in printing time is 1 minute out of 1:17 hours</p>
    <p>o Signing your G-code is very limiting</p>
    <p>o It can be offline</p>
    <p>o It can be generalized</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scale up the attack Proposal:</p>
    <p>oAutomatic attack of G-Code files</p>
    <p>oThe files contain critical manufacturing information that stored only there</p>
    <p>oThe files are hard to verify</p>
    <p>Automatic search for weak spots: find significantly smaller joint points</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scale up the attack (Cont.)  Split printing moves into two, skipping the part that intersects with the gaps</p>
    <p>Integrate the script into worm for maximum reach</p>
    <p>=&gt; G0 X106.0 154.450</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions A real threat!</p>
    <p>o Expect to see a lot of research and developments in this field o Opportunity to shape the security in this industry</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>digitalistmag</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
