<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>USENIX WOOT 2018  TU Berlin  Electrical Engineering and Computer Science  Chair for Security in Telecommunications  13. August 2018</p>
    <p>Swipe Your Fingerprints! How Biometric Authentication Simplifies Payment, Access and Identity Fraud Julian Fietkau, Starbug, Jean-Pierre Seifert Security in Telecommunications - Technische Universitt Berlin</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18</p>
    <p>A Norwegian tech company challenging the status quo of identification  Build smart cards secured by your fingerprint instead of a secret PIN  Match-on-card Principle: Fingerprint data stored and processed only on the card  Already started to integrate their Platform into multiple Products</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Access Control Payment ID card</p>
    <p>2</p>
    <p>(not available)(available) (under test)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18</p>
    <p>3</p>
    <p>Access Control Demo Kit</p>
    <p>Get it from the online-shop ~ $200  Programmable NFC tag  Match-on-card platform</p>
    <p>Easy to use  Much faster than PIN  Nothing to remember</p>
    <p>How secure is this?</p>
    <p>Introduction - Access Control Demo Kit</p>
    <p>Green LED</p>
    <p>Sensor</p>
    <p>Clam Shell</p>
    <p>Red LED</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18Introduction - How Fingerprint Authentication Works?</p>
    <p>Skin is formed by ridges and valleys</p>
    <p>Unique for everyone and hence can be used to identify a human</p>
    <p>Minutiae-based Matching: Special sections are called minutiae ridge end, ridge bifurcation,</p>
    <p>4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18Introduction - Minutiae-based Matching</p>
    <p>Enrollment</p>
    <p>5</p>
    <p>[1]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18Introduction - Minutiae-based Matching</p>
    <p>Verification</p>
    <p>suffering from a lot of noise</p>
    <p>6</p>
    <p>Variations of the same finger: Pressure, Rotation, Dryness, Cuts,</p>
    <p>Similarities of different fingers: Everyone has either loop, whorl or arch fingerprint (58.5%, 35%, 6.5%) [3]</p>
    <p>Fresh Template Stored Template</p>
    <p>= 876 Similarity Score</p>
    <p>Score &gt;= Threshold ?</p>
    <p>or REJECTACCEPT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18</p>
    <p>7</p>
    <p>Analysis - Hardware</p>
    <p>Remove the cover</p>
    <p>Identify components  CPU &amp; Sensor  NFC, Batterie, LEDs</p>
    <p>All components are connected with wires</p>
    <p>What do they send?  Record the signals</p>
    <p>Frontside Backside</p>
    <p>CPU</p>
    <p>Sensor</p>
    <p>LEDLED</p>
    <p>CPU</p>
    <p>Sensor Logic</p>
    <p>Analyzer</p>
    <p>Wires</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18</p>
    <p>8</p>
    <p>Analysis - Communication</p>
    <p>Insecure on-device communication</p>
    <p>(Data send from the sensor)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18</p>
    <p>9</p>
    <p>Proof of Concept - Man in the Middle</p>
    <p>Cutting the wires and connect each end to an FPGA  Create a Design to pass-through or modify the communication data  Spoof the device in various ways, while a real test person is enrolled</p>
    <p>Spoof or pass-through</p>
    <p>CPU FPGA Sensor</p>
    <p>SPI</p>
    <p>MEM</p>
    <p>MOSI</p>
    <p>CLK</p>
    <p>MISO</p>
    <p>MOSI CLK</p>
    <p>MISO</p>
    <p>UART - USB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18</p>
    <p>10</p>
    <p>Replay a Valid Authentication</p>
    <p>Spoof or pass-through</p>
    <p>CPU FPGA Sensor</p>
    <p>SPI</p>
    <p>MEM</p>
    <p>MOSI</p>
    <p>CLK</p>
    <p>MISO</p>
    <p>MOSI CLK</p>
    <p>MISO</p>
    <p>UART - USB</p>
    <p>Accepted on first try, repeated multiple times  No replay or livenesses detection in place, no tamper protection violated</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18</p>
    <p>11</p>
    <p>Fuzzing the Payload!</p>
    <p>Reversing the protocol data and identify points of interest</p>
    <p>Change values and replay: Sensor version, image size, fuzz some random values  no relevant changes</p>
    <p>Change pre-images  still accepted</p>
    <p>Create a tool to overwrite the full image send by the sensor.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18</p>
    <p>12</p>
    <p>Vendor: fingerprint data cannot be extracted from the card</p>
    <p>Requested the test person intentionally touched a smart card surface  Search for suitable fingerprint residues:  Use a light source and align the card by 90 degree  Take pictures with standard iPhone 5 camera</p>
    <p>Created an extraction process to get a digital dummy we can inject.</p>
    <p>ACCE PT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18</p>
    <p>13</p>
    <p>Fingerprints on Digital Images</p>
    <p>Related work of Starbug [4]  Canon EOS-D1 X 200mm lens, outdoor daylight  Same extraction, but we need to flip and scale it.</p>
    <p>ups cale</p>
    <p>flip improve</p>
    <p>ACCEPT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18</p>
    <p>14</p>
    <p>Algorithmic Weaknesses</p>
    <p>Access to in-depth functions of the card allows black box analysis of the algorithm</p>
    <p>Proprietary fingerprint algorithm  Robust, fast &amp; most power efficient one  Patented in 2013</p>
    <p>Corner Case Evaluation  Missing 50% of a fingerprint is OK  Create minimal fingerprint to unlock  Ridges w/o minutiae can be removed</p>
    <p>or replaced with arbitrary ones</p>
    <p>Apply blur filter for better dummies</p>
    <p>Accept Accept Reject</p>
    <p>Accept Accept Reject</p>
    <p>Accept Accept Reject</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18</p>
    <p>15</p>
    <p>Algorithmic Weaknesses</p>
    <p>ISO/IEC 19794-2 Compliance</p>
    <p>Enrollment: minimum of 16 minutiae We enrolled and verified samples with 4.</p>
    <p>Verification: minimum of 12 minutiae We enrolled &gt; 16 minutiae and reduce it to 9.</p>
    <p>Hard to measure with black box testing, but the examples show that the ISO requirements are already violated.</p>
    <p>Enrolled Accept</p>
    <p>Enrolled Accept</p>
    <p>Enrolled Accept</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18</p>
    <p>16</p>
    <p>Known Template Attack</p>
    <p>Insecure memory technology, Software bugs, Side channel attacks,   Template data can be leaked</p>
    <p>Generate Fingerprints just from Template data?  Take the leaked template of the enrolled user  Create clearly counterfeit fingerprints just from this data</p>
    <p>ACCEPT ACCEPT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18</p>
    <p>17</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Scrutinised a (state-of-the-art) device of a new match-on-card platform  Weak matching algorithm with badly chosen thresholds  No software and hardware countermeasures in place (only memory protection)</p>
    <p>This match-on-card platform can be easily attacked in 3/4 ways according to threat model [5]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18Conclusion</p>
    <p>How to improve this and similar devices?</p>
    <p>Use 3-factor authentication: Card, Fingerprint and PIN (by default)</p>
    <p>Choose strong thresholds and decrease the false match rate, ISO/IEC 19794-2.</p>
    <p>Apply replay and liveness detection:</p>
    <p>Rolling or fuzzy hashes of already-seen fingerprints. (related work)</p>
    <p>Process multiple samples and integrate more sophisticated sensors.</p>
    <p>Protect the on-device communication: Encryption.</p>
    <p>Hardware countermeasures: Logic duplication, mesh detectors,</p>
    <p>Prevent side-channels: Dummy instructions, side channel free algorithms,</p>
    <p>18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18Conclusion</p>
    <p>Our research is always intended to help people, improve systems and point out risks to customers and stakeholders.</p>
    <p>Informed the company before publication  Requested to remove the name and all brands  Payment and ID cards are fundamentally different  The analyzed card is discontinued</p>
    <p>Access Card Demo Kits are still available  We dont know whether and how the fundamental differences impair</p>
    <p>the attacks on this or other devices</p>
    <p>19</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18Conclusion</p>
    <p>Research Paper: Swipe Your Fingerprints! https://www.usenix.org/conference/woot18/presentation/fietkau</p>
    <p>Check out our GitHub-repo, tools and lots of test data! https://github.com/julieeen/swipe</p>
    <p>Questions and requests jfietkau@sect.tu-berlin.de starbug@berlin.ccc.de jpseifert@sect.tu-berlin.de</p>
    <p>20</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18References</p>
    <p>[1] Product images from the Company Press Kit (anonymised)</p>
    <p>[2] ISO/IEC 19794-2 standard</p>
    <p>[3] The Fingerprints-World-Map</p>
    <p>[4] Starbug, Ich sehe, also bin ich ... du, Talk at 31C3, 2014.</p>
    <p>[5] Drmuth, Oswald, and Pastewka. Side-Channel Attacks on Fingerprint Matching Algorithms</p>
    <p>[6] Cappelli, Raffaele, et al., Fingerprint image reconstruction from standard templates., IEEE transactions on pattern analysis and machine intelligence 29.9 (2007).</p>
    <p>[7] Aditi Roy et al., MasterPrint: Exploring the Vulnerability of Partial Fingerprint-Based Authentication Systems., IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security 12.9 (2017): 2013-2025.</p>
    <p>[8] GitHub Repository [9] Saleae, The logic analyzer youll love to use.</p>
    <p>[10] Henniger, Scheuermann and Kniess. On security evaluation of fingerprint recognition systems. International Biometric Performance Testing Conference (IBPC). 2010.</p>
    <p>21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WOOT18Related Work</p>
    <p>Starbug, Ich sehe, also bin ich ... du [4] Collect and physically clone the biometric features with fingerprint fuming Extracting fingerprints from touched objects or photos of the victim, e.g. German Politicians</p>
    <p>Aditi Roy et al., MasterPrint [6] Synthesize fingerprints based on similarities from huge fingerprint databases, to impersonate users with a given probability. Do not allow to target a specific person. No real authentication system was bypassed, The generated MasterPrints are not published</p>
    <p>Known template attacks for minutiae-based matching algorithms [7] Create sophisticated and natural-looking fingerprints only from the numerical template data Evaluated the approach against a number of undisclosed state-of-the-art algorithms</p>
    <p>22</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
