<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dynamical Construction of a Core-Based Dynamical Construction of a Core-Based Group-Shared Multicast Tree in Mobile Ad Group-Shared Multicast Tree in Mobile Ad</p>
    <p>Hoc NetworksHoc Networks</p>
    <p>B.H. Liu, M.J. Tsai, and W.C. Ko Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>National Tsing Hua University</p>
    <p>Hsing Chu, Taiwan, ROC</p>
    <p>Speaker : Bing-Hong Liu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Agenda</p>
    <p>Introduction  The Heuristic  Simulation  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>core</p>
    <p>Introduction(1/2)</p>
    <p>Core-based group-shared tree  Shared by group members and rooted at core node  Core distributes the packets to and from all group</p>
    <p>members</p>
    <p>core</p>
    <p>Traditional Local broadcast operation</p>
    <p>Find a minimum non-leaf multicast tree</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction(2/2)</p>
    <p>Minimum non-leaf multicast tree Problem  No polynomial time approximation scheme</p>
    <p>unless P=NP  A distributed heuristic is needed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Reduction</p>
    <p>A reduction on one node reforms tree structure between this node and its all neighbors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Which node does the reduction?</p>
    <p>It leads us to define the profit of each tree node</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Profit Value  Nodes profit can be simply defined</p>
    <p>If the number of its neighbors is smaller than or equal to 2  Set to 0</p>
    <p>Otherwise  Set to the number of its neighbors - 2</p>
    <p>The node with larger profit value (&gt; 0) in its neighborhood can do the reduction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distributed Reduction Method(1/2) A cycle is constitute</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>This problem is solved by the election model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distributed Reduction Method(2/2)  Election model</p>
    <p>Each tree node elects a candidate with largest profit in its neighborhood</p>
    <p>A node can do the reduction when it is the candidate of each of itself and all neighbors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation(1/2)  Environment</p>
    <p>Network topology is generated by geometrically distributed network model [1]</p>
    <p>Group members are randomly selected from all nodes in the network</p>
    <p>Cost  The number of non-leaves in the multicast tree</p>
    <p>Comparison  Graph-center tree (GCT), multicast-center tree</p>
    <p>(MCT), and random-member tree (RMT)  RMT applied with our reduction method (RRMT)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation(2/2)</p>
    <p>X axis: The number of group members</p>
    <p>Y axis: The average ratio of the cost of other multicast tree to that of RRMT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>A heuristic is to reduce the cost of the multicast tree when the local broadcast operation is used</p>
    <p>RMT applied with our heuristic gets better performance than original one</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reference</p>
    <p>[1] S.K.S. Gupta and P.K. Srimani, Adaptive Core Selection and Migration Method for Multicast Routing in Mobile Ad Hoc Networks, IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems, vol. 14, no. 1, 2003,</p>
    <p>pp.2738.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
