<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sensorless, Permissionless Information Exfiltration with Wi-Fi Micro-Jamming</p>
    <p>R O M O G E N ( R O M O G @ P O S T. B G U . A C . I L )</p>
    <p>O M E R S H WA R T Z ( O M E R S H V @ P O S T. B G U . A C . I L )</p>
    <p>K F I R Z V I ( Z V I K F @ P O S T. B G U . A C . I L )</p>
    <p>Y O S S I O R E N ( Y O S @ B G U . A C . I L )</p>
    <p>B E N - G U R I O N U N I V E R S I T Y O F T H E N E G E V, I S R A E L</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background A covert listening device, more commonly known as a bug or a wire, is usually a combination of a miniature radio transmitter with a microphone. The use of bugs, called bugging, is a common technique in surveillance, espionage and police investigations.  - Wikipedia</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Previous Works Farshteindiker et al. [1] used a devices gyroscope to exfiltrate data through a victim device.</p>
    <p>A piezoelectric device causes interferences to the gyroscope sensor that are readable through a javascript running on the device.</p>
    <p>[1] Farshteindiker, Benyamin, Nir Hasidim, Asaf Grosz, and Yossi Oren. &quot;How to Phone Home with Someone Else's Phone: Information Exfiltration Using Intentional Sound Noise on Gyroscopic Sensors.&quot; In WOOT. 2016.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Objectives Develop and evaluate an exfiltration technique that maintains the advantages:</p>
    <p>While reducing the limitations:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Contribution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>&quot;Covert channels through external interference.&quot; Shah and Blaze [2] introduced the concept of an interference channel, which they defined as a covert channel that works by creating external interference on a shared communications medium</p>
    <p>[2] Shah, Gaurav, and Matt Blaze. &quot;Covert channels through external interference.&quot; Proceedings of the 3rd USENIX conference on Offensive technologies (WOOT09). 2009.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interference Channel The sender cannot communicate directly with the receiver.</p>
    <p>The victim is an uninvolved, unknowing device performing normal communications.</p>
    <p>The receiver is capable of receiving some output from the victim and has the ability to separate the benign data from the payload.</p>
    <p>The malicious communication is hiding in plain sight.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Micro-Jamming Many communication protocols, including 802.11, incorporate CCA (Clear Channel Assessment) mechanisms to maintain non-distruptiveness.</p>
    <p>By briefly jamming the radio channel, Wi-Fi frames and responses can be delayed for several milliseconds.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Micro-Jamming</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Micro-Jamming</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Micro-Jamming</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Micro-Jamming</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Traditional Jamming vs Micro-Jamming Traditional Jamming Micro-Jamming</p>
    <p>Mode of operation Packet loss Packet delay</p>
    <p>Network layers affected At least 1-2 Only layer 1</p>
    <p>Required transmission power Stronger than blocked signal Minimum required for sensing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test Setup - Active</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test Setup - Active</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test Setup - Active ATMEGA256RFR2 Xplained Pro evaluation board</p>
    <p>Keysight 33622A waveform generator</p>
    <p>Tektronix RSA604 real-time signal analyzer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Successful data transfer at rates of 40 bits-per-second with &lt;10% error rate.</p>
    <p>Effective to a range of 15+ meters, works through walls.</p>
    <p>Found functional at low transmission powers of -17 dBm, or 20 microwatts.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Micro-Jamming Done Passively When an antenna switches its impendence in a given frequency, it modulates reflects any ambient radio signals while imposing a frequency shift.</p>
    <p>Previous works[3] have used this phenomenon to shift one Wi-Fi channel to another while modulating data on top of it.</p>
    <p>Using similar techniques, it is possible to jam a Wi-Fi channel using zero energy for transmission.</p>
    <p>[3] Bryce Kellogg, Vamsi Talla, Shyamnath Gollakota, and Joshua R. Smith. Passive wi-fi: Bringing low power to wi-fi transmissions. 13th USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation, NSDI 2016, Santa Clara, CA, USA.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test Setup - Passive</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test Setup  Passive</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Test Setup  Passive</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Traditional Jamming vs Micro-Jamming (cont)</p>
    <p>Traditional Jamming Micro-Jamming</p>
    <p>Range vs transmission power Small, must overcome existing signals</p>
    <p>Large</p>
    <p>Can be done passively? Not effectively? Demonstrated in the paper</p>
    <p>Detectability Shows in standard network logs</p>
    <p>Hard to differentiate from noise</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions Micro-jamming was shown as an effective development over traditional jamming as a covert channel.</p>
    <p>Using micro-jamming, an implant can transmit over longer distances and use less power than with traditional jamming.</p>
    <p>In addition, micro-jamming allows for lower-profile exfiltration of data that is harder to detect without actively looking with the right equipment.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You  Any Questions?</p>
    <p>Rom Ogen (romog@post.bgu.ac.il)</p>
    <p>Omer Shwartz (omershv@post.bgu.ac.il)</p>
    <p>Kfir Zvi (zvikf@post.bgu.ac.il)</p>
    <p>Yossi Oren (yos@bgu.ac.il)</p>
    <p>https://iss.oy.ne.ro/Microjam</p>
    <p>Come see our live demo at the USENIX poster session!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
