<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Feasibility Study of Radio-frequency</p>
    <p>Retroreflector Attack</p>
    <p>Satohiro Wakabayashi, Seita Maruyama, Tatsuya Mori, Shigeki Goto, Masahiro Kinugawa, Yu-ichi Hayashi</p>
    <p>Waseda University, National Institute of Technology Sendai College, Nara Institute of Science and Technology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background: (passive) EM side-channel attack</p>
    <p>H E L L</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Radio-Frequency Retroreflector Attack (RFRA)</p>
    <p>is an active electromagnetic side-channel attack  aims to steal the targets signals by actively irradiating the targeted device</p>
    <p>with a radio wave</p>
    <p>A malicious circuit (retroreflector) is embedded in the target device in advance</p>
    <p>retroreflector</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background of RFRA  The Thing: a predecessor of RFID and RFRA (mid 20th century)  Possible use of RFRA in the intelligence community (R. J. Anderson 2008)  NSA ANT catalog: ANGRYNEIGHBOR (2014)  RFRA demo/talk: DEF CON 22, USENIX WOOT2015 (M. Ossmann)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack overview</p>
    <p>TX RX</p>
    <p>Antennas</p>
    <p>Communication cable</p>
    <p>Target signal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Retroreflector</p>
    <p>FET</p>
    <p>Communication cable S D</p>
    <p>G</p>
    <p>Signal</p>
    <p>GND S G D</p>
    <p>Antenna</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Retroreflector  Retroreflector consists of  field-effect transistor (FET) chip  wire that can work as a dipole antenna</p>
    <p>FET is very small  It is easy to implement anywhere</p>
    <p>An attacker needs to transmit radio waves that is resonant frequency of dipole antenna</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Questions  It is known that the RFRA works in practice  Our research question is: Is the RFRA a feasible attack?  The attackable distance between target and attacker  The limit of the speed of the target signal  Real-world applications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack setup</p>
    <p>Oscilloscope</p>
    <p>Function Generator</p>
    <p>TX</p>
    <p>RX</p>
    <p>SDR (USRP)</p>
    <p>PC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Equipment</p>
    <p>Insturument Model</p>
    <p>Antenna Ettus Research LP0410</p>
    <p>SDR USRP N210Up to 50 MS/s</p>
    <p>Attacker PC ASUS ROG G752VS</p>
    <p>FET ATF-54143</p>
    <p>Instruments used in the experiments</p>
    <p>OS Windows 10</p>
    <p>SDR software toolkit GNU Radio 3.7.11</p>
    <p>CPU Core i7 7700HQ 2.8 GHz/4 Core</p>
    <p>RAM 32 GB</p>
    <p>List of software and PC used for SDR</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results on distance</p>
    <p>Target signal 2 Mbps</p>
    <p>SDR sampling rate is 10 MS/s 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results on rate of target signal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results on rate of target signal</p>
    <p>Attacked from 1 m, SDR sampling rate is 25 MS/s 5 Mbps 10 Mbps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary of the experiment  The total cost of setup is approximately 5000 US dollars.  The attack succeeded from 10m distance  10 m is enough flexibility in setting up the attack equipment</p>
    <p>The attack succeeded to the target signal of 10 Mbps  USB keyboard may be attackable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Application  10 Mbps communication is attackable (previous experiment)  USB transfer rates are   USB low-speed mode: 1.5 Mbps  USB full-speed mode: 12 Mbps  USB high-speed mode: 480 Mbps</p>
    <p>USB low-speed mode is attackable!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Application  Most of USB keyboards use USB low-speed mode  Is RFRA effective for real-world applications?</p>
    <p>Eavesdrop typing of USB keyboard and evaluate the accuracy  We typed pangram</p>
    <p>ex) My faxed joke won a pager in the cable TV quiz show.</p>
    <p>We developed program to detect typed keys from an eavesdropped waveform</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation</p>
    <p>D+ D</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Result</p>
    <p>Error rate</p>
    <p>Distance [m] Error rate [%]</p>
    <p>Error point (1.5 m)</p>
    <p>paper in the cable tv</p>
    <p>paper in th cable tv</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Result</p>
    <p>Waveforms we eavesdropped (0.5, 1.0, 1.5 m)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitation  Attackable target communication speed depends on the sampling rate of SDR  high-performance hardware can extend the limitation</p>
    <p>The resonant frequency is changed by the shape of target cable.  Attack becomes difficult if victim wears a cable because the shape of cable</p>
    <p>changes frequently</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Countermeasures  The best solution is encryption.  Detecting malicious circuit in the physical layer  There was a previous study on detecting hardware key loggers  If a FET is embedded at the time of manufacturing, this approach may not be</p>
    <p>directly applicable</p>
    <p>Monitoring malicious/reflected radio waves  Quite difficult</p>
    <p>Further research is needed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future work  Some conditions are not clear  Frequency of irradiation radio waves  Antenna position</p>
    <p>Attacking analog signals  Audio cable (less than 20 kHz)  VGA cable (25 MHz)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  Using 5000 dollars setup  Attackable from 10 m  Attackable 10 Mbps signal</p>
    <p>We showed that RFRA is applicable for USB devices</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
