<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>oops! :(</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>&quot;Privacy Slider&quot;</p>
    <p>Kauer et al.: Improving Privacy Settings for Facebook by Using Interpersonal Distance as Criterion</p>
    <p>Selection based on intersocial connectedness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Wedges</p>
    <p>Radar metaphore</p>
    <p>Friend groups &lt;=&gt; Wedges</p>
    <p>Distance from center &lt;=&gt;</p>
    <p>Tie strength</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Wedges</p>
    <p>A  Circle selection</p>
    <p>All friends up to specific tie strength are selected, neglecting friend groups</p>
    <p>Example use-case:</p>
    <p>A family trip to the amusement park</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Wedges</p>
    <p>B  Wedge selection</p>
    <p>All friends up to specific tie strength inside a group are selected</p>
    <p>Example use-case:</p>
    <p>Pictures of me at a university party</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Wedges</p>
    <p>C  Excluding selection</p>
    <p>All friends inside a group beginning at a specific tie strength are selected</p>
    <p>Example use-case:</p>
    <p>A rock band member asks for some nice techno events</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Wedges</p>
    <p>D  Sickle selection</p>
    <p>All friends inside a group inside a specific tie strength interval are selected</p>
    <p>Example use-case:</p>
    <p>A rock band member asks for some nice techno events</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Wedges</p>
    <p>E  Multi layer selection</p>
    <p>All friends inside a group inside multiple tie strength intervals are selected</p>
    <p>Example use-case:</p>
    <p>A picture of illegal fireworks you bought in a foreign country</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Wedges</p>
    <p>F  Single selection</p>
    <p>The clicked friend is added to the selection</p>
    <p>Example use-case:</p>
    <p>A picture of your new girlfriend</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Wedges  Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User study</p>
    <p>Goal:</p>
    <p>Compare Privacy Wedges to the current standard (e.g. Facebook) in terms of</p>
    <p>Performance (e.g. error rate)</p>
    <p>Usability and user experience</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User study</p>
    <p>Goal:</p>
    <p>Compare Privacy Wedges to the current standard (e.g. Facebook) in terms of</p>
    <p>Performance (e.g. error rate)</p>
    <p>calculate false positives / false negatives with example posts compared to ground truth</p>
    <p>Usability and user experience</p>
    <p>AttrackDiff questionnaire</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Procedure  1 Week before experiment: User hands in a list of his Facebook</p>
    <p>friends, ordered by tie strength and categorized in friend lists</p>
    <p>User has to select the audience using Privacy Wedges or Facebook for 12 potentially dangerous facebook posts, given by the examiner.</p>
    <p>Number of selectable friends is increased after each task</p>
    <p>Share the post with the eight closest university friends</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Procedure</p>
    <p>Attrakdiff questionnaire after each condition.</p>
    <p>1 Week after experiment:</p>
    <p>Examiner asks for each post in the experiment, and each friend in the friend list, whether this friend should actually have received the post or not (ground truth)</p>
    <p>For each post, participant is asked to score the severity of an unwanted disclosement (false positive) or missed opportunity (false negative)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Participants</p>
    <p>26 volunteers</p>
    <p>18 to 54 years old (mean 24)</p>
    <p>9 female, 15 male</p>
    <p>Different occupations (Business / Finance, Engineers, students..)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results  error rate</p>
    <p>Significantly lower false positives for Privacy Wedges</p>
    <p>Significantly lower false positives for Facebook!</p>
    <p>But: FP scored more severe than FN</p>
    <p>Mean FN severity: 6.03 (1=highest, 10=lowest) Mean FP severity: 2.48 (1=highest, 10=lowest)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results - UX</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results - UX</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations</p>
    <p>Small sample set , used convenience sampling</p>
    <p>Limited scalability due to limited space in the UI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future work &amp; Other applications</p>
    <p>Use incremental magnifying to place all friends in the UI</p>
    <p>Visualize audience of already published posts with Privacy Wedges</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Proposed UI for audience selection for facebook posts, using a radar metaphore and tie strength as a criterion.</p>
    <p>Results show that unwanted disclosures are reduced at the cost of missed opportunities</p>
    <p>Future versions should address the scalability issue.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
