<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Influence of Privacy Attitudes &amp; Privacy Cue Framing on</p>
    <p>Android APP Choices Prashanth Rajivan &amp; Jean Camp</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>People and Privacy Warnings</p>
    <p>People express preference for privacy but do not behave in a privacy preserving manner</p>
    <p>Click through most of the privacy warnings</p>
    <p>Reasons:</p>
    <p>Lack of motivation</p>
    <p>Inattention</p>
    <p>Uncertainty &amp; Information asymmetry</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Decisions are made either using description or from experience</p>
    <p>Privacy decision from experience? - But risk to ones privacy is not frequent</p>
    <p>Privacy risk has to described to the user</p>
    <p>Current Risk Descriptions: Too much &amp; Too Late</p>
    <p>Presenting easy to understand privacy risk icons/cues would help people make low risk app choices.</p>
    <p>But what does that entail? - What are the governing human factor variables?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Framing descriptions to nudge user decisions</p>
    <p>Past research on framing of privacy cues is inconclusive</p>
    <p>There could be other variables that mediates the effect of privacy risk framing</p>
    <p>Privacy attitude is considered an important variable</p>
    <p>No known empirical work on the effects of privacy attitudes</p>
    <p>Question: How does privacy attitude in association with privacy risk framing influence app choices in Android ?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy attitude was manipulated through priming  Privacy Priming at the start of the experiment</p>
    <p>Concise version of the IUIPC questionnaire</p>
    <p>Priming through memory recall</p>
    <p>Augment participants concern for privacy online</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Compared 3 Privacy Cues</p>
    <p>No visual cue was the control condition</p>
    <p>Social Cues for communicating emotion</p>
    <p>Emoticon &amp; Eyes</p>
    <p>Risk framed (Negative)</p>
    <p>Security Mental Model based cue</p>
    <p>Lock</p>
    <p>Privacy framed (Positive)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A 4X2 between subjects experiment design</p>
    <p>IV1: Visual cues to communicate privacy</p>
    <p>IV2: Privacy Priming</p>
    <p>Total: 8 experimental conditions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interactive Android Playstore Simulation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User experiment with 480 MTurk participants</p>
    <p>Participants: 18 years and above, familiar with Android, were paid $2.50</p>
    <p>Randomly assigned to one of the 8 conditions - 60 participants in each condition</p>
    <p>Cues or no cues, Primed or not primed</p>
    <p>8 categories of apps with 8 apps in each - 4 apps excelled in at least 2 variables</p>
    <p>Chose 4 apps in each category in degree of preference</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparing effect of privacy score across conditions</p>
    <p>Comparing effect of app rating across conditions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Time taken to make app choice was measured and compared</p>
    <p>Participants primed for privacy spent more time choosing apps</p>
    <p>20 seconds more in average</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Priming for privacy led to increased concern</p>
    <p>But priming for privacy did not have a significant effect on app choices by itself</p>
    <p>Presenting privacy cues in general led to more risk and benefits based choices</p>
    <p>With several good options: Framing did not make a difference</p>
    <p>With lack of good options: Participants using privacy framed cues and who were primed for privacy made consistent risk based choices</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
