<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Julie Haney &amp; Wayne Lutters</p>
    <p>University of Maryland, Baltimore County</p>
    <p>SOUPS WSIW 17 - July 12, 2017</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cyber attacks and threats are on the rise</p>
    <p>People often fail to implement basic cybersecurity practices</p>
    <p>Shortage of cybersecurity professionals</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Promote security best practices, educate, persuade, serve as change agents for security adoption</p>
    <p>Address diverse audiences</p>
    <p>Rarely identified by their titles</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Little is known about necessary skills for security advocates</p>
    <p>No clear career track for advocates</p>
    <p>Traditional security education and training almost solely focused on technical skills, not on developing advocacy competencies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Understand the characteristics and motivations of cybersecurity advocates</p>
    <p>Identify effective advocacy techniques within the security field</p>
    <p>Support security community efforts to recruit and develop these advocates</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>19 semi-structured interviews and online demographic survey</p>
    <p>Recruitment  Researcher contacts  Internet searches  Snowballing</p>
    <p>Iterative, inductive coding and analysis to identify core concepts (Grounded Theory)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Educational background  9 participants with at least one degree in a non-technical field  6 with no technical degree</p>
    <p>Careers  Experience in technical and non-technical fields  Industry, government, higher education, non-profits  Internal and external advocates</p>
    <p>They needed a translator to translate law to geekAnd I learned that I sort of have a unique aptitude in this area where law and information security policy intersect.</p>
    <p>P15</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>This is a business that is very technology oriented, and full of peoplewho want to one-up you. So if you cant kind of deal with that, its going to be hard for you to be an effective advocate because people will kind of eat you up unless youre pretty convincing.</p>
    <p>P04</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>If youre a computer scientist, and all you know is the computer science, and you dont have the empathy, you dont have the skills to listen,you dont have that psychological side, I dont think you can make it work.</p>
    <p>P03</p>
    <p>We are terrible at soft skills. Were very mono-cultured and bring technical solutions.</p>
    <p>P11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Communication skills</p>
    <p>People skills</p>
    <p>Being able to translate complicated things very simply is crucial to advocating security.</p>
    <p>P02</p>
    <p>I think people have to have a high emotional intelligence and especially empathy.</p>
    <p>P18</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Personal attributes</p>
    <p>Career and collaborative attributes</p>
    <p>Whenever I walk in the room, I assume Im the stupidest one there, and everything works out great.</p>
    <p>P10</p>
    <p>The goal is to surface beliefs, combine them with other beliefs, come to a set of shared beliefs.</p>
    <p>P11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Awareness of environment, technology, people, and social and cultural structures</p>
    <p>Communicating the why [T]heres a lot of mythology and a lot of things we do because we heard its the right thing to do, and we have no idea why, but everybody else seems to be doing it... And so trying to get people to stop and think it through, figure out whats actually going to be effective and look at the threat models.</p>
    <p>P07</p>
    <p>You need to translate technical findings into the need for business action. And to do that, you have to understand the business at some level.</p>
    <p>P10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I think were making the world a better place.</p>
    <p>P06</p>
    <p>Its important because of the implications of not doing it the significance and the potential of loss of dollars, of information, of man hours, of intellectual property, sensitive information.</p>
    <p>P01</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Establish continuing education efforts to aid progression from security professional to advocate</p>
    <p>Encourage development of change agent skills</p>
    <p>Support educational opportunities to facilitate discipline diversity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Incorporate and emphasize non-technical skills as important to the success of security professionals</p>
    <p>Attract new populations to the cybersecurity field by marketing security as a people-oriented, service profession</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>jhaney1@umbc.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
