<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WorkOut: I/O Workload Outsourcing for Boosting RAID Reconstruction PerformanceReconstruction Performance</p>
    <p>Suzhen Wu1, Hong Jiang2, Dan Feng1, Lei Tian12, Bo Mao1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background MotivationMotivation WorkOut Performance Evaluations Conclusion</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RAID Reconstruction</p>
    <p>R th d t t t f il d di kRecovers the data content on a failed disk Two metrics</p>
    <p>Reconstruction time User response timeUser response time</p>
    <p>Categories Off li st tiOff-line reconstruction On-line reconstruction (commonly deployed)</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challengesg</p>
    <p>Higher error rates than expectedg p Complete disk failures [Schroeder07, Pinheiro07, Jiang08]g ] Latent sector errors [Bairavasundaram07]</p>
    <p>Correlation in drive failuresCorrelation in drive failures e.g. after one disk fails, another disk failure will likely occur soonwill likely occur soon.</p>
    <p>RAID reconstruction might become the i l l tcommon case in large-scale systems.</p>
    <p>Increasing number of drives</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reconstruction and Its Performance Impact 70 times</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I/O Intensity Impact on Reconstruction 21 times</p>
    <p>~4 times</p>
    <p>Both the reconstruction time and user response time increase with IOPS.</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 6</p>
    <p>p</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Intuitive Idea</p>
    <p>Observation Performing the rebuild IOs and user IOs simultaneously leads to disk bandwidth y contention and frequent long seeks to and from the multiple separate data areas.</p>
    <p>Our intuitive ideaOur intuitive idea To redirect the amount of user IOs that are issued to the degraded RAID setissued to the degraded RAID set. But, What to redirect? &amp; Where to redirect to?</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What To Redirect</p>
    <p>Access localitycc ca ty Existing studies on workload analysis revealed that strong spatial and temporal locality exists that strong spatial and temporal locality exists even underneath the storage cache.</p>
    <p>Answer to what to redirect? P l d tPopular read requests All write requests</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Where To Redirect To</p>
    <p>Availability of spare or free space in data centers</p>
    <p>A spare pool including a number of disksp p g Free space on other RAID sets</p>
    <p>Answer to Where to redirect to?Answer to Where to redirect to? Spare or free space</p>
    <p>C iComparison Existing approaches: in the context of a single RAID set Our approach: in the context of data centers</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 9 with multiple RAID sets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main Idea of WorkOut</p>
    <p>Workload Outsourcing (Workout)W r a ut urc ng (W r ut) Temporarily redirect all write requests and popular read requests originally targeted at the popular read requests originally targeted at the degraded RAID set to a surrogate RAID set, to significantly improve on-line reconstruction g y p performance.</p>
    <p>GoalGoal Approaches reconstruction-time performance of the off-line reconstruction without of the off line reconstruction without affecting user-response-time performance at the same time.</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 10</p>
    <p>m m .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WorkOut Architecture</p>
    <p>Administrator</p>
    <p>Popular Data Identifier</p>
    <p>Administrator Interface Surrogate</p>
    <p>Space ManagerIdentifier Request</p>
    <p>Redirector</p>
    <p>Space Manager Reclaimer</p>
    <p>Fa ile</p>
    <p>d D</p>
    <p>is k</p>
    <p>D is</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>D is</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>D is</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>D is</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>D is</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>Sp ar</p>
    <p>e D</p>
    <p>is k</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Structure</p>
    <p>D T bl l t bl th t th D_Table: a log table that manages the redirected data</p>
    <p>D Fl 1 W it d t f th li ti D_Flag=1: Write data from the user application D_Flag=0: Popular read data from D-RAID to S-RAID</p>
    <p>R LRU: n LRU st l list th t id ntifi s th R_LRU: an LRU-style list that identifies the most recent reads</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithm During Reconstructiong g</p>
    <p>WorkflowWorkflow For each write, it will be redirected to its previous location or a new location on the previous location or a new location on the surrogate RAID set according to whether it is an overwrite or notan overwrite or not. For each read, Check the D_Table:</p>
    <p>Whether it hits D Table or not?Whether it hits D_Table or not? If a hit, full hit or partial hit? If a miss, whether it hits R_LRU?</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithm During Reclaimg g</p>
    <p>The redirected write data should be The redirected write data should be reclaimed back to the newly recovered RAID set after the reconstruction process set after the reconstruction process completes. All b h k d i D T blAll requests must be checked in D_Table:</p>
    <p>Each write request is served by the recovered RAID set and the corresponding log in D_Table should be deleted if it exists. Read requests can be also handled well, but it is complicated to explain in a short time. More d l b f d</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 14 details can be found in our paper.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Choicesg</p>
    <p>Optional De ice</p>
    <p>p surrogate RAID set</p>
    <p>Device Overhead Performance Reliability Maintainability</p>
    <p>A dedicated A dedicated surrogate RAID1 set</p>
    <p>medium medium high simple</p>
    <p>A dedicated surrogate RAID5 set</p>
    <p>high high high simple D5 s t</p>
    <p>A live surrogate RAID5 t</p>
    <p>low low medium-high complicated RAID5 set</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 15</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Consistency</p>
    <p>Data Protection In order to avoid data loss caused by a disk failure in the surrogate RAID set, all g redirected write data in the surrogate RAID set should be protected by a redundancy scheme, such as RAID1 or RAID5.</p>
    <p>Metadata Protection The content of D_Table should be stored in a NVRAM during the entire period when NVRAM during the entire period when WorkOut is activated, to prevent data loss in the event of a power supply failure</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 16</p>
    <p>the event of a power supply failure.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Evaluation</p>
    <p>Prototype implementation A built-in module in MD Incorporated into PR &amp; PRO</p>
    <p>Experimental setup Intel Xeon 3.0GHz processor, 1GB DDR memory, 15 S t SATA di k (10GB) Li 2 6 11Seagate SATA disks (10GB), Linux 2.6.11</p>
    <p>Methodology O l lOpen-loop: trace replay</p>
    <p>Trace: Financial1, Financial2, Websearch2 Tool: RAIDmeterTool: RAIDmeter</p>
    <p>Closed-loop: TPC-C-like benchmark</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 17</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Results Trace Reconstruction Time (second)</p>
    <p>Off-line PR WorkOut+PR Speedup PRO WorkOut+PRO Speedup</p>
    <p>Fin1</p>
    <p>Fin2 745.19 453.32 1.64 705.79 431.24 1.64</p>
    <p>Web 9935.6 7623.22 1.30 9888.27 7851.36 1.26</p>
    <p>Trace Average User Response Time during Reconstruction (millisecond)g p g ( ) Normal Degraded PR WorkOut+PR Speedup PRO WorkOut+PRO Speedup</p>
    <p>Fin1 7.92 9.52 12.71 4.43 2.87 9.83 4.58 2.15 Fin2 8.13 13.36 25.8 9.69 2.66 22.97 10.19 2.25</p>
    <p>Web 18.46 26.95 38.57 28.35 1.36 35.58 29.12 1.22</p>
    <p>Degraded RAID set: RAID5, 8 disks, 64KB stripe unit size Surrogate RAID set: RAID5, 4 disks, 64KB stripe unit size Minimum reconstruction bandwidth: 1MB/s</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 18</p>
    <p>Minimum reconstruction bandwidth: 1MB/s</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Percentage of Redirected Requestsg q</p>
    <p>Minimum reconstruction bandwidth of 1MB/s</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 19</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sensitivity Study (1)</p>
    <p>m s)</p>
    <p>on T</p>
    <p>im e</p>
    <p>(s )</p>
    <p>se T</p>
    <p>im e</p>
    <p>(m</p>
    <p>co ns</p>
    <p>tr uc</p>
    <p>ti o</p>
    <p>ge R</p>
    <p>es po</p>
    <p>ns</p>
    <p>R ec</p>
    <p>A ve</p>
    <p>ra g</p>
    <p>D ff b d d h</p>
    <p>(a) (b)</p>
    <p>Different minimum reconstruction bandwidth: 1MB/s, 10MB/s, 100MB/s</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 20</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sensitivity Study (2)</p>
    <p>) 40 45</p>
    <p>m s) PR</p>
    <p>on T</p>
    <p>im e</p>
    <p>(s )</p>
    <p>ns e</p>
    <p>T im</p>
    <p>e (m PRO</p>
    <p>WorkOut</p>
    <p>ec on</p>
    <p>st ru</p>
    <p>ct io</p>
    <p>PR PRO</p>
    <p>ag e</p>
    <p>R es</p>
    <p>po n</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>PRO WorkOut</p>
    <p>A ve</p>
    <p>ra</p>
    <p>D ff b f d k (5 8 11)</p>
    <p>(a) (b)</p>
    <p>Different number of disks (5, 8, 11)</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sensitivity Study (3)</p>
    <p>n T</p>
    <p>im e</p>
    <p>(s )</p>
    <p>PR WorkOut</p>
    <p>on st</p>
    <p>ru ct</p>
    <p>io n</p>
    <p>R ec</p>
    <p>o</p>
    <p>RAID10 RAID6</p>
    <p>(a) (b)</p>
    <p>Different RAID level: RAID10 (4 disks), RAID6 (8 disks)</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 22</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Different Surrogate Setg</p>
    <p>Dedicated RAID1</p>
    <p>Live RAID5 PRThe same reconstruction time for the</p>
    <p>Dedicated RAID1: 2 disks</p>
    <p>Dedicated RAID1: 2 disks Dedicated RAID5: 4 disks Live RAID5: 4 disks (Replaying the Fin1 workload on it)</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 23</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TPC-C-like Benchmark</p>
    <p>ti on</p>
    <p>R at</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>d T</p>
    <p>ra ns</p>
    <p>ac t</p>
    <p>N or</p>
    <p>m al</p>
    <p>iz ed</p>
    <p>(a) Transaction rate (b) Reconstruction time</p>
    <p>Minimum reconstruction bandwidth of 1MB/s</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 24</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ExtendibilityRe-synchronizationy y (s</p>
    <p>)</p>
    <p>m s)</p>
    <p>at io</p>
    <p>n T</p>
    <p>im e</p>
    <p>ns e</p>
    <p>T im</p>
    <p>e (m</p>
    <p>yn ch</p>
    <p>ro ni</p>
    <p>za</p>
    <p>ag e</p>
    <p>R es</p>
    <p>po n</p>
    <p>R e</p>
    <p>sy</p>
    <p>A ve</p>
    <p>ra</p>
    <p>( ) (b)</p>
    <p>Re-synchronization: RAID5, 8 disks, 64KB stripe unit size</p>
    <p>(a) (b)</p>
    <p>Surrogate RAID set: RAID5, 4 disks, 64KB stripe unit size Minimum Re-synchronization bandwidth: 1MB/s</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 25</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>WorkOut outsources a significant amount of I/O t f th d d d user I/O requests away from the degraded</p>
    <p>RAID set to a surrogate RAID set, thus i i RAID t ti fimproving RAID reconstruction performance; Insights and guidance for storage system designers and administrators by exploiting three design options; WorkOut can improve the performance of other background support RAID tasks such as g pp re-synchronization.</p>
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 26</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HUST &amp; UNL 27</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
