<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>pStore: a Semantic-Aware File Store</p>
    <p>Christos Karamanolis Magnus Karlsson Chunqiang Tang* Zhichen Xu</p>
    <p>*U. of Rochester</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>page 26/19/03 Zhichen Xu, HOTOS-IX</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>storage systems are extensions to human memory but there is a huge gap between the two  human brains are smart  the storage systems are dumb</p>
    <p>this is because we associate meanings (semantics) to the things we remember, but the storage systems today dont !</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>page 36/19/03 Zhichen Xu, HOTOS-IX</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>when we search for something  we may remember this something has certain property  we may have abstract notion of the object (e.g. tiger has stripes)  we may do so according to the relationships of this object to other</p>
    <p>objects, e.g., this paper was written by a student of</p>
    <p>when we memorize things, we may  remember only the differences of an object to another object  recognize that many objects belong to the same category</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>page 46/19/03 Zhichen Xu, HOTOS-IX</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>we discover meanings of things incrementally; we realize usage of things gradually</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>page 56/19/03 Zhichen Xu, HOTOS-IX</p>
    <p>Todays contents are full of semantics</p>
    <p>example: a digital movie studio  hundreds of scenes  millions of data objects a variety of semantic information</p>
    <p>every version of an object is annotated with changes done</p>
    <p>info. about versions and dependencies among files is important when, e.g., rendering a scene</p>
    <p>an artist may search for material that other people have edited/produced</p>
    <p>the view of what data are stored in the system may be different depending on the application and user</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>page 66/19/03 Zhichen Xu, HOTOS-IX</p>
    <p>Vision</p>
    <p>capture and use semantic information for   fast searching and retrieval of data</p>
    <p>combine with exiting techniques for searching (indexing, semantic vectors, content-specific tools)</p>
    <p>improve completeness and accuracy of searching</p>
    <p>efficient data storage  data compression based on semantic relations of data</p>
    <p>improved performance  data hoarding, data placement and replication/caching  efficient rich media distribution and streaming</p>
    <p>highly available data sharing  balance consistency &amp; availability according to semantics  sophisticated access control and security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>page 76/19/03 Zhichen Xu, HOTOS-IX</p>
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>What are the common semantic relations of interest?</p>
    <p>How to capture semantic information?</p>
    <p>How to handle dynamic evolution of semantics?</p>
    <p>What are the basic tools and APIs users/applications require?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>page 86/19/03 Zhichen Xu, HOTOS-IX</p>
    <p>Approach</p>
    <p>use a generic data model to capture semantic metadata  handle dynamic evolution/elaboration of schema  more generic than the existing semantic file systems</p>
    <p>use RDF (semantic web) for semi-structured data  basic relations: similarity (e.g., versions), dependencies, associative,</p>
    <p>context</p>
    <p>extract the commonality of data management applications in a generic framework  the data model, basic mechanisms and APIs make</p>
    <p>building customized solutions easy  event model, customized namespaces, security, searching,</p>
    <p>archiving</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>page 96/19/03 Zhichen Xu, HOTOS-IX</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
