<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Green Switch: Designing for Sustainability in Mobile Computing</p>
    <p>Riikka Puustinen &amp; Galit Zadok SustainIT10 22 February 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mobile &amp; Sustainability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mobile &amp; Sustainability 3 trends converging</p>
    <p>Smart Phone</p>
    <p>Consumption &amp; Replacement</p>
    <p>User Growth6B = 2013 All = 2015</p>
    <p>EU = 500,000,000</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Sustainability efforts The lifecycle efforts</p>
    <p>EU most comprehensive legislation in place</p>
    <p>Nokia, Sony Ericsson, and Samsung most active</p>
    <p>Greenpeace vigilant on Greenwashing</p>
    <p>Going Green more costly to manufacturers</p>
    <p>Consumer sentiment rising (Samsung Blue Earth)</p>
    <p>Legislation forces efforts  July 2007, EU law WEEE</p>
    <p>Regulation  Waste Electrical and Electronic</p>
    <p>Equipment  Producers of WEEE =</p>
    <p>responsibility in disposal  Handset manufacturers now</p>
    <p>promote free of charge takeback programs</p>
    <p>Network Infrastructure  Little financial incentives for</p>
    <p>operators in developed economies</p>
    <p>Innovation in developing world, as power is scarce and costly</p>
    <p>Ofcom: 3G services will greatly increase energy consumption</p>
    <p>Chargers:  reduce no-load energy</p>
    <p>consumptions  Nokia, Sony Ericsson</p>
    <p>reduction of 80%-90%  Universal Charging Solution</p>
    <p>(UCS), efficient, eliminates redundancy.</p>
    <p>Handset while in use</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Handset while in use Bigger portion and growing</p>
    <p>Image: Apple Inc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our growing energy consumption</p>
    <p>Image: Africa Interactive, http://tinyurl.com/yc9s8tn</p>
    <p>Proliferation of charging solutions Smart Phones &amp; 3G: much bigger impact of use-phase</p>
    <p>Charging mobiles in rural Africa Mobile growth highlights Energy Poverty</p>
    <p>Batteries do not follow Moores Law (Only 10% improvement per annum)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Battery challenge is getting tougher and frustrating users.</p>
    <p>Smart Phone</p>
    <p>Slim Design</p>
    <p>Smaller Capacity</p>
    <p>Higher Needs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Energy Consumption of handset Growing impact of 3G</p>
    <p>iPhone CNET reviews: 43% - 60% energy reduction with 3G off</p>
    <p>Impact on network:</p>
    <p>x12 Increase in data throughput greatly increases (x4) microcell power consumption - Ofcom UK</p>
    <p>Understanding the Environmental Impact of Communication Systems. Plextec, Eftec for Ofcom. April 2009.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Northwestern University research on Android Devices  Idle = 49.3% Active = 50.7%  In active mode = CPU &amp; Screen  Users on power optimisations</p>
    <p>75%   5%   20%</p>
    <p>A. Shye, B. Scholbrock, G. Memik. Into the Wild: Studying Real User Activity Patterns to Guide Power Optimization for Mobile Architectures.</p>
    <p>Energy Consumption of handset where does it all go?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Energy Hierarchy Sustainability lessons from others</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Great opportunity for Sustainability Mobile phone  mobile computing device</p>
    <p>Brains &amp; Budgets now being spent.</p>
    <p>Address sustainability at critical design level.</p>
    <p>Reducing energy consumption is better for user experience and the</p>
    <p>environment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Methodology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Green Switch Design Method</p>
    <p>Aim: YES to all, to achieve meaningful impact.</p>
    <p>Green Switch Checklist Y N Eco-centric Green Appeal</p>
    <p>Reduction in energy consumption</p>
    <p>Human-centric Mass-Market Appeal Beneficial</p>
    <p>Convenient</p>
    <p>Good Value</p>
    <p>Socially Acceptable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Green appeal</p>
    <p>Does it reduce energy consumption? Technical aspects  System processes</p>
    <p>Long-running frequent timers  Idle time-outs for resources  Demand paging</p>
    <p>Idle &amp; call state  Device and battery power status</p>
    <p>Network connections  Moving between cells/networks  Data transfer  Radio receivers and transmitters like cellular</p>
    <p>radio, WLAN, GPS, and Bluetooth</p>
    <p>Central Processing Unit  Symmetric Multiprocessing  Idle de-fragmentation  Code optimisation</p>
    <p>Analyse your application to see where the most power is used concentrate optimising these areas.</p>
    <p>Screen status  Screen saver and backlight usage</p>
    <p>Screen brightness  SD Card  Media Players</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Green appeal</p>
    <p>Does it reduce energy consumption?</p>
    <p>Design aspects  Visual Design</p>
    <p>Energy-efficient colours  Image optimisation  Scalable visual assets  Generic visual assets  Code vs. graphics</p>
    <p>Animations and UI effects  Allow turning off when device</p>
    <p>is locked or application in the background</p>
    <p>Use as low frame rate as possible</p>
    <p>Audio  Avoid unnecessarily high audio</p>
    <p>quality</p>
    <p>Interaction Design  Optimise user flow for efficiency  Connection points between</p>
    <p>devices  Connections from device to</p>
    <p>online service</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mass-Market appeal</p>
    <p>Is it beneficial and relevant for the user?</p>
    <p>A tangible benefit</p>
    <p>Enablers  Mobile device is</p>
    <p>Location independent  Portable multi-purpose tool  Contextual</p>
    <p>Ensure that the product/service is relevant to the user in the appropriate context.</p>
    <p>Image: Intivations ZTE S316 solar powered phone</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mass-Market appeal</p>
    <p>Is it convenient to use?</p>
    <p>A product should contribute to effortless use  Reliable  Easy to use</p>
    <p>Enablers  Mobile devices are</p>
    <p>Identifiable and personal  Interruptible  Designed to allow</p>
    <p>distractions and support easy recovery</p>
    <p>Image: Spotify</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mass-Market appeal</p>
    <p>Is it good value?</p>
    <p>Advantage or monetary worth compared to the price paid for it.</p>
    <p>Cost can be  Monetary value  Psychological cost</p>
    <p>Enablers  Quality vs. the cost of using</p>
    <p>the product</p>
    <p>Image: BBC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mass-Market appeal</p>
    <p>Is it socially acceptable?</p>
    <p>Conform to norms, follow the rules of target society</p>
    <p>Support ideal self-image</p>
    <p>Enablers  A mobile device can</p>
    <p>Extend social interaction  Be an item of fashion</p>
    <p>Image: Research in Motion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary  Use-phase:</p>
    <p>Impact is growing  Impacts client and server energy consumption</p>
    <p>Opportunity now to integrate sustainability at critical design level.  For impact, both address environmental *and* end-user needs.  Energy reduction in Mobile Computing is about sustainability</p>
    <p>*and* better user experience.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>{galit, riikka}@thegreenswitch.org</p>
    <p>www.thegreenswitch.org</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
