<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tatsuru Higurashi* Hayato Kobayashi* * Takeshi Masuyama* Kazuma Murao*</p>
    <p>* Yahoo Japan Corporation * RIKEN AIP</p>
    <p>Extractive Headline Generation</p>
    <p>Based on Learning to Rank</p>
    <p>on Community Question Answering</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contents</p>
    <p>Motivation and Approach</p>
    <p>Proposed method</p>
    <p>Experiment and Results</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contents</p>
    <p>Motivation and Approach</p>
    <p>Proposed method</p>
    <p>Experiment and Results</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Community Question Answering Service</p>
    <p>Post Question</p>
    <p>Answer of User A No solution other than</p>
    <p>moving.</p>
    <p>Get Answers CQA</p>
    <p>Question Advice please. A dog kept in the next house barks from morning to night. ... How can I effectively manage this problem?</p>
    <p>Answer of User B Please contact the</p>
    <p>public health center.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Push Notification obtain quick answers</p>
    <p>Directly linked to the quality of CQA</p>
    <p>Respondent</p>
    <p>Push Notification of Question</p>
    <p>Push Notification in CQA</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>Push</p>
    <p>Notification</p>
    <p>CQA Yahoo! Chiebukuro</p>
    <p>Contents of Posted Question</p>
    <p>Headline of Posted Question</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Snippet Extraction Makes Headline Informative</p>
    <p>Posted Question Nice to meet you, thank you in advance. I'm a man in my thirties. Advice please.</p>
    <p>A dog kept in the next house barks from morning to night. Neighbors have given the owner cautions against it,</p>
    <p>......</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>Nice to meet you, thank you in advance. I'm a...</p>
    <p>Prefix Headline: Uninformative</p>
    <p>Snippet headline: Informative</p>
    <p>...A dog kept in the next house barks from morning...</p>
    <p>Approach Extract a mid-substring as a snippet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Advantages of Snippet Headlines</p>
    <p>Practical</p>
    <p>Snippet headlines never include generative errors</p>
    <p>Commercial services</p>
    <p>(Yahoo! Chiebukuro) cannot</p>
    <p>accept generative errors</p>
    <p>Abstractive methods cannot</p>
    <p>completely avoid generative</p>
    <p>errors</p>
    <p>A/B testing on Yahoo! Chiebukuro push notifications of smartphones</p>
    <p>Snippet Headline</p>
    <p>Prefix Headline</p>
    <p>Average Answer Rate</p>
    <p>Effective</p>
    <p>2.4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Neural Headline Generation:</p>
    <p>[Takase+ 16][Chopra+ 16][Kiyono+ 17][Zhou+ 17][Raffael+ 17]</p>
    <p>Sentence Compression:</p>
    <p>[Woodsend+ 10][Alfonseca+ 13][Colmenares+ 15]</p>
    <p>Extractive Summarization:</p>
    <p>[Kobayashi+ 15][Yogatama+ 15][Cheng&amp;Lapata 16][Nallapati+ 17]</p>
    <p>CQA Data:</p>
    <p>[Bhasker+ 13] [Ishigaki+ 17][Surdenau+ 08][Celikyilmaz 09]</p>
    <p>Related Work of Headline Generation and CQA</p>
    <p>Our research is first attempt to address extractive headline generation for</p>
    <p>CQA service with substring of question based on learning to rank</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contents</p>
    <p>Motivation and Approach</p>
    <p>Proposed Method</p>
    <p>Experiment and Results</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of Our Proposed Method</p>
    <p>Posted Question Nice to meet you, thank you in advance. I'm a man in my thirties. Advice please. A dog kept in the next house barks from morning to night...</p>
    <p>Candidate Generation Candidate Ranking Candidates</p>
    <p>candidate1</p>
    <p>candidate2</p>
    <p>candidate3</p>
    <p>Ranked Headline</p>
    <p>Ranked Headline ...A dog kept in the next house barks from morning to night...</p>
    <p>candidate4</p>
    <p>Question</p>
    <p>candidate3</p>
    <p>candidate1</p>
    <p>candidate4</p>
    <p>candidate2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Candidate Generation</p>
    <p>Generated Candidate Snippet  ...</p>
    <p>Nice to meet you, thank you in advance, I'm a...</p>
    <p>...  ... ... Advice please. A dog kept in the next house ...</p>
    <p>...  ... ... A dog kept in the next house barks from morning ...</p>
    <p>Make sentence which starts from beginning of each sentences of question.</p>
    <p>Cut subsequent sentences if it has over 20 Japanese characters.</p>
    <p>Put ellipsis at front and end of substring.</p>
    <p>EllipsisEllipsis</p>
    <p>Cut subsequent sentences if over 20 Japanese characters</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pairwise Learning to Rank</p>
    <p>L2-regularized L2-loss linear rankSVM</p>
    <p>1</p>
    <p>= ,   = , &gt; , , ,   , ,,</p>
    <p>[Lee 2014] Lee, ChingPei and Lin, ChihJen: Largescale Linear Ranksvm. Neural Computation, 26(4)</p>
    <p>Candidate Ranking</p>
    <p>:   :   :</p>
    <p>(  = max(0,1  )2)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Creation: Crowdsourcing</p>
    <p>Randomly Sorted Headline Candidate score 1 ... Neighbors have given the owner cautions against ... 2 2 ... This area has only private houses, not rented ... 0 3 ... How can I effectively manage this problem? 1 4 ... However, I will go crazy if I have to keep enduring ... 0 5 ... A dog kept in the next house barks from morning ... 6 6 Nice to meet you, thank you in advance, I'm a ... 0 7 ... Advice please. A dog kept in the next house ... 1</p>
    <p>Instruction for workers Select the best option from the list so that users can guess the content of the question and distinguish it from other ones.</p>
    <p>Number of votes by</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ratio of questions whose prefix headlines were most voted</p>
    <p>candidates was 61.8%</p>
    <p>= Room for improvement for prefix headline was up to 38.2%.</p>
    <p>Crowdsourcing Results</p>
    <p>Our Goal  Improve uninformative headlines of 38.2%  Remaining 61.8% unchanged</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contents</p>
    <p>Motivation and Approach</p>
    <p>Proposed Method</p>
    <p>Experiment and Results</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Features</p>
    <p>Bag-of-Words: 30,820 dimension sparse vector based on tf-idf</p>
    <p>Embedding: 100 dimension dense vector based on doc2vec</p>
    <p>Position: 10 dimension binary vector representing candidate position</p>
    <p>Features for Ranking Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Compared Methods</p>
    <p>Simple Baselines</p>
    <p>Prefix: Select first candidate  DictDel: Delete uninformative sentence with rule (Used in A/B testing)  Random: Select randomly</p>
    <p>Unsupervised Baselines</p>
    <p>ImpTfidf: Select most important candidate with highest tf-idf value  SimTfidf: Select most similar candidate to original question with cosine similarity  LexRank: Select candidate with highest score based on LexRank (Erkan&amp;Radev 2004)</p>
    <p>Supervised Baselines</p>
    <p>SVM: Select candidate with highest confidence learned as classification task  SVR: Select candidate with highest predicted votes learned as regression task</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation Metrics</p>
    <p>Average Votes</p>
    <p>Measures how appropriate candidates selected by each method  Determines the overall performance of each method  Corresponds to DCG@1</p>
    <p>Change Rate</p>
    <p>Measures how much each method changed the default prefix headline  Determines the impact of application to actual CQA service.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Quantitative Analysis</p>
    <p>Method Avarage Votes Change Rate</p>
    <p>Ideal 5.56 38.2</p>
    <p>MLRank(ours) 4.28 9.9</p>
    <p>Prefix 4.19 0</p>
    <p>DictDel 4.23 2.2</p>
    <p>Random 1.39 85.9</p>
    <p>ImpTfidf 1.68 81.1</p>
    <p>SimTfidf 2.27 79.3</p>
    <p>LexRank 2.27 55.7</p>
    <p>SVM 4.09 16.7</p>
    <p>SVR 3.00 52.5</p>
    <p>MLRank(ours) performed the best among all methods.</p>
    <p>Prefix(First sentence) can be a good summary.</p>
    <p>DictDel(Rule-Based) was more useful than Prefix.</p>
    <p>Change rate of DictDel was small, which means small impact on service.</p>
    <p>Change rates of unsupervised methods were high, but the overall performances were low</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Qualitative Analysis</p>
    <p>Examples of prefix headline and snippet headline</p>
    <p>Prefix Headline Snippet Headline</p>
    <p>I am sorry if the category is wrong. Now, my wallet is torn</p>
    <p>... Now, my wallet is torn, and Im having a hard time. A new one ...</p>
    <p>I am a 27-year-old woman. Owing to my environment, there is little chance of new ...</p>
    <p>... Owing to my environment, there is little chance of new encounters with men ...</p>
    <p>Uninformative expressions are successfully excluded, and informative experssions are added</p>
    <p>I am sorry if the category is wrong.</p>
    <p>I am a 27-year-old woman. encounters with</p>
    <p>men</p>
    <p>having a hard time. A new one</p>
    <p>and Im</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contents</p>
    <p>Motivation and Approach</p>
    <p>Proposed Method</p>
    <p>Experiment and Results</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Addressed a snippet headline generation task for push notifications of CQA</p>
    <p>Showed empirical evidence that snippet headlines are more effective than prefix headlines 2.4 times in average answer rate</p>
    <p>Proposed extractive headline generation method based on learning to rank</p>
    <p>Created dataset including headline candidates with &quot;headline-ness&quot; scores by crowdsourcing</p>
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Investigate effectiveness in practical situations on web service.</p>
    <p>Make the dataset publicly available.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Copyright (C) 2019 Yahoo Japan Corporation. All Rights Reserved.Copyright (C) 2019 Yahoo Japan Corporation. All Rights Reserved.</p>
    <p>Thank you</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
