<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WikiQA: A Challenge Dataset for Open-Domain Question AnsweringYi Yang</p>
    <p>*, Scott Wen-tau Yih#, Christopher Meek#</p>
    <p>*Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta #Microsoft Research, Redmond</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Question Answering with Knowledge Base  Large-scale knowledge bases (e.g., Freebase)  KB-specific semantic parsing (e.g., [Berant+ 13], [Yih+ 15])</p>
    <p>Question Answering with Free Text  High-quality, reliable text (e.g., Wikipedia, news articles)</p>
    <p>Open-domain Question Answering</p>
    <p>What are the names of Obamas daughters?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Answer Sentence Selection</p>
    <p>Given a factoid question, find the sentence in the candidate set that  Contains the answer  Can sufficiently support the answer</p>
    <p>Q: Who won the best actor Oscar in 1973? S1: Jack Lemmon was awarded the Best Actor Oscar for Save the Tiger (1973). S2: Academy award winner Kevin Spacey said that Jack Lemmon is remembered</p>
    <p>as always making time for others.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Based on the TREC-QA data</p>
    <p>Standard benchmark for answer sentence selection  Dependency tree matching (e.g., [Wang+ 07], [Wang+ 10], [Yao+ 13])  Tree kernel SVMs (e.g., [Severyn &amp; Moschitti 13])  Latent word alignment with lexical semantic matching (e.g., [Yih+ 13])  Deep neural network models (e.g., [Yu+ 14], [Wang+ 15])</p>
    <p>QASent Dataset [Wang+ 07]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Question distribution  Contain questions from human editors</p>
    <p>Candidate selection bias  Output from the systems participating in TREC-QA  Sentences need to share non-stopwords from the questions</p>
    <p>Excluding questions that have no correct answers</p>
    <p>Issues with QASent Dataset</p>
    <p>Q: How did Seminole war end? A: Ultimately, the Spanish Crown ceded the colony to United States rule.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Question distribution  Questions sampled from Bing query logs</p>
    <p>Candidate selection  Candidate sentences are from summary paragraphs of</p>
    <p>Wikipedia pages</p>
    <p>Including questions that have no correct answers  Answer Triggering: detecting whether a correct answer</p>
    <p>exists in candidate sentences</p>
    <p>WikiQA Dataset</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Introduction  WikiQA Dataset  Data construction and annotation  Data statistics</p>
    <p>Experiments  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions sampled from Bing query logs  Search queries starting with a WH-word  Filter out entity queries (e.g., how I met your mother)  Select queries issued by at least 5 users and have clicks to</p>
    <p>Wikipedia</p>
    <p>Data Construction  Questions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Candidate sentences  Use all sentences from the summary paragraph of the</p>
    <p>Wikipedia page</p>
    <p>Data Construction  Sentences</p>
    <p>Who wrote second Corinthians?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Step 1: Does the short paragraph answer the question?</p>
    <p>Sentence Annotation by Crowdsourcing</p>
    <p>Question: Who wrote second Corinthians? Second Epistle to the Corinthians The Second Epistle to the Corinthians, often referred to as Second Corinthians (and written as 2 Corinthians), is the eighth book of the New Testament of the Bible. Paul the Apostle and Timothy our brother wrote this epistle to the church of God which is at Corinth, with all the saints which are in all Achaia.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Step 2: Check all the sentences that can answer the question in isolation (assuming coreferences and pronouns have been resolved correctly)</p>
    <p>Sentence Annotation by Crowdsourcing</p>
    <p>Question: Who wrote second Corinthians? Second Epistle to the Corinthians  The Second Epistle to the Corinthians, often referred to as Second Corinthians</p>
    <p>(and written as 2 Corinthians), is the eighth book of the New Testament of the Bible.</p>
    <p>Paul the Apostle and Timothy our brother wrote this epistle to the church of God which is at Corinth, with all the saints which are in all Achaia.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Statistics: # Questions</p>
    <p># of questions</p>
    <p>QASent WikiQA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Statistics: # Questions &amp; Sentences</p>
    <p># of questions # of sentences</p>
    <p>QASent WikiQA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Question Classes (UIUC Question Taxonomy)</p>
    <p>Desc . 7%</p>
    <p>Hu man 29%</p>
    <p>Nu meri c 31%</p>
    <p>Locatio n 16%</p>
    <p>Abbr . 1% En</p>
    <p>tity 16%</p>
    <p>QASent</p>
    <p>Desc . 36%</p>
    <p>Hu man 16%</p>
    <p>Nu meri c 22%</p>
    <p>Locatio n 12%</p>
    <p>Abbr . 1% En</p>
    <p>tity 14%</p>
    <p>WikiQA</p>
    <p>Category Description/Definition has the most questions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Introduction  WikiQA Dataset  Experiments  Baseline systems  Evaluation on answer sentence selection  Evaluation metric &amp; results on answer triggering</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Word matching count (Wd-Cnt)  # non-stopwords in Q that also occur in S</p>
    <p>Latent word alignment (Wd-Algn) [Yih+ ACL-13]</p>
    <p>Convolutional NN (CNN) [Yu+ DLWorkshop-14]  Convolutional NN &amp; Wd-Cnt (CNN-Cnt)</p>
    <p>Baseline Systems</p>
    <p>: What is the fastest car in the world?</p>
    <p>: The Jaguar XJ220 is the dearest, fastest and most sought after car on the planet.</p>
    <p>(  ,)=(h)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>QASent 0</p>
    <p>Wd-Cnt Wd-Algn CNN CNN-Cnt</p>
    <p>M ea</p>
    <p>n R</p>
    <p>ec ip</p>
    <p>ro ca</p>
    <p>l R an</p>
    <p>k (M</p>
    <p>R R</p>
    <p>) Evaluation on Answer Sentence Selection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>QASent WikiQA* 0</p>
    <p>Wd-Cnt Wd-Algn CNN CNN-Cnt</p>
    <p>M ea</p>
    <p>n R</p>
    <p>ec ip</p>
    <p>ro ca</p>
    <p>l R an</p>
    <p>k (M</p>
    <p>R R</p>
    <p>) Evaluation on Answer Sentence Selection</p>
    <p>* 1,242 (40.8%) questions that have correct answer sentences in the candidate set</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Answer Triggering</p>
    <p>Given a question and a candidate answer sentence set  Detect whether there exist correct answers in the sentences  Return a correct answer if there exists one</p>
    <p>Evaluation metric  Question-level precision, recall and F1 score</p>
    <p>Data  All questions in WikiQA are included in this task</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CNN-Cnt +Q-Length +S-Length +Q-Class +All</p>
    <p>Q ue</p>
    <p>st io</p>
    <p>nle</p>
    <p>ve l F</p>
    <p>or e</p>
    <p>Evaluation on Answer Triggering</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CNN-Cnt +Q-Length +S-Length +Q-Class +All</p>
    <p>Q ue</p>
    <p>st io</p>
    <p>nle</p>
    <p>ve l F</p>
    <p>or e</p>
    <p>Evaluation on Answer Triggering</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CNN-Cnt +Q-Length +S-Length +Q-Class +All</p>
    <p>Q ue</p>
    <p>st io</p>
    <p>nle</p>
    <p>ve l F</p>
    <p>or e</p>
    <p>Evaluation on Answer Triggering</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WikiQA: A new dataset for open-domain QA  Question distribution: questions sampled from Bing query logs  Candidate selection: sentences from Wikipedia summary</p>
    <p>paragraphs  Enable Answer Triggering by including questions w/o answers</p>
    <p>Experiments  Different model behaviors on WikiQA and QASent datasets  Simple word-matching baseline is no longer strong  Answer triggering remains a challenging task</p>
    <p>Conclusion (1/2)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions (2/2)</p>
    <p>Future Work  Investigate advanced semantic matching methods  Encoder-decoder semantic matching (e.g., [Sutskever+ NIPS-14])  Structured text semantic matching (e.g., [Hu+ NIPS-14])  Improve the performance of answer triggering</p>
    <p>Data &amp; Evaluation Script: http:// aka.ms/WikiQA  Includes answer phrases labeled by authors</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
