<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>German in Flux:</p>
    <p>Detecting Metaphoric Change via Word Entropy</p>
    <p>August 4, 2017</p>
    <p>Dominik Schlechtweg, Stefanie Eckmann, Enrico Santus, Sabine Schulte im Walde, Daniel Hole</p>
    <p>dominik.schlechtweg@gmx.de, stefanie.eckmann@campus.lmu.de, esantus@mit.edu, schulte@ims.uni-stuttgart.de, holedan@gmail.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>I Our aim:</p>
    <p>I overall: build a computational model detecting semantic change</p>
    <p>I in this paper: distinguish metaphoric change from semantic stability</p>
    <p>I How we do it:</p>
    <p>I exploit the idea of semantic generality from hypernym detection</p>
    <p>I apply entropy to distributional semantic model I sample language German I introduce the first resource for evaluation of models of</p>
    <p>metaphoric change</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Shortcomings of Related Work</p>
    <p>I Previous work includes mainly:</p>
    <p>(i) spatial displacement models (ii) word sense induction models</p>
    <p>I quantify the degree of overall change rather than being able to qualify different types</p>
    <p>I do not examine metaphoric change</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Metaphoric Change</p>
    <p>I frequent and important type of semantic change</p>
    <p>I source and target concept are related by similarity or a reduced comparison (cf. Koch, 2016, p. 47)</p>
    <p>earlier: ... mu ich mich vmbweltzen / vnd kan keinen schlaff in meine augen bringen ... I have to turn around and cannot bring sleep into my eyes.</p>
    <p>later: Kinadon wollte den Staat umwalzen ... Kinadon wanted to revolutionize the state ...</p>
    <p>(i) creates polysemy</p>
    <p>(ii) often results in more abstract or general meanings</p>
    <p>assumption: (i) and (ii) imply extension and dispersion in the range of linguistic contexts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Corpus</p>
    <p>I Deutsches Textarchiv (erweitert) (DTA)</p>
    <p>I large: provides more than 2447 lemmatized and POS-tagged texts (with more than 140M tokens)</p>
    <p>I covers long time period: late 15th to the early 20th century</p>
    <p>I balanced: includes literary and scientific texts as well as functional writings</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Word Entropy</p>
    <p>I corresponds to entropy of word vector</p>
    <p>I is assumed to reflect semantic generality in hypernym detection</p>
    <p>I is given by</p>
    <p>H (C ) =  n</p>
    <p>i=1</p>
    <p>P (ci | w ) log2 P (ci | w )</p>
    <p>where P (ci | w ) is the occurrence probability of context word ci given target word w</p>
    <p>I measures the unpredictability of w s co-occurrences</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>I no standard test set of semantic or metaphoric change</p>
    <p>I we create a small but first test set via annotation (28 items)</p>
    <p>I annotators judged 560 context pairs for a metaphorical relation</p>
    <p>Workflow:</p>
    <p>(i) preselect 14 changing words (ii) add 14 stable distractors (iii) identify a date of change (iv) extract 20 contexts for each target from before and after date</p>
    <p>of change (v) for each word combine contexts between time periods randomly (vi) annotation of context pairs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Annotation</p>
    <p>I steps to identify metaphoric relation of C1 to C2:</p>
    <p>I C1 is less concrete than C2 I C1 is less human-oriented than C2 I C1 is not related to bodily action in contrast to C2 I C1 is less precise than C2</p>
    <p>I agreement:  (Fleiss Kappa) between .40 and .46</p>
    <p>I result is gold ranking of targets for strength of metaphoric change</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Annotation Results</p>
    <p>target POS type date meaning score Donnerwetter N met 1805 thunderstorm &gt; thunderstorm, blowup 0.78</p>
    <p>... Unhoflichkeit N sta 1605 discourtesy 0.1</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>Table 1 : Sample of test set items ordered by their annotated degree of metaphoric change.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Table 2 : Correlation () between predicted and gold ranks. Significance is determined with a t-test.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Result Analysis</p>
    <p>I ausstechen 1605: Von einem Bawren / welcher einem Kalbskopff die Augen</p>
    <p>austach. About a Farmer / who cut out the eyes of a calfs head.</p>
    <p>I gold rank: 12/28, entropy: 13, frequency: 17</p>
    <p>I Donnerwetter 1631: Die Lufft ist hei / vnd gibt viel Blitzen vnd Donnerwetter ...</p>
    <p>The air is hot / and there are many lightnings and thunderstorms ...</p>
    <p>I gold rank: 1/28, entropy: 27, frequency: 15</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>I you can annotate semantic change in a corpus (so do it)</p>
    <p>I entropy correlates strongly and significantly with degree of metaphoric change</p>
    <p>I frequency correlates moderately, but non-significantly on small data set</p>
    <p>I annotation and model are generalizable to different types of semantic change</p>
    <p>https://github.com/Garrafao/MetaphoricChange</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
