<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>University of Stuttgart Institute for Natural Language Processing</p>
    <p>Adversarial Training for Satire Detection: Controlling for Confounding Variables June 3rd, 2019</p>
    <p>Robert McHardy, Heike Adel and Roman Klinger</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Satire &amp; Research Goals Model/Data Experiments &amp; Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Motivation 1: Satire or not?</p>
    <p>After years of ghting there nally is a settlement</p>
    <p>between the Gema and Youtube . It became known today , that in future every music video is allowed to be played back in Germany again, as long as the audio is removed (translated from German)</p>
    <p>University of Stuttgart McHardy/Adel/Klinger June 3rd, 2019 2 / 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Satire &amp; Research Goals Model/Data Experiments &amp; Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Motivation 2: Satire or not?</p>
    <p>Erfurt ( dpo )  It is an organization which operates outside of law and order, funds numerous NPD operatives and is to a not inconsiderable extent involved in the series of murders of the so-called Zwickauer Zelle. (translated from German)</p>
    <p>DPA is a German news agency  DPO does not exist (in this context).</p>
    <p>University of Stuttgart McHardy/Adel/Klinger June 3rd, 2019 3 / 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Satire &amp; Research Goals Model/Data Experiments &amp; Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Satire</p>
    <p>Form of art to critize in an entertaining manner  Stylistic devices include humor, irony, sarcasm  Goal: Mimic regular news in diction  Its not misinformation or desinformation (fake news): Articles typically contain satire markers (similar to irony or sarcasm)</p>
    <p>Automatic Satire Detection Automatically distinguish satirical news from regular news  Challenging task (even for humans)</p>
    <p>University of Stuttgart McHardy/Adel/Klinger June 3rd, 2019 4 / 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Satire &amp; Research Goals Model/Data Experiments &amp; Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Previous Work</p>
    <p>Yang et al. 2017, De Sarkar et al. 2018</p>
    <p>Created data sets which are automatically labeled from publication source  Potential limitation: Models might learn characteristics of publication sources instead of actual characteristics of satire  (evaluation is not faulty, they use di erent publication sources for validation than for training)</p>
    <p>Bad generalization to unseen publication sources?  Interpretation of models (regarding concepts of satire)</p>
    <p>misleading?</p>
    <p>University of Stuttgart McHardy/Adel/Klinger June 3rd, 2019 5 / 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Satire &amp; Research Goals Model/Data Experiments &amp; Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Our Contributions</p>
    <p>We propose adversarial training: Improve robustness of model against confounding variable of publication sources  We show that adversarial training is crucial for the model to pay attention to satire instead of publication characteristics  We publish a large German data set for satire detection.</p>
    <p>First dataset in German  First dataset including publication sources  Largest resource for satire detection so far</p>
    <p>University of Stuttgart McHardy/Adel/Klinger June 3rd, 2019 6 / 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Satire &amp; Research Goals Model/Data Experiments &amp; Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Model</p>
    <p>input layer</p>
    <p>LSTM layer</p>
    <p>attention layer</p>
    <p>feature extractor</p>
    <p>satire detector</p>
    <p>publication identifier</p>
    <p>satire? (yes/no) publication name</p>
    <p>J s  s</p>
    <p>J s   f</p>
    <p>Jp p</p>
    <p>J p  f</p>
    <p>University of Stuttgart McHardy/Adel/Klinger June 3rd, 2019 7 / 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Satire &amp; Research Goals Model/Data Experiments &amp; Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Data Collection and Selection</p>
    <p>Regular news: Der Spiegel, Der Standard, Die Zeit, Sddeutsche Zeitung  Satire: Der Enthller, Eulenspiegel, Nordd. Nach., Der Postillon, Satirepatzer, Die Tagespresse, Titanic, Welt (Satire), Der Zeitspiegel, Eine Zeitung, Zynismus24  Articles from January 1st, 2000 and May 1st, 2018</p>
    <p>Average Length</p>
    <p>Publication #Articles Article Sent. Title</p>
    <p>Regular 320,219 663.45 17.79 6.86 Satire 9,643 269.28 18.73 9.52</p>
    <p>University of Stuttgart McHardy/Adel/Klinger June 3rd, 2019 8 / 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Satire &amp; Research Goals Model/Data Experiments &amp; Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Research Question 1: Performance</p>
    <p>How does a decrease in publication classi cation performance through adversarial training a ect the satire classi cation performance?</p>
    <p>University of Stuttgart McHardy/Adel/Klinger June 3rd, 2019 9 / 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Satire &amp; Research Goals Model/Data Experiments &amp; Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Research Question 2: Attention Weights</p>
    <p>Is adversarial training e ective for avoiding that the model pays most attention to the characteristics of publication source rather than actual satire?</p>
    <p>n o ad</p>
    <p>v Erfurt ( dpo ) - It is an organization which operates outside of law and order , funds numerous NPD operatives and is to a not inconsiderable extent involved in the series of murders of the so called Zwickauer Zelle .</p>
    <p>ad v Erfurt ( dpo ) - It is an organization which operates outside of law and order , funds</p>
    <p>numerous NPD operatives and is to a not inconsiderable extent involved in the series of murders of the so called Zwickauer Zelle .</p>
    <p>n o ad</p>
    <p>v</p>
    <p>After all , the proposal to allow family reunion only inclusive mothers-in-law is being discussed , whereof the Union hopes for an off-putting effect .</p>
    <p>ad v After all , the proposal to allow family reunion only inclusive mothers-in-law is being</p>
    <p>discussed , whereof the Union hopes for an off-putting effect .</p>
    <p>University of Stuttgart McHardy/Adel/Klinger June 3rd, 2019 10 / 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Satire &amp; Research Goals Model/Data Experiments &amp; Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Conclusion and Availability</p>
    <p>Observation: Satire detection models learn characteristics of publication sources</p>
    <p>Our Contributions</p>
    <p>Adversarial training to control for this confounding variable  Considerable reduction of publication identi cation performance while satire detection remains on comparable levels  Attention weights show e ectiveness of our approach  First German dataset for satire detection  Dataset and code available at: http://www.ims.uni-stuttgart.de/data/germansatire</p>
    <p>University of Stuttgart McHardy/Adel/Klinger June 3rd, 2019 11 / 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>University of Stuttgart Institute for Natural Language Processing</p>
    <p>Adversarial Training for Satire Detection: Controlling for Confounding Variables June 3rd, 2019</p>
    <p>Robert McHardy, Heike Adel and Roman Klinger</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
