<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Inequality on the Edge Lengths of Triangular Meshes</p>
    <p>Minghui Jiang Utah State University</p>
    <p>CCCG August 18, 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Theorem</p>
    <p>For any two triangular meshes A and B of the same polygon C, if the number of vertices in A is at most the number of vertices in B, then the maximum length of an edge in A is at least the minimum distance between two vertices in B.</p>
    <p>A B</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quality Measures for Triangular Meshes</p>
    <p>Most previous algorithms for mesh generation either maximize the minimum angle or minimize the maximum angle of a triangular mesh.</p>
    <p>The triangular meshes generated by such algorithms bounded maximum-to-minimum angle ratios, but not bounded maximumto-minimum edge length ratios.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Length-uniform Triangular Meshes</p>
    <p>Aurenhammer et al. [Theoretical Computer Science (2002), 879895] studied the problem of approximating length-uniform triangular meshes.</p>
    <p>Given a convex polygon P and a positive integer n, triangulate P using n Steiner points:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Approximation Algorithm</p>
    <p>Aurenhammer et al. proposed an algorithm that, with some reasonable assumptions on the input, achieves a constant approximation ratio for each of the three criteria.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Analysis</p>
    <p>For a convex polygon P and a positive integer n,</p>
    <p>dlong = min T</p>
    <p>max eE(T )</p>
    <p>length(e),</p>
    <p>where T ranges over all Steiner triangulations of P with n Steiner points, and E(T ) is the set of edges in the triangulation T .</p>
    <p>d = max S</p>
    <p>min u,vS  V (P )</p>
    <p>distance(u, v),</p>
    <p>where S ranges over all sets of n Steiner points in P , and V (P ) is the set of vertices of the polygon P .</p>
    <p>The approximation ratios of Aurenhammer et al.s algorithm crucially depend on the ratio of the two numbers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Conjecture</p>
    <p>By a simple area argument, Aurenhammer et al. proved that</p>
    <p>dlong</p>
    <p>and conjectured that dlong  d.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conjecture Confirmed by Theorem</p>
    <p>For any two triangular meshes A and B of the same polygon C, if the number of vertices in A is at most the number of vertices in B, then the maximum length of an edge in A is at least the minimum distance between two vertices in B.</p>
    <p>dlong = min T</p>
    <p>max eE(T )</p>
    <p>length(e),</p>
    <p>d = max S</p>
    <p>min u,vS  V (P )</p>
    <p>distance(u, v),</p>
    <p>dlong  d.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>P, S, T  A, B, C</p>
    <p>Let S be a set of n Steiner points in P that realizes the minimum pairwise distance d among the point set S  V (P ).</p>
    <p>Let T be a Steiner triangulation of P with n Steiner points such that the maximum edge length is dlong.</p>
    <p>S and T are guaranteed by the definitions of d and dlong.</p>
    <p>Let C be the convex polygon P .  Let A be T .  Let B be any triangulation of the point set S  V (P ) such</p>
    <p>that the minimum edge length is d.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>S  B Initialize B to a triangle of any three points in S including a</p>
    <p>closest pair, then add the remaining points one by one:</p>
    <p>If the point in inside some triangle, add three new edges to split the triangle into three triangles.</p>
    <p>If the point in on some edge, split the edge into two edges, then add additional edges if necessary to split the adjacent triangles.</p>
    <p>If the point is outside all triangles, add a new edge from the point to each visible vertex.</p>
    <p>Note that the initial edge between the closest pair is never split and remains in the mesh.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simplex and Simplicial Complex</p>
    <p>A d-simplex is the convex hull of d + 1 affinely independent vertices (that is, d + 1 points in general position) in some Euclidean space of dimension d or higher.</p>
    <p>A simplicial complex is a set K of simplices such that</p>
    <p>A simplex  is a face of another simplex  if the vertices of  are a subset of the vertices of  .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>r(K) and (K)</p>
    <p>For a simplicial complex K in the plane, where a 0-simplex is a point, a 1-simplex is a line segment, and a 2-simplex is a triangle, denote by r(K) the number of r-simplices in K, 0  r  2. Define the Euler characteristic of K as (K) = 0(K)  1(K) + 2(K).</p>
    <p>A B</p>
    <p>0(A) = 4, 1(A) = 6, 2(A) = 3, 0(B) = 4, 1(B) = 5, 2(B) = 2, and (A) = (B) = 1.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Area and Perimeter</p>
    <p>For a 1-simplex , denote by || the length of , and denote by (, K) the number of 2-simplices in K having  as a face. Then (, K) = 0, 1, or 2.</p>
    <p>Define the area of K as the total area of the 2-simplices in K. Define the perimeter of K as</p>
    <p>(2  (, K))||, where</p>
    <p>ranges over all 1-simplices in K.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Triangular Mesh As Simplicial Complex</p>
    <p>2-simplices are triangles,</p>
    <p>1-simplices are edges,</p>
    <p>0-simplices are polygon vertices and Steiner points.</p>
    <p>The Euler characteristic of the triangular mesh is exactly one minus the number of holes in the polygon.</p>
    <p>The area and the perimeter of the triangular mesh (as a simplicial complex) are respectively the same as the area and the perimeter (in the normal sense) of the polygon.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Proof</p>
    <p>For any two triangular meshes A and B of the same polygon C, if the number of vertices in A is at most the number of vertices in B, then the maximum length of an edge in A is at least the minimum distance between two vertices in B.</p>
    <p>Denote by max(T ) and min(T ), respectively, the maximum length of an edge and the minimum distance between two vertices in a triangular mesh T . We will prove the contrapositive:</p>
    <p>Let A and B be two triangular meshes of the same polygon C. Suppose that min(B) &gt; max(A). Then 0(B) &lt; 0(A).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The 40-Year Old Lemma</p>
    <p>Our proof will use the following lemma by Folkman and Graham [Canadian Mathematical Bulletin (1969), 745752]:</p>
    <p>Let K be a simplicial complex in the plane. Suppose that the distance between any two 0-simplices in K is at least 1. Then the total number of 0-simplices in K is at most 2</p>
    <p>In other words, if min(K)  ?, then 0(K)  ???. Our goal: if min(B) &gt; max(A), then 0(B) &lt; 0(A).</p>
    <p>To use this lemma, we could let B = K, then try to relate 0(A) to the area, perimeter, and Euler characteristic of B (or of A).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bounding the Area of A</p>
    <p>For any triangle of edge lengths at most , we can transform it into an equilateral triangle of edge length exactly  as follows.</p>
    <p>Note that the area of the triangle does not decrease during this transformation. Since an equilateral triangle of edge length  has an area exactly</p>
    <p>3</p>
    <p>3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bounding the Perimeter of A</p>
    <p>Denote by 0(T ) the number of vertices in a triangular mesh T that are on the boundary of the underlying polygon, including the polygon vertices and possibly additional Steiner vertices on the boundary.</p>
    <p>A B</p>
    <p>0(A) = 3 and 0(B) = 4. Since A has exactly 0(A) edges on the boundary of C, the</p>
    <p>perimeter of A is at most 0(A)  max(A).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2(A), 0(A), 0(A), and (A)</p>
    <p>Each boundary edge of a triangular mesh is incident to one triangle. Each internal edge of a triangular mesh is incident to two triangles. Each triangle has three edges. Thus by doublecounting we have</p>
    <p>= 1(A) = 32(A) + 0(A)</p>
    <p>Recall that (A) = 0(A)  1(A) + 2(A). Thus</p>
    <p>(A) = 0(A)  32(A) + 0(A)</p>
    <p>= 2(A) = 20(A)  0(A)  2(A).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Finally. . . 0(B)</p>
    <p>2 3  area(B) 2min(B)</p>
    <p>+ 1</p>
    <p>+ (B) (by Lemma)</p>
    <p>= 2 3  area(A) 2min(B)</p>
    <p>+ 1</p>
    <p>+ (A)</p>
    <p>&lt; 2 3  area(A) 2max(A)</p>
    <p>+ 1</p>
    <p>+ (A)</p>
    <p>2 3  2(A)</p>
    <p>3</p>
    <p>2max(A) +</p>
    <p>max(A) + (A)</p>
    <p>= 1</p>
    <p>= 1</p>
    <p>(</p>
    <p>+ 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Variation?</p>
    <p>We have proved the following:</p>
    <p>For any two triangular meshes A and B of the same polygon C, if the number of vertices in A is at most the number of vertices in B, then the maximum length of an edge in A is at least the minimum distance between two vertices in B.</p>
    <p>A natural question is whether the following is also true:</p>
    <p>For any two triangular meshes A and B of the same polygon C, if the number of vertices in A is at most the number of vertices in B, then the maximum edge length of A is at least the minimum edge length of B.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Example</p>
    <p>A B</p>
    <p>max(A)  min(B) = min(B)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Counter-example</p>
    <p>A B</p>
    <p>Two triangular meshes A and B of the same unit equilateral triangle C such that A and B have the same number of vertices but every edge of B is longer than every edge of A.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From A to A</p>
    <p>A A</p>
    <p>A has (5+1)(5+2)/2 = 21 vertices and uniform edge length 1/5. A has (4 + 1)(4 + 2)/2 = 15 vertices and uniform edge length 1/4.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From A to A and Z</p>
    <p>A A</p>
    <p>Z</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From A and Z to B</p>
    <p>A B</p>
    <p>Z</p>
    <p>B has 15 + 2  3 = 21 vertices and minimum edge length  1/4.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A and B</p>
    <p>A B</p>
    <p>A has 21 vertices and uniform edge length 1/5. B has 21 vertices and minimum edge length  1/4.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Construction Can Be Generalized</p>
    <p>For each k  5, there are two triangular meshes A and B of the unit equalateral triangle such that</p>
    <p>A has (k + 1)(k + 2)/2 vertices and uniform edge length 1/k.</p>
    <p>B has k(k + 1)/2 + 3(k 3) = (k + 1)(k + 2)/2 + 2(k 5) vertices and minimum edge length close to 1/(k  1).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Another False Statement</p>
    <p>The following statement is false too:</p>
    <p>For any two triangular meshes A and B of the same polygon C, if the number of vertices in A is at most the number of vertices in B, then the maximum triangle perimeter of A is at least the minimum triangle perimeter of B.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Counter-example</p>
    <p>A B</p>
    <p>Each triangular mesh has four vertices: three vertices of the triangle and one Steiner point.</p>
    <p>Maximum triangle perimeter of A: 1 + 2</p>
    <p>= 2.15 . . ..</p>
    <p>Minimum triangle perimeter of B: 1 + 1 2</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p>= 2.36 . . ..</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The End</p>
    <p>An updated version of the paper is online at</p>
    <p>http://www.cs.usu.edu/mjiang/</p>
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
