<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tutorial 6:</p>
    <p>Applications of Natural Language Processing in Clinical Research and Practice</p>
    <p>Yanshan Wang1, Ahmad P. Tafti1, Sunghwan Sohn1, Rui Zhang2 1Department of Health Sciences Research, Mayo Clinic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of Natural Language Processing in Clinical Domain</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data capture and sharing</p>
    <p>Advanced clinical processes</p>
    <p>Improved Outcome</p>
    <p>HITECH Act law 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation for Clinical NLP</p>
    <p>Demographics, Lab results, Medication, Diagnosis</p>
    <p>Clinical notes Patient provided information Family history Social history Radiology reports Pathology reports</p>
    <p>Structured Data</p>
    <p>Unstructured Data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Nature of EHR Data</p>
    <p>Primary function is to record clinical events and facilitate billing and the communication among the care team.  Significant dependence on narrative text,</p>
    <p>which is often the gold standard for clinical findings.  Using administrative/billing structured</p>
    <p>data as a surrogate for clinical data is problematic  Variations in coding, miscoding,</p>
    <p>incomprehensive  Misleading</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Speakers and Topics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Big Data Infrastructure for Large-scale Clinical NLP</p>
    <p>Big Data Social Media  Harnessing Social Media; What and Why?  Quantitative and Qualitative Analysis of Social Media  How We Can Draw Demographic-Specific Disparities Using Social</p>
    <p>Media  Gender-Specific  Age-Specific  Ethnicity-Specific</p>
    <p>Case Study: Gender Disparity in Side Effects Reporting of Chronic Pain Medications</p>
    <p>Ahmad P. Tafti is a Research Associate at Mayo Clinic, with a deep passion for improving health informatics using diverse medical data sources combined with advanced computational methods. Dr. Tafti's major interests are AI, machine learning, and computational health informatics. Dr. Tafti has published over 20 first-author peer-reviewed publications in prestigious journals and conferences (e.g., CVPR, AMIA, ISVC, JMIR, PLOS, IEEE Big Data), addressing medical text and medical image analysis and understanding using advanced computational strategies.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Advances of NLP in Clinical Research Rui Zhang is an Associate Professor and KcKnight Presidential Fellow in the College of Pharmacy and the Institute for Health Informatics (IHI), and also graduate faculty in Data Science at the University of Minnesota (UMN). He is the Leader of NLP Services in Clinical and Transnational Science Institution (CTSI) at the UMN. His work has been recognized on a national scale including Journal of Biomedical Informatics Editors Choice, nominated for Distinguished paper in AMIA Annual Symposium and Marco Ramoni Distinguished Paper Award for Translational Bioinformatics, as well as highlighted by The Wall Street Journal.</p>
    <p>Background of NLP to Support Clinical Research  NLP Systems and Tools for Clinical Research  Use Case 1: NLP to Support Dietary Supplement Safety Research  Use Case 2: NLP to Support Mental Health Research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clinical Information Extraction</p>
    <p>About EHR and its challenges  Clinical information extraction (IE)</p>
    <p>Methodology review (NLP techniques)  strength/weakness</p>
    <p>Clinical documentation variations and their effects on NLP tools  NLP tool portability</p>
    <p>Case study of NLP tool portability (asthma ascertainment)</p>
    <p>Sunghwan Sohn is an Associate Professor of Biomedical Informatics at Mayo Clinic. He has expertise in mining large-scale EHRs to unlock unstructured and hidden information using natural language processing and machine learning, thus creating new capacities for clinical research and practice in order to achieve better patient solutions. He has been involved in the development of cTAKES, the most popular NLP tool in the clinical domain. Dr. Sohn's research facilitates the best use of EHRs to solve clinical problems and improve public health.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Patient Cohort Retrieval using EHRs Yanshan Wang is a Research Associate at Mayo Clinic. His current work is centered on developing novel NLP and artificial intelligence (AI) methodologies for facilitating clinical research and solving real-world clinical problems. Dr. Wang has extensive collaborative research experience with physicians, epidemiology researchers, and statisticians. Dr. Wang has published over 40 peer-reviewed articles at referred computational linguistic conferences (e.g., NAACL), and medical informatics journals and conference (e.g., JBI, JAMIA, JMIR and AMIA). He has served on program committees for EMNLP, NAACL, IEEE-ICHI, IEEE-BIBM.</p>
    <p>Cohort retrieval  Approaches for cohort retrieval</p>
    <p>Medical concept embedding  Information retrieval  Deep patient representation</p>
    <p>Case studies  Patient cohort retrieval for clinical trials accrual</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Big Data Social Media</p>
    <p>Harnessing Social Media in Healthcare; What and Why?</p>
    <p>Quantitative and Qualitative Analysis of Social Media</p>
    <p>How We Can Draw Demographic-Specific Disparities Using Social Media</p>
    <p>Gender-Specific</p>
    <p>Age-Specific</p>
    <p>Ethnicity-Specific</p>
    <p>[Case Study: Gender Disparity in Side Effects Reporting of Chronic Pain Medications]</p>
    <p>Big Data Infrastructures for large-scale clinical NLP: Healthcare Social Media Mining</p>
    <p>Division of Digital Health Sciences Mayo Clinic</p>
    <p>Ahmad Tafti, PhD</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Big Data Social Media</p>
    <p>https://www.statista.com/statistics/282087/number-of-monthly-active-twitterusers/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Harnessing Social Media in Healthcare; What and Why? (Contd.)</p>
    <p>The rapid and extensive growth of social media persuades an increasing number of patients to use this technology for health related reasons.</p>
    <p>It has impacted the communication style that patients and physicians can take to discuss and share health related events, such as disease diagnosis and treatment, symptoms, medications, and drug side effects.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Harnessing Social Media in Healthcare; What and Why? (Contd.)</p>
    <p>Healthcare-Generated Health Data</p>
    <p>Patient-Generated Health Data</p>
    <p>o EHRs o Clinical Notes o Radiology Reports o Vital Signs o Medical Images o</p>
    <p>o Active/First Symptoms o Pain o Logistics o Drug Reviews o</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Harnessing Social Media in Healthcare; What and Why? (Contd.)</p>
    <p>Social media posts offer a unique opportunity to capture information about patient experiences with health events.</p>
    <p>Social media information can be used to develop patient-centered decision support tools that can be integrated with the EHR to facilitate discussions on treatment choices, risks, and benefits.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Harnessing Social Media in Healthcare; What and Why? (Contd.)</p>
    <p>Benefits and Advantages  Faster, Easier Communication  Professional Networking  Professional Education  Organizational promotion  Boost internal and external visibility  Customer feedback  Impress potential customers  User-generated content  Patient care  Patient education</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Harnessing Social Media in Healthcare; What and Why? (Contd.)</p>
    <p>Challenges  Unstructured data  Garbage mixed with gold (information quality issues)  Damage to Professional Image  Breaches of Patient Privacy  Legal and licensing Issues</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Harnessing Social Media in Healthcare; What and Why?</p>
    <p>Advices and Guidelines on How to Use This Wealth Of Data  Social Media Guidelines Issued by Health Care Institutions  IRBs Protocols  License agreements of the social media</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Qualitative Analysis of Social Media</p>
    <p>Source Gender Availability Age Availability Ethnicity Availability Location Availability</p>
    <p>Twitter No No No Yes</p>
    <p>Google+ Yes Yes No Yes</p>
    <p>Drugs.com No No No No</p>
    <p>DailyStrength Yes Yes No Yes</p>
    <p>WebMD Yes Yes No No</p>
    <p>MedHelp No No No No</p>
    <p>Patient.info Yes No No No</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Qualitative Analysis of Social Media</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Web Crawler/APIs</p>
    <p>Text Processing</p>
    <p>Gender Classification  Ethnicity Classification</p>
    <p>Sentence Classification</p>
    <p>Top Distinctive Terms and Dominant Topics</p>
    <p>Scientific Visualization</p>
    <p>Training Dataset</p>
    <p>SM-Dataset MedTagger</p>
    <p>Framework</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Gender Classification</p>
    <p>Gender API: https://gender-api.com gender-guesser: https://pypi.org/project/gender-guesser genderize.io: https://genderize.io NameAPI: https://www.nameapi.org NamSor: https://www.namsor.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study: Gender Disparity in Side Effects Reporting of Chronic Pain Medications</p>
    <p>We are filtering the posts using a list of pain/chronic pain related keywords and healthrelated ones. The rationale of selecting the keywords is to cover/pull the posts as much as we can. Here is the list based on our best practices:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Filtering the data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Filtering the data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Filtering the data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Example: Good Reviews</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Example: Good Reviews</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Example: Bad Reviews</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sentence Classification: ADEs vs Non-ADEs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sentence Classification: ADEs vs Non-ADEs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Visualization Results: An Example</p>
    <p>Figure 1. (Left) Women were more likely than men to report side effects from gabapentin. Women: 239 posts out of 1407 associated with gabapentin (including side effects, indication, and/or other topics)Men: it was 281 out of 1,973 posts. (Right) Gender-specific comparative visualization across five different side effects of gabapentin. **Note: all side effects identified in this exercise are previously reported side effects of gabapentin.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Visualization Results: An Example</p>
    <p>Figure 2. Percentwise proportion of women and men who did shared their pain-related experiences within three opioid class medications in Twitter, within last 30 days. One can see the number of Oxycodone and Ritalin tweets generated by women is greater than those generated by men. For Methadone, it shows men discussed the medication a little more than women.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Advances of Natural Language Processing in Clinical Research</p>
    <p>Rui Zhang, Ph.D. Associate Professor and McKnight Presidential Fellow,</p>
    <p>Department of Pharmaceutical Care &amp; Health Systems, and Institute for Health Informatics</p>
    <p>University of Minnesota, Twin Cities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background of NLP to Support Clinical Research  NLP Systems and Tools for Clinical Research  Use Case 1: NLP to Support Dietary Supplement</p>
    <p>Safety Research  Use Case 2: NLP to Support Mental Health</p>
    <p>Research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clinical Research Informatics (CRI)  CRI involves the use of informatics in the discovery and</p>
    <p>management of new knowledge relating to health and disease.</p>
    <p>It includes management of information related to clinical trials and also involves informatics related to secondary research use of clinical data.</p>
    <p>It involves approaches to collect, process, analyze, and display health care and biomedical data for research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>JAMA 2014;311(24):2479-80</p>
    <p>Healthcare Big Data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Structured vs. Unstructured Data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Structured vs. Unstructured Data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Leveraging Natural Language Processing (NLP) to Unlock Unstructured Data</p>
    <p>A field of Artificial Intelligence (AI)  Applications that automatically analyze natural language</p>
    <p>(English, Chinese)  Computational linguistics + domain knowledge  Tasks</p>
    <p>Word sense disambiguation (WSD)  Named entity recognition (NER)  Relation extraction (RE)  Negation identification (NegIde)  Semantic role labelling (SRL)  Information extraction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Word Sense Disambiguation (WSD)  Word sense: a meaning of a word.  Acronym</p>
    <p>The patient underwent a left BK amputation. Sense: below knee</p>
    <p>BK viremia in the past. Sense: BK (virus)</p>
    <p>Abbreviation  CT of head showed old CVA on left side.</p>
    <p>Sense: cerebrovascular accident  Straight with no CVA tenderness.</p>
    <p>Sense: costovertebral angle</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Named Entity Recognition (NER)</p>
    <p>http://text-machine.cs.uml.edu/cliner/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Determine relationships between entities or events</p>
    <p>We used hemofiltration to treat a patient with digoxin overdose that was complicated by refractory hyperkalemia. [PMID: 3718110]</p>
    <p>Relationship: Hemofiltration-TREATS-Patients</p>
    <p>Relationship Extraction (RE)</p>
    <p>https://semrep.nlm.nih.gov</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Negation Identification (NegIde)  Identify pertinent Negatives from narrative clinical reports</p>
    <p>- The chest X-ray showed no infiltrates - The patient denied experiencing chest pain -  no murmurs, rubs or gallops - murmurs, rubs and gallops are absent</p>
    <p>Journal of Biomedical Informatics 34, 301310 (2001)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Semantic Role Labeling  Detect the semantic role played by each noun phrase</p>
    <p>associated with the verb of a sentence  Agent: Noun Phrase (NP) before the verb  Patient: NP after the verb  Instrument: NP in a Prepositional Phrase (PP)</p>
    <p>PatientAgent</p>
    <p>S</p>
    <p>NP VP PP</p>
    <p>We dissected cautery</p>
    <p>NPINVBN</p>
    <p>a cystic artery</p>
    <p>NPIN</p>
    <p>out with</p>
    <p>Instrument</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Information Extraction  Automated extraction of family and observation predications</p>
    <p>from unstructured text  Supplied text: &quot;Heart disease on the father side of the family.</p>
    <p>Mother has arthritis.  Extracted elements:</p>
    <p>Constituent: family {FAMILY HISTORY: FAMMEMB}  Constituent: observation {Heart disease: C1576434}  Constituent: family {father side of the family: Paternal*}  Constituent: family {Mother: MTH}  Constituent: observation {arthritis: C1692886}</p>
    <p>Predications:  Family Member{father side of the family}, Observation{Heart disease},</p>
    <p>Negated{false}  Family Member{Mother}, Observation{arthritis}, Negated{false}</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Leveraging NLP in Clinical Research</p>
    <p>NLP (extract, classify, summarize)</p>
    <p>Biomedical Literature</p>
    <p>!&quot;#$%&amp;#'(</p>
    <p>!&quot;#$%&amp;#')</p>
    <p>!&quot;#$%&amp;#'*</p>
    <p>'''''''+++''''' '''''''''''' ''''''''''''</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>Clinical Notes</p>
    <p>Social history  Function score  Medical history  Smoking status</p>
    <p>Biomedical knowledge (Subject  Predicate - Object)</p>
    <p>Clinical researchers 14</p>
    <p>Social Media</p>
    <p>Pharmacovigilance signals (Drug/supplement</p>
    <p>adverse Events)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Leveraging Big Data for Pharmacovigilance</p>
    <p>https://knowledgent.com/whitepaper/big-data-enabling-better-pharmacovigilance/ 15</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Shared NLP Tasks</p>
    <p>Challenges  Lack of shared resources and evaluation (de-identification,</p>
    <p>recognition of medical concepts, semantic modifies, temporal information)</p>
    <p>Shared tasks  Informatics for Integrating Biology and the Bedside (i2b2)</p>
    <p>challenges  Conference and Labs of the evaluation Forum (CLEF) eHealth</p>
    <p>challenges  Semantic Evaluation (SemEval) challenges</p>
    <p>J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc., 14 (5) (2007), p. 550 Springer International Publishing (2016), 10.1007/978-3-319-44564-9_24 pp. 255266 Computational Linguistics, San Diego, California (2016), pp. 1052-1062</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Open source NLP Systems</p>
    <p>http://ctakes.apache.org/ http://clamp.uth.edu/index.php https://github.com/nlpie/biomedicus BioNLP Workshop of the Association for Computational Linguistics; June 29, 2007</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Chaining NLP Tasks: Pipelines</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of Clinical Research and NLP</p>
    <p>The goal of clinical research (trial, cohort study):  To assess the association between a risk factor or</p>
    <p>intervention with an clinical outcome  Internal validation: measured on the original study sample  External validation: measured on a different sample</p>
    <p>The goal of NLP method development  To produce computational solutions to special problem</p>
    <p>Intrinsic: measuring on attaining its immediate objective  Extrinsic: evaluating its usefulness in an overarching goal where</p>
    <p>NLP is part of a more complex process</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of Clinical Research and NLP</p>
    <p>NLP development mainly focuses on intrinsic evaluation  Document (patient status, report type)  Documents section (current med, past med history, discharge summary)  Named entities and concepts (diagnosis, symptoms, treatments)  Semantic attributes (negation, severity, temporality)</p>
    <p>Intrinsic evaluation may not be informative when they apply on higher level problem (patient level) or new data  In clinical practice, any &gt;0% error rate (the misclassification of a drug or a</p>
    <p>history of severe allergy) is unacceptable  True negative are rarely considered in NLP evaluation, but is key factor in</p>
    <p>clinical research (medical screening)  It is unclear how best to incorporate and interpret NLP</p>
    <p>performance when using outputs from NLP approaches in clinical research.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP-PIER (Patient Information Extraction for Research)</p>
    <p>AMIA Joint Summit. 2016: 150159.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP-PIER  A clinical notes processing platform including an</p>
    <p>NLP query and search engine for clinical and translational researchers</p>
    <p>System is secured by an authentication and authorization layer</p>
    <p>System was designed to give clinical researchers access to NLP capabilities for searching clinical notes in an environment that is compliant for accessing protected health information (PHI)</p>
    <p>http://athena.ahc.umn.edu/nlppier/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP-PIER</p>
    <p>Users only have access to sets of notes that are defined externally and configured in the Elasticsearch engine</p>
    <p>Access granted through CTSI-BPIC  Provide researchers direct access to patient data in</p>
    <p>free text of 170 million clinical notes for &gt;2.9 million patients (as of May 2019)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP-PIER Search Capabilities  Keyword searching</p>
    <p>Advanced query syntax  NOT, AND, OR</p>
    <p>Grouping</p>
    <p>Distance syntax</p>
    <p>Identified UMLS concepts  Historical, negated modifiers</p>
    <p>Word vector - based query expansion  Misspellings</p>
    <p>Contextually related terms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other Capabilities</p>
    <p>Personalized filters  Set export settings  Save and share queries  Query expansion  Patient/encounter counts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Query Help Options</p>
    <p>Select Query Template</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Settings Menu</p>
    <p>Change number of displayed filters here</p>
    <p>Select type of filters that are enabled here</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Query Expansion Word Vectors</p>
    <p>Find Common Misspellings Here</p>
    <p>Find Related Terms Here</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EMERSE (Electronic Medical Record Search Engine)</p>
    <p>Enables users to search clinical notes (dictated or typed) from our electronic medical record (CareWeb and MiChart) for terms.</p>
    <p>EMERSE aids in cohort identification, eligibility determination and data abstraction in a variety of research, clinical, and operational settings</p>
    <p>Similar to PIER search engine  Expert curated Synonyms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Search with Synonyms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Visualization with NER</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cohort Identification</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Use Case 1: NLP to Support Dietary Supplement Safety Research</p>
    <p>Expanding Supplement Terminology from Clinical Notes  Detecting Supplement Use Status  Detecting Safety Signals about Supplements in Clinical Notes  Mining biomedical Literature to Discover DSIs  Active Learning to Reduce Annotation Costs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction to Dietary Supplements  Dietary supplements  Herbs, vitamins, minerals, probiotics, amino acids, others.</p>
    <p>Use of supplements increasing  More than half of U.S. adults take dietary supplements (Center</p>
    <p>for Disease Control and Prevention)  One in six U.S. adults takes a supplement simultaneously with</p>
    <p>prescription medications  Sales over $6 billion per year in U.S. (American Botanical</p>
    <p>Council, 2014)</p>
    <p>https://nccih.nih.gov/health/supplements Use of complementary and alternative medicine by children in Europe: Published data and expert perspectives. Complement Ther Med. 2013 4;21. Kaufman, Kelly, JAMA. 2002;287(3):337-344. Dietary Supplement Use Among U.S. Adults Has Increased Since NHANES III (19881994). 2014(Nov 4, 2014). CDC. 34</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Safety of Dietary Supplements  Doctors often poorly informed about supplements</p>
    <p>75.5% of 1,157 clinicians  Supplements are NOT always safe</p>
    <p>Averagely 23,000 annual emergency visits for supplements adverse events</p>
    <p>Drug-supplement interactions (DSIs)  Concomitant administration of supplements and drugs</p>
    <p>increases risks of DSIs  Example: Docetaxel &amp; St Johns Wort (hyperforin component</p>
    <p>induces docetaxel metabolism via P450 3A4)</p>
    <p>Kaufman, Kelly, JAMA. 2002;287(3):337-344. Geller et al. New England J Med. 2015; 373:1531-40. Gurley BJ. Molecular nutrition &amp; food research. 2008, 52(7):772-9.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Regulation for Dietary Supplements  Regulated by Dietary Supplement Health and Education</p>
    <p>Act of 1994 (DSHEA)  Different regulatory framework from prescription and over-the</p>
    <p>counter drugs</p>
    <p>Safety testing and FDA approval NOT required before marketing  Postmarketing reporting only required for serious adverse</p>
    <p>events (hospitalization, significant disability or death)</p>
    <p>Department of Health and Human Services, Food and Drug Administration. New dietary ingredients in dietary supplements  background for industry. March 3, 2014 Dietary Supplement and Nonprescription Drug Consumer Protection Act. Public Law 109-462, 120 Stat 4500.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limited Supplements Research</p>
    <p>Supplement safety research is limited  Not required for clinical trials  Not found until new supplement is on the market  Voluntary adverse events reporting underestimates the</p>
    <p>safety issues  Pharmacy studies only focuses on specific supplements  DSI documentation is limited due to less rigorous</p>
    <p>regulatory rules on supplements  No existing standard supplement terminology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limited Supplements Research</p>
    <p>Limited knowledge on supplements 1,2  Safety (adverse effects, interactions, precautions, etc.)  Efficacy  Mechanism of action  Bioavailability/dosing  Metabolism/excretion  Other essential data elements (naming, type, source,</p>
    <p>origin, etc.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Informatics to Support Supplements Research  Online resources  Provides DS knowledge across various resources  Need informatics method to standard and integrate knowledge</p>
    <p>Biomedical literature  Contains pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics knowledge  Discover undefined pathways for DSIs  Find potential DSIs by linking information  Limited studies to discover DSIs</p>
    <p>Electronic health records  EHR provides patient data for supplement use  Detailed supplements usage information documented in clinical</p>
    <p>notes  No studies investigating the supplements in clinical notes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Lexical variations of supplements in clinical notes  Detailed usage information related to supplements  No standardized and consistent DS knowledge</p>
    <p>representation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thesaurus-based method (e.g., MeSH, SNOMED-CT)  Distributional semantics</p>
    <p>Word similarity is estimated based on the distribution of the words in the corpus  Traditional methods</p>
    <p>Vector models (high dimensional; sparsity issue)  Word embeddings</p>
    <p>Reveal hidden relationship between words (similarity and relatedness)</p>
    <p>More efficient; can be trained a large amount of unannotated data</p>
    <p>Mikolov T, Chen K, Corrado G, Dean J. Efficient estimation of word representations in vector space. arXiv preprint arXiv:1301.3781. 2013 Jan 16. Tang B, Cao H, Wang X, Chen Q, Xu H. Evaluating word representation features in biomedical named entity recognition tasks. BioMed research international. 2014;2014. Pakhomov SV, Finley G, McEwan R, Wang Y, Melton GB. Corpus domain effects on distributional semantic modeling of medical terms. Bioinformatics. 2016 Aug 16;32(23):3635-44.41</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Objective</p>
    <p>To apply word embedding models to expand the terminology of DS from clinical notes: semantic variants, brand names, misspellings  Corpus size  Compare two word embedding models</p>
    <p>Word2vec, GloVe</p>
    <p>calcium chamomile cranberry dandelion flaxseed garlic ginger</p>
    <p>ginkgo ginseng glucosamine lavender melatonin turmeric valerian</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method Overview</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model Training</p>
    <p>Corpus size</p>
    <p>Hyperparameter tuning  Window size (i.e., 4, 6, 8, 10, and 12)  Vector size (i.e., 100, 150, 200, 250)</p>
    <p>Glove trained on the same corpus  Window size and vector size</p>
    <p>Optimal parameters were chosen based on human annotation (intrinsic evaluation)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Figure 1. The number of semantic similar terms identified by human experts based on 40 top-ranked terms by word2vec for each DS from 7 corpora</p>
    <p>N um</p>
    <p>be r o</p>
    <p>f s em</p>
    <p>an tic</p>
    <p>v ar</p>
    <p>ia nt</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Vo ca</p>
    <p>bu la</p>
    <p>ry s</p>
    <p>iz e</p>
    <p>Vocabulary size Semantic variants Brand names Misspellings</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Query Expansion Examples Initial Query word2vec Expanded Query Expanded Examples</p>
    <p>Black cohosh</p>
    <p>Misspelling: black kohosh, black kohash; Brand name: remifemin Estroven Estrovan estraven icool amberen amberin Estrovera EstroFactor</p>
    <p>Please try black cohash or Estroven for hot flashes.  Pt has discontinued Remifemin but still has symptoms.  Recommend Estroven trial for symptoms of menopause.</p>
    <p>Turmeric Misspelling: tumeric  Pt emailed wondering about taking Tumeric  Patient states that she sometimes takes the supplements</p>
    <p>Tumeric</p>
    <p>Folic acid Brand name: Folgard, Folbic Other name: Folate</p>
    <p>Patient is willing to try Folgard if ok with provider.  Patient is on folate and does not smoke.</p>
    <p>Valerian Misspelling: velarian Brand name: myocalm pm, somnapure</p>
    <p>Taking Velarian root and benadryl as well  I would recommend moving to 6mg dose first, then trying</p>
    <p>somnapure if still not helping.</p>
    <p>Melatonin Misspelling: Melantonin, melotonin Brand name: alteril, neuro sleep</p>
    <p>Can try melantonin for sleep aid.  Try alteril - it is over the counter sleep aid Let me know if</p>
    <p>this is not better over the next few weeks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Comparison of Base and Expanded Queries Queries Number of clinical notes Number of patients</p>
    <p>Dietary supplements</p>
    <p>Number of expanded terms</p>
    <p>Base query Expanded query</p>
    <p>Additional records found</p>
    <p>Percentage increase (%)</p>
    <p>Base query</p>
    <p>Expanded query</p>
    <p>Additional patients found</p>
    <p>Percentage increase (%)</p>
    <p>Black cohosh 3 13,782 23,641 9,859 71.54 5,560 8,833 3,273 58.87 Calcium 10 7,024,626 7,053,856 29,230 0.42 950,282 950,992 710 0.07</p>
    <p>Cranberry 3 187,586 189,239 1,653 0.88 71,860 72,499 639 0.89</p>
    <p>Dandelion 2 4,316 4,375 59 1.37 2,155 2,191 36 1.67 Fish oil 1 1,305,996 1,311,777 5,781 0.44 192,326 195,015 2,689 1.40</p>
    <p>Folic acid 3 839,710 1,058,627 218,917 26.07 107,897 159,768 51,871 48.07</p>
    <p>Garlic 1 91,342 92,481 1,139 1.25 28,657 28,784 127 0.44</p>
    <p>Ginger 0 88,870 88,870 0 0 53,867 53,867 0 0</p>
    <p>Ginkgo 3 19,020 27,502 8,482 44.60 5,202 7,080 1,878 36.10 Ginseng 2 9,663 10,748 1,085 11.23 3,754 4,112 358 9.54 Glucosamine 5 468,774 469,925 1,151 0.25 68,013 68,106 93 0.14</p>
    <p>Green tea 2 29,810 29,816 6 0.02 12,853 12,856 3 0.02</p>
    <p>Melatonin 1 647,389 647,601 212 0.03 101,994 102,041 47 0.05</p>
    <p>Milk thistle 1 18,930 19,298 368 1.94 3,245 3,279 34 1.05 Saw palmetto 1 38,934 38,947 13 0.03 6,708 6,709 1 0.01 Turmeric 3 25,172 37,959 12,787 50.80 6,583 10,758 4,175 63.42 Valerian 2 15,023 15,330 307 2.04 6,435 6,589 154 2.39 Vitamin E 0 384,072 384,072 0 0 68,284 68,284 0 0 47</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Comparison with External Source</p>
    <p>Comparison between word embedding expanded queries and external source expanded queries (task 2) for 14 DS (selected examples)</p>
    <p>Dietary supplements</p>
    <p>Number of</p>
    <p>external source terms</p>
    <p>Number of word</p>
    <p>embedding expanded</p>
    <p>terms</p>
    <p>Number of clinical notes Number of patients</p>
    <p>External source query</p>
    <p>Word embedding query</p>
    <p>Additional records found</p>
    <p>Percentage increase (%)</p>
    <p>Base query Word embedding query</p>
    <p>Additional records found</p>
    <p>Percentage increase (%)</p>
    <p>Calcium 15 12 7453873 7543569 89696 1.20 1000906 1002211 1305 0.13</p>
    <p>Cranberry 21 3 196944 198625 1681 0.85 76697 77327 630 0.82</p>
    <p>Flaxseed 10 2 169349 169343 -6 0.00 45229 45222 -7 -0.02</p>
    <p>Ginkgo 6 3 20275 28093 7818 38.56 5855 7791 1936 33.07</p>
    <p>Turmeric 18 3 35719 48749 13030 36.48 8962 13486 4524 50.48</p>
    <p>External sources: Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database (NMCD), Dietary Supplement Label Database (DSLD)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fan et al, AMIA Joint Summit 2017:493-501. (The 2nd place in Student Paper Competition) Fan Y, et al., BMC Medical Informatics &amp; Clinical Decision. 2018, 18(Suppl 2): 51.</p>
    <p>To classify the use status of the supplements in clinical notes into four categories: Continuing, Discontinued, Started, and Unclassified</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Performance comparison</p>
    <p>*P: precision, R: recall, F: F-measure</p>
    <p>Type 1: raw unigrams without normalization; Type 2: unigrams (normalized); Type 3: TF-IDF (term frequency  inversed document frequency) for unigrams; Type 4: bigrams; Type 5: unigrams + bigrams; Type 6: unigrams + bigrams + trigrams; Type 7: indicator words only; Type 8: unigrams + bigrams + indicator words with distance (window size); Type 9: unigrams + bigrams + trigrams + indicator words with distance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance comparison</p>
    <p>The Performance of Maximum Entropy with Type 8 in Test Set</p>
    <p>The Performance of Classifier on 25 dietary supplements</p>
    <p>Fan Y, et al., BMC Medical Informatics &amp; Clinical Decision. 2018, 18(Suppl 2): 51.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deep Learning Text Classification Methods</p>
    <p>Word-level CNN  Filter size: [1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6], number of filters: 256</p>
    <p>Bi-LSTM  Hidden units: 256</p>
    <p>Stacked Bi-LSTM  Layers: 2, Hidden units: 128</p>
    <p>Models Precision Recall F-measure (weighted)</p>
    <p>Word-CNN 0.808 0.804 0.803</p>
    <p>Bi-LSTM 0.882 0.880 0.879</p>
    <p>Stacked Bi-LSTM 0.918 0.916 0.916</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>http://www.wsj.com/articles/what-you-should-know-about-how-your-supplements-interact-with-prescription-drugs-1456777548 http://www.foxnews.com/health/2016/03/01/what-should-know-about-how-supplements-interact-with-prescription-drugs.html</p>
    <p>Researchers at the University of Minnesota in Minneapolis are exploring interactions between cancer drugs and dietary supplements, based on data extracted from 23 million scientific publications, according to lead author Rui Zhang, a clinical assistant professor in health informatics. In a study published last year by a conference of the American Medical Informatics Association, he says, they identified some that were previously unknown.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Literature-based Discovery</p>
    <p>We have shown that ECHINACEA preparations and some common alkylamides weakly inhibit several cytochrome P450 (CYP) isoforms, with considerable variation in potency. (19790031)</p>
    <p>Echinacea - INHIBITS - CYP450</p>
    <p>Tamoxifen and toremifene are metabolised by the cytochrome p450 enzyme system, and raloxifene is metabolised by glucuronide conjugation. (12648026)</p>
    <p>CYP450 - INTERACTS_WITH - Toremifene</p>
    <p>Named entity recognition (NER), Relationship extraction</p>
    <p>Echinacea - &lt;Potentially Interacts With&gt; - Toremifene</p>
    <p>Big Data: 28 million abstracts</p>
    <p>X1-Y1 X2-Y2  Xm-Ym</p>
    <p>Y1-Z1 Y3-Z2  Yn-Zn</p>
    <p>&amp;</p>
    <p>X1-Z1 Y5-Z8  Xk-Zt</p>
    <p>&amp;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Drug/Supplement Predicate Gene/Gene Class Predicate Supplement/Dru g</p>
    <p>Known</p>
    <p>Echinacea INH CYP450 INT Docetaxel Y</p>
    <p>Echinacea INH CYP450 INT Toremifene N</p>
    <p>Echinacea STI CYP1A1 INT Exemestane N</p>
    <p>Grape seed extract INH CYP3A4 INT Docetaxel N</p>
    <p>Kava preparation STI CYP3A4 INT Docetaxel Y</p>
    <p>Results: Selected Interactions</p>
    <p>INH, INHIBITS; STI, STIMULATES; INT, INTERACTS_WITH</p>
    <p>Echinacea: fights the common cold and viral infections Grape seed extract: cardiac conditions Kava: treat sleep problems, relieve anxiety and stress</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Selected Predications Semantic predication</p>
    <p>Citations</p>
    <p>Echinacea INHIBITS CYP450</p>
    <p>We have shown that ECHINACEA preparations and some common alkylamides weakly inhibit several cytochrome P450 (CYP) isoforms, with considerable variation in potency. (19790031)</p>
    <p>Grape seed extract INHIBITS CYP3A4</p>
    <p>Four brands of GSE had no effect, while another five produced mild to moderate but variable inhibition of CYP3A4, ranging from 6.4% by Country Life GSE to 26.8% by Loma Linda Market brand. (19353999)</p>
    <p>Melatonin INHIBITS Cyclooxygenase-2</p>
    <p>Moreover, Western blot analysis showed that melatonin inhibited LPS/IFNgamma-induced expression of COX-2 protein, but not that of constitutive cyclooxygenase. (18078452).</p>
    <p>CYP450 INTERACTS_WITH Toremifene</p>
    <p>Tamoxifen and toremifene are metabolised by the cytochrome p450 enzyme system, and raloxifene is metabolised by glucuronide conjugation. (12648026)</p>
    <p>CYP3A INHIBITS Docetaxel</p>
    <p>Because docetaxel is inactivated by CYP3A, we studied the effects of the St. John's wort constituent hyperforin on docetaxel metabolism in a human hepatocyte model. (16203790)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP tasks requires human annotations  Time consuming and labor intensive</p>
    <p>Active learning reduces annotation costs  Used in biomedical and clinical texts  Effectiveness varies across datasets and tasks</p>
    <p>Chen Y, Lasko TA, Mei Q, Denny JC, Xu H. A study of active learning methods for named entity recognition in clinical text. J Biomed Inform 2015; 58: 118. Chen Y, Cao H, Mei Q, Zheng K, Xu H. Applying active learning to supervised word sense disambiguation in MEDLINE. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013; 20 (5): 10016. 57</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Objectives</p>
    <p>To assess the effectiveness of AL methods on filtering incorrect semantic predication</p>
    <p>To evaluate various query strategies and provide a comparative analysis of AL method through visualization</p>
    <p>Vasilakes J, Rizvi R, Melton G, Pakhomov S, Zhang R. J Am Med Info Assoc Open. 2018 58</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method Overview</p>
    <p>Query strategies:  Uncertainty sampling  Representative sampling  Combined sampling</p>
    <p>Evaluation:  10-fold cross validation  Training = 2700, L0=270  Testing = 300 using AUC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Datasets and Annotations</p>
    <p>Substance interaction (3,000):  INTERACTS_WITH, STIMULATES, or INHIBITS</p>
    <p>Clinical Medicine (3,000):  ADMINISTERED_TO, COEXISTS_WITH, COM- PLICATES,</p>
    <p>DIAGNOSES, MANIFESTATION_OF, PRE- CEDES, PREVENTS, PROCESS_OF, PRODUCES, TREATS, or USES</p>
    <p>Inter-rater agreement:  Kappa: 0.74 (SI), 0.72 (CM)  Percentage agreement: 87% (SI), 91% (CM)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Comparison</p>
    <p>When L is small and U is large:  it is unlikely that L is representative of U  given that L is small and unrepresentative, the prediction model trained on L is likely to be poor.</p>
    <p>|U| is the size of the current unlabeled set |L| is the size of the current labeled set 61</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Uncertainty Sampling</p>
    <p>Query Strategy ALC Passive Learning 0.590 Uncertainty Sampling 0.597  0.607</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Representative Sampling</p>
    <p>Query Strategy ALC Passive Learning 0.590 Uncertainty Sampling 0.597  0.607 Representative Sampling</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Combined Sampling</p>
    <p>Query Strategy ALC Passive Learning 0.590 Uncertainty Sampling 0.597  0.607 Representative Sampling</p>
    <p>ID (manual ) 0.642</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Dynamic</p>
    <p>Passive Learning</p>
    <p>Query Strategy ALC Passive Learning 0.590 Uncertainty Sampling 0.597  0.607 Representative Sampling</p>
    <p>ID (manual ) 0.642 ID (dynamic ) 0.641</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Analysis</p>
    <p>Uncertainty Sampling (worst performing)</p>
    <p>Representative Sampling (best performing)</p>
    <p>Vasilakes J, Rizvi R, Melton G, Pakhomov S, Zhang R. J Am Med Info Assoc Open. 2018</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Use Case 2: NLP in Mental Health Research</p>
    <p>NLP to Extract Symptoms of Severe Mental Illness (SMI) from Clinical Texts</p>
    <p>Deep Neural Network for Phenotyping Youth Depression</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Mental illness is a condition that affects a persons thinking, feeling, and behavior</p>
    <p>There are five major categories of mental illnesses:  Anxiety disorders  Mood disorders  Schizophrenia and psychotic disorders  Dementia  Eating disorders</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mental Health Records</p>
    <p>Most salient information for research and clinical practice in text filed (70%)  Self-reported experience  Determining treatment initiation and outcome evaluation  90 documents per patient (South London and Maudsley</p>
    <p>mental health trust)  Most clinical researchers and clinicians collect data</p>
    <p>using standardized instrument  Beck Depression Inventory (BDI)  the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANNS)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background  SMI: schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder and bipolar disorder  Diagnoses (ICD or DSM) form semantically convenient unit  Mental disorders have broad symptomatic manifestations</p>
    <p>Schizophrenia (all, or few of associated symptoms)  Symptomatology, compared to diagnoses, offer more objective</p>
    <p>patient grouping  Objective:  develop NLP models to capture key symptoms of SMI to</p>
    <p>facilitate the secondary use of mental health data in research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>Data:  EHR from a large mental health providing serving 1.2</p>
    <p>million residents in UK  3.5 million documents</p>
    <p>NLP task  Sentence classification  Symptom keywords  Clinical relevant modifier terms (product subclassification)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SMI Keywords and Modifiers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Information Extraction  TextHunter  Built around ConText algorithm* and GATE framework</p>
    <p>Matching keywords using regular expression  Providing annotation interface  Construct SVM model for the concept and evaluate</p>
    <p>Uses bag-of-word features and knowledge engineering features from ConText</p>
    <p>* The ConText algorithm provides context -whether the event occurred (Negation: affirmed or negated), who experienced it (Experiencer: patient or other), and when it occurred (Temporality: historical, recent, not particular) - for a given event from a sentence. [BioNLP Workshop of the Association for Computational Linguistics; June 29, 2007]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Comparison</p>
    <p>Annotated 50 symptoms with 37211 instances (Cohens  of 0.83)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background  EHR analysis can support recruitment in clinical research  Diagnosis codes are frequently missing  NLP can detect features in clinical notes and outperformed</p>
    <p>features by experts</p>
    <p>NLP outperformed diagnosis for classifying mood state (ROC: 0.850.88 vs 0.540.55)</p>
    <p>Objective  To identify individuals who meet inclusion criteria as well as</p>
    <p>unsuitable patients who would require exclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data</p>
    <p>Phenotype of youth depression  Inclusion: Ages 12-18 with DSM defined Major</p>
    <p>Depressive Disorder or Dysthymic Disorder  Exclusion: schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, autism,</p>
    <p>epilepsy, personality disorder, developmental delay and traumatic brain injury</p>
    <p>Data:  366 patients with 861 physician documents</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dictionary-based Method</p>
    <p>Brute force  Positive dictionary (inclusion)  Negative dictionary (exclusion)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deep Neural Network  Training: 748 docs, 101 suitable and 657 unsuitable pts  Test: 103 docs, 25 suitable, 78 unsuitable pts  Implemented in H2O.ai R package  Two models (DL0 and DL1)  Construct an aggregate predictor (DL1+0)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Comparison</p>
    <p>Demonstrate the potential for this approach for patient recruitment purposes</p>
    <p>A larger sample size is required to build a truly reliable recommendation system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges from NLP Perspective</p>
    <p>Large and labeled datasets are not available for many NLP methods (e.g., neural network)</p>
    <p>Evaluation is still performed based on intrinsic criteria, not for a specific clinical problem  Timely detection of suicidal behavior risk</p>
    <p>Suicidal behavior is relatively rare (low precision)  Ensure an appropriate sample to provide interpretable NLP output</p>
    <p>NLP tasks are more complex  From simply NER to ascertain novel and complex entities</p>
    <p>(makers of socioeconomic status, life experience)  From single institution to a multi-site application</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Rui Zhang, Ph.D. Email: zhan1386@umn.edu</p>
    <p>Research Lab: http://ruizhang.umn.edu/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clinical Information Extraction Sunghwan Sohn, PhD Division of Digital Health Sciences, Mayo Clinic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Learning Objects</p>
    <p>Methodology review (high-level) 3) Explore clinical documentation variations and</p>
    <p>IE-based NLP tool portability  Case study of NLP tool portability (asthma</p>
    <p>ascertainment)</p>
    <p>challenges</p>
    <p>technology</p>
    <p>application</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Electronic Health Records</p>
    <p>Unstructured Data  ~80% of EHRs  Often</p>
    <p>ungrammatical/fragment of text, use of abbreviations</p>
    <p>Clinical notes, radiology reports, operation notes, etc.</p>
    <p>Structured Data</p>
    <p>Retrieve using query Extract using NLP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges of EHR  Volume</p>
    <p>Much of EHR is free text  Requires natural language processing Clinical IE</p>
    <p>Variability  Clinical practice and workflow vary across</p>
    <p>institutions  Clinical language is not homogenous Clinical documentation variation</p>
    <p>Portability  Out-of-box NLP models dont work well NLP system portability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP can facilitate the extraction and mining of text for structured information and knowledge</p>
    <p>Unstructured Text</p>
    <p>Structured Content Clinical decision</p>
    <p>support</p>
    <p>Knowledge discovery</p>
    <p>Information extraction</p>
    <p>Automated chart review</p>
    <p>Information retrieval</p>
    <p>Image courtesy of National Institutes of Health</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clinical IE - methodologies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dictionary Lookup</p>
    <p>Map medical text to the concepts in dictionary</p>
    <p>Dictionary resources  Existing: UMLS, SNOMED-CT, RxNorm,</p>
    <p>etc.  Custom-built</p>
    <p>Predefined concepts (by medical experts)  Can follow the standard when using</p>
    <p>(inter)national resources  Enable interoperability between</p>
    <p>computer systems  Tools: MetaMap, cTAKES, MedTagger,</p>
    <p>MedXN</p>
    <p>An overview of MetaMap: historical perspective and recent advances. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2010 May-Jun</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rule-based (Expert System AI)</p>
    <p>Regular expression and rules  Flexible handling string and pattern</p>
    <p>variations  Suitable to implement existing criteria, expert</p>
    <p>logics  Interpretable, customizable  Labor intensive  Tools: UIMA Ruta, MedTaggerIE</p>
    <p>Chemical threats diagnosis expert system (CTDES) in Advanced Materials Research  November 2012</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Machine Learning AI  Suitable for problems with no</p>
    <p>explicit criteria</p>
    <p>Require feature engineering  Not interpretable  Applications</p>
    <p>named entity recognition, adverse drug reaction, disease prediction, relation extraction</p>
    <p>Popular techniques:  SVM, CRF, decision tree, Nave</p>
    <p>Bayes, random forest</p>
    <p>IE architecture &amp; BIO tagging</p>
    <p>https://www.nltk.org</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deep Learning</p>
    <p>No feature engineering  Popular techniques</p>
    <p>RNN (based on LSTM), CNN  Applications</p>
    <p>named entity recognition, relation extraction</p>
    <p>DL Information extraction: Words a sequence of tokens embedding layer in RNN softmax to classify tokens entity</p>
    <p>Effective Use of Bidirectional Language Modeling for Transfer Learning in Biomedical Named Entity Recognition, arXiv:1711.07908</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deep Learning</p>
    <p>Require large training set</p>
    <p>Transfer learning to overcome the burden of large training data  use pre-train the</p>
    <p>models weights for the main task</p>
    <p>Bidirectional Recurrent Neural Networks for Medical Event Detection in Electronic Health Records, arXiv:1606.07953</p>
    <p>use language modeling (on PubMed abstracts) as a transfer learning approach to pretrain the NER models weights.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Right approach?</p>
    <p>Not about selecting fancy technology, but about understanding the strengths / weaknesses and the nature of your project.</p>
    <p>Input Output</p>
    <p>Input Rule</p>
    <p>Rule</p>
    <p>Output</p>
    <p>Rule based</p>
    <p>ML based</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Right approach? Cont.</p>
    <p>Variance (pattern)</p>
    <p>D at</p>
    <p>a (s</p>
    <p>iz e)</p>
    <p>Dict. lookup</p>
    <p>Rules</p>
    <p>Machine learning</p>
    <p>Deep learning</p>
    <p>Interpretable (outcome) C</p>
    <p>us to</p>
    <p>m iz</p>
    <p>ab le</p>
    <p>(lo gi</p>
    <p>c)</p>
    <p>Deep learning</p>
    <p>Machine learning</p>
    <p>Rules</p>
    <p>Dict. lookup</p>
    <p>Data perspective User perspective</p>
    <p>Hybrid</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clinical Documentation Variations &amp; NLP System Portability</p>
    <p>The performance of a NLP system often varies across institutions and sources of data</p>
    <p>Whenever an NLP system developed in one corpus is applied to another corpus, there are questions: How similar are these two corpora? If two corpora differ how does the</p>
    <p>difference affect the NLP system portability?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What was known/not known - NLP system portability  Known</p>
    <p>Validity of portability by comparing the system performance</p>
    <p>Lacked  A systematic analysis of the heterogeneous</p>
    <p>EHR corpus (clinical documentation variations)</p>
    <p>Here  Types of clinical documentation variations  How they affect NLP system portability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Variations of Clinical Documentation</p>
    <p>Process variation  Due to various clinical practice and workflow across</p>
    <p>institutions  Eg) data format, section, note type</p>
    <p>Syntactic (lexical) variation  Clinical language is not homogeneous  Eg) different words/concepts in cardiology,</p>
    <p>orthopedics, ophthalmology</p>
    <p>Semantic variation  Concept representation  Eg) Asthma, destructive airway disease</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Similarity Measure</p>
    <p>Create a vector space model  Calculate cosine similarity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Corpus Similarity</p>
    <p>The entire corpus of each institution was compared as a whole using  tf-idf: each corpus was represented by a</p>
    <p>normalized tfidf vector  tf-ipf: word distribution at a patient level  Topic: compare corpora by topic (LDA)</p>
    <p>The topic !&quot; for the corpus C is defined as</p>
    <p># !&quot; $ = &amp; '(*</p>
    <p># !&quot; +,,$ # +, $ = &amp; '(*</p>
    <p>#(!&quot;|+,) 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Medical Concept Similarity</p>
    <p>A vector representation of medical concepts for each corpus was created using the definition of  cfidf (concept frequency-inverse document</p>
    <p>frequency)  cfipf (concept frequency-inverse patient</p>
    <p>frequency)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Note Type Similarity</p>
    <p>Clinical documents have various note types based on the event  e.g., admission, discharge, progression</p>
    <p>Among institutions  May have different note types  Same note type may contain heterogeneous topics</p>
    <p>Compare topic distributions of note types the topic !&quot; for the clinical note type T is defined by</p>
    <p># !&quot; $ = &amp; '(*</p>
    <p>#(!&quot;|-.) 0*</p>
    <p>where 0* is the number of documents in the note type $</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study</p>
    <p>Between Mayo Clinic and Sanford Childrens Hospital (SCH)  clinical documentation variations  performance of the NLP asthma ascertainment</p>
    <p>system</p>
    <p>EHR  Birth cohort  Mayo* GE-based vs. SCH EPIC</p>
    <p>*changed to EPIC in 2018</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Similarities between Mayo and SCH</p>
    <p>Data source tf-idf tf-ipf topic</p>
    <p>Whole corpus 0.669 0.581 0.944</p>
    <p>Asthma-related concepts</p>
    <p>word-level similarity</p>
    <p>semantic similarityMessage</p>
    <p>(Word level) Even though clinicians have heterogeneous clinical language that shows up in different EHR systems,</p>
    <p>(Concept level) Clinicians share common semantics to describe asthma episodes/events</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clinical documentation variations and NLP system portability: a case study in asthma birth cohorts across institutions. J Am Med Inform Assoc. Published online November 30, 2017.</p>
    <p>A heat map of note type similarity (based on topics)</p>
    <p>Bottom: Mayo Right: SCH</p>
    <p>SCH Telephone Encounter &lt;-&gt; Mayo Test MIS, Supervisory, and Miscellaneous</p>
    <p>SCH Progress Note &lt;-&gt; Mayo Test MIS, Supervisory, and Limited Exam</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP Tool - Asthma Ascertainment</p>
    <p>Implements the predetermined asthma criteria (NLP-PAC)  based on</p>
    <p>presence/absence of asthma-related concepts</p>
    <p>Clinical documentation variations and NLP system portability: a case study in asthma birth cohorts across institutions, J Am Med Inform Assoc. Published online November 30, 2017. doi:10.1093/jamia/ocx138</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP-PAC</p>
    <p>Expert rule-based system  Implemented into the MedTaggerIE</p>
    <p>open source IE framework built under Apache UIMA</p>
    <p>mcn|ASTHMA|2004****|PhD: C1:C2|&lt;PhD&gt;docname::2011 3::Asthma::#1 Asthma&lt;C1&gt;docname::2011 2::wheezing::Brief summary of clinical history and reason for ED eval: .wheezing, respiratory distress and respiratory rate in the 90's.</p>
    <p>Application of a Natural Language Processing Algorithm to Asthma Ascertainment. An Automated Chart Review. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2017 Aug 15; 196 (4):430-437.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tokenizer</p>
    <p>POS Tagger*</p>
    <p>SentenceAnnotator</p>
    <p>SectionAnnotator</p>
    <p>InformationExtractor</p>
    <p>ChunkAnnotator*</p>
    <p>ContextAnnotator</p>
    <p>Collection Readers</p>
    <p>CAS Consumers</p>
    <p>SecTag (Denny et al)</p>
    <p>MedTagger (Torii et al)</p>
    <p>ConText (Chapman et al)</p>
    <p>OpenNLP components In cTAKES</p>
    <p>separates domain-specific NLP knowledge engineering from the generic NLP process</p>
    <p>MedTagger (Torii et al) MedTagger (Torii et al)</p>
    <p>* Indicates optional components</p>
    <p>MedTagger</p>
    <p>An information extraction framework for cohort identification using electronic health records, AMIA Summits on Translational Science, 2013</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MedTaggerIE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP-PAC portability to SCH</p>
    <p>Mayo NLP-PAC system on the SCH cohort  deal with process variations</p>
    <p>eg) sentence parsing, section segmentation</p>
    <p>refine the algorithm eg) note type to be excluded, assertion adjustment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP-PAC performance for asthma ascertainment</p>
    <p>Metrics Mayo (N=497)</p>
    <p>SCH stage 1 (prototype, N=298)</p>
    <p>SCH stage 2 (refinement, N=298)</p>
    <p>sensitivity specificity PPV NPV F-score</p>
    <p>Out-of-box Refinement</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP system portability</p>
    <p>Understand clinical documentation variations</p>
    <p>Out-of-box system produces considerably lower performance  deal with process variations to be</p>
    <p>technically operable</p>
    <p>Further refined system produced comparable performance (eg, negation sublanguage)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary Right approach of clinical IE (Volume)</p>
    <p>need to understand strengths/weaknesses and nature of the problem</p>
    <p>EHR data are different among institutions (Variability)  exist various types of clinical documentation variations</p>
    <p>Document variations play different roles in assessing the NLP system application (Portability)  Need systematic adjustments to deal with the data</p>
    <p>heterogeneity and improve performance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Patient Cohort Retrieval using Electronic Health Records</p>
    <p>Yanshan Wang Research Associate</p>
    <p>Department of Health Sciences Research Mayo Clinic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Agenda</p>
    <p>Introduction  Basic Concepts</p>
    <p>EHR, Phenotyping, Evidence-based Clinical Research, Knowledge Base, Common Data Model</p>
    <p>Patient Cohort Retrieval  NLP Approaches for Cohort Retrieval</p>
    <p>Medical Concept Embedding  Information Retrieval  Deep Patient Representation</p>
    <p>Case Study: clinical trials eligibility screening for gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction  What do we do?</p>
    <p>How can you contact me?  Email: wang.yanshan@mayo.edu  LinkedIn, Twitter (yanshan_wang) 3</p>
    <p>DA TA</p>
    <p>EHR NLP AI</p>
    <p>Computer scientist &amp; Informatician</p>
    <p>ML</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why take this tutorial?</p>
    <p>Patient cohort retrieval is still labor expensive today.  Most information is embedded in</p>
    <p>unstructured EHRs.  Natural language processing is under</p>
    <p>utilized for cohort retrieval.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Goal of this tutorial</p>
    <p>To get an understanding of basic concepts about cohort retrieval in clinical domain.  To connect NLP theory with clinical</p>
    <p>knowledge.  To get an introduction into clinical use</p>
    <p>cases of cohort retrieval.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Suggested reading</p>
    <p>Books</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Suggested reading</p>
    <p>Papers  A review of approaches to identifying patient phenotype</p>
    <p>cohorts using electronic health records. Shivade et al. 2013.  Case-based reasoning using electronic health records</p>
    <p>efficiently identifies eligible patients for clinical trials. Miotto et al. 2015.</p>
    <p>A survey of practices for the use of electronic health records to support research recruitment. Obeid et al. 2017.</p>
    <p>Clinical information extraction applications: a literature review. Wang et al. 2018</p>
    <p>Using clinical natural language processing for health outcomes research: Overview and actionable suggestions for future advances. Velupillai et al. 2018.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Concepts</p>
    <p>Electronic Health Record  Phenotyping  Evidence-based clinical research  Knowledge bases  Common Data Model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Concepts</p>
    <p>Electronic Health Record</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Concepts</p>
    <p>Phenotyping  The phenotype (as opposed to genotype, which is the set of</p>
    <p>genes in our DNA responsible for a particular trait) is the physical expression, or characteristics, of that trait.</p>
    <p>Phenotyping is the practice of developing algorithms designed to identify specific phenomic traits within an individual1.</p>
    <p>Digital phenotyping using EHRs  Traditionally, clinical studies often use self-report</p>
    <p>questionnaires or clinical staff to obtain phenotypes from patients. (slow, expensive, could not scale).</p>
    <p>EHR data come in both structured and unstructured formats, and the use of both types of information can be essential for creating accurate phenotypes2.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Concepts</p>
    <p>Phenotyping  Phenotyping is the practice of developing algorithms</p>
    <p>designed to identify specific phenomic traits within an individual1.</p>
    <p>Digital Phenotyping using EHRs  EHR data come in both structured and unstructured</p>
    <p>formats, and the use of both types of information can be essential for creating accurate phenotypes2.</p>
    <p>Source: Wei, W. Q., &amp; Denny, J. C. (2015). Extracting research-quality phenotypes from electronic health records to support precision medicine. Genome medicine, 7(1), 41.</p>
    <p>(NLP)</p>
    <p>(NLP)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evidence-based clinical research</p>
    <p>Observational studies  Types of studies in epidemiology, such as the cohort study</p>
    <p>and the case-control study.  The investigators retrospectively assess associations</p>
    <p>between the treatments given to participants and their health status.</p>
    <p>Randomized control trials  Clinical trials are prospective biomedical or behavioral</p>
    <p>research studies on human participants that are designed to answer specific questions about biomedical or behavioral interventions including new treatments, such as novel vaccines, drugs, and medical devices.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Concepts</p>
    <p>Cohort/Eligibility Criteria  Inclusion criteria  Exclusion criteria</p>
    <p>https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT03690193?cond=alzheimer%27s+disease&amp;rank=5</p>
    <p>clinicaltrials.gov</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Concepts</p>
    <p>Knowledge Bases  UMLS (Unified Medical Language System) (including the Metathesaurus,</p>
    <p>Semantic Network, the Specialist Lexicon)  Used as a knowledge base and resource for a lexicon. Metathesaurus</p>
    <p>provides the medical concept identifiers. Semantic Network specifies the semantic categories for the medical concepts.</p>
    <p>SNOMED-CT  Standardized vocabulary of clinical terminology.</p>
    <p>LOINC  Standardized vocabulary for identifying health measurements, observations,</p>
    <p>and documents.  MeSH</p>
    <p>NLM controlled vocabulary thesaurus used for indexing articles for PubMed articles.</p>
    <p>MedDRA  Terminologies specific to adverse event.</p>
    <p>RxNorm  Terminologies specific to medications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Concepts</p>
    <p>Common Data Model  Common Data Model (CDM) is a specification that</p>
    <p>describes how data from multiple sources (e.g., multiple EHR systems) can be combined. Many CDMs use a relational database.</p>
    <p>Observational Medical Outcomes Partnership (OMOP) CDM by Observational Health Data Sciences and Informatics (OHDSI)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OMOP CDM v. 5.0</p>
    <p>Source: https://www.ohdsi.org/data-standardization/the-common-data-model/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Patient Cohort Retrieval for Clinical Trials using NLP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clinical Trials Eligibility Screening and Recruitment</p>
    <p>Clinical trials recruitment  Randomized clinical trials are fundamental to the</p>
    <p>advancement of medicine. However, patient recruitment for clinical trials remains the biggest barrier to clinical and translational research.</p>
    <p>Cancer patients are eligible1</p>
    <p>Cancer patients are participate1</p>
    <p>Clinical trials fail to retain enough patients2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP for Clinical Trials Eligibility Screening</p>
    <p>Natural Language Processing</p>
    <p>All patients</p>
    <p>Eligible patients</p>
    <p>E xp</p>
    <p>ed ite</p>
    <p>p at</p>
    <p>ie nt</p>
    <p>s cr</p>
    <p>ee ni</p>
    <p>ng a</p>
    <p>nd</p>
    <p>in cr</p>
    <p>ea se</p>
    <p>p at</p>
    <p>ie nt</p>
    <p>r ec</p>
    <p>ru itm</p>
    <p>en t r</p>
    <p>at es</p>
    <p>EHR</p>
    <p>Recruit</p>
    <p>Clinical trials criteria</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP Approaches for Cohort Retrieval</p>
    <p>Medical Concept Embedding  Information Retrieval  Deep Patient Representation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Medical Concept Embedding</p>
    <p>Cohort Criteria</p>
    <p>NLP Engine</p>
    <p>EHRs</p>
    <p>Concept Concept</p>
    <p>Concept Concept</p>
    <p>Concept</p>
    <p>Concept Concept</p>
    <p>Concept Concept</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Medical Concept Embedding</p>
    <p>Cohort Criteria</p>
    <p>NLP Engine</p>
    <p>EHRs</p>
    <p>Concept Concept</p>
    <p>Concept Concept</p>
    <p>Concept</p>
    <p>Concept Concept</p>
    <p>Concept Concept</p>
    <p>Knowledge-based</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Medical Concept Extraction and Representation</p>
    <p>Luo, Zhihui, et al. &quot;Corpus-based approach to creating a semantic lexicon for clinical research eligibility criteria from UMLS.&quot; Summit on Translational Bioinformatics 2010 (2010): 26.  Weng, Chunhua, et al. &quot;EliXR: an approach</p>
    <p>to eligibility criteria extraction and representation.&quot; Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association 18.Supplement_1 (2011): i116-i124.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Semantic Lexicon Extraction</p>
    <p>UMLS-based lexicon discovery from text  Retrieved 10,000 eligibility criteria sentences from</p>
    <p>clinicaltrials.gov.</p>
    <p>Luo, Zhihui, et al. &quot;Corpus-based approach to creating a semantic lexicon for clinical research eligibility criteria from UMLS.&quot; Summit on Translational Bioinformatics 2010 (2010): 26.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Semantic Lexicon Extraction</p>
    <p>UMLS-based lexicon discovery from text  Processed the corpus to identify</p>
    <p>UMLS-recognizable semantic units</p>
    <p>that matched the medical concepts in</p>
    <p>the MRCONSO table of the</p>
    <p>Metathesaurus of UMLS.</p>
    <p>Used the Stanford tagger and the</p>
    <p>Penn Treebank tag set for part-of</p>
    <p>speech (POS) tagging. All words</p>
    <p>tagged as nouns, verbs, adjectives or</p>
    <p>adverbs were considered content</p>
    <p>words, which potentially had semantic</p>
    <p>types in the UMLS Semantic Network.</p>
    <p>Used MRSTY table of the</p>
    <p>Metathesaurus and rules to find</p>
    <p>semantic terms. Luo, Zhihui, et al. &quot;Corpus-based approach to creating a semantic lexicon for clinical research eligibility criteria from UMLS.&quot; Summit on Translational Bioinformatics 2010 (2010): 26.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Semantic Lexicon Extraction</p>
    <p>UMLS-based lexicon discovery from text  Investigated the coverage of the</p>
    <p>sample corpus provided by annotation procedure, using the Metathesaurus, Semantic Network, and preference rules.</p>
    <p>Luo, Zhihui, et al. &quot;Corpus-based approach to creating a semantic lexicon for clinical research eligibility criteria from UMLS.&quot; Summit on Translational Bioinformatics 2010 (2010): 26.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Eligibility criteria extraction and representation using CDM</p>
    <p>Kang, Tian, et al. &quot;EliIE: An open-source information extraction system for clinical trial eligibility criteria.&quot; Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association 24.6 (2017): 1062-1071.</p>
    <p>EHRs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations of Concept Embedding</p>
    <p>Accuracy of medical concept extraction  Extensive annotation efforts  Generalizability/Portability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deep Patient Representation</p>
    <p>Miotto, Riccardo, et al. &quot;Deep patient: an unsupervised representation to predict the future of patients from the electronic health records.&quot; Scientific reports 6 (2016): 26094.</p>
    <p>Rajkomar, Alvin, et al. &quot;Scalable and accurate deep learning with electronic health records.&quot; NPJ Digital Medicine 1.1 (2018): 18.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deep Patient</p>
    <p>Slide courtesy of Dr. Miotto</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide courtesy of Dr. Miotto</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide courtesy of Dr. Miotto</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide courtesy of Dr. Miotto</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deep Patient Representation for Cohort Retrieval</p>
    <p>Miotto, Riccardo, and Chunhua Weng. &quot;Case-based reasoning using electronic health records efficiently identifies eligible patients for clinical trials.&quot; Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association 22.e1 (2015): e141-e150.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Information Retrieval for Cohort Retrieval</p>
    <p>Wang et al. &quot;Test Collections for EHR-based Clinical Information Retrieval.&quot; JAMIA Open. In press.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IR Tool for Cohort Retrieval</p>
    <p>Structur ed</p>
    <p>data</p>
    <p>Unstruct ured data</p>
    <p>Collating Results</p>
    <p>User Interface (visualization, analytics, reporting, etc.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Structured EHR</p>
    <p>Structured Data</p>
    <p>Unstructured EHR</p>
    <p>Data Retrieval</p>
    <p>Unstructured Concepts</p>
    <p>Clinical Texts</p>
    <p>Data Retrieval</p>
    <p>Unstructured Query</p>
    <p>EHR CDR</p>
    <p>Full-text Query</p>
    <p>Structured Query</p>
    <p>Transform Index</p>
    <p>Structured Index</p>
    <p>Unstructured Index</p>
    <p>Parse/Edit Filtered Cohort</p>
    <p>Relevant Cohort</p>
    <p>End User</p>
    <p>NLP</p>
    <p>Structured Data Flow</p>
    <p>Unstructured Data Flow</p>
    <p>Cohort Retrieval Enhanced Analysis by Text from EHR (CREATE)</p>
    <p>ICD9/10, CPT, SNOMED CT ...</p>
    <p>&quot;Adults with inflammatory bowel disease (ulcerative colitis or Crohn's disease)&quot;</p>
    <p>Index</p>
    <p>Index</p>
    <p>Machine Learning</p>
    <p>IR for Cohort Retrieval Prototype: CREATE</p>
    <p>Liu, Sijia, et al. &quot;CREATE: Cohort Retrieval Enhanced by Analysis of Text from Electronic Health Records using OMOP Common Data Model.&quot; arXiv preprint arXiv:1901.07601 (2019).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study: clinical trials eligibility screening for gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD)</p>
    <p>Identify a cohort of patients with and without chronic reflux using the definitions spelled out below. We wish to</p>
    <p>test people with and without chronic reflux as our working hypothesis is that the prevalence of Barrett's</p>
    <p>esophagus is comparable between those with and without chronic reflux.</p>
    <p>Inclusion criteria : 1. Age greater than 50 years.</p>
    <p>could be used to define GERD broadly are chronic (&gt; 3 mo) use of a proton pump inhibitor (drug names include</p>
    <p>omeprazole, esomeprazole, pantoprazole, rabeprazole, dexlansoprazole, lansoprazole) or a H2 receptor blocker</p>
    <p>(ranitidine, famotidine, cimetidine). Prior endoscopic diagnosis of erosive esophagitis can also be used to make a diagnosis of GERD.</p>
    <p>Exclusion criteria 1. Previous history of esophageal adenocarcinoma/cancer or Barrett's esophagus, previous history of</p>
    <p>endoscopic ablation for Barrett's esophagus.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>i2b2 (informatics for integrating biology and bedside)</p>
    <p>Using ontology knowledge bases to represent EHR data.  Standardized EHR data designed for multi</p>
    <p>site research and population health research.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Criteria ICD 9 ICD 10 CPT 4 Medication Addressed by I2B2 Addressed by ACE</p>
    <p>Inclusion 1. Age greater than 50 years. Yes 2. Gastroesophageal reflux disease (any of 2.1, 2.2, 2.3)</p>
    <p>omeprazole,</p>
    <p>esomeprazole,</p>
    <p>pantoprazole,</p>
    <p>rabeprazole,</p>
    <p>dexlansoprazole,</p>
    <p>lansoprazole, ranitidine,</p>
    <p>famotidine, cimetidine</p>
    <p>(duration of use &gt;= 3</p>
    <p>months?)</p>
    <p>code for esophagitis</p>
    <p>No No</p>
    <p>Yes</p>
    <p>No Partially</p>
    <p>Yes</p>
    <p>warfarin Yes</p>
    <p>Coumadin Yes</p>
    <p>K22.711</p>
    <p>K22.719</p>
    <p>Yes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Screening patients by Inclusion criteria 1, 3, 4, 7 and all Exclusion criteria using</p>
    <p>i2b2. Get patient set A (n=31749)</p>
    <p>From patient set A, screening patients by Inclusion criteria 2.1 using i2b2. Get</p>
    <p>patient set B (n=8667)</p>
    <p>From patient set A, screening patients by Inclusion criteria 2.2 using i2b2. Get</p>
    <p>patient set C (n=1577)</p>
    <p>From patient set A, screening patients by Inclusion criteria 2.3, 5, 6 using ACE and CREATE. Get patient set D (n=230)</p>
    <p>Union patient sets B, C, and D. Get patient set E (n=9080)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clinical NLP: Challenges and Opportunities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data!!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data!!</p>
    <p>HIPPA</p>
    <p>PHI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data!!</p>
    <p>HIPPA: the Health Insurance Portability &amp; Accountability Act of 1996 public law  To ensure the privacy of Americans</p>
    <p>personal health records by protecting the security and confidentiality of health care information  an Individuals Protected Health Information (PHI).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data!!</p>
    <p>PHI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data!!</p>
    <p>Is it true?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Public Corpora</p>
    <p>Challenges Data  i2b2 NLP Challenges data  OHNLP Challenge data  TREC 2011 and 2012 Medical Records track</p>
    <p>MIMIC II  &gt; 40,000 de-identified intensive care unit stays</p>
    <p>Mtsamples  publicly available transcribed medical reports</p>
    <p>THYME corpus  de-identified clinical, pathology, and radiology</p>
    <p>records Wang, Yanshan, et al. &quot;Clinical information extraction applications: a literature review.&quot; Journal of biomedical informatics 77 (2018): 34-49.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Public Corpora</p>
    <p>Challenges Data  i2b2 NLP Challenges data  OHNLP Challenge data  TREC 2011 and 2012 Medical Records track</p>
    <p>MIMIC II  &gt; 40,000 de-identified intensive care unit stays</p>
    <p>Mtsamples  publicly available transcribed medical reports</p>
    <p>THYME corpus  de-identified clinical, pathology, and radiology</p>
    <p>records Wang, Yanshan, et al. &quot;Clinical information extraction applications: a literature review.&quot; Journal of biomedical informatics 77 (2018): 34-49.</p>
    <p>Available Under a Data Use Agreement</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interpretation of Machine/Deep Learning</p>
    <p>Why false positive?? Why false negative??</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NLP is Still Under-utilized</p>
    <p>Source: Wang, Yanshan, et al. &quot;Clinical information extraction applications: a literature review.&quot; Journal of biomedical informatics 77 (2018): 34-49.</p>
    <p>The number of natural language processing (NLP)-related articles compared to the number of electronic health record (EHR) PubMed articles from 2002 through 2015.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>Yanshan Wang  wang.yanshan@mayo.edu</p>
    <p>Ahmad P. Tafti  tafti.ahmad@mayo.edu</p>
    <p>Sunghwan Sohn  Sohn.sughwan@mayo.edu</p>
    <p>Rui Zhang  zhan1386@umn.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
