<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Self-Disclosure and Relationship Strength in Twitter Conversations</p>
    <p>JinYeong Bak, Suin Kim, Alice Oh {jy.bak, suin.kim}@kaist.ac.kr, alice.oh@kaist.edu</p>
    <p>Department of Computer Science, KAIST</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In social psychology  Degree of self-disclosure in a relationship depends on</p>
    <p>the strength of the relationship  Strategic self-disclosure can strengthen the relationship</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>I like you too!</p>
    <p>Youre my best friend!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In social psychology  Degree of self-disclosure in a relationship depends on</p>
    <p>the strength of the relationship  Strategic self-disclosure can strengthen the relationship</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Hello~</p>
    <p>Hi</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In social psychology  Degree of self-disclosure in a relationship depends on</p>
    <p>the strength of the relationship  Strategic self-disclosure can strengthen the relationship</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Im from</p>
    <p>Korea. I want to be your friend</p>
    <p>Where are you</p>
    <p>from?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hypothesis</p>
    <p>Twitter conversations also show a similar pattern  Dyads with high relationship strength show more self</p>
    <p>disclosure behavior  Dyads with low relationship strength show less self-disclosure</p>
    <p>behavior</p>
    <p>I like you too!</p>
    <p>Youre my best friend!</p>
    <p>Hello~</p>
    <p>Hi</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology  Twitter Data  131K users  2M conversations</p>
    <p>Relationship Strength  Chain frequency (CF)  Chain length (CL)</p>
    <p>Self-Disclosure  Personal information  Open communication  Profanity</p>
    <p>Analysis with Topic Models  Latent Dirichlet allocation (LDA, [Blei, JMLR 2003])  Aspect and sentiment unification model (ASUM, [Jo, WSDM 2011])</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Twitter Conversation  A Twitter conversation chain  3 or more tweets  at least one reply by each user</p>
    <p>Our Twitter conversation data  Oct 2011 to Dec 2011  131K users  2M chains  11M tweets</p>
    <p>https://twitter.com/#!/britneyspears</p>
    <p>Example of a conversation chain</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relationship Strength  Social psychology literature states relationship strength can</p>
    <p>be measured by communication frequency and length [Granovetter, 1973; Levin and Cross, 2004]</p>
    <p>CF: chain frequency  The number of conversational chains between the dyad</p>
    <p>averaged per month  CL: chain length  The length of conversational chains between the dyad</p>
    <p>averaged per month  Relationship strength  A high CF or CL for a dyad means the relationship is strong  A low CF or CL for a dyad means the relationship is weak</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Self-Disclosure  Open communication - Openness  Negative openness  Nonverbal openness  Emotional openness  Receptive openness  difficult to find in tweets  General-style openness  not clearly defined in the literature</p>
    <p>Personal Information  Personally Identifiable Information (PII)  Personally Embarrassing Information (PEI)</p>
    <p>Profanity  nigga, ass, wtf, lmao</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Negative openness</p>
    <p>Method  We use ASUM with emoticons as seed words</p>
    <p>[ Aspect and sentiment unification model for online review analysis, Jo, WSDM11]  ASUM is LDA-based joint model of topic and sentiment  ASUM takes unannotated data and classifies each sentence (tweet) as</p>
    <p>positive/negative/neutral</p>
    <p>Self-Disclosure - Openness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Self-Disclosure - Openness Nonverbal openness</p>
    <p>Method  We look for emoticons, lol, xxx  Emoticons are like facial expressions -- :) :( :P  lol (laughing out loud) and xxx (kisses) are very frequently used in a</p>
    <p>similar manner to nonverbal openness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Self-Disclosure - Openness Emotional openness</p>
    <p>Method  Look for tweets that contain common expressions of feeling words</p>
    <p>[We feel fine (Harris, J, 2009)]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Self-Disclosure  Personal Information Personally Identifiable Information (PII)</p>
    <p>Personally Embarrassing Information (PEI)</p>
    <p>Ex) name, location, email address, job, social security number</p>
    <p>Ex) clinical history, sexual life, job loss, family problem</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Self-Disclosure  Personal Information  Discover topics in each conversation  Use LDA [Blei, JMLR 2003] with  = 300  LDA outputs a topic proportion for each conversation  LDA outputs a multinomial word distribution for each topic</p>
    <p>Find related topics  Annotate conversations that best represent each topic  Use Amazon Mechanical Turk  Turkers annotated conversations for</p>
    <p>existence of PII  existence of PEI  keywords</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Self-Disclosure  Personal Information Example of PII, PEI and Profanity topics  Shown by high probability words in each topic</p>
    <p>PII 1 PII 2 PEI 1 PEI 2 PEI 3 Profanity</p>
    <p>san tonight pants teeth family nigga</p>
    <p>live time wear doctor brother lmao</p>
    <p>state tomorrow boobs dr sister shit</p>
    <p>texas good naked dentist uncle ass</p>
    <p>south ill wearing tooth cousin bitch</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>weak  strong weak  strong</p>
    <p>weak  strong weak  strong</p>
    <p>sentiment nonverbal emotional profanity PII &amp; PEI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>weak  strong</p>
    <p>weak  strong</p>
    <p>emotional PII &amp; PEI</p>
    <p>weak  strong</p>
    <p>weak  strong</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Interpretation  Emotional openness  When they are not very close, they express frequent</p>
    <p>encouragements, or polite reactions to baby or pets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Interpretation  PII  When they meet new acquaintances, they use PII to introduce</p>
    <p>themselves</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Analyzing outliers: a dyad linked weakly but shows high selfdisclosure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  Collected a large corpus of Twitter conversations  Measured relationship strength by conversation frequency</p>
    <p>and conversation length  Measured self-disclosure by  Negative, nonverbal, emotional openness  PII, PEI  Profanity</p>
    <p>Annotated PII and PEI using Mturk  Confirmed hypothesis that stronger relationships show</p>
    <p>more self-disclosure behaviors  Found some exceptions in emotional openness and PII</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>Any questions or comments?</p>
    <p>JinYeong Bak jy.bak@kaist.ac.kr</p>
    <p>Department of Computer Science, KAIST</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Backup slides</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Interpretation  Emotional openness  When they are not very close, they express frequent greetings,</p>
    <p>encouragements, or polite reactions to baby or pets</p>
    <p>Weak 1: greeting</p>
    <p>Weak 2: encourage</p>
    <p>ment</p>
    <p>Weak 3: baby/pets</p>
    <p>following ill love</p>
    <p>thanks sure thanks</p>
    <p>followers soon cute</p>
    <p>welcome better aww</p>
    <p>follow want pretty</p>
    <p>Top 3 topics in weak relationships</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future work  Relationship strength  Network distance, community, relationship duration</p>
    <p>Emotion  Suggest new semi-supervised model</p>
    <p>PII and PEI  Time, place  Structure of questions and answers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method  Self-Disclosure  Personal Information  Personally Identifiable Information(PII)</p>
    <p>Information that can be used to uniquely identify a person</p>
    <p>Personally Embarrassing Information(PEI)  Information that the damage that can be done by people that they know,</p>
    <p>the people for whom they might be embarrassed in front of [boyd, danah. 2010]</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
