<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Search-based Neural Structured Learning for Sequential Question Answering</p>
    <p>Mohit Iyyer, Wen-tau Yih, Ming-Wei Chang. ACL2017</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenging research problem</p>
    <p>Advocated in semantic parsing [Pasupat &amp; Liang 2015]</p>
    <p>But, a natural way to interact with a question answering system?</p>
    <p>Answer Highly Compositional Questions What is the power of the super hero who is from the most common</p>
    <p>home world and appeared after 2010?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Answer Sequences of Simple Questions</p>
    <p>Who are the super heroes from Earth?</p>
    <p>Who appeared after 2010?</p>
    <p>Dragonwing and Harmonia</p>
    <p>Harmonia</p>
    <p>What is her power?</p>
    <p>Elemental</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MSR SQA Dataset (aka.ms/sqa)  Sequences of questions, with annotated answers</p>
    <p>(coordinates)</p>
    <p>Our Task: Sequential Question Answering (SQA)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Start from WikiTableQuestions [Pasupat &amp; Liang 2015]  Use the same tables and same training/testing splits  Find complicated questions in WikiTableQuestions as intents</p>
    <p>Intent Sequence of simple questions  All answers to questions must be cells in the table  Final answer must be same as that of the original intent  Encourage simple questions and use of references</p>
    <p>SQA Dataset Creation (1/2)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Original Intent  What super hero from Earth appeared most recently?</p>
    <p>Sequence of simple questions 1. Who are all of the super heroes? 2. Which of them came from Earth? 3. Of those, who appeared most recently?</p>
    <p>Data statistics  2,022 intents  6,066 question sequences (3 annotators per intent)  17,533 total questions (~2.9 questions per sequence)</p>
    <p>SQA Dataset Creation (2/2)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Semantic parsing  Tables as independent single-table database  Goal: Question Structured Query (semantic parse)</p>
    <p>Solution recipe  Define the formal query (semantic parse) language  Define the states/actions &amp; action transition  Run-time: search for the best end state  Learning: reward-guided structured-output learning</p>
    <p>Approach: Dynamic Semantic Parser (DynSP)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The formal query language is independent of data  Preferably language used by external system (e.g.,</p>
    <p>DBMS, APIs)</p>
    <p>A SQL-like language (select &amp; conjunctions of conditions)</p>
    <p>Which super heroes came from Earth and first appeared after 2009? SELECT Character WHERE {Home World = Earth}</p>
    <p>{First Appeared &gt; 2009}</p>
    <p>Formal Query Language</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>State: a (partial) semantic parse  Action: add a primitive statement to a (partial)</p>
    <p>semantic parse</p>
    <p>Which super heroes came from Earth and first appeared after 2009? (1)select-column Character (2)cond-column Home World (3)op-equal Earth (4)cond-column First Appeared (5)op-gt 2009</p>
    <p>: legitimate set of actions given a state  For example, no select-column after select-column</p>
    <p>States &amp; Actions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Which super heroes came from Earth? (1)select-column Character (2)cond-column Home World (3)op-equal Earth</p>
    <p>Search</p>
    <p>0 1 2</p>
    <p>3 Select C</p>
    <p>haracter  Cond on Home World Value = Earth</p>
    <p>Select Powers</p>
    <p>1</p>
    <p>1   2</p>
    <p>2</p>
    <p>A state is essentially a sequence of actions  The goodness of a state:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Value of is determined by a neural-network model  Actions of the same type (e.g., select-column)</p>
    <p>share the same neural-network module</p>
    <p>Neural Network Modules (1/2)</p>
    <p>0 2 31Select Character Cond on Home World Value = Earth 1 2 3</p>
    <p>Which super heroes came from Earth? ,</p>
    <p>(0,1)  (1,2)  (2 ,3)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modules are selected dynamically as search progresses  Similar to [Andreas et al. 2016], but structures are not pre-determined</p>
    <p>Network design reflects the semantics of the action</p>
    <p>Neural Network Modules (2/2)</p>
    <p>Select Character</p>
    <p>Q: Which super heroes came from Earth?</p>
    <p>character</p>
    <p>Bi-LSTM Word Embedding</p>
    <p>Word Embedding initialized with GloVe</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Indirect supervision: only answers are available</p>
    <p>Algorithm (for each question):  Find the reference semantic parse that evaluates to the gold answers  Find the predicted semantic parse based on the current model  Derive loss by comparing them; update model parameters by</p>
    <p>stochastic gradient decent</p>
    <p>Reward-guided Structured Learning</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ideal case: reference parse that evaluates to the gold answers  True reward: (answers = gold answers)</p>
    <p>Beam search: find the parse with highest approximated reward  Approximated reward: (Jaccard)</p>
    <p>Find the Reference Semantic Parse</p>
    <p>Which super heroes came from Earth?, {Dragonwing, Harmonia}</p>
    <p>0 1 2</p>
    <p>3 Select C</p>
    <p>haracter  Cond on Home World Value = Earth</p>
    <p>Select Powers</p>
    <p>1</p>
    <p>1   2</p>
    <p>2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ideal case: every state satisfies the following constraint:  (: reference, : margin)</p>
    <p>Beam search: find the most violated semantic parse</p>
    <p>Find the Predicted Semantic Parse</p>
    <p>0 1 2</p>
    <p>3 Select C</p>
    <p>haracter  Cond on Home World Value = Earth</p>
    <p>Select Powers</p>
    <p>1</p>
    <p>1   2</p>
    <p>2</p>
    <p>Which super heroes came from Earth?, {Dragonwing, Harmonia}</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>For questions that are not the first in a sequence, allow a special subsequent statement  Modules of subsequent conditions consider both previous and current</p>
    <p>questions  Answers would be a subset of previous answers</p>
    <p>Which super heroes came from Earth?  Which of them breathes fire? SUBSEQUENT WHERE {Powers = Fire breath}</p>
    <p>Extension to Question Sequence</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Floating Parser (FP) [Pasupat &amp; Liang. ACL-15]  Map questions to logical forms  Feature-rich system that aims to output the correct semantic parse</p>
    <p>Neural Programmer (NP) [Neelakantan et al. ICLR-17]  Neural modules that are not tied to a specific formal language  Output a probability distribution over table cells given a question</p>
    <p>Both FP &amp; NP were designed for WikiTableQuestions  Contains more long, complicated but independent questions</p>
    <p>Related Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Answer Accuracy (%)</p>
    <p>All Sequence 0</p>
    <p>FP NP DynSP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Answer Accuracy (%)</p>
    <p>Position 1 Position 2 Position 3 0</p>
    <p>FP NP DynSP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cherry</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lemon: Semantic Matching Errors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lemon: Language Expressiveness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An end-to-end joint learning framework  Formulated as a state/action search problem  Neural networks constructed dynamically as search progresses</p>
    <p>A first step towards Conversational QA</p>
    <p>Next steps  Efficient training to test more expressive formal languages and neural</p>
    <p>network modules  External data or interactive learning for better semantic matching</p>
    <p>Reflections on DynSP</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
