<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PUBLIC</p>
    <p>Daniel Dahlmeier ACL 2017 - Vancouver</p>
    <p>On the Challenges of Translating NLP Research into Commercial Products</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Research Applied Research Engineering $$$</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Innovation = Novelty + Impact</p>
    <p>Useful</p>
    <p>Science</p>
    <p>Bohr Pasteur</p>
    <p>Edison</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lack of value focus</p>
    <p>Lack of Reproducibility</p>
    <p>Lack of (Domain) Data</p>
    <p>Overemphasis on test scores</p>
    <p>Difficulty of adoption</p>
    <p>Timelines</p>
    <p>Challenges to Innovation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lack of value focus</p>
    <p>Lack of Reproducibility</p>
    <p>Lack of (Domain) Data</p>
    <p>Overemphasis on test scores</p>
    <p>Difficulty of adoption</p>
    <p>Timelines</p>
    <p>Challenges to Innovation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From Business Problem to NLP Problem The cheat sheet</p>
    <p>What is the job?</p>
    <p>Do you need automation?</p>
    <p>Can you write the rules?</p>
    <p>Can you formulate your</p>
    <p>problem clearly?</p>
    <p>Do you have a regular pattern</p>
    <p>Do you have data?</p>
    <p>Do you have meaningful features?</p>
    <p>Can you measure success</p>
    <p>Rule-basedManual work</p>
    <p>Refine your problem</p>
    <p>Collect data Enhance data / look for different data sources</p>
    <p>Yes</p>
    <p>Yes No</p>
    <p>Yes</p>
    <p>Yes Yes</p>
    <p>No</p>
    <p>Yes</p>
    <p>No No No</p>
    <p>No</p>
    <p>NLP</p>
    <p>No Yes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SAP is hiring ML and NLP experts! Come and talk to us at the SAP booth! sap.com/ml icn.sap.com/jobs.html</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>No part of this publication may be reproduced or transmitted in any form or for any purpose without the express permission of SAP SE or an SAP affiliate company.</p>
    <p>The information contained herein may be changed without prior notice. Some software products marketed by SAP SE and its distributors contain proprietary software components of other software vendors. National product specifications may vary.</p>
    <p>These materials are provided by SAP SE or an SAP affiliate company for informational purposes only, without representation or warranty of any kind, and SAP or its affiliated companies shall not be liable for errors or omissions with respect to the materials. The only warranties for SAP or SAP affiliate company products and services are those that are set forth in the express warranty statements accompanying such products and services, if any. Nothing herein should be construed as constituting an additional warranty.</p>
    <p>In particular, SAP SE or its affiliated companies have no obligation to pursue any course of business outlined in this document or any related presentation, or to develop or release any functionality mentioned therein. This document, or any related presentation, and SAP SEs or its affiliated companies strategy and possible future developments, products, and/or platform directions and functionality are all subject to change and may be changed by SAP SE or its affiliated companies at any time for any reason without notice. The information in this document is not a commitment, promise, or legal obligation to deliver any material, code, or functionality. All forward-looking statements are subject to various risks and uncertainties that could cause actual results to differ materially from expectations. Readers are cautioned not to place undue reliance on these forward-looking statements, and they should not be relied upon in making purchasing decisions.</p>
    <p>SAP and other SAP products and services mentioned herein as well as their respective logos are trademarks or registered trademarks of SAP SE (or an SAP affiliate company) in Germany and other countries. All other product and service names mentioned are the trademarks of their respective companies. See http://global.sap.com/corporate-en/legal/copyright/index.epx for additional trademark information and notices.</p>
    <p>2017 SAP SE or an SAP affiliate company. All rights reserved.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Appendix</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SAPs vision for enterprise machine learning</p>
    <p>Create your own intelligent infrastructure</p>
    <p>SAP Cloud Platform and SAP HANA</p>
    <p>Do the ImpossibleAutomate Knowledge Work</p>
    <p>Image-based Ariba commerce  Contextual Concur travel concierge</p>
    <p>Self-driving customer service  Conversational sales bots  Customer retention insights</p>
    <p>Vision-enabled manufacturing  Contextual logistics</p>
    <p>Video-aware marketing  Visual store execution</p>
    <p>Drone and satellite-based asset management</p>
    <p>Transformational HR services</p>
    <p>Lights out finance operations</p>
    <p>SAP Leonardo Machine Learning</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Build your intelligent enterprise now SAP makes machine learning incredibly simple</p>
    <p>SAP Assets</p>
    <p>Re-imagine business processes with digital intelligence</p>
    <p>Increased customer satisfaction with superior service</p>
    <p>Increase revenue with superior sales targeting and execution</p>
    <p>Improving quality time at work for employees</p>
    <p>Enabling product, process and business model innovations</p>
    <p>Business Outcomes</p>
    <p>Training and Lifecycle</p>
    <p>management</p>
    <p>Applications/tools</p>
    <p>Business Services</p>
    <p>Functional Services</p>
    <p>SAP Cloud Platform and SAP HANA</p>
    <p>SAP Leonardo Machine Learning</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
