<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Saif M. Mohammad National Research Council Canada</p>
    <p>Saif.Mohammad@nrc-cnrc.gc.ca @SaifMMohammad</p>
    <p>Obtaining Reliable Human Ratings of Valence, Arousal, and Dominance for 20,000 English Words</p>
    <p>Obtaining Reliable Human Ratings of Valence, Arousal, and Dominance for 20,000 English Words. Saif M. Mohammad. In Proceedings of the 56th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), Melbourne, Australia, July 2018.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Core Dimensions of Meaning</p>
    <p>Influential factor analysis studies (Osgood et al., 1957; Russell, 1980, 2003) have shown that the three most important, largely independent, dimensions of word meaning:  valence (V): positive/pleasure  negative/displeasure  arousal (A): active/stimulated  sluggish/bored  dominance (D): powerful/strong  powerless/weak</p>
    <p>Thus, when comparing the meanings of two words, we can compare their V, A, D scores. For example:  banquet indicates more positiveness than funeral  nervous indicates more arousal than lazy  queen indicates more dominance than delicate</p>
    <p>valence</p>
    <p>arousal</p>
    <p>dominance</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>This work:</p>
    <p>Obtaining Reliable Human Ratings of Valence, Arousal, and Dominance for 20,000 English Words</p>
    <p>Obtaining Reliable Human Ratings of Valence, Arousal, and Dominance for 20,000 English Words. Saif M. Mohammad. In Proceedings of the 56th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), Melbourne, Australia, July 2018.</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>This work:</p>
    <p>Obtaining Reliable Human Ratings of Valence, Arousal, and Dominance for 20,000 English Words</p>
    <p>Obtaining Reliable Human Ratings of Valence, Arousal, and Dominance for 20,000 English Words. Saif M. Mohammad. In Proceedings of the 56th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), Melbourne, Australia, July 2018.</p>
    <p>fine-grained</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Human annotations of words for VAD</p>
    <p>For use by automatic systems:  predicting VAD of words  predicting sentiment and emotions of sentences, tweets, etc.  detecting stance, personality traits, well-being, cyber-bullying, etc.</p>
    <p>To draw inferences about people:  to understand how we (or different groups of people) use language to express</p>
    <p>meaning and emotions  analyze text written/spoken by different groups of people  analyze VAD judgments of different groups of people</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work: Existing VAD Lexicons</p>
    <p>Affective Norms of English Words (ANEW) (Bradley and Lang, 1999)  ~1,000 words  9-point rating scale</p>
    <p>Warriner et al. Norms (Warriner et al. 2013)  14,000 words  9-point rating scale</p>
    <p>Small number of VAD lexicons in non-English languages as well  E.g.:  Moors et al. (2013) for Dutch  Vo et al. (2009) for German  Redondo et al. (2007) for Spanish</p>
    <p>rating scale</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work: Existing VAD Lexicons</p>
    <p>Affective Norms of English Words (ANEW) (Bradley and Lang, 1999)  ~1,000 words  9-point rating scale</p>
    <p>Warriner et al. Norms (Warriner et al. 2013)  14,000 words  9-point rating scale</p>
    <p>Small number of VAD lexicons in non-English languages as well  E.g.:  Moors et al. (2013) for Dutch  Vo et al. (2009) for German  Redondo et al. (2007) for Spanish</p>
    <p>rating scale</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rating scales:</p>
    <p>source: imgur</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rating scales:</p>
    <p>source: xkcd</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rating scales:</p>
    <p>ACL-2018 Reviewing Scale</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rating scales:</p>
    <p>source: Wikimedia Commons</p>
    <p>Likert Item (Likert 1932)</p>
    <p>Note: A Likert scale is the sum of responses on several Likert items.</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problems with rating scales:</p>
    <p>fixed granularity  difficult to maintain consistency across annotators  difficult for an annotator to be self consistent  scale region bias</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparative Annotations</p>
    <p>Paired Comparisons (Thurstone, 1927; David, 1963): If X is the property of interest (positive, useful, etc.), give two terms and ask which is more X  less cognitive load  helps with consistency issues  requires a large number of annotations  order N2, where N is number of terms to be annotated</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BestWorst Scaling (BWS) (Louviere &amp; Woodworth, 1990)</p>
    <p>The annotator is presented with four words (say, A, B, C, and D) and asked:  which word is associated with the most/highest X (property of interest, say valence)  which word is associated with the least/lowest X</p>
    <p>By answering just these two questions, five out of the six inequalities are known  For e.g.:</p>
    <p>If A: highest valence  and D: lowest valence, then we know:</p>
    <p>A &gt; B, A &gt; C, A &gt; D, B &gt; D, C &gt; D</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BestWorst Scaling (Louviere &amp; Woodworth, 1990)</p>
    <p>Each of these BWS questions can be presented to multiple annotators.  We can obtain real-valued scores for all the terms using a simple counting method</p>
    <p>(Orme, 2009)</p>
    <p>score(w) = (#best(w) - #worst(w)) / #annotations(w)</p>
    <p>the scores range from: -1 (least X) X = property of interest, say valence</p>
    <p>to 1 (most X)</p>
    <p>the scores can then be used to rank all the terms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BestWorst Scaling (Louviere &amp; Woodworth, 1990)</p>
    <p>preserves the comparative nature  keeps the number of annotations down to about 2N  leads to more reliable, less biased, more discriminating annotations</p>
    <p>(Kiritchenko and Mohammad, 2017, Cohen, 2003)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Creating the Valence, Arousal, and Dominance Lexicon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Term Selection</p>
    <p>Selected:</p>
    <p>All terms in the NRC Emotion Lexicon (Mohammad and Turney, 2013): ~14,000  labels indicate association with eight basic emotions</p>
    <p>anger, anticipation, disgust, fear, joy, sadness, surprise, and trust (Plutchik, 1980)  includes terms that occur frequently in the Google n-gram corpus</p>
    <p>All terms in ANEW (Bradley and Lang, 1999): ~1000</p>
    <p>All terms in the Warriner et al. lexicon (2013): ~14,000</p>
    <p>Words from the Rogets Thesaurus categories corresponding to the eight basic Plutchik emotions: ~520</p>
    <p>High-frequency content terms, including emoticons, from the Hashtag Emotion Corpus (a tweets corpus) (Mohammad, 2012): ~1000</p>
    <p>Total: 20,007 terms</p>
    <p>We wanted to include:  commonly used English terms  terms common in tweets  terms that denotate or connotate emotions</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Best-Worst Questionnaires</p>
    <p>Q1. Which of the four words below is associated with the MOST happiness / pleasure / positiveness / satisfaction / contentedness / hopefulness OR LEAST unhappiness / annoyance / negativeness / dissatisfaction / melancholy / despair? (Four words listed as options)</p>
    <p>Q2. Which of the four words below is associated with the LEAST happiness / pleasure / positiveness / satisfaction / contentedness / hopefulness OR MOST unhappiness / annoyance / negativeness / dissatisfaction / melancholy / despair? (Four words listed as options)</p>
    <p>Similar questions for arousal and dominance</p>
    <p>This study was approved by the NRC Research Ethics Board (NRC-REB) under protocol number 2017-98. REB review seeks to ensure that research projects involving humans as participants meet Canadian standards of ethics.</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Crowdsourcing and Quality Control</p>
    <p>About 2% of the data was annotated internally beforehand (by the author)  These gold questions are interspersed with other questions  If one gets a gold question wrong, they are immediately notified of it  feedback to improve task understanding</p>
    <p>If ones accuracy on the gold questions falls below 80%,  they are refused further annotation  all of their annotations are discarded Mechanism to avoid malicious or random annotations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Valence, Arousal, and Dominance Annotations (with BWS)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Valence, Arousal, and Dominance Annotations (with BWS)</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Valence, Arousal, and Dominance Annotations (with BWS)</p>
    <p>~1000 annotators for each task</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Valence, Arousal, and Dominance Annotations (with BWS)</p>
    <p>minimum and median annotations per 4-tuple</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Valence, Arousal, and Dominance Annotations (with BWS)</p>
    <p>number of pairs of bestworst annotations</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BestWorst Scaling (Louviere &amp; Woodworth, 1990)</p>
    <p>Each of these BWS questions can be presented to multiple annotators.  We can obtain real-valued scores for all the terms using a simple counting method</p>
    <p>(Orme, 2009)</p>
    <p>score(w) = (#best(w) - #worst(w)) / #annotations(w)</p>
    <p>the scores range from: -1 (least X) X = property of interest, say valence</p>
    <p>to 1 (most X)</p>
    <p>the scores can then be used to rank all the terms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Entries in the VAD Lexicon</p>
    <p>Scores are in the range 0 (lowest V/A/D) to 1 (highest V/A/D)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reliability (Reproducibility) of Annotations</p>
    <p>Average split-half reliability (SHR): a commonly used approach to determine consistency (Kuder and Richardson, 1937; Cronbach, 1946)</p>
    <p>Pearson correlation: -1(most inversely correlated) to 1(most correlated)</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Split-Half Reliability Scores for VAD Annotations</p>
    <p>Annotations # Terms # Annotations V A D</p>
    <p>Warriner et al. (2013) 13,915 20 per term 0.91 0.79 0.77</p>
    <p>Markedly lower SHR for A and D. The dominance ratings seem especially problematic since the Warriner V-D correlation is 0.71.</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Split-Half Reliability Scores for VAD Annotations</p>
    <p>Annotations # Terms # Annotations V A D</p>
    <p>Warriner et al. (2013) 13,915 20 per term 0.91 0.79 0.77</p>
    <p>Ours (Warriner terms) 13,915 6 per tuple 0.95 0.91 0.91</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Split-Half Reliability Scores for VAD Annotations</p>
    <p>Annotations # Terms # Annotations V A D</p>
    <p>Warriner et al. (2013) 13,915 20 per term 0.91 0.79 0.77</p>
    <p>Ours (Warriner terms) 13,915 6 per tuple 0.95 0.91 0.91</p>
    <p>Ours (all terms) 20,007 6 per tuple 0.95 0.90 0.90</p>
    <p>These SHR scores show for the first time that highly reliable fine-grained ratings can be obtained for valence, arousal, and dominance. Also, our V-D correlation is 0.48.</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NRC VAD Lexicon and the Warriner et al. Lexicon: How Different are the Scores?</p>
    <p>Pearson correlations r</p>
    <p>The especially low correlations for dominance and arousal indicate that our lexicon has substantially different scores and rankings of terms.</p>
    <p>Annotations V A D</p>
    <p>Ours-Warriner (for overlapping terms)</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Create the large and reliable VAD lexicon</p>
    <p>Analyze VAD judgments of different groups of people</p>
    <p>Done:</p>
    <p>On to:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Shared Understanding of VAD: Within and Across Demographic Groups</p>
    <p>Human cognition and behaviour are impacted by evolutionary and socio-cultural factors  These factors impact different groups of people differently  Consider gender  Men, women, and other genders are substantially more alike than different  However, they have encountered different socio-cultural influences  Often these disparities have been a means to exert unequal status and asymmetric power</p>
    <p>relations  Gender studies examine</p>
    <p>both the overt and subtle impacts of these socio-cultural influences  ways to mitigate the inequity  how different genders perceive and use language</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demographic Survey</p>
    <p>Annotators could optionally respond to a separate survey asking for their demographic information:  age  gender  country  personality traits  we asked how they viewed themselves across the big five personality traits</p>
    <p>(Barrick and Mount, 1991)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment</p>
    <p>For each demographic attribute, we partitioned the annotators into two groups:  male (m) and female (f)  those 18 to 35 (35) and those over 35 (&gt;35)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment</p>
    <p>For each demographic attribute, we partitioned the annotators into two groups:  male (m) and female (f)  those 18 to 35 (young) and those over 35 (grownups)  agreeable (Ag) and Disagreeable (Di)  extrovert (Ex) and introvert (In)  and so on</p>
    <p>Calculated  the extent to which people within the same group agreed with each other on the</p>
    <p>VAD annotations  whether the differences in average agreements in each group are significant</p>
    <p>chi-square test for independence and significance level of 0.05</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Differences in Average Agreements: Gender</p>
    <p>Valence Arousal Dominance FF vs. MM</p>
    <p>F = female M = male</p>
    <p>Sub-group with Significantly Higher Agreement</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Valence Arousal Dominance FF vs. MM MM FF MM</p>
    <p>Women have a higher shared understanding of the degree of arousal of words. Men have a higher shared understanding of the dominance and valence of words.</p>
    <p>F = female M = male</p>
    <p>Differences in Average Agreements: Gender</p>
    <p>Sub-group with Significantly Higher Agreement</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Valence Arousal Dominance YY vs. GG</p>
    <p>Differences in Average Agreements: Age</p>
    <p>Y = young G = grownups</p>
    <p>Sub-group with Significantly Higher Agreement</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Valence Arousal Dominance YY vs. GG GG GG YY</p>
    <p>Y = young G = grownups</p>
    <p>Differences in Average Agreements: Age</p>
    <p>The young have a higher shared understanding of the dominance of words. The grownups have a higher shared understanding of valence and arousal of words.</p>
    <p>Sub-group with Significantly Higher Agreement</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Differences in Average Agreements: Big 5 Traits</p>
    <p>Valence Arousal Dominance AgAg vs. DiDi AgAg AgAg DiDi CoCo vs. EaEa - CoCo CoCo ExEx vs. InIn ExEx ExEx ExEx NeNe vs SeSe SeSe - SeSe OpOp vs ClCl OpOp OpOp OpOp Ag = Agreeableness (friendly and compassionate) Di = Disagreeableness (careful in whom to trust, argumentative) Co = Conscientiousness (efficient and organized) Ea = Easygoing (easy-going and carefree) Ex = Extrovert (outgoing, energetic, seek the company of others) In = Introvert (solitary, reserved, meeting many people causes anxiety) Ne = Neurotic (often feel anger, anxiety, depression, and vulnerability) Se = Secure (rarely feel anger, anxiety, depression, and vulnerability) Op = Open to experiences (inventive and curious; seek out new experiences) Cl = Closed to experiences (consistent and cautious; anxious about new experiences)</p>
    <p>Sub-group with Significantly Higher Agreement</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Create the large and reliable VAD lexicon Analyze VAD judgments of different groups of people</p>
    <p>Applications and Summary</p>
    <p>Done:</p>
    <p>On to:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Selected Applications and Future Work</p>
    <p>Source of features for systems in sentiment, emotion, and other affect-related tasks</p>
    <p>useful to create emotion-aware word embeddings and emotion-aware sentence representations</p>
    <p>Source of gold (reference) scores, to evaluate automatic methods of determining V, A, and D</p>
    <p>Study the interplay between the basic emotion model and the VAD model of emotions (Mohammad, 2018: LREC paper)  Companion lexicon: NRC Emotion Intensity Lexicon</p>
    <p>provides real-valued affect intensity scores for ~6000 words with four basic emotions (anger, fear, sadness, joy)</p>
    <p>Study the role of high VAD words in high emotion intensity sentences, tweets, snippets from literature</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Created the NRC Valence, Arousal, and Dominance Lexicon:  has entries for about 20,000 English words  has fine-grained real-valued scores for V, A, and D (core dimensions of meaning)  showed that the annotations are reliable (high split-half reliability scores)</p>
    <p>Showed that certain demographic attributes impact how we view the world around us.</p>
    <p>The VAD lexicon is useful in a wide range of applications and research projects.</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The NRC Valence, Arousal, and Dominance Lexicon provides ratings of valence, arousal, and dominance for ~20,000 English words http://saifmohammad.com/WebPages/nrc-vad.html</p>
    <p>The NRC WordEmotion Association Lexicon aka NRC Emotion Lexicon provides associations for ~14,000 words with eight emotions http://saifmohammad.com/WebPages/NRC-Emotion- Lexicon.htm</p>
    <p>The NRC Emotion Intensity Lexicon aka Affect Intensity Lexicon provides intensity scores for ~6000 words with four emotions (anger, fear, joy, sadness) http://saifmohammad.com/WebPages/AffectIntensity.htm</p>
    <p>The NRC WordColour Association Lexicon provides associations for ~14,000 words with 11 common colours http://saifmohammad.com/WebPages/lexicons.html</p>
    <p>(anger, fear, joy, sadness, anticipation, disgust, surprise, trust)</p>
    <p>@SaifMMohammad</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pictures Attribution</p>
    <p>Family by b farias from the Noun Project Shovel and Pitchfork by Symbolon from the Noun Project Checklist by Nick Bluth from the Noun Project Generation by Creative Mahira from the Noun Project Human by Adrien Coquet from the Noun Project Search by Maxim Kulikov from the Noun Project</p>
    <p>https://thenounproject.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Resources Available at: www.saifmohammad.com  NRC Valence, Arousal, and Dominance Lexicon  NRC Emotion Lexicon and Emotion Intensity Lexicon  Interactive visualizations</p>
    <p>Saif M. Mohammad Saif.Mohammad@nrc-cnrc.gc.ca @SaifMMohammad</p>
    <p>Many thanks to Svetlana Kiritchenko, Michael Wojatzki, and Norm Vinson for helpful discussions.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
