<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Generating Fine-Grained Open Vocabulary Entity Type Descriptions</p>
    <p>Rajarshi Bhowmik and Gerard de Melo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction  Knowledge Graph</p>
    <p>Vast repository of structured facts</p>
    <p>Why short textual description?  Can succinctly characterize an entity and its type</p>
    <p>Goal: Generate succinct textual description from factual data 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivating Problem</p>
    <p>Fixed inventory of ontological types (e.g. Person)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivating Problem</p>
    <p>Abstract ontological types can be misleading</p>
    <p>Missing short textual descriptions for many entities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Application: QA and IR</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More Applications: Named Entity Disambiguation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Desiderata</p>
    <p>Discerning most relevant facts  Nationality and occupation for a person</p>
    <p>E.g. Swiss tennis player, American scientist  Genre, regions and release year for a movie</p>
    <p>E.g. 1942 American comedy film</p>
    <p>Open vocabulary: applicable any kind of entity</p>
    <p>Generated text is coherent, succinct and non-redundant</p>
    <p>Sufficiently concise to be grasped at a single glance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Contributions</p>
    <p>Dynamic memory-based generative model  jointly leverages fact embeddings + context of the generated</p>
    <p>sequence</p>
    <p>Benchmark dataset  10K entities with large variety of types  Sampled from Wikidata</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Model Architecture</p>
    <p>3 key modules:  Input Module</p>
    <p>Dynamic Memory Module  Output Module</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Input Module  Input</p>
    <p>set of N facts {f1, f2, ,fN}</p>
    <p>Output  concatenation of Fact</p>
    <p>Embeddings [f1, f2, , fN]</p>
    <p>Learn Fact Embeddings using Word Embeddings + Positional Encoder</p>
    <p>Positional Encoder:</p>
    <p>!&quot;= $%&amp; ' ()  +&quot;)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dynamic Memory Module  Current context</p>
    <p>Attention weighted sum of fact embeddings</p>
    <p>!&quot; = $%&amp;' ($&quot;)*  Attentions weights</p>
    <p>depends on two factors:  How much information from</p>
    <p>a particular fact is used by the previous memory state</p>
    <p>How much information of a particular fact is invoked in the current context of the output sequence</p>
    <p>Update memory state with  current context  previous memory state  current output context 11</p>
    <p>Number of memory updates = Length of output sequence</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Output Module  Decode the current memory</p>
    <p>state to generate the next word  Decoder GRU input:</p>
    <p>current memory state mt,  previous hidden state h(t-1)</p>
    <p>previous word w(t-1)</p>
    <p>During Training: ground truth  During evaluation: predicted word</p>
    <p>Concatenate output of GRU with the current context vector ct</p>
    <p>Pass through a fully connected layer followed by a Softmax</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation: Benchmark Dataset Creation</p>
    <p>Sampled from Wikidata RDF dump and transformed to a</p>
    <p>suitable format</p>
    <p>Sampled 10K entities with a English description and at least 5</p>
    <p>facts</p>
    <p>fact = (property name , property value).</p>
    <p>Transformed into a phrasal form by concatenating the words</p>
    <p>of the property name and its value</p>
    <p>E.g. (Roger Federer, occupation, tennis player)  occupation tennis player</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation: Baselines  Fact-to-sequence Encoder-Decoder Model</p>
    <p>Sequence-to-sequence model (Sutskever et al.) is tweaked to work on the fact embeddings generated by positional encoder</p>
    <p>Fact-to-sequence Model with Attention Decoder  Decoder module uses an attention mechanism</p>
    <p>Static Memory  Ablation study : No memory update using the dynamic context of the</p>
    <p>output sequence</p>
    <p>Dynamic Memory Networks (DMN+)  Xiong et al.s model with minor modifications  A question module gets a input question such as Who is Roger</p>
    <p>Federer? or What is Star Wars?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation: Results</p>
    <p>Model B-1 B-2 B-3 B-4 ROUGE-L METEOR CIDEr Facts-to-seq 0.404 0.324 0.274 0.242 0.433 0.214 1.627</p>
    <p>Facts-to-seq w. Attention</p>
    <p>Static Memory</p>
    <p>DMN+ 0.281 0.234 0.236 0.234 0.275 0.139 0.912</p>
    <p>Our Model 0.611 0.535 0.485 0.461 0.641 0.353 3.295</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation: Examples W ikidata Item G round Truth</p>
    <p>D escription G enerated</p>
    <p>D escription</p>
    <p>M atches Q 669081 m unicipality in Austria M unicipality in Austria</p>
    <p>Q 23588047 m icrobial protein found in M ycobacterium Abscessus</p>
    <p>m icrobial protein found in M ycobacterium Abscessus</p>
    <p>M ore specific Q 1865706 footballer Finnish footballer</p>
    <p>Q 19261036 num ber natural num ber</p>
    <p>M ore general Q 7815530 South C arolina</p>
    <p>politician Am erican politician</p>
    <p>Q 4801958 2011 H indi film Indian film</p>
    <p>Sem antic drift Q 16164685 polo player w ater polo player</p>
    <p>Q 1434610 1928 film film m aker</p>
    <p>A lternative Q 7364988 D ean of York British academ ic</p>
    <p>Q 1165984 cyclist G erm an bicycle racer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation: Attention Visualization</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Short textual descriptions facilitate instantaneous grasping of key information about entities and their types</p>
    <p>Discerning crucial facts and compressing it to a succinct description</p>
    <p>Dynamic memory-based generative architecture achieves this</p>
    <p>Introduced a benchmark dataset with 10K entities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>https://github.com/kingsaint/Open-vocabulary-entity-type-description</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
