<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Identifying Transferable Information Across Domains for Cross-domain</p>
    <p>Sentiment Classification</p>
    <p>Authors: Raksha Sharma, Pushpak Bhattacharyya, Sandipan Dandapat and Himanshu Sharad Bhatt</p>
    <p>Affiliation: IIT Bombay &amp; Xerox Research Center of India</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>- Getting manually labeled data in each domain for sentiment analysis is always an expensive and a time consuming task, cross-domain sentiment analysis provides a solution.</p>
    <p>- However, polarity orientation (positive or negative) and the significance of a word to express an opinion often differ from one domain to another.</p>
    <p>Changing Significance: Entertaining, boring, one-note, etc. are significant for classification in the movie domain.</p>
    <p>Changing Polarity: Unpredictable plot of a movie //Positive sentiment</p>
    <p>Unpredictable behaviour of a machine //Negative sentiment</p>
    <p>raksha.sharma1@tcs.com 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Definition</p>
    <p>- Significant Consistent Polarity (SCP) words represent the transferable (usable) information across domains.</p>
    <p>- We present an approach based on 2 test and cosine-similarity between context vector of words to identify polarity preserving significant words across domains.</p>
    <p>- Furthermore, we show that a weighted ensemble of the classifiers enhances the cross-domain classification performance.</p>
    <p>raksha.sharma1@tcs.com 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technique: Find SCP Significant Consistent Polarity (SCP): S  T //Transferable information from the source (S) to the target (T) for cross-domain SA.</p>
    <p>S: Significant words with their polarity orientation in the labeled source domain: 2 test</p>
    <p>H0 : unpredictable has equal distribution in the positive and negative corpora Ha : unpredictable has significantly different count in either positive or negative corpus If X2 score is greater than 3.85</p>
    <p>=&gt; p-value  0.05</p>
    <p>=&gt; Probability of the observed value given null hypothesis is true is less than 0.05</p>
    <p>=&gt; Reject the Null hypothesis</p>
    <p>=&gt; unpredictable has occurred significantly more often in one of the class with a 2 score of 4.5.</p>
    <p>=&gt; CwP &gt; CwN , hence unpredictable is positiveraksha.sharma1@tcs.com 4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technique: Find SCP (2) T: Significant words with their polarity orientation in the unlabeled target domain:</p>
    <p>Significance: NormalizedCountt(Significants(w)) &gt;   Significantt(w)</p>
    <p>Polarity:</p>
    <p>Note: We construct a 100 dimensional vector for each candidate word from the unlabeled target domain data.</p>
    <p>Significant Consistent Polarity (SCP): S  T</p>
    <p>//Transferable information from the source to the target for cross-domain SA.</p>
    <p>raksha.sharma1@tcs.com 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Inferred polarity orientation in the Target Domain</p>
    <p>Word Great (Pos-pivot)</p>
    <p>Bad (Neg-pivot)</p>
    <p>Polarity</p>
    <p>Horrible 0.25 0.31 Negative</p>
    <p>Awful 0.08 0.31 Negative</p>
    <p>Terrible 0.05 0.21 Negative</p>
    <p>Fantastic 0.23 0.04 Positive</p>
    <p>Amazing 0.24 0.04 Positive</p>
    <p>Wonderful 0.25 0.01 Positive</p>
    <p>Cosine-similarity score with the Pos-pivot (great) and Neg-pivot (bad), and inferred polarity orientation of words in the movie domain.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>F-score for SCP words identification task E : Electronics B : Books K : Kitchen D : DVD SCL: Structured Correspondence Learning (Bhatt et al., 2015)</p>
    <p>Gold standard SCP words: Application of 2 test in both the domains considering target domain is also labeled gives us gold standard SCP words from the corpus. No manual annotation.</p>
    <p>Available at: http://www.cs.jhu.edu/~mdredze/datasets/sentiment/ind ex2.html</p>
    <p>Figure-1: F-score for SCP words identification task (source -&gt; target) with respect to gold standard SCP words.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Domain Adaptation Algorithm Cs(exampleDoc) = -0.07 (wrong prediction, negative) Ct(exampleDoc) = 0.33 (correct prediction, positive)</p>
    <p>Ws = 0.765 , Wt = 0.712</p>
    <p>raksha.sharma1@tcs.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cross-domain Results</p>
    <p>We obtained a strong positive correlation (r) of 0.78 between F-score (figure-1) and cross-domain accuracy (system-3).</p>
    <p>Sys1 Sys2 Sys3 Sys4 Sys5 Sys6</p>
    <p>D-&gt;B 62 64.2 67 66 76.5 78.5</p>
    <p>E-&gt;B 63 58.9 68.3 67 75.6 76.3</p>
    <p>K-&gt;B 67 68.75 67.85 69 71.2 74</p>
    <p>B-&gt;D 76 81 80.5 77 81.5 81.5</p>
    <p>E-&gt;D 68 71 77.5 71.5 74 80.4</p>
    <p>K-&gt;D 69 69 74 71 75.2 77</p>
    <p>B-&gt;E 68 66 73 69 79 81.2</p>
    <p>K-&gt;E 76 75.75 80 78 81 82</p>
    <p>K-&gt;E 76 75.75 80 78 81 82</p>
    <p>B-&gt;K 66 67.5 72 69 79.2 80.5</p>
    <p>D-&gt;K 65.76 67 71 66 80 81</p>
    <p>E-&gt;K 74.25 75 85.75 76 84 85.75</p>
    <p>System Name: Transferred Info System-1: Common-unigrams System-2: SCL (Bhatt et al, 2015) System-3: SCP System-4: System-1 + iterations System-5: System-2 + iterations System-6: System-3 + iterations</p>
    <p>raksha.sharma1@tcs.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion - Significant Consistent Polarity (SCP) words shows a strong positive correlation of 0.78 with</p>
    <p>the sentiment classification accuracy achieved in the unlabeled target domain.</p>
    <p>- Essentially, a set of less erroneous transferable features lead to a more accurate classification system in the unlabeled target domain.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
