<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All Rights Reserved  Alcatel-Lucent 2010</p>
    <p>Secure Cloud Computing with a Virtualized Network Infrastructure</p>
    <p>Fang Hao, T.V. Lakshman, Sarit Mukherjee, Haoyu Song</p>
    <p>Bell Labs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All Rights Reserved  Alcatel-Lucent 2010 2</p>
    <p>Cloud Security: All or Nothing?</p>
    <p>Max sharing, low cost  Low security</p>
    <p>No sharing, high cost  Max security</p>
    <p>Amazon EC2 Government Cloud</p>
    <p>Good enough security</p>
    <p>with low cost?</p>
    <p>Shared computing, storage, &amp; network</p>
    <p>Dedicated infrastructure, secured facility</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All Rights Reserved  Alcatel-Lucent 2010 3</p>
    <p>Secure Elastic Cloud Computing (SEC2): Design Goals</p>
    <p>Isolation: private IP address space and networks, no trespassing traffic</p>
    <p>Transparency: users dont see underlying data center infrastructure; they only see their own (logical) network</p>
    <p>Location independence: users VMs and networks can be physically allocated anywhere in data center</p>
    <p>Easy policy control: users can change policy settings for cloud resources on the fly</p>
    <p>Scalability: service scale only restricted by total among of resources available, not dependent on customer composition</p>
    <p>A few large enterprises vs. many small business or individual users</p>
    <p>Low cost: use off-the-shelf devices whenever possible</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All Rights Reserved  Alcatel-Lucent 2010 4</p>
    <p>Provide Isolation in Traditional Data Center Architecture</p>
    <p>Unique VLAN can be set up for each user  VLAN extended to</p>
    <p>hypervisors</p>
    <p>Each VLAN can have its own IP address space</p>
    <p>VLAN extended beyond L3 boundaries via VLAN trunking</p>
    <p>VM VM</p>
    <p>Access</p>
    <p>Aggregation</p>
    <p>Core</p>
    <p>VM VM VM</p>
    <p>L3</p>
    <p>L2</p>
    <p>Constraints</p>
    <p>VLAN scalability  Maximum 4K VLAN Ids &lt;&lt; number of users</p>
    <p>Per-user policy customization is difficult  E.g. port 80 traffic  firewall  NAT  load balancer host</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All Rights Reserved  Alcatel-Lucent 2010 5</p>
    <p>Secure Elastic Cloud Computing (SEC2): Main Idea</p>
    <p>Partition data center network into smaller domains  Use VLANs to isolate customers within a domain  No global VLANs  VLAN ids reused across domains</p>
    <p>Glue different edge domains together via one central domain  Special forwarding elements (FE) deployed at border of central and edge</p>
    <p>domain  Central controller (CC) stores mapping between user and their VLANs in</p>
    <p>each edge domain  Traffic between edge domains are tunneled through central domain by FEs</p>
    <p>Per-user policy control  Middleboxes attached to FEs  Policy routing enforced by FEs  CC stores per-customer policy, allow on-the-fly user configuration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All Rights Reserved  Alcatel-Lucent 2010 6</p>
    <p>SEC2 Architecture</p>
    <p>Customers within an edge domain isolated by VLANs; one VLAN per customer subnet</p>
    <p>Core domain transports packets between edge domains; No VLAN in core, flat L2 network</p>
    <p>FEs resolve addresses, enforce policies, forward packets; MAC-in-MAC tunnel between FEs across core domain</p>
    <p>CC stores address mapping, policy rules, VM locations</p>
    <p>Same customer across multiple domains see one logical network</p>
    <p>Middleboxes attached to FE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All Rights Reserved  Alcatel-Lucent 2010 7</p>
    <p>Integration with Users On-Site Network</p>
    <p>Customer site is a special edge domain</p>
    <p>User in-cloud network can be connected to its on-site network via VPN</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All Rights Reserved  Alcatel-Lucent 2010 8</p>
    <p>Data Forwarding</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All Rights Reserved  Alcatel-Lucent 2010 9</p>
    <p>Security via Isolation and Access Control</p>
    <p>Potential attack on Amazon EC2 outlined by Ristenpart et al. CCS09</p>
    <p>Key is to determine co-resident VMs by  Determine matching Dom0 IP address via traceroute  Test for small round-trip time  Check for numerically close IP addresses</p>
    <p>None of such attack works in SEC2  Traceroute is disabled between different users</p>
    <p>They dont even know others IP address</p>
    <p>All packets across different users are forced to go through FEs round-trip time wont reveal location</p>
    <p>Private IP addresses: no correlation between different users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All Rights Reserved  Alcatel-Lucent 2010 10</p>
    <p>Concluding Remarks</p>
    <p>SEC2: a step towards good enough, low cost secure cloud solutions</p>
    <p>Security via isolation and access control  Scalable: well beyond 4K limit imposed by VLAN  Low cost</p>
    <p>Allow high resource utilization  Most networking equipments are off-the-shelf, e.g., switches within both</p>
    <p>edge domains and core domain are regular L2 switches  FEs can be L2 switches enhanced with Openflow or SoftRouter</p>
    <p>like functions</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
