<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pseudo Trust: Zero-Knowledge Based Authentication in Anonymous Peer-to-Peer</p>
    <p>Protocols Li Lu, Lei Hu</p>
    <p>State Key Lab of Information Security, Graduate School of Chinese Academy of Sciences</p>
    <p>Jinsong Han, Yunhao Liu, Lionel M. Ni</p>
    <p>Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</p>
    <p>Jinpeng Huai School of Computer Science,</p>
    <p>State Key Lab of Software Developing Environment, Beihang University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Authentication</p>
    <p>To make one person trust another one. Who is talking to whom must be as valid as whom he or she claimed.</p>
    <p>Is he/she the valid person who is searching a public database? Is he/she the valid person who provide you a movie without virus? Is the collaborating company legal? Is a cheater who send you an e-mail?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>However</p>
    <p>Your machine may be accessed by a hacke r. You may receive fraudulent. advertisement via e-mail. The goal of authentication: A host will com municate with a server while he can deter mine its identity.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity or Privacy</p>
    <p>the right to be let alone: one of the rights most cherished by people. Who is talking to whom should be confidential or private in the Internet.</p>
    <p>Who is searching a public database?</p>
    <p>Which movie are you downloading?</p>
    <p>Which companies are collaborating?</p>
    <p>Who are you talking to via e-mail?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>However Your machines IP uniquely identifies you across web sites.</p>
    <p>Nothing illegal about cross-referencing.</p>
    <p>The goal of Internet anonymity: A host can communicate with a server while nobody can determine its identity</p>
    <p>www.ticket-agency.com</p>
    <p>www.insurance-advertisement.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Previous approaches: Authentication</p>
    <p>Authentication in P2P is used to help evaluating reputations of peers. To know Who want to download or searching from Whom. Indeed, current P2P trust designs are identity-based, where one peer does not trust another before knowing its identity. Not trying to protect the identitys anonymity of peers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Previous approaches: Anonymity</p>
    <p>Anonymity is the state of being indistinguishable from other members of some group. Dont know Who is Searching or Downloading What from Who m. Main goal is to hide initiators and responders re al identities, such as IP address, post address, e tc. Not trying to authenticate the validity of peers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IPD CIPC B</p>
    <p>Anonymity Examples: Mix &amp; Onion</p>
    <p>A B C D</p>
    <p>IPD</p>
    <p>IPC</p>
    <p>IPB IPD</p>
    <p>MIPC IPD M D C B</p>
    <p>IPD M D C</p>
    <p>IPC</p>
    <p>M D</p>
    <p>ABCD</p>
    <p>Public keys IP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity Example: APFS</p>
    <p>Server</p>
    <p>Client</p>
    <p>However, APFS is just for file delivery, without identity authentication.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tradeof</p>
    <p>Authentication is Identity-based  Leaking the real identity of peer, such as</p>
    <p>IP address, post address</p>
    <p>Anonymity is to hide the identity.  Vulnerable to many active attacks,</p>
    <p>especially impersonation and man-inmiddle-attack.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic goal: A New Mutual Anonymity Authentication for P2PNon ID-based authentication</p>
    <p>No need to know real identity of peer before authentication. Pseudonym-based authentication.</p>
    <p>Invulnerable to many active attacks. Impersonation Man-in-Middle-Attack Replay</p>
    <p>Lightweight: efficient pseudonym generation and authentication.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Query and Downloading in Unstructured P2P Systems Flooding based query  Reversed path based response</p>
    <p>Direct downloading</p>
    <p>Initiator Query Responder Response Downloading</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pseudonym generation</p>
    <p>),,( 21 ppIDhSeed</p>
    <p>),( nSeedhPI</p>
    <p>We use cryptographic hash function to generate pseudony m PI:</p>
    <p>Where moduli , and are two big primes.21, pp</p>
    <p>These two primes are kept as peers secrets. Due to the one-way and collision-resistant properties of hash function, a malicious peer cannot impersonate other peers pseudonym.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Design: Pseudo Trust</p>
    <p>Initiator I</p>
    <p>Tail node IT</p>
    <p>Responder R</p>
    <p>Onion Path Flooding</p>
    <p>Query q</p>
    <p>Query Sending</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Response</p>
    <p>Initiator I</p>
    <p>Responder R</p>
    <p>Query q</p>
    <p>Response; prove your pseudonym.</p>
    <p>TCP Link</p>
    <p>RT</p>
    <p>Onion Path between R and</p>
    <p>RTTail node</p>
    <p>ITTail node</p>
    <p>Onion Path between I and</p>
    <p>IT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mutual authentication</p>
    <p>Initiator I</p>
    <p>ITTail node</p>
    <p>Responder R</p>
    <p>RT</p>
    <p>Onion Path between R and</p>
    <p>RTTail node</p>
    <p>Onion Path between I and</p>
    <p>IT</p>
    <p>Authentication request</p>
    <p>Challenge messageRequest verification</p>
    <p>Proof generation</p>
    <p>Proof verification</p>
    <p>TCP Link</p>
    <p>Responder authenticates initiator.</p>
    <p>Similar procedure for Initiator authenticating responder</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Remarks on mutual authentication</p>
    <p>The zero-knowledge identification protocol is used to implement pseudonym-base authentication. Session key exchange is embedded in the mutual authentication. After authentication, initiator and responder can use the session key to protect file confidentiality and integrity. For example, using symmetric-key encryption and massage authentication code.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Several important issues</p>
    <p>Security Anonymity degree Impersonation Man-in-Middle-attack</p>
    <p>Overhead Traffic overhead Cryptographic overhead</p>
    <p>Response time of queries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Analysis</p>
    <p>Completely anonymity Resistant to impersonation and replay. Man-in-Middle attacker gets nothing from authentication Resistant to inner attacks</p>
    <p>Tail nodes are attackers. Initiator or responder is attack.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trace Driven Simulation</p>
    <p>Physic network: Gnutella Overlay network: DSS Clip2 trace In a variety of network sizes ranging from hundreds to thousands. For each simulation, we take the average r esult from 1,000 runs.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Time(seconds)</p>
    <p>A cc</p>
    <p>um ul</p>
    <p>at iv</p>
    <p>e P</p>
    <p>er ce</p>
    <p>nt ag</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>Gnutella APFS Direct Authentication PT</p>
    <p>The response time of APFS is approximately 3 times that of overt Gn utella, while PT is around 7 times that of overt Gnutella.</p>
    <p>The time consumed in anonymous paths of PT constitutes a major p art of the whole latency.</p>
    <p>The time consumption of authentication is indeed trivial.</p>
    <p>Response Time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>T ra</p>
    <p>ffi c</p>
    <p>st re</p>
    <p>tc h</p>
    <p>Search scope</p>
    <p>Traffic Overhead</p>
    <p>The figure above plots the extra traffic cost brought about by authentication procedures.</p>
    <p>Traffic stretch is defined as the traffic cost ratio between PT plus Gnutella, and Gnutella only</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prototype Implementation</p>
    <p>We implemented a prototype in our labs at the C hinese Academy of Sciences, the campus of Beih ang University and Hong Kong University of Scien ce and Technology. We test:</p>
    <p>The extra computation overhead caused by PT. Overall latency of pseudo identity authentication proce dures in the Internet environment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Number of quadratic residues</p>
    <p>T im</p>
    <p>e c</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>su m</p>
    <p>p tio</p>
    <p>n (m</p>
    <p>s) PIV 2.66G PIV 1.8G PM 1.4G PIII 450M</p>
    <p>Number of quadratic residues</p>
    <p>T im</p>
    <p>e c</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>su m</p>
    <p>p tio</p>
    <p>n (m</p>
    <p>s) PIV 2.66G PIV 1.8G PM 1.4G PIII 450M</p>
    <p>Number of quadratic residues</p>
    <p>T im</p>
    <p>e c</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>su m</p>
    <p>p tio</p>
    <p>n (m</p>
    <p>s) PIV 2.66G PIV 1.8G PM 1.4G PIII 450M</p>
    <p>Pseudonym certificate generation</p>
    <p>Computational Overhead</p>
    <p>Proof generation</p>
    <p>Verification</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>T im</p>
    <p>e c</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>su m</p>
    <p>p a</p>
    <p>tio n</p>
    <p>(m s)</p>
    <p>Number of quadratic residues</p>
    <p>length of moduli n=2048 bits length of moduli n=1024 bits</p>
    <p>T im</p>
    <p>e c</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>su m</p>
    <p>p a</p>
    <p>tio n</p>
    <p>(m s)</p>
    <p>Number of quadratic residues</p>
    <p>length of moduli n=2048 bits length of moduli n=1024 bits</p>
    <p>T im</p>
    <p>e c</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>su m</p>
    <p>p a</p>
    <p>tio n</p>
    <p>(m s)</p>
    <p>Number of quadratic residues</p>
    <p>length of moduli n=2048 bits length of moduli n=1024 bits</p>
    <p>Time Consumption in Message Transmission</p>
    <p>CAN test MAN test</p>
    <p>WAN test</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Li Lu, Lei Hu</p>
    <p>State Key Lab of Information Security, Graduate School of Chinese Academy of Sciences</p>
    <p>Jinsong Han, Yunhao Liu, Lionel M. Ni</p>
    <p>Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</p>
    <p>Jinpeng Huai</p>
    <p>School of Computer Science, State Key Lab of Software Developing Environment,</p>
    <p>Beihang University</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
