<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exemplar Encoder Decoder for Neural Conversation</p>
    <p>Generation By</p>
    <p>Gaurav Pandey, Danish Contractor, Vineet Kumar and Sachindra Joshi</p>
    <p>IBM Research AI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Generative Models for Conversations</p>
    <p>Context encoder: (1) RNN (2) hierarchical RNN  Decoder: RNN  Objective: log probability of GT response given context.  Can generate novel responses for novel contexts!!</p>
    <p>Context Context Encoder</p>
    <p>Context Embedding</p>
    <p>Decoder Response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Retrieval Models for Conversations  Retrieve a response from a nearest neighbor index constructed</p>
    <p>from the training data.  Can be used for closed domain problems.  Advantages:  Answers are grounded in the domain.  Easy to prune answers according to requirements.</p>
    <p>Disadvantage:  Can not generate novel responses.</p>
    <p>Can we use generative models to fix this?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exemplar Encoder Decoder  Build an index from all context-response pairs offline.  For each context c:  Retrieve a set of exemplar contexts and corresponding responses.</p>
    <p>Match the exemplar contexts with c and get the similarities.  Use these similarities to weigh the exemplar responses.</p>
    <p>Input Context</p>
    <p>(1), (1)</p>
    <p>(), ()</p>
    <p>(2), (2)</p>
    <p>Index Exemplar conversations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Matching Exemplar Contexts</p>
    <p>Customer : i am getting wst non-complaint for tem install Agent: okay . . let me create a ticket to l2 support team Customer : ok .</p>
    <p>Customer: hi . today i have received the wst noncompliance. Agent: i see that you have an issue with wst non complaints. Customer: its regarding the tem</p>
    <p>Customer : i received an email action required : it security noncompliance reported by wst. Agent: is this showing as wst non complaint ? Customer : yes ... seems . may i show you the mail that i received ?</p>
    <p>Customer : regarding wst non-compliant report . i am unable to install tivoli endpoint manager ( tem Agent: what is error report you get ? Customer : this one.</p>
    <p>Encoder</p>
    <p>Encoder</p>
    <p>Encoder</p>
    <p>Encoder</p>
    <p>(1)</p>
    <p>(2)</p>
    <p>(3)</p>
    <p>Normalized similarities</p>
    <p>Input Context</p>
    <p>Exemplar contexts</p>
    <p>The normalized similarities are used to weigh the exemplar responses.</p>
    <p>c</p>
    <p>(1)</p>
    <p>(2)</p>
    <p>(3)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(1)</p>
    <p>(2)</p>
    <p>()</p>
    <p>(1)</p>
    <p>(2)</p>
    <p>()</p>
    <p>= log</p>
    <p>=1</p>
    <p>() ( | ())</p>
    <p>(1)</p>
    <p>( ) D</p>
    <p>EC O</p>
    <p>D ER</p>
    <p>R ESP</p>
    <p>O N</p>
    <p>SE EN</p>
    <p>C O</p>
    <p>D ER</p>
    <p>r</p>
    <p>()</p>
    <p>()</p>
    <p>( )</p>
    <p>Exemplar Decoder</p>
    <p>(1)</p>
    <p>(2)</p>
    <p>()</p>
    <p>C O</p>
    <p>N T EX</p>
    <p>T</p>
    <p>EN C O</p>
    <p>D ER</p>
    <p>C O</p>
    <p>N T EX</p>
    <p>T</p>
    <p>EN C O</p>
    <p>D ER</p>
    <p>c</p>
    <p>Likelihood Computation</p>
    <p>Exemplar Encoder</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analyzing the Objective c r</p>
    <p>(, )</p>
    <p>log( ) = log  (,)</p>
    <p>( , ) (| )</p>
    <p>log  1</p>
    <p>( , ) ( | )</p>
    <p>Think of exemplar contexts and responses as latent variables</p>
    <p>= log  1</p>
    <p>( ()) ()</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation  Exemplar Encoder Decoder  Hierarchical Recurrent Encoder  TF-IDF for retrieving exemplar conversations</p>
    <p>Datasets used:  Ubuntu Dialogue Corpus  IBM Tech Support Dataset</p>
    <p>Comparison Metrics  Activity and Entity metrics  Embedding metrics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Activity and Entity metrics</p>
    <p>Ubuntu Dialogue Corpus</p>
    <p>For comparison, the retrieval only model has an activity F1 score of 4.23 and entity F1 score of 2.72 respectively.</p>
    <p>These metrics compare the precision, recall and F1 score of specific nouns and verbs present in the generated response as compared to the groundtruth response.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Embedding metrics  These metrics compare the word embeddings of the generated response</p>
    <p>with the words of the groundtruth response.  These metrics do not correlate with human judgements for Ubuntu</p>
    <p>Corpus1.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Generated and retrieved responses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion  A generative model that utilizes similar conversations for</p>
    <p>response generation.  Can generate novel responses while ensuring that the</p>
    <p>responses are grounded in the domain.  Incorporating retrieved conversations during generation</p>
    <p>improves performance as evident from several metrics.  The proposed idea is general and can be used for image</p>
    <p>captioning and neural machine translation.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
