<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>JOINT REASONING FOR TEMPORAL AND CAUSAL</p>
    <p>RELATIONS</p>
    <p>Qiang Ning, Zhili Feng, Hao Wu, Dan Roth</p>
    <p>University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign &amp; University of Pennsylvania</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TIME IS IMPORTANT</p>
    <p>Understanding time is key to understanding events q Timelines (in stories, clinical records), time-slot filling, Q&amp;A, common sense</p>
    <p>[June, 1989] Chris Robin lives in England and he is the person that you read about in Winnie the Pooh. As a boy, Chris lived in Cotchfield Farm. When he was three, his father wrote a poem about him. His father later wrote Winnie the Pooh in 1925. q Where did Chris Robin live?</p>
    <p>q When was Chris Robin born?  Based on text: &lt;=1922</p>
    <p>q Requires identifying relations between events, and temporal reasoning.  Temporal relation extraction</p>
    <p>q Events are associated with time intervals: !&quot;#$%#&amp; ,!()*&amp; , !&quot;#$%#+ ,!()*+ q A happens BEFORE/AFTER B; Time is often expressed implicitly q 2 explicit time expressions per 100 tokens, but 12 temporal relations</p>
    <p>poem [Chris at age 3] ,-./0</p>
    <p>Winnie the Pooh [1925](Wikipedia: 1920)</p>
    <p>Clearly, time sensitive.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EXAMPLE</p>
    <p>More than 10 people (e1: died), he said. A car (e2: exploded) Friday in the middle of a group of men playing volleyball.</p>
    <p>Temporal question: Which one happens first? q e1 appears first in text. Is it also earlier in time? q e2 was on Friday, but we dont know when e1 happened. q No explicit lexical markers, e.g., before, since, or during.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EXAMPLE: TEMPORAL DETERMINED BY CAUSAL</p>
    <p>More than 10 people (e1: died), he said. A car (e2: exploded) Friday in the middle of a group of men playing volleyball.</p>
    <p>Temporal question: Which one happens first?  Obviously, e2:exploded is the cause and e1:died is the effect.  So, e2 happens first.</p>
    <p>In this example, the temporal relation is determined by the causal relation.</p>
    <p>Note also that the lexical information is important here; its likely that explode BERORE die, irrespective of the context.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EXAMPLE: CAUSAL DETERMINED BY TEMPORAL</p>
    <p>People raged and took to the street (after) the government stifled protesters.</p>
    <p>Causal question: q Did the government stifle people because people raged?</p>
    <p>q Or, people raged because the government stifled people?</p>
    <p>q Both sound correct and we are not sure about the causality here.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EXAMPLE: CAUSAL DETERMINED BY TEMPORAL</p>
    <p>People raged and took to the street (after) the government stifled protesters.</p>
    <p>Causal question: q Did the government stifle people because people raged? q Or, people raged because the government stifled people? q Since stifled happened earlier, its obvious that the cause is stifled</p>
    <p>and the result is raged.</p>
    <p>In this example, the causal relation is determined by the temporal relation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>THIS PAPER</p>
    <p>Event relations: an essential step of event understanding, which supports applications such as story understanding/completion, summarization, and timeline construction. q [There has been a lot of work on this; see Ning et al. ACL18, presented</p>
    <p>yesterday. for a discussion of the literature and the challenges.]</p>
    <p>This paper focuses on the joint extraction of temporal and causal relations. q A temporal relation (T-Link) specifies the relation between two events</p>
    <p>along the temporal dimension.  Label set: before/after/simultaneous/</p>
    <p>q A causal relation (C-Link) specifies the [cause  effect] between two events.  Label set: causes/caused_by</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TEMPORAL AND CASUAL RELATIONS</p>
    <p>T-Link Example: John worked out after finishing his work.  C-Link Example: He was released due to lack of evidence.</p>
    <p>Temporal and causal relations interact with each other. q For example, there is also a T-Link between released and lack</p>
    <p>The decisions on the T-Link type and the C-link type depend on each other, suggesting that joint reasoning could help.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RELATED WORK</p>
    <p>Obviously, temporal and causal relations are closely related (were not the first who discovered this).</p>
    <p>NLP researchers have also started paying attention to this direction recently. q CaTeRs: Mostafazadeh et al. (2016) proposed an annotation framework,</p>
    <p>CaTeRs, which captured both temporal and causal aspects of event relations in common sense stories.</p>
    <p>q CATENA: Mirza and Tonelli (2016) proposed to extract both temporal and causal relations, but only by post-editing temporal relations based on causal predictions.</p>
    <p>q</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CONTRIBUTIONS</p>
    <p>extraction system q Enforce declarative constraints originating from the physical nature of</p>
    <p>causality</p>
    <p>with causal relations, with new temporal annotations.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TEMPORAL RELATION EXTRACTION: AN ILP APPROACH [DO ET AL. EMNLP12]</p>
    <p>Notations q --Event node set. &quot;, $,%   are events. q '  --temporal relation label q )* +, Boolean variable  is there a of relation r between &quot; -./ $? (Y/N) q 0*(+,)--score of event pair (&quot;, $) having relation '</p>
    <p>; &lt;=</p>
    <p>; &gt;</p>
    <p>?&gt; &quot;$ 4&gt;(&quot;$)</p>
    <p>@AB D-D &quot;, $,%  ,'F,'G</p>
    <p>; &gt;</p>
    <p>Uniqueness</p>
    <p>Transitivity</p>
    <p>'K--the relation dictated by 'F and 'G</p>
    <p>The sum of all softmax scores in this document</p>
    <p>Global assignment of relations:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PROPOSED JOINT APPROACH</p>
    <p>Notations q --Event node set. &quot;, $,%   are events. q '  --temporal relation label q )* +, Boolean variable  is there a of relation r between &quot; -./ $? (Y/N) q 0*(+,)--score of event pair (&quot;, $) having relation ' q 3  4--causal relation; with corresponding variables 56(+,) and 76(+,) q 89, 8: = -'&lt;max</p>
    <p>@,A CD E FE &quot;$ 9E &quot;$ + H4 H &quot;$ :H &quot;$</p>
    <p>JK3 L-L &quot;, $,%  ,'N,'O</p>
    <p>P E</p>
    <p>Cause must be before effect</p>
    <p>The causal part</p>
    <p>Global assignment of T &amp; C relations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SCORING FUNCTIONS</p>
    <p>!&quot; = $%&amp;max *</p>
    <p>+ ,-</p>
    <p>+ 0</p>
    <p>6 34 96 34</p>
    <p>Two scoring functions are needed in the objective above  :;(=&gt;)--score of event pair (3, 4) having temporal relation %  AB(=&gt;)--score of event pair (3, 4) having causal relation C</p>
    <p>Scoring functions  We use the soft-max scores from temporal/causal classifiers (or the log of the soft</p>
    <p>max scores)</p>
    <p>Choose your favorite model for the classifiers; here: sparse averaged perceptron</p>
    <p>Features for a pair of events: q POS, token distance</p>
    <p>q modal verbs in-between (i.e., will, would, can, could, may and might)</p>
    <p>q temporal connectives in-between (e.g., before, after and since)</p>
    <p>q Whether the two verbs have a common synonym from their synsets in WordNet</p>
    <p>q The head word of the preposition phrase that covers each verb</p>
    <p>Can we use more than just this local information?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BACK TO THE EXAMPLE: TEMPORAL DETERMINED BY CAUSAL</p>
    <p>More than 10 people (e1: died), he said. A car (e2: exploded) Friday in the middle of a group of men playing volleyball.</p>
    <p>Temporal question: Which one happens first?</p>
    <p>Obviously, e2:exploded is the cause and e1:died is the effect.</p>
    <p>So, e2 happens first.</p>
    <p>In this example, the temporal relation is determined by the causal relation.</p>
    <p>Note also that the lexical information is important here; its likely that explode BERORE die, irrespective of the context.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TEMPROB: PROBABILISTIC KNOWLEDGE BASE</p>
    <p>Source: New York Times 1987-2007 (#Articles~1M)</p>
    <p>Preprocessing: Semantic Role Labeling &amp; Temporal relations model</p>
    <p>Result: 51K semantic frames, 80M relations</p>
    <p>Then we simply count how many times one frame is before/after another frame, as follows. http://cogcomp.org/page/publication_view/830</p>
    <p>Frame 1 Frame 2 Before After concern protect 92% 8%</p>
    <p>conspire kill 95% 5%</p>
    <p>fight overthrow 92% 8%</p>
    <p>accuse defend 92% 8%</p>
    <p>crash die 97% 3%</p>
    <p>elect overthrow 97% 3%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SOME INTERESTING STATISTICS IN TEMPROB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SOME INTERESTING STATISTICS IN TEMPROB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SCORING FUNCTIONS: ADDITIONAL FEATURE FOR CAUSALITY</p>
    <p>!&quot; = $%&amp;max *</p>
    <p>+ ,-</p>
    <p>+ 0</p>
    <p>6 34 96 34</p>
    <p>Two scoring functions are needed in the objective above  :;(=&gt;)--score of event pair (3, 4) having temporal relation %  AB(=&gt;)--score of event pair (3, 4) having causal relation C</p>
    <p>How to obtain the scoring functions  We argue that this prior distribution based on TemProb is correlated with causal</p>
    <p>directionality, so it will be a useful feature when training AB(=&gt;).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RESULT ON TIMEBANK-DENSE</p>
    <p>TimeBank-Dense: A Benchmark Temporal Relation Dataset  The performance of temporal relation extraction:</p>
    <p>q CAEVO: the temporal system proposed along with TimeBank-Dense q CATENA: the aforementioned work post-editing temporal relations</p>
    <p>based on causal predictions, retrained on TimeBank-Dense.</p>
    <p>System P R F1 ClearTK (2013) 53 26 35 CAEVO (2014) 56 42 48 CATENA (2016) 63 27 38 Ning et al. (2017) 47 53 50 This work 46 61 52</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A NEW JOINT DATASET</p>
    <p>TimeBank-Dense has only temporal relation annotations, so in the evaluations above, we only evaluated our temporal performance.</p>
    <p>EventCausality dataset has only causal relation annotations.  To get a dataset with both temporal and causal relation</p>
    <p>annotations, we choose to augment the EventCausality dataset with temporal relations, using the annotation scheme we proposed in our paper [Ning et al., ACL18. A multi-axis annotation scheme for event temporal relation annotation.]</p>
    <p>*due to re-definition of events</p>
    <p>Doc Event T-Link C-Link TimeBank-Dense 36 1.6K 5.7K</p>
    <p>EventCausality 25 0.8K - 0.6K</p>
    <p>Our new dataset 25 1.3K 3.4K 0.2K*</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The temporal performance got strictly better in P, R, and F1.  The causal performance also got improved by a large margin.  Comparing to when gold temporal relations were used, we can</p>
    <p>see that theres still much room for causal improvement.  Comparing to when gold causal relations were used, we can see</p>
    <p>that the current joint algorithm is very close to its best.</p>
    <p>RESULT ON OUR NEW JOINT DATASET Temopral Causal</p>
    <p>P R F Acc.</p>
    <p>Temporal Scoring Fn. 67 72 69</p>
    <p>Causal Scoring Fn. - - - 71</p>
    <p>Joint Inference 69 74 71 77 Joint+Gold Temporal 100 100 100 92</p>
    <p>Joint+Gold Causal 69 74 72 100</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CONCLUSION</p>
    <p>We presented a novel joint inference framework, Temporal and Causal Reasoning (TCR) q Using an Integer Linear Programming (ILP) framework applied to the</p>
    <p>extraction problem of temporal and causal relations between events.</p>
    <p>To show the benefit of TCR, we have developed a new dataset that jointly annotates temporal and causal annotations q Showed that TCR can improve both temporal and causal components</p>
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
