<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Leveraging distributed representa0ons and lexico-syntac0c fixedness for token-level predic0on</p>
    <p>of the idioma0city of English verbnoun combina0ons</p>
    <p>Milton King and Paul Cook University of New Brunswick</p>
    <p>Fredericton, Canada</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mul0word Expressions</p>
    <p>Expressions of mul0ple words that can exhibit an idioma0c meaning  Ivory tower  Hit up  Take a walk</p>
    <p>Verb noun combina0ons  See stars  Kick the bucket</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Idioma0c vs Literal</p>
    <p>Pull plug  (I) They pulled the plug on the Department of Health funding</p>
    <p>(L) Unfortunately someone pulled the sink plug  See stars  (I) It caught him on the head and he went down seeing liAle sparkling stars</p>
    <p>(L) Its sDll dark enough to see the brightest stars</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Idiom Token Classifica0on</p>
    <p>Determine if an MWE instance is idioma0c  They pulled the plug on the project [IdiomaDc/Literal]</p>
    <p>Applica0ons  Machine transla0on</p>
    <p>Kick the bucket [mourir/frapper avec le pied]  Sentence comple0on</p>
    <p>Keegan is ready to pull the plug on [a deal / the tv]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of Approach</p>
    <p>Supervised approach  VNC token instances are represented via use of an embedding model</p>
    <p>Embedding models  Skip-thoughts  Word2vec  Siamese CBOW</p>
    <p>SVM classifier</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lexico-Syntac0c Fixedness</p>
    <p>The idioma0c meaning of an expression is typically restricted to a small number of lexico-syntac0c paVerns</p>
    <p>See star (Idioma0c)  Ac0ve voice, no determiner, plural noun</p>
    <p>See stars</p>
    <p>See star (Literal)  Ac0ve voice, determiner, singular noun</p>
    <p>See a star  Passive voice, plural noun</p>
    <p>Stars were seen 6</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PaVerns</p>
    <p>Afsaneh Fazly et al. 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Canonical Form</p>
    <p>Afsaneh Fazly et al. 2009</p>
    <p>Lexico-syntac0c paVerns that idioma0c usages tend to occur in</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Integra0ng Canonical Forms</p>
    <p>Unsupervised method used in Fazly et al. to iden0fy canonical forms</p>
    <p>One-dimensional binary vector represen0ng if the expression is in the canonical form</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VNC-Tokens Dataset Cook et al. 2008</p>
    <p>Dev  14 MWEs  Training</p>
    <p>270 Idiom  179 Literal</p>
    <p>Tes0ng  92 Idiom  53 Literal</p>
    <p>Test  14 MWEs  Training  298 Idiom  172 Literal</p>
    <p>Tes0ng  90 Idiom  53 Literal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accuracy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results per class</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Averaging word2vec embeddings outperforms all other models used</p>
    <p>Canonical form feature improves results  Future work  Unseen MWEs  Other embedding models</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you</p>
    <p>This work was financially supported by NSERC, NBIF, and University of New</p>
    <p>Brunswick</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results per class</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
