<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bidding Clubs a subset of a talk given at Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht</p>
    <p>Kevin Leyton-Brown Yoav Shoham Moshe Tennenholtz</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 2Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>What kind of intelligent system could help bidders in an auction?</p>
    <p>proxy bidders (eBay, etc.) really just transform English into 2nd-price auction</p>
    <p>automation aggregation of information from different auctions bidding advice, decision support bidding clubs</p>
    <p>instead of helping one user, help a group aggregate bidders market power unlike buyer clubs, bidders interests not aligned</p>
    <p>self-enforcing collusive agreement: increase expected utility</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 3Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Collusion Example Imagine a first-price auction with 6 bidders, 3 of whom decide to collude in advance</p>
    <p>Is there a pre-agreement that can benefit some, but penalize none?</p>
    <p>Nave proposal: each bidder submits her valuation the two low bidders drop out the bidder with the highest valuation bids lower in the main auction</p>
    <p>Bidders have an incentive to lie in the pre-auction! this is true even if the high bidder pays the other two to drop out</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 4Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Bidding Clubs * with Y. Shoham, M. Tennenholtz (EC00)</p>
    <p>Bidders: N = {1, 2, , n}: a set of bidders who will participate in an auction, A G  N: a set of bidders who are invited to participate in a pre-auction</p>
    <p>Coordinator c: Can c hold a pre-auction that will benefit some of G and penalize none?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 5Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Assumptions: Coordinator The coordinator:</p>
    <p>invites some subset of bidders to participate non-binding invitation</p>
    <p>may enforce payments from, between bidders cannot cost money to operate acts only as a representative of bidders</p>
    <p>why can it be trusted to act reliably? one way of looking at it is that c combines with A to form a new mechanism cs behavior is fully specified, common knowledge</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 6Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Assumptions: Bidders</p>
    <p>IPV model, no externalities</p>
    <p>IID from distribution F First-price auction equilibrium bid:</p>
    <p>b(F, n, v) F regular:</p>
    <p>b(F, n+1, vi) &gt; b(F, n, vi), n  2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 7Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Deviation from standard GT setting</p>
    <p>Uninvited agents are not aware of the possibility of the existence of a coordinator</p>
    <p>they believe that each bid placed corresponds to a single bidder</p>
    <p>they may be wrong about the number of bidders actually participating in auction</p>
    <p>Is this realistic? Maybe so for electronic auctions.</p>
    <p>Equilibrium concept Bayes-Nash with misconceptions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 8Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Bidding Club Protocol 1. Coordinator c invites agents from G to</p>
    <p>participate in a pre-auction 2. Bidders decide whether to accept the invitation 3. c asks agents for their valuations</p>
    <p>agents may lie!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 9Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Problem Illustration (assuming all invited bidders participate in the pre-auction)</p>
    <p>b|G|</p>
    <p>b1</p>
    <p>cs Pre-Auction</p>
    <p>Main Auction</p>
    <p>b|G|+1 bn</p>
    <p>c submits a set of bids based on bids in</p>
    <p>the pre-auction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 10Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Utility-Improving Coordinator</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 11Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Second-Price Auction: Protocol * in the spirit of Graham &amp; Marshall, 1987</p>
    <p>A utility-improving coordinator exists for second-price auctions. 1. Agents from G submit valuations to coordinator c 2. If any agent chose not to participate:</p>
    <p>submit a bid for each agent i who did elect to participate with price offer vi, and end the protocol</p>
    <p>vsec , 0) to c 6. c gives a payment of p to all agents in G</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 12Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Calculating p Assume agents truthful, participate</p>
    <p>Taking into account only n, |G|, F, it is possible for c to calculate his expected gain, g</p>
    <p>c gains whenever both the global highest and secondhighest bids are members of the bidding club</p>
    <p>Pick any s  |G|; set p = g/s On expectation c will:</p>
    <p>be budget balanced when s = |G| make a profit when s &gt; |G|</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 13Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Why this works Incentive Compatibility:</p>
    <p>With p = 0, the allocation rule and payment rule are exactly the same as in second-price auction</p>
    <p>the standard argument for incentive compatibility applies</p>
    <p>p does not depend on agents declarations, so this payment does not affect agents strategies</p>
    <p>The bidding club increases agents expected gain Exactly the same outcome as in second-price auction</p>
    <p>But: all bidders receive an additional payment of p &gt; 0 Declining participation is not informative:</p>
    <p>All bidders from G will bid their valuations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 14Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Observations</p>
    <p>The coordinators maximum loss in a given round is |G|p = |G|g/s.</p>
    <p>Since s may be arbitrarily big, maximum loss may be set arbitrarily close to 0</p>
    <p>c keeps all but an arbitrarily small fraction of g Efficiency of the auction is preserved</p>
    <p>Revenue equivalence: doesnt hold because a bidder in G who bids 0 can still gain p</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 15Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>First-Price Auction: Protocol A utility-improving coordinator exists for first-price auctions</p>
    <p>submit a bid for each agent i who did elect to participate with price offer b(F, n, vi), and end the protocol</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 16Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Calculating p Assume agents truthful, participate</p>
    <p>Taking into account only n, |G|, F, it is possible for c to calculate his expected gain, g</p>
    <p>c gains b(F, n, v1) - b(F, m, v1) whenever the globally highest bidder is a member of G</p>
    <p>Pick any s  |G|; set p = g/s as before</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 17Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Why this works Incentive Compatibility:</p>
    <p>With p = 0, the allocation rule and payment rule are exactly the same as in first-price auction</p>
    <p>c implements a revelation mechanism p does not depend on agents declarations, so this payment does not affect agents strategies</p>
    <p>The bidding club increases agents expected gain Exactly the same outcome as in first-price auction</p>
    <p>But: all bidders receive an additional payment of p &gt; 0 Declining participation is not informative:</p>
    <p>Every agent in G will follow the equilibrium strategy</p>
    <p>The bidding club benefits agents outside G their equilibrium bids are reduced</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht 18Friday, July 13, 2001</p>
    <p>Other bidding club protocols</p>
    <p>Ive described: Second-Price (/Japanese) First-price (/Dutch)</p>
    <p>Other protocols: General mechanisms</p>
    <p>with valuations drawn from a finite set</p>
    <p>N parallel 2nd-price auctions for substitute goods Two parallel auctions for complementary goods</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
