<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pos t</p>
    <p>Lun ch</p>
    <p>Sess ion</p>
    <p>Cooperative Strategies and Optimal Scheduling for Tree Networks</p>
    <p>Alexandre de Baynast, Omer Gurewitz, Edward W. Knightly</p>
    <p>RWTH Aachen, Germany Rice University, Houston, TX</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>To develop and analyze a low-complexity cooperative protocol for wireless tree networks that significantly increases the average throughput for any user independently of its position in the tree.</p>
    <p>Objective</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Network approach In a conventional multi-hop routing, each node relays (forwards) its neighbors traffic in addition to its own traffic</p>
    <p>In an upstream traffic each node forwards its successors (childrens) traffic along with its own traffic to its predecessor (parent in the tree(</p>
    <p>e.g.,</p>
    <p>N. Ben Salem and J.P. Hubaux, A Fair Scheduling for Wireless Mesh Networks, Proceedings of WiMesh 2005</p>
    <p>C. Jaeweon and Z.J. Haas, On the throughput enhancement of the downstream channel in cellular radio networks through multihop relaying, IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications, 2004</p>
    <p>S D</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Information Theory approach Each node broadcasts its traffic, any other node collects the data from all transmissions, decodes it and</p>
    <p>rebroadcasts it (decodes and forwards(.</p>
    <p>e.g., P. Gupta and P.R. Kumar, Towards an information theory of large networks: an achievable rate region&quot;, IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, 2003</p>
    <p>S D</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Solution</p>
    <p>Cheap cooperative strategy When node S is transmitting, nodes R1 AND R2 are listening though R1 only can decode the message. In order to exploit the overheard information, our protocol is designed such that R1 transmits only some extra information to help R2 to decode the message.</p>
    <p>At least 50% throughput gain!</p>
    <p>S R1 DR2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Model</p>
    <p>Network Model</p>
    <p>m-ary Regular Tree Topology  Single Gateway  L Layers  S-TDMA (block synchronization)  All nodes are fully backlogged</p>
    <p>Interference Model  Spatial Reuse Factor F  Collision Free</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Model</p>
    <p>Physical Model</p>
    <p>Half Duplex (Single Radio)  Fix Channel Gain for all links  No sample synchronization  No multi-user detection</p>
    <p>-8</p>
    <p>-6</p>
    <p>-4</p>
    <p>-2</p>
    <p>Normalized distance (hops)</p>
    <p>R e</p>
    <p>c e</p>
    <p>iv e</p>
    <p>d S</p>
    <p>N R</p>
    <p>( d</p>
    <p>B )</p>
    <p>Decode threshold</p>
    <p>Interference threshold OSI Model L 2-3</p>
    <p>L 1</p>
    <p>Channel attenuation vs. distance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow Achievable Rate</p>
    <p>A flow achievable rate is measured by the rate granted to the flow on its bottleneck link</p>
    <p>jik ji i,jt</p>
    <p>k CtR</p>
    <p>k ji</p>
    <p>,,minmax ,</p>
    <p>S D2.01, St</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow Achievable Rate</p>
    <p>A flow achievable rate is measured by the rate granted to the flow on its bottleneck link</p>
    <p>jik ji i,jt</p>
    <p>k CtR</p>
    <p>k ji</p>
    <p>,,minmax ,</p>
    <p>S</p>
    <p>D1.01, St 1.04,3 t</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Achievable Rate vs Fairness</p>
    <p>The achievable rate is determined by the flow that gets the lowest rate</p>
    <p>s kRR</p>
    <p>NkSs minmax</p>
    <p>,,2,1</p>
    <p>S S</p>
    <p>S</p>
    <p>D</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Parking Lot (m=1): Non Cooperative Case</p>
    <p>Achievable Rate:</p>
    <p>)( 1</p>
    <p>)(2 ,,1 PC</p>
    <p>FNFNF</p>
    <p>PC NFR</p>
    <p>Pd</p>
    <p>P PCSingle Link Capacity:</p>
    <p>F hops apart = optimal spatial reuse</p>
    <p>First F=4 layers fully utilized = Optimal Schedule</p>
    <p>FN time slots</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Parking Lot (m=1): Optimal Power Allocation</p>
    <p>For a given fixed total power P, higher rate can be achieved if the closer nodes transmit with higher power than the farther nodes</p>
    <p>Achievable Rate:     )(1,,,1 PC FN</p>
    <p>NFR</p>
    <p>Gain &lt; 25% for any chain</p>
    <p>size</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Parking Lot (m=1): Cooperative Case</p>
    <p>-2 0 2 4 6 8 10 12 14 -5</p>
    <p>-2 0 2 4 6 8 10 12 14 -5</p>
    <p>RELA Y (TR</p>
    <p>P RELA</p>
    <p>Y (TR P</p>
    <p>((</p>
    <p>=rate of two-hop link / rate of one-hop link &lt; 1</p>
    <p>F-1</p>
    <p>F</p>
    <p>F-1 F+1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Turbo Relay Protocol (TRP) ~ Hop by Hop</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TRP vs. Conventional Hop by Hop RelayingTRP vs. Conventional Hop by Hop Relaying</p>
    <p>TRP</p>
    <p>Parking Lot (m=1): Cooperative Case</p>
    <p>Achievable Rate:</p>
    <p>)( 1</p>
    <p>NF NFR</p>
    <p>At least 50% throughput gain</p>
    <p>with TRP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>m-ary Tree (m&gt;1): Cooperative Case</p>
    <p>)(</p>
    <p>FN NFmR</p>
    <p>)( 12/</p>
    <p>FN NFmR</p>
    <p>TRP</p>
    <p>Hop-by-Hop</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>m-ary Tree (m&gt;1): Cooperative Case</p>
    <p>TRP vs. Conventional Hop by Hop RelayingTRP vs. Conventional Hop by Hop Relaying</p>
    <p>SNR (dB)</p>
    <p>T h</p>
    <p>ro u</p>
    <p>g hp</p>
    <p>u t g</p>
    <p>ai n</p>
    <p>( %</p>
    <p>)</p>
    <p>m=5 m=4 m=3 m=2</p>
    <p>Pathloss exponent = 2; Spatial Reuse = 5</p>
    <p>throughput gain &gt; 90%</p>
    <p>throughput gain &gt; 60%</p>
    <p>100% throughput</p>
    <p>gain with TRP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>We proposed the Turbo-Relaying Protocol (TRP) to increase each nodes throughput of upstream transmission in tree topologies. We showed that our approach can achieve up to 100% throughput gain over the basic multihop hop-by-hop transmission, for any regular tree with any connectivity degree.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Turbo Relay Protocol (TRP) ~ Hop by Hop</p>
    <p>In turbocharged engines, the combustion air is already precompressed before being supplied to the engine. The engine aspirates the same volume of air, but due to the higher pressure, more air mass is supplied into the combustion chamber. Consequently, more fuel can be burnt, so that the engines power output increases related to the same speed and swept volume</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
