<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MINING MULTI-FACETED OVERVIEWS OF ARBITRARY TOPICS IN A TEXT COLLECTION</p>
    <p>Xu Ling, Qiaozhu Mei, ChengXiang Zhai, Bruce Schatz</p>
    <p>Presented by: Qiaozhu Mei, UIUC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>The common task: mining and extracting information from a text collection with ad hoc information needs  Structured, faceted summarization  Clustering search results  Integrating expert/customer reviews  Semi-structured summarization of scientific</p>
    <p>literatures  Etc. etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multifaceted Text Overview</p>
    <p>Even if relevant information is found:</p>
    <p>Too much information  103 research papers  104 customer</p>
    <p>reviews  105 web search</p>
    <p>results</p>
    <p>Facet2: Design</p>
    <p>Facet 1: Price</p>
    <p>Facet3: Driving experience</p>
    <p>- A multifaceted overview</p>
    <p>Sentence 1,  Sentence 2,   Sentence k,</p>
    <p>price 0.4 finance 0.3 cheap 0.05 interest 0.05</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multi-Faceted Overview Mining  Unsupervised</p>
    <p>A topic clustering problem  Limitations:</p>
    <p>Topics do not necessarily reflect users preferences  Summarizing a topic cluster is still challenging</p>
    <p>Supervised  A categorization problem with training examples  Limitations:</p>
    <p>Predefined facets, may not fit the need of a particular user</p>
    <p>Only works for a predefined domain and topics  Training examples for each facet are often unavailable</p>
    <p>What is missing here?</p>
    <p>User interactions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More Realistic New Setup</p>
    <p>Allow a user to flexibly describe each facet with keywords (1-2)  Let the user determine what they want</p>
    <p>Mine a multi-faceted overview in a semisupervised way  No need of training examples  Technical challenge: how to cast it as a</p>
    <p>semi-supervised learning problem</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example (1): Consumer vs. Editor Facets Generated Overview (10k</p>
    <p>customer rev.) Editor's Review (1)</p>
    <p>Body Styles, Exterior Design</p>
    <p>Like the minor exterior styling changes from 2005 to 2006. Tried the Camry XLE first, nice ride, but lacked a few features i wanted, like dual zone A/C, and didn't like the wood trim.</p>
    <p>... Available trim levels include ... The VP provides air conditioning, power windows ...</p>
    <p>Powertrai ns</p>
    <p>Safety</p>
    <p>Interior Design</p>
    <p>The interior is beautiful - I got all of the features and the navigation is extremely easy to use. Accord's interior is top notch, nice design, clear gauges, comfy seats, lots of storage space</p>
    <p>The seating arrangements are topnotch, and the interior design and materials quality continue the high-caliber standards ... The car's backseat is among the roomiest in the segment...</p>
    <p>Driving Impressio ns</p>
    <p>Honda accord 2006</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example (2): Different Facets</p>
    <p>Facet s</p>
    <p>User Input</p>
    <p>Generated Overview</p>
    <p>Design design, style</p>
    <p>Like the minor exterior styling changes from 2005 to 2006. Accord's interior is top notch, nice design, clear gauges, comfy seats, lots of storage space</p>
    <p>Engine engine, fuel</p>
    <p>Financ e</p>
    <p>finance, price</p>
    <p>When I bought it I was amazed at the trim level for the price. It is extremely fun to drive, fit and finish is fantastic, the oversteer could easily be corrected, at the price, it has no peer and is 10k less then a comparable BMW</p>
    <p>Safety safety</p>
    <p>Drivin g</p>
    <p>comfort, fun</p>
    <p>What if the users want an overview with different facets?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Approach</p>
    <p>Two-stage framework, using probabilistic topic models  Model each facet with a language model (word distribution)  Facet model initialization</p>
    <p>bootstrapping method to expand the original facet keywords with additional correlated words in the document collection</p>
    <p>Facet model estimation: to guide a generative topic model with user defined facets  Propose probabilistic mixture models to estimate the word</p>
    <p>distribution of every facet  Meanwhile, constraining a facet model to be close to the user</p>
    <p>specification</p>
    <p>Generate the overview: apply the estimated facet models to categorize the sentences into a semistructured overviews</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bootstrapped facet model initialization</p>
    <p>design feature</p>
    <p>fun</p>
    <p>drive</p>
    <p>comforta ble</p>
    <p>price</p>
    <p>horsepowe r</p>
    <p>smooth</p>
    <p>performanc e</p>
    <p>fuel</p>
    <p>safety</p>
    <p>reliability</p>
    <p>exteri or</p>
    <p>roof</p>
    <p>seat</p>
    <p>cheap</p>
    <p>engine performance 0.5 fuel 0.5</p>
    <p>performance 0.4 fuel 0.3 horsepower 0.05 engine 0.03 smooth 0.03</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>d w j</p>
    <p>d jj</p>
    <p>j jdwzdwc</p>
    <p>jdwzdwcwp wp</p>
    <p>'</p>
    <p>),,'(),'(</p>
    <p>),,(),()|( )|(</p>
    <p>Semi-supervised facet model estimation</p>
    <p>Guide facet model estimation with Dirichlet Priors</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>Dirichlet prior, can be interpreted as pseudo word counts - Initialized distr.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Semi-supervised facet model estimation</p>
    <p>Guide facet model estimation with Regularization</p>
    <p>the log likelihood of the text collection</p>
    <p>propagates the constraint through the entire collection according to document similarities</p>
    <p>Constrains the estimated facet models to close to the initial facet models</p>
    <p>)()()()1(),( TTT CRCRCLCCO</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
    <p>The gene summarization task in biomedical literature</p>
    <p>The car review mining task</p>
    <p>for online customer reviews</p>
    <p>Our proposed system, especially the regularized Topic model, is quite effective in mining multifaceted overviews</p>
    <p>Facets Prior Reg MQR SI 0.44 0.45 0.47 GI 0.51 0.47 0.41 GP 0.20 0.22 0.20 EL 0.22 0.25 0.18 MP 0.25 0.25 0.20 WFPI 0.09 0.19 0.15 Avg. 0.29 0.31 0.27</p>
    <p>Facets Prior Reg MQR BS 0.193 0.200 0.174</p>
    <p>PP 0.273 0.278 0.207 SF 0.235 0.243 0.208</p>
    <p>IF 0.309 0.324 0.294 DI 0.316 0.319 0.264 Avg. 0.265 0.273 0.229</p>
    <p>ROUGE-1 Average R scores</p>
    <p>Precision @5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>- Please stop by our poster on Tuesday</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
