<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Price of The Price of UncertaintyUncertainty</p>
    <p>Maria-Florina Balcan Georgia Tech Avrim Blum Carnegie Mellon</p>
    <p>Yishay Mansour Tel-Aviv/Google</p>
    <p>ACM-EC 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Games are an abstractionGames are an abstraction Costs/payoffs are a function of players</p>
    <p>actions. No external influences  If all repeatedly play same way, get exact</p>
    <p>same payoff</p>
    <p>Assume all players incentives are modeled</p>
    <p>High-level question: What happens to natural dynamics if these dont quite hold?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Wed like to think that if we get people into a good equilibrium, and players are selfish, reasonably myopic, etc, then behavior will stay there.</p>
    <p>High-level question: What happens to natural dynamics if these dont quite hold?</p>
    <p>Games are an abstractionGames are an abstraction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Wed like to think that if we get people into a good equilibrium, and players are selfish, reasonably myopic, etc, then behavior will stay there.</p>
    <p>But what if there are small fluctuations in underlying cost/payoff structure?</p>
    <p>Games are an abstractionGames are an abstraction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Wed like to think that if we get people into a good equilibrium, and players are selfish, reasonably myopic, etc, then behavior will stay there.</p>
    <p>But what if there are small fluctuations in underlying cost/payoff structure?</p>
    <p>Or a few players acting unpredictably?</p>
    <p>Can small fluctuations or a few unpredictable players cause natural dynamics to spin out of control and get system into a high-cost state?</p>
    <p>Games are an abstractionGames are an abstraction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>High-level questionHigh-level question</p>
    <p>A few ways this could happen:  Small changes cause good equilibria to disappear,</p>
    <p>only bad ones left. (economy?)  Bad behavior by a few players causes pain for all</p>
    <p>(nukes)  Neither of above, but instead through more subtle</p>
    <p>interaction with dynamics</p>
    <p>Focus here on this last issue.</p>
    <p>Can small fluctuations or a few unpredictable players cause natural dynamics to spin out of control and get system into a high-cost state?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Focus of this workFocus of this work Games with the following properties:  Potential games, best/better-response</p>
    <p>dynamics.  Low Price of Stability. (good equilibria exist)</p>
    <p>Game has good equilibria even after perturbation.</p>
    <p>Small gap between potential and social cost.  Single perturbation cant make</p>
    <p>dynamics do bad things.</p>
    <p>No individual player can influence cost of others by too much.</p>
    <p>OPT</p>
    <p>PoS  OPT</p>
    <p>cost</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ModelModel  Players follow best (or better) response</p>
    <p>dynamics.  Costs of resources can fluctuate between</p>
    <p>moves: cit 2 [ci/(1+), ci(1+)]</p>
    <p>(alternatively, one or more Byzantine players who move between time steps)</p>
    <p>Play begins in a low-cost state.  How bad can things get?</p>
    <p>Price-of-Uncertainty() of game = maximum ratio of eventual social cost to initial cost.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ModelModel  Players follow best (or better) response</p>
    <p>dynamics.  Costs of resources can fluctuate between</p>
    <p>moves: cit 2 [ci/(1+), ci(1+)]</p>
    <p>Price-of-Uncertainty() of game = maximum ratio of eventual social cost to initial cost.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ModelModel  Players follow best (or better) response dynamics.  Costs of resources can fluctuate between moves: cit 2</p>
    <p>[ci/(1+), ci(1+)]</p>
    <p>Price-of-Uncertainty() of game = maximum ratio of eventual social cost to initial cost.</p>
    <p>One way to look at this:  Define graph: one node for each state. Edge u ! v if</p>
    <p>perturbation can cause BR to move from u to v.  What do the reachable sets</p>
    <p>look like?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Set-cover gamesSet-cover games  n players (points)  m sets, with costs c1,,cm.</p>
    <p>Each player chooses some set that covers it.  Players split cost with all others choosing same</p>
    <p>set. c1 c2 c3 cm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Set-cover gamesSet-cover games  Price of anarchy = n</p>
    <p>Price of stability = O(log(n)).  Potential  2 [cost, costlog(n)]</p>
    <p>n- 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main resultsMain results Set-cover games:Set-cover games:  If  = O(1/nm) then PoU = O(log n).  However, for any constant  &gt; 0, PoU = (n).  Also, a single Byzantine player can take state</p>
    <p>from a PNE of cost O(OPT) to one of cost (n OPT).</p>
    <p>Upper bounds hold even for better-response</p>
    <p>Lower bounds hold even for best-response</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main resultsMain results General fair-cost-sharing games:General fair-cost-sharing games:</p>
    <p>Matroid congestion games:Matroid congestion games:  Here, better-response is easy to lure astray.</p>
    <p>Can make state exponentially worse by using even an exponentially-small .</p>
    <p>So, focus on best-response.</p>
    <p>s t</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Main resultsMain results General fair-cost-sharing games:General fair-cost-sharing games:  If many players for each (si,ti) pair (ni = (m)),</p>
    <p>then PoU = O(1) even for constant  &gt;0.  Open for general number of players.</p>
    <p>Matroid congestion games: Matroid congestion games: (strategy sets are bases of matroid. E.g., set-cover where must choose k sets)</p>
    <p>If  = O(1/nm) then PoU = O(log n) for fair costsharing.</p>
    <p>In general, if  = O(1/nm) then PoU = O(GAP).  Better-response not enough.</p>
    <p>Also positive results for Also positive results for -nice games, bounds for -nice games, bounds for consensus, job schedulingconsensus, job scheduling</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Set-Cover games Set-Cover games (lower bound)(lower bound) Two kinds of players:  n of Class I:</p>
    <p>n-1 of Class II:</p>
    <p>Plus one Byzantine player  Implies bound for case that costs can fluctuate</p>
    <p>by factor of 2. More complicated ex for !1/n1/2.</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>n- n- n- n- n-</p>
    <p>n/2 n/3 n/4  n/n</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Set-Cover games Set-Cover games (upper bound)(upper bound) For upper bound, think of players in</p>
    <p>sets as a stack of chips.  View ith position in stack j as having</p>
    <p>cost cj/i. Load chips with value equal to initial cost.</p>
    <p>When player moves from j to k, move top chip. Cost of position goes up by at most (1+)2.</p>
    <p>cj ck</p>
    <p>At most mn different positions. So, following the path of any chip and removing loops, cost of final set is at most (1+)2nm times its value.</p>
    <p>So, if  = O(1/nm) then PoU = O(log n).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Matroid gamesMatroid games In matroid games, can think of each player</p>
    <p>as controlling a set of chips.</p>
    <p>Nice property of best response in matroids:  Can always order the move so that each</p>
    <p>individual chip is doing better-response.  Apply previous argument.  Fails for better-response.</p>
    <p>Here, can get player to do kind of binary counting, bad even for exponentiallysmall .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fair cost sharing in general graphsFair cost sharing in general graphs If many players of each type, can also show best</p>
    <p>response dynamics cant do badly.</p>
    <p>Outline of argument:  Hard to analyze cost of state directly, instead</p>
    <p>track upper bound c*(St) = cost(S0 [  [ St).</p>
    <p>c* changes at most m times.</p>
    <p>Many players of each type ) average cost of each is low compared to c* ) each change to c* is small.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PoU versus Price of AnarchyPoU versus Price of Anarchy Main focus: games with both good and bad</p>
    <p>equilibria.  Can small fluctuations or single Byzantine</p>
    <p>player cause behavior to move from good to bad?</p>
    <p>Can also have cases where state can get worse even than worst equilibrium.</p>
    <p>Market-sharing: 2 vs log(n) even for bestresponse.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PoU versus Price of AnarchyPoU versus Price of Anarchy nice games [AAEMS-EC08] : incentives grow</p>
    <p>stronger as cost gets above  times optimal (typically  = PoA).</p>
    <p>Here, at least can show state wont get above O() times optimal, even with substantial perturbation or many Byzantine players (random order).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary and open problemsSummary and open problems Looking at: when can small perturbations or a few</p>
    <p>bad players lead natural dynamics astray?  When is it safe to turn your back?</p>
    <p>Upper/lower bounds for a number of classes of games.</p>
    <p>Open problems:  Close gap for set-cover [1/(mn), 1/n1/2].  General case of fair cost-sharing games?  Cyclic order best resp</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
