<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Topic-Sentiment Mixture: Modeling Facets and Opinions</p>
    <p>in Weblogs</p>
    <p>Qiaozhu Mei, Xu Ling, Matthew Wondra, Hang Su, and ChengXiang Zhai</p>
    <p>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign  Yahoo! Inc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Opinion Analysis?</p>
    <p>Customers: need peer opinions to make purchase decisions</p>
    <p>Business providers:  need customers opinions to improve product  need to track opinions to make marketing decisions</p>
    <p>Social researchers: want to know peoples reactions about social events</p>
    <p>Government: wants to know peoples reactions to a new policy</p>
    <p>Psychology, education, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Illustrative Example</p>
    <p>Should I buy an iPod?</p>
    <p>Thumb up or thumb down?</p>
    <p>Positive, negative, neutral (Sentiments)</p>
    <p>Are their opinions changing?</p>
    <p>Negative before 2005, but positive</p>
    <p>recently (Dynamics)</p>
    <p>What do people say about ipod?</p>
    <p>Price, battery, warranty, nano,  (Topics)  What aspects are good/bad?</p>
    <p>Sound is good, battery is bad..</p>
    <p>(Faceted opinions)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Extracting Opinions from Blogs?</p>
    <p>Easy to collect: huge amount, clean format</p>
    <p>Broadly distributed: demographics  Topic diversified: free discussion about any</p>
    <p>topic/product/event</p>
    <p>Opinion rich: highly personalized</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evidence from Blog Search</p>
    <p>availability</p>
    <p>Broad distribution Positive: the trail leads to fascinating places that are richly</p>
    <p>Negative: when I first watched the big-screen version of The Da Vinci Code, I fell asleep twice. Not once. Twice!</p>
    <p>Opinion rich</p>
    <p>Topic diversity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Existing Blog-opinion Analysis Work</p>
    <p>Opinmind: sentiment classification/search of blogs</p>
    <p>No faceted analysis, no neutral fact description: Not informative enough to support decision making</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Existing Blog-opinion Analysis Work (Cont.)</p>
    <p>Use content to predict sales  Blog level topic analysis</p>
    <p>Information Diffusion through blogspace</p>
    <p>Use topic bursting to predict sales spikes</p>
    <p>E.g., [Gruhl et al. 2005]</p>
    <p>No sentiment analysis, no faceted analysis: what if the hot discussion is Negative?</p>
    <p>Hot criticisms may not lead to sales spikes</p>
    <p>[from Gruhl et al. 2005]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Whats Missing Here?</p>
    <p>Discussions are faceted  E.g. iPod: battery? Price? Nano?   Usually different opinions on different facets</p>
    <p>Opinions have polarities  Positive, negative, and neutral</p>
    <p>Non-discriminative analysis may lead to wrong decision</p>
    <p>Opinions are changing over time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Goal</p>
    <p>Model the mixture of facets and opinions (topics and sentiments)</p>
    <p>Generate a faceted opinion summarization for ad hoc query</p>
    <p>Track the change of opinions over time</p>
    <p>time</p>
    <p>strength Positive Negative</p>
    <p>Topic-sentiment dynamics (Topic = Price)</p>
    <p>Neutral</p>
    <p>Query: Dell Laptop</p>
    <p>Topic-sentiment summary</p>
    <p>positive negative</p>
    <p>Topic 2 (Battery)</p>
    <p>Topic 1 (Price)</p>
    <p>neutral</p>
    <p>my Dell battery sucks</p>
    <p>Stupid Dell laptop battery</p>
    <p>One thing I really like about this Dell battery is the Express Charge feature.</p>
    <p>i still want a free battery from dell..</p>
    <p>it is the best site and they show Dell coupon code as early as possible</p>
    <p>Even though Dell's price is cheaper, we still don't want it.</p>
    <p>mac pro vs. dell precision: a price comparis..</p>
    <p>DELL is trading at $24.66</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges in Opinion Analysis from Blogs</p>
    <p>Topics and sentiments are mixed together</p>
    <p>No existing facet structure for ad hoc topics  Difficult to identify sentiment polarities</p>
    <p>Difficult to associate sentiment polarities with facets</p>
    <p>Difficult to segment topics and sentiments  Tracking sentiment dynamics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach: Modeling TopicSentiment Mixture</p>
    <p>Use language models to represent facets and sentiments  Facets represented with topic models, extracted in an</p>
    <p>unsupervised/semi-supervised way</p>
    <p>Sentiment models extracted in a supervised way</p>
    <p>Model the mixture of topics and sentiments with a probabilistic generative model</p>
    <p>Segment associated topics and sentiments with a topical hidden Markov model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Probabilistic Model of Topic-Sentiment Mixture</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>1</p>
    <p>2</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>Facet 1</p>
    <p>Facet k</p>
    <p>Facet 2</p>
    <p>Background B</p>
    <p>Choose a facet (subtopic) i</p>
    <p>battery 0.3 life 0.2..</p>
    <p>nano 0.1 release 0.05 screen 0.02 ..</p>
    <p>apple 0.2 microsoft 0.1 compete 0.05 ..</p>
    <p>Is 0.05 the 0.04 a 0.03 ..</p>
    <p>love 0.2 awesome 0.05 good 0.01 ..</p>
    <p>suck 0.07 hate 0.06 stupid 0.02 ..</p>
    <p>P N</p>
    <p>P</p>
    <p>F</p>
    <p>N</p>
    <p>P</p>
    <p>F</p>
    <p>N</p>
    <p>P</p>
    <p>F</p>
    <p>N</p>
    <p>battery</p>
    <p>love</p>
    <p>hate</p>
    <p>the</p>
    <p>Draw a word from the mixture of topics and sentiments ( )F P N</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>p ic</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>The Generation Process</p>
    <p>1</p>
    <p>2</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>d1</p>
    <p>d2</p>
    <p>dk</p>
    <p>2, d, F</p>
    <p>k, d, F</p>
    <p>1, d, F</p>
    <p>j, d, N</p>
    <p>j, d, P</p>
    <p>1</p>
    <p>2</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>P</p>
    <p>N</p>
    <p>N e</p>
    <p>u tra</p>
    <p>l, F a</p>
    <p>cts P</p>
    <p>o s itiv</p>
    <p>e N</p>
    <p>e g</p>
    <p>a tiv</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>w</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>))]|()|()|((</p>
    <p>)1(</p>
    <p>)|(log[),()log(</p>
    <p>,,,,,,</p>
    <p>NNdjPPdjjFdj</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>j djB</p>
    <p>B Cd Vw</p>
    <p>wpwpwp</p>
    <p>BwpdwcC</p>
    <p>p(w| i ) p(w| T )</p>
    <p>p(w|i), p(w| p), p(w| N) c an be estimated with Maxi mum Likelihood Estimator (MLE) through an EM algo rithm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Learning Sentiment Models</p>
    <p>Problem: Sentiment expressions are topic-biased  E.g., fearful is negative in general , but how about for a</p>
    <p>ghost movie?  E.g., heavy is positive for rock music, but how about for</p>
    <p>laptops?</p>
    <p>Impossible to create training data for every ad hoc topic</p>
    <p>Solution:  Collect sentiment labeled data with diversified topics  Learn a general sentiment model from the mixed training data in training</p>
    <p>mode  Use this general sentiment model as prior, get the topic-biased</p>
    <p>sentiment models in testing mode</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Estimating Topic Models</p>
    <p>Problem: no existing facet structure for ad hoc topics</p>
    <p>Unsupervised extraction: facets might not be what you like  E.g., user wants battery, price and sound quality  System returns ipod nano, ipod video, ipod</p>
    <p>shuffle..  Solution: Incorporate user specified interests into</p>
    <p>automatically extracted facets  User provides hints; add priors into the topic model  Using MAP estimation instead of MLE  See paper for technical details</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sentiment Segmentation and Dynamics Tracking</p>
    <p>Design a topic-sentiment enhanced HMM</p>
    <p>Associate states with topic/sentiment models</p>
    <p>Learn the transition prob. and segment the text</p>
    <p>Plot the sentiment dynamics by counting segments over time ( tagged with each facet and sentiment)</p>
    <p>E</p>
    <p>T3T2</p>
    <p>1</p>
    <p>P N</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>T1</p>
    <p>From and to E</p>
    <p>the battery really sucks and it's really heavy in my part but where could you find laptops so affordable nowadays?...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment Setup  Training data for sentiment models (diversified topics,</p>
    <p>downloaded from Opinmind)</p>
    <p>Test dataset: created by querying Google blog search and crawling from original sites (ad hoc)</p>
    <p>Datasets # docs Time Period Query Term</p>
    <p>iPod 2988 01/06 ~ 11/06 ipod</p>
    <p>Da Vinci Code 1000 01/06 ~ 10/06 da+vinci+code</p>
    <p>Topic # Pos # Neg Topic # Pos # Neg</p>
    <p>laptops 346 142 people 441 475</p>
    <p>movies 396 398 banks 292 229</p>
    <p>universities 464 414 insurances 354 297</p>
    <p>airlines 283 400 nba teams 262 191</p>
    <p>cities 500 500 cars 399 334</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: General Sentiment Models  Sentiment models trained from diversified topic mixture</p>
    <p>v.s. single topics Pos-Cities Neg-Cities Pos-Mix Neg-Mix</p>
    <p>beautiful hate love suck</p>
    <p>love suck awesome hate</p>
    <p>awesome people good stupid</p>
    <p>amaze traffic miss ass</p>
    <p>live drive amaze fuck</p>
    <p>good fuck pretty horrible</p>
    <p>night stink job shitty</p>
    <p>nice move god crappy</p>
    <p>time weather yeah terrible</p>
    <p>air city bless people</p>
    <p>greatest transport excellent evil</p>
    <p># topic mixture in training data</p>
    <p>KL Divergence between learnt</p>
    <p>p and N and unseen topic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Facets and Topic Models (I)</p>
    <p>Facets for iPod :</p>
    <p>No Prior With Prior</p>
    <p>Battery, nano Marketing Ads, spam Nano Battery</p>
    <p>battery apple free nano battery</p>
    <p>shuffle microsoft sign color shuffle</p>
    <p>charge market offer thin charge</p>
    <p>nano zune freepay hold usb</p>
    <p>dock device complete model hour</p>
    <p>itune company virus 4gb mini</p>
    <p>usb consumer freeipod dock life</p>
    <p>hour sale trial inch rechargable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Facets and Topic Models (II)</p>
    <p>Facets for the Da Vinci Code</p>
    <p>No Prior With Prior</p>
    <p>Story Book Background Movie Religion</p>
    <p>landon author jesus movie religion</p>
    <p>secret idea mary hank belief</p>
    <p>murder holy gospel tom cardinal</p>
    <p>louvre court magdalene film fashion</p>
    <p>thrill brown testament watch conflict</p>
    <p>clue blood gnostic howard metaphor</p>
    <p>neveu copyright constantine ron complaint</p>
    <p>curator publish bible actor communism</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Faceted Opinions (the Da Vinci Code)</p>
    <p>Neutral Positive Negative</p>
    <p>Facet 1: Movie</p>
    <p>... Ron Howards selection of Tom Hanks to play Robert Langdon.</p>
    <p>Tom Hanks stars in the movie,who can be mad at that?</p>
    <p>But the movie might get delayed, and even killed off if he loses.</p>
    <p>Directed by: Ron Howard Writing credits: Akiva Goldsman ...</p>
    <p>Tom Hanks, who is my favorite movie star act the leading role.</p>
    <p>protesting ... will lose your faith by ... watching the movie.</p>
    <p>After watching the movie I went online and some research on ...</p>
    <p>Anybody is interested i n it?</p>
    <p>... so sick of people making such a big deal about a FICTION book and movie.</p>
    <p>Facet 2: Book</p>
    <p>I remembered when i first read the book, I finished the book in two days.</p>
    <p>Awesome book. ... so sick of people making such a big deal about a FICTION book and movie.</p>
    <p>Im reading Da Vinci Code now.</p>
    <p>So still a good book to past time.</p>
    <p>This controversy book cause lots conflict in west society.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Comparison with Opinmind</p>
    <p>Faceted opinions from TSM Facets Thumbs Up Thumbs Down</p>
    <p>iPod Nano (sweat) iPod Nano ok so ... Ipod Nano is a cool design, ...</p>
    <p>WHAT IS THIS SHIT??!! ipod nanos are TOO small!!!!</p>
    <p>Battery the battery is one serious example of excellent relibability</p>
    <p>Poor battery life ... ...iPods battery completely died</p>
    <p>iPod Video My new VIDEO ipod arrived!!! Oh yeah! New iPod video</p>
    <p>fake video ipod Watch video podcasts ...</p>
    <p>Opinions from Opinmind:</p>
    <p>Thumbs Up Thumbs Down</p>
    <p>I love my iPod, I love my G5... I hate ipod.</p>
    <p>I love my little black 60GB iPod Stupid ipod out of batteries...</p>
    <p>I LOVE MY iPOD  hate ipod  = 489..</p>
    <p>I love my iPod. my iPod looked uglier...surface...</p>
    <p>- I love my iPod. i hate my ipod.</p>
    <p>... iPod video looks SO awesome ... microsoft ... the iPod sucks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Sentiment Dynamics</p>
    <p>Facet: the book  the da vinci code. ( Bursts during the movie, Pos &gt; Neg )</p>
    <p>Facet: the impact on religious beliefs. ( Bursts during the movie, Neg &gt; Pos )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary and Future Work</p>
    <p>Algorithm: A new way to model the mixture of topics and sentiments</p>
    <p>Application: A new way to summarize faceted opinions, and track their dynamics</p>
    <p>Future Work:  Beyond unigram language model?</p>
    <p>Better segmentation of sentiments and topics?</p>
    <p>Adapting existing facet structures?</p>
    <p>Develop an end user application for opinion analysis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
