<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Time-dependent Similarity Time-dependent Similarity Measure of Queries Using Measure of Queries Using</p>
    <p>Historical Click-through DataHistorical Click-through Data</p>
    <p>Time-dependent Similarity Time-dependent Similarity Measure of Queries Using Measure of Queries Using</p>
    <p>Historical Click-through DataHistorical Click-through Data</p>
    <p>Qiankun Zhao*, Steven C. H. Hoi*, Tie-Yan Liu, et al.</p>
    <p>Presented by: Tie-Yan Liu</p>
    <p>* This work was done when Zhao and Hoi were interns at Microsoft Research Asia</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OutlineOutline</p>
    <p>Background  Observations and Motivation  Our approach  Empirical study  Future work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BackgroundBackground</p>
    <p>A dilemma for Web search engines  Very short queries ~2.5  Inconsistency of term usages</p>
    <p>The Web is not well-organized  Users express queries with their own</p>
    <p>vocabulary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background (contd)Background (contd)</p>
    <p>Solution: query expansion  Document term based expansion (KDD00,</p>
    <p>SIGIR05)  a query can be expanded with top keywords in the</p>
    <p>top-k relevant documents</p>
    <p>Query term based expansion (WWW02, CIKM04)  a query can be expanded with similar queries (queries</p>
    <p>are similar if they lead to similar pages, pages are similar if they are visited by issuing similar queries)</p>
    <p>Click-though data were used for query expansion in many previous work.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background (contd)Background (contd)</p>
    <p>Click-through data  Log data about the interactions between users</p>
    <p>and Web search engines</p>
    <p>Typical Click-through data representation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(month)</p>
    <p>Observation 1Observation 1</p>
    <p>Accuracy of query similarity</p>
    <p>Calculated only from the clickthrough data in that time interval.</p>
    <p>Calculated from all the clickthrough data before that time point</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Observation 2Observation 2</p>
    <p>Event driven and dynamic character of query similarity</p>
    <p>the keyword firework and related pages are becoming more popular one week before the</p>
    <p>event and reach the peak on July 4th</p>
    <p>firework + injuries&quot; and firework + picture have a little delay in terms of the number</p>
    <p>of times being issued and visited.</p>
    <p>firework + injuries&quot; and firework + picture have a little delay in terms of the number</p>
    <p>of times being issued and visited.</p>
    <p>firework + market&quot; and firework + show&quot; become</p>
    <p>popular and reach their peaks a few days before</p>
    <p>July 4th</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MotivationsMotivations</p>
    <p>Exploit the click-through data for semantic similarity of queries by incorporating temporal information</p>
    <p>To combine explicit content similarity and implicit semantic similarity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our ApproachOur Approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Time-Dependent Concepts Time-Dependent Concepts</p>
    <p>Calendar schema and pattern</p>
    <p>Example  Calendar schema &lt;day, month, year&gt;  Calendar pattern &lt;15, *,*&gt;  &lt;15, 1, 2002&gt; is contained in the pattern &lt;15, *,*&gt;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Time-Dependent ConceptsTime-Dependent Concepts</p>
    <p>Click-Through Subgroup</p>
    <p>Example  Based on the schema &lt;day, week&gt;, and the pattern</p>
    <p>&lt;1,*&gt;, &lt;2,*&gt;,,&lt;7,*&gt;, we can partition the data into 7 groups, which correspond to Sun, Mon, Tue, , Sat.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Similarity MeasureSimilarity Measure  For efficiency and simplicity, we measure the query similarity in a</p>
    <p>certain time slot only based on the click-through data.  Vector representation of queries with respect to clicked docu</p>
    <p>ments.</p>
    <p>wi is defined by Page Frequency (PF) and Inverted Query Frequ ency (IQF)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Similarity MeasureSimilarity Measure  Query similarity measures</p>
    <p>Cosine function  Marginalized kernel</p>
    <p>By introducing query clusters, one can model the query si milarity in a more semantic way.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Time-Dependent Similarity Measure Time-Dependent Similarity Measure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Empirical EvaluationEmpirical Evaluation</p>
    <p>Dataset  Click-through log of a commercial search engine:</p>
    <p>June 16, 2005 to July 17,2005  Total size of 22GB  Only queries from US</p>
    <p>Calendar schema and pattern  &lt;hour, day, month&gt;, &lt;1, *, *&gt;, &lt;2, *, *&gt;,   Divide the data into 24 subgroups  Average subgroup size: 59,400,000 query-page pairs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Empirical ExamplesEmpirical Examples</p>
    <p>Kids+toy, map+route</p>
    <p>Time-dependent daily similarityIncremented daily similarity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Empirical ExamplesEmpirical Examples</p>
    <p>weather + forecast, fox + news</p>
    <p>Time-dependent daily similarityIncremented daily similarity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quality EvaluationQuality Evaluation</p>
    <p>Experimental Settings  Partition 32-day dataset into two parts</p>
    <p>First part for model construction  Second part for model evaluation</p>
    <p>Accuracy is defined as the percentage of difference between the a ctual similarity and the model-based prediction</p>
    <p>1000 representative query pairs, similarity larger than 0.3 using t he entire dataset</p>
    <p>Half of them are top queries of the month  Half are selected manually related to real world events such as hurri</p>
    <p>cane.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental ResultsExperimental Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental ResultsExperimental Results</p>
    <p>Here distance is the time difference between the first test data record and the last m odel construction data record. For example, when the distance is 1 and the training data size is 10, we summarize all the accuracy values that use the I to 10+i days as training and use the 10+1+i as testing.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental ResultsExperimental Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ConclusionConclusion</p>
    <p>Presented a preliminary study of the dynamic nature of query similarity using click-through data</p>
    <p>Observed and verified that query similarity are dynamic and event driven with real data</p>
    <p>Proposed an time-dependent model  For our future work, we will investigate an</p>
    <p>adaptive way to determine the most suitable time granularity for two given queries.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks!Thanks!</p>
    <p>tyliu@microsoft.com http://research.microsoft.com/users/t yliu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
