<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hierarchical Indexing and Flexible Element Retrieval for Structured Document</p>
    <p>Hang Cui School of Computing, NUS</p>
    <p>Ji-Rong Wen Microsoft Research Asia</p>
    <p>Tat-Seng Chua School of Computing, NUS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivations and problems</p>
    <p>Hierarchical index propagation and pruning</p>
    <p>Flexible element retrieval</p>
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivations and problems</p>
    <p>Hierarchical index propagation and pruning</p>
    <p>Flexible element retrieval</p>
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Motivations  More structured and semi-structured documents</p>
    <p>on the Web.  Users want to explore more of the document</p>
    <p>structure.  Access only relevant parts of a document, i.e. sections</p>
    <p>or paragraphs</p>
    <p>IR cant help  Document as the smallest resulting unit.</p>
    <p>Not Question Answering!  Cant provide views of the internal document structure.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Encarta Articles  An Example  Online encyclopedia.</p>
    <p>Well structured XML documents.</p>
    <p>Nodes (elements)  documents, sections and paragraphs (leaf nodes)</p>
    <p>Text contained in paragraphs, which constitute sections and documents.</p>
    <p>Document</p>
    <p>Section Section SectionParagraph</p>
    <p>Section Section SectionParagraph</p>
    <p>Paragraph ParagraphParagraph Paragraph Paragraph Paragraph</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Problems  A document covers multiple aspects of a central</p>
    <p>topic  Represented by sections or paragraphs.  Users usually want just one of the aspects.</p>
    <p>How to achieve this goal by utilizing the document structure?  Flexible element retrieval to get elements at arbitrary</p>
    <p>level rather than only leaf nodes.  Let each element at different levels have proper</p>
    <p>keywords description.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Our contributions  Building index with the same hierarchical structure as the</p>
    <p>document has.  Not just index the leaf nodes.</p>
    <p>Keywords propagation mechanism.  Assign proper keywords to each levels nodes (push broad-sense</p>
    <p>keywords to upper-level nodes).  Why cant use weight propagation technique?  Considering terms distributions.</p>
    <p>Flexible element retrieval according to queries.  With the hierarchical index, the system can access arbitrary-level</p>
    <p>elements  documents, sections or paragraphs w.r.t queries.  Avoid assembling separate text fragments with leaf nodes</p>
    <p>retrieval only.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivations and problems</p>
    <p>Hierarchical index propagation and pruning</p>
    <p>Flexible element retrieval</p>
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Hierarchical Indexing for Structured Documents  Term weighting for the leaf nodes and the</p>
    <p>intermediate elements.  Combining the statistics of the term</p>
    <p>occurrences and the distributions.  Term selection threshold.</p>
    <p>Propagation and pruning of the index terms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Term Weighting for Paragraphs  Paragraphs are atomic without children</p>
    <p>elements.</p>
    <p>Consider the term occurrences only  TFIDF measure.</p>
    <p>i jiji</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>N PttfPtWeight ln)),(ln(),(</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Term Weighting for Intermediate elements</p>
    <p>Document-level or section-level elements.</p>
    <p>Taking into account the term distributions in the immediately descendant elements.</p>
    <p>),()),(1ln(),( jijiji EtIEttfEtWeight</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Measuring Term Distributions  Entropy-like measurement</p>
    <p>How even a term is distributed in all the immediatedescendant elements of an intermediate element.</p>
    <p>Normalization factor  the theoretic maximum entropy.</p>
    <p>)(</p>
    <p>),(</p>
    <p>),( ln),(</p>
    <p>)(</p>
    <p>)(</p>
    <p>),(</p>
    <p>),(</p>
    <p>),( ln),(</p>
    <p>),(</p>
    <p>subN Ettf</p>
    <p>Ettf</p>
    <p>subttf subttf</p>
    <p>subNsubN</p>
    <p>Ettf</p>
    <p>Ettf</p>
    <p>subttf subttf</p>
    <p>EtI</p>
    <p>ji</p>
    <p>ESub ji</p>
    <p>ki ki</p>
    <p>ESub</p>
    <p>ji</p>
    <p>ESub ji</p>
    <p>ki ki</p>
    <p>ji</p>
    <p>jk</p>
    <p>jk</p>
    <p>jk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Term Selection  Term weights are normalized to the range of 0</p>
    <p>and 1 for the purpose of comparison.</p>
    <p>Compare the terms within one element.  Select those terms with the weights beyond a</p>
    <p>threshold as the index terms for this element.</p>
    <p>Repeat this process from bottom up.  Broader-sense terms can be propagated to upper</p>
    <p>level elements.</p>
    <p>Term pruning to avoid duplications of index terms.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Terms Propagation and Pruning Algorithm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>An illustration of the process</p>
    <p>Qi ng Dynast y Manchu Kang Xi Hi st or y Chi na</p>
    <p>Tang Dynast y</p>
    <p>Sui Sui Yang Hi st ory Chi na</p>
    <p>Sect i on Sect i on</p>
    <p>Document</p>
    <p>Qi ng Manchu Kang Xi</p>
    <p>Tang Sui Yang</p>
    <p>Hi st ory Dynast y</p>
    <p>Economy</p>
    <p>Chi na</p>
    <p>The Document Structure</p>
    <p>The I ndex Structure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivations and problems</p>
    <p>Hierarchical index propagation and pruning</p>
    <p>Flexible element retrieval</p>
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Flexible Element Retrieval  No term duplications along one path.  The path of an element</p>
    <p>including all the elements from this node to the root.</p>
    <p>Ranking relevant elements is equal to rank their paths.</p>
    <p>Q</p>
    <p>i i pip</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>N PathtWeightPathlevance</p>
    <p>ln),()(Re</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Path Ranking Algorithm 1. Find all elements that contain at least one query term. 2. Get paths for all candidate elements and merge the</p>
    <p>paths, that is, merge two paths into one if one is a part of the other.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Result Browsing  The prototype interface can</p>
    <p>Highlight the relevant parts of the selected document.</p>
    <p>Allow the user to browse results in the original document structure.</p>
    <p>Query example  the Manchu Qing Dynasty  A section in China  The whole document for Qing Dynasty</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Prototype Interface</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivations and problems</p>
    <p>Hierarchical index propagation and pruning</p>
    <p>Flexible element retrieval</p>
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Evaluation  Data Set</p>
    <p>41,942 XML documents in various topics from Encarta online encyclopedia.</p>
    <p>Ten experimental queries  Can be answered by only parts of the relevant document,</p>
    <p>e.g. Fleet Street in London answered by a paragraph of the document London.</p>
    <p>Relevance judgment made by human assessors  for each query, there is a group of paragraphs representing relevant sections or such paragraphs.</p>
    <p>Baseline system (TFIDF Para)  Indexing paragraph nodes only.  Applying TFIDF measure to weight terms and using cosine</p>
    <p>similarity to retrieve answers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Performance Evaluation  Use precision, recall and F-value as</p>
    <p>performance metrics.  Two sets of hierarchical index</p>
    <p>Utilizing titles and without considering titles.</p>
    <p>Answer selection threshold  Fixed numbers 0.1  0.9, used by most of existing</p>
    <p>systems.  Dynamic thresholds  Avg and Avg + Std_Dev</p>
    <p>Compared our system with TFIDF Para using different answer selection thresholds.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Results of Performance Comparison  Figures are impressive</p>
    <p>Improvements on precision are 48.83% (w/ titles) and 41.67% (w/o titles) in average.</p>
    <p>For F-Values, improvements are 56.02% (w/ titles) and 40.89% (w/o titles).</p>
    <p>Recall slightly decreases with some threshold settings (too rigorous threshold for index term selection).</p>
    <p>User feedback  Our system can find more meaningful units instead of</p>
    <p>separate paragraphs, including some paragraphs not actually containing query terms.</p>
    <p>Users are clear of their context when browsing the answers within the original document structure.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Threshold Setting  Our system is less sensitive to the answer selection</p>
    <p>threshold settings.  Dynamic threshold is a good alternative for such structured</p>
    <p>document retrieval.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivations and problems</p>
    <p>Hierarchical index propagation and pruning</p>
    <p>Flexible element retrieval</p>
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Conclusions  A novel hierarchical index propagation and</p>
    <p>pruning mechanism to generate structured index.</p>
    <p>Flexible element retrieval of getting arbitrarylevel relevant elements is realized on the hierarchical index.</p>
    <p>It can better satisfy users than previous passage retrieval systems.</p>
    <p>More work can be done on generating hierarchical index for federate search.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation for ECIR03, Pisa, Italy</p>
    <p>Thanks!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
