<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two kinds of work</p>
    <p>Jonathan Furner</p>
    <p>GSE&amp;IS, UCLA</p>
    <p>VRA :: March 29, 2007</p>
    <p>Cataloging cultural objects</p>
    <p>cultural objects</p>
    <p>works</p>
    <p>works of visual art</p>
    <p>built works</p>
    <p>cultural artifacts</p>
    <p>documentary images</p>
    <p>CCO: What is a work?</p>
    <p>a distinct intellectual or artistic creation limited</p>
    <p>primarily to [physical] objects and structures made by humans</p>
    <p>excluded are literary works, musical works, works in</p>
    <p>the performing arts, and other intangible culture</p>
    <p>CCO: What is an image?</p>
    <p>a visual representation [or depiction] of a work</p>
    <p>a surrogate for a work that documents it</p>
    <p>typically in photographic, photomechanical, or digital</p>
    <p>format</p>
    <p>i.e., what is held in visual resources collections</p>
    <p>CCO: What is an image? contd</p>
    <p>always excluded are paintings, drawings, sculpture, and</p>
    <p>as works themselves</p>
    <p>some photographs that depict works may similarly be</p>
    <p>treated as works themselves</p>
    <p>depending on the stature of the photographer and the</p>
    <p>aesthetic or historical value of the photograph</p>
    <p>CCOs entity--relationship model</p>
    <p>Work</p>
    <p>Image</p>
    <p>Source</p>
    <p>Personal and corporate name</p>
    <p>Geographic place</p>
    <p>Concept</p>
    <p>Subject</p>
    <p>(see Fig. 1, p. 20)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Treatment of depicted works</p>
    <p>the work depicted in an image should be treated as a Related Work of that image</p>
    <p>similarly, any image depicting a work should be treated as a Related Image of that work</p>
    <p>if a work depicts another work, the depicted work should be treated as a Subject of the work at hand (see CCO 6.2.1.2.8)</p>
    <p>if the depicted work is described in its own catalog record, then it should also be treated as a Related Work of the work at hand</p>
    <p>Some examples of complex relationships</p>
    <p>a photo by Durandelle of the Eiffel Tower: http://www.vraweb.org/ccoweb/cco/example57.html</p>
    <p>Work: Eiffel Tower</p>
    <p>Work: photo</p>
    <p>Some examples of complex relationships, contd</p>
    <p>an image of a plan of a building, and an image of the building</p>
    <p>Work: building Image</p>
    <p>Work: plan Image</p>
    <p>Some examples of complex relationships, contd</p>
    <p>Is the work-to-be-cataloged the manuscript page, or the photo?</p>
    <p>Some examples of complex relationships, contd</p>
    <p>Work: sarcophagus</p>
    <p>Work: manuscript page Image: photo</p>
    <p>Work: sarcophagus</p>
    <p>Work: manuscript page</p>
    <p>Work: photo Image: slide</p>
    <p>option A</p>
    <p>option B</p>
    <p>Work in CCO vs. Work in FRBR/RDA</p>
    <p>note 2, p. 41: Work in CCO is more concrete</p>
    <p>than work as defined in FRBR ... The work in</p>
    <p>CCO is usually a physical entity, whereas that in</p>
    <p>FRBR is an abstraction or intellectual entity, such</p>
    <p>as a literary work or a musical composition.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FRBRs E-R model (simplified)</p>
    <p>Work</p>
    <p>Expression</p>
    <p>Manifestation</p>
    <p>Item</p>
    <p>Person</p>
    <p>Corporate body</p>
    <p>Concept</p>
    <p>Object</p>
    <p>Event</p>
    <p>Place</p>
    <p>Group 1 Group 2 Group 3</p>
    <p>FRBRs Group 1 entities</p>
    <p>a work is a distinct intellectual or artistic creation ... an</p>
    <p>abstract entity</p>
    <p>an expression is the specific intellectual or artistic</p>
    <p>form that a work takes each time it is realized; the</p>
    <p>intellectual or artistic realization of a work in the form of</p>
    <p>alpha-numeric, musical, or choreographic notation, sound,</p>
    <p>image, object, movement, etc., or any combination of such</p>
    <p>forms</p>
    <p>FRBRs Group 1 entities, contd</p>
    <p>a manifestation is the physical embodiment of an expression of a work ... [the set of] all the physical objects that bear the same characteristics, in respect to both intellectual content and physical form</p>
    <p>an item is a single exemplar [or instance] of a manifestation ... a concrete entity ... in many instances a single physical object</p>
    <p>FRBRs Group 1 entities, contd</p>
    <p>Works ... are realized through</p>
    <p>Expressions ... are embodied in</p>
    <p>Manifestations ... are exemplified by</p>
    <p>Items</p>
    <p>A literary example</p>
    <p>work: Cervantes Don Quixote</p>
    <p>expression: Grossmans English translation of Don Quixote</p>
    <p>manifestation: Eccos 2003 edition of Grossmans text</p>
    <p>item: my copy of Eccos 2003 edition</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A musical example</p>
    <p>work: Andersson, Ulvaeus, and Andersons Dancing queen</p>
    <p>expression: Abbas performance of Dancing queen</p>
    <p>recorded in 1975</p>
    <p>manifestation: the recording released as a single in</p>
    <p>item: my copy of the single</p>
    <p>An example from the visual arts</p>
    <p>work: Magrittes The human condition</p>
    <p>expression: the specific realization [in 1935] of [The human condition] in the form of ... an image</p>
    <p>manifestation: [the set of] all the physical objects that [share] the same ... intellectual content [as that expression] and physical form</p>
    <p>item: the instance of The human condition hanging in a private collection</p>
    <p>Ontology of art</p>
    <p>a subfield of the philosophy of art</p>
    <p>What sorts of things are works of art?</p>
    <p>What is the nature of the various sorts of relationship that exist between works of art and things of other sorts?</p>
    <p>In what does the identity of a work of art (of a given sort) consist?</p>
    <p>Are translations ... cover versions ... directors cuts ... new works, or just different expressions of the same work?</p>
    <p>Why worry?</p>
    <p>designers of catalogs need to know how records</p>
    <p>should be grouped and linked so that catalog</p>
    <p>users can find the objects they want</p>
    <p>FRBR, Lubetzky, Cutter ... : records representing</p>
    <p>objects should be grouped by the works they</p>
    <p>instantiate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Philosophers views on ontology of literature</p>
    <p>most see literary works as (Peircean) types, each instantiated by multiple tokens</p>
    <p>types tokens</p>
    <p>word-types word-occurrences</p>
    <p>sentences utterances</p>
    <p>works copies</p>
    <p>Philosophers views on ontology of literature, contd</p>
    <p>a type can be characterized as:</p>
    <p>a fixed sequence of words in a given language (Goodman)</p>
    <p>a fixed sequence of words specifying what counts as a correct</p>
    <p>instance (Wolterstorff: norm kind)</p>
    <p>a fixed sequence of words indicated by a given author at a given</p>
    <p>time (Levinson)</p>
    <p>a fixed sequence of words arrived at by an authors following a</p>
    <p>given set of contextual influences (Currie: action type)</p>
    <p>Philosophers views on ontology of literature, contd</p>
    <p>some see works as megatypes</p>
    <p>the (propositional) meaning shared by two instances -including paraphrases, translations, etc. (Stevenson)</p>
    <p>megatypes types tokens</p>
    <p>concepts word-types word-occurrences</p>
    <p>propositions sentences utterances</p>
    <p>works translations copies</p>
    <p>Philosophers views on ontology of art</p>
    <p>uniform theories</p>
    <p>unitive theories: the type/token distinction isnt characteristic of</p>
    <p>any arts</p>
    <p>there are neither types nor tokens (Collingwood)</p>
    <p>there are no tokens (Currie)</p>
    <p>there are no types (Goodman): CCO?</p>
    <p>dualist theories: the type/token distinction is characteristic of all</p>
    <p>arts: FRBR?</p>
    <p>Philosophers views on ontology of art, contd</p>
    <p>non-uniform theories</p>
    <p>the type/token distinction is characteristic of some</p>
    <p>arts, but not others (Wolterstorff, Davies)</p>
    <p>singular works: paintings, hewn sculptures, Polaroids, many</p>
    <p>buildings</p>
    <p>type-works that can have multiple tokens: cast</p>
    <p>sculptures, photographs from negatives, prints (as well as</p>
    <p>literary works, theatrical works, and musical works)</p>
    <p>Two and a half questions</p>
    <p>Should CCO be modified to reflect a FRBResque view of the relationships existing between (abstract) type-works and (concrete) token-items -- and if so, how?</p>
    <p>Should FRBR be modified to reflect a CCOesque view of the relationships existing between (concrete) works and (concrete) images -- and if so, how?</p>
    <p>If images are type-works, how useful is the work/image distinction?</p>
    <p>Is image more usefully conceived as a Work Type than as a Record Type?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bibliography</p>
    <p>Baca, Murtha, et al. (2006). Cataloging cultural objects: A guide to describing cultural works and their images. Chicago, IL: American Library Association.</p>
    <p>IFLA Study Group on the Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records. (1998). Functional requirements for bibliographic records. Mnchen: K. G. Saur.</p>
    <p>Stevenson, C. L. (1957). On What is a poem? Philosophical Review 66: 329-362.</p>
    <p>Wolterstorff, N. (1992). Ontology of artworks. In A companion to aesthetics, ed. D. Cooper, 310-314. Oxford: Blackwell.</p>
    <p>Howell, R. (2002). Ontology and the nature of the literary work. Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism 60: 67-79.</p>
    <p>Thomasson, A. L. (2003). The ontology of art. In The Blackwell guide to aesthetics, ed. P. Kivy, 78-92. Oxford: Blackwell.</p>
    <p>Davies, S. (2006). Varieties of art. In The philosophy of art, 81-108. Oxford: Blackwell.</p>
    <p>Jonathan Furner Graduate School of Education and Information Studies</p>
    <p>University of California, Los Angeles furner@gseis.ucla.edu</p>
    <p>Thank you.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
