<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Patch-based Image Patch-based Image Interpolation: Interpolation:</p>
    <p>Algorithms and Algorithms and ApplicationsApplicationsXin LiXin Li</p>
    <p>Lane Dept. of CSEELane Dept. of CSEE</p>
    <p>West Virginia UniversityWest Virginia University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Where Does Patch Come Where Does Patch Come from?from?</p>
    <p>Neuroscience: Neuroscience: receptive fields of receptive fields of neighboring cells in neighboring cells in human vision system human vision system have severe have severe overlappingoverlapping</p>
    <p>Engineering: patch Engineering: patch has been under the has been under the disguise of many disguise of many different names such different names such as as windowswindows in digital in digital filters, filters, blocksblocks in JPEG in JPEG and the and the supportsupport of of wavelet bases, wavelet bases,</p>
    <p>Cited from D. Hubel, Eye, Brain and Vision, 1988</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Patch-based Image Patch-based Image ModelsModels</p>
    <p>Local modelsLocal models  Markov Random Field (MRF) and higher-order extensions Markov Random Field (MRF) and higher-order extensions</p>
    <p>(e.g., Field-of-Expert)(e.g., Field-of-Expert)  Transform-based: PCA, DCT, waveletsTransform-based: PCA, DCT, wavelets</p>
    <p>Nonlocal modelsNonlocal models  Bilateral filtering (Tomasi et al. ICCV1998)Bilateral filtering (Tomasi et al. ICCV1998)  Texture synthesis via Nonparametric resampling (Efros&amp;LTexture synthesis via Nonparametric resampling (Efros&amp;L</p>
    <p>eung ICCV1999)eung ICCV1999)  Exemplar-based inpainting (Criminisi et al. TIP2004)Exemplar-based inpainting (Criminisi et al. TIP2004)  Nonlocal mean denoising (Buades et al. CVPR2005)Nonlocal mean denoising (Buades et al. CVPR2005)  Total Least-Square denoising (Hirakawa&amp;Parks TIP2006)Total Least-Square denoising (Hirakawa&amp;Parks TIP2006)  Block-matching 3D denoising (Dabov et al. TIP2007)Block-matching 3D denoising (Dabov et al. TIP2007)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Bayesian Formulation of A Bayesian Formulation of Image Interpolation Image Interpolation</p>
    <p>ProblemProblem</p>
    <p>( | , ) ( | ) ( | , )</p>
    <p>( | )</p>
    <p>p H p H p H</p>
    <p>p H</p>
    <p>y x x x y</p>
    <p>y</p>
    <p>Unobservable data Observable</p>
    <p>data</p>
    <p>Image prior (e.g., sparsity-based)</p>
    <p>Likelihood (our focus here)</p>
    <p>Model class (e.g., local vs. nonlocal)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Simple Extension of A Simple Extension of BM3DBM3D</p>
    <p>Basic idea: combine BM3D with progressive thresholding (Guleryuz TIP2006)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>x y bicubic NEDI1 this work</p>
    <p>Interpolation of LR Interpolation of LR ImagesImages</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Go Back to Biology Go Back to Biology</p>
    <p>Spatially random distribution of rod/cone cells keeps aliasing artifacts out of our vision</p>
    <p>cone</p>
    <p>rods</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>x y DT KR this work</p>
    <p>Interpolation of Interpolation of Nonuniformly-sampled Nonuniformly-sampled</p>
    <p>ImagesImages</p>
    <p>DT- Delauney Triangle-based (griddata under MATLAB)</p>
    <p>KR- Kernal Regression-based (Takeda et al. IEEE TIP 2007)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modeling Spatial Modeling Spatial RandomnessRandomness</p>
    <p>Extensively studied in geostatistics and Extensively studied in geostatistics and environmental statistics (e.g., spatial environmental statistics (e.g., spatial distribution of animals and plants)distribution of animals and plants)</p>
    <p>Mathematically modeled by Mathematically modeled by homogeneous Poisson process (density homogeneous Poisson process (density parameterparameter))  Lack of positional differentiationLack of positional differentiation  Lack of scale differentiationLack of scale differentiation</p>
    <p>Empirically there exist quadrant-based Empirically there exist quadrant-based and distance-based randomness metrics and distance-based randomness metrics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Monte-Carlo Based Monte-Carlo Based Optimization Optimization</p>
    <p>Iterative procedure: randomly pick two locations (one black and the other white), if swapping them decreases the energy, accept it; otherwise accept it with some probability</p>
    <p>The lower energy the more random</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Importance of Locations Importance of Locations</p>
    <p>before optimization</p>
    <p>after optimization</p>
    <p>Identical reconstruction algorithm; only differ on sampling locations</p>
    <p>In biological world: evolution + development</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Random Sampling</p>
    <p>Pattern</p>
    <p>interpolationquantization channel</p>
    <p>sensor node</p>
    <p>S</p>
    <p>Application intoApplication into Compressive ImagingCompressive Imaging</p>
    <p>How is it different from conventional image coding system? No bits are spent on coding the location information (random=no cost).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Coding ResultsCoding Results</p>
    <p>R=0.21bpp original ours</p>
    <p>PSNR=27.85dB SSIM=0.8750</p>
    <p>SPIHT PSNR=28.82dB SSIM=0.8637</p>
    <p>R=0.81bpp original ours</p>
    <p>PSNR=28.10dB SSIM=0.9182</p>
    <p>SPIHT PSNR=22.98dB SSIM=0.7512</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Error Resilience ResultsError Resilience Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ConclusionsConclusions</p>
    <p>A good image prior is useful to many A good image prior is useful to many processing tasks involving incomplete or noisy processing tasks involving incomplete or noisy observationobservation</p>
    <p>As we move from local to nonlocal models, the As we move from local to nonlocal models, the location of sampling points becomes important location of sampling points becomes important  location (address) and intensity (data) are  location (address) and intensity (data) are the same thing cited from T. Kohonen the same thing cited from T. Kohonen Self-SelfOrganization and Associative MemoryOrganization and Associative Memory</p>
    <p>Image processing is at the intersection of Image processing is at the intersection of science and engineering- will BM3D lead to a science and engineering- will BM3D lead to a new class of SOM? new class of SOM?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
