<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Marketing for participation: How can Electronic Dissertation</p>
    <p>Services win authors?</p>
    <p>Bettina Berendt</p>
    <p>Elke Brenstein</p>
    <p>Yunfan Li</p>
    <p>Bert Wendland</p>
    <p>Humboldt University Berlin  Institute of Information Systems (www.wiwi.hu-berlin.de/~berendt)</p>
    <p>Inst. for Computer Uses in Education / Inst. of Work Psychology</p>
    <p>Electronic Publishing Group, Computer and Media Services</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ETD success</p>
    <p>To be successful, an ETD service must o employ advanced technology</p>
    <p>o know about and reach its market</p>
    <p>To know the market, it needs to answer these Qs: o What is the (main) goal of the service?</p>
    <p>o Does the service have other goals (e.g. image-building)? What are the financial constraints?</p>
    <p>o Who are the target group(s)?</p>
    <p>o Do they use and like the service? Why (not)?</p>
    <p>o What methods are adequate for answering these Qs?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HU doctoral dissertations (without Medical Faculty)</p>
    <p>EDOC authors</p>
    <p>non-EDOC authors</p>
    <p>Total no.s of online publications by German universities</p>
    <p>http://edoc.hu-berlin.de</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions and goals of the study (1): EDOC target groups and goals</p>
    <p>authors</p>
    <p>EDOC authors</p>
    <p>readers</p>
    <p>EDOC readers</p>
    <p>EDOC goal: enable everyone who wants to publish online to do so</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions and goals (2): Dissertation authors attitudes, experiences, wishes</p>
    <p>EDOC non-/not-yet-authors</p>
    <p>Dont publish online because they  dont wish to?  do not feel capable / adequately supported?  are unaware of the possibility?</p>
    <p>(EDOC readers: A separate study)</p>
    <p>EDOC authors</p>
    <p>Publication on EDOC is a fast &amp; easy way to satisfy the German university publication requirements.  I have learned about EDOC (too) late.  The formatting requirements are difficult.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>Participants: all HU doctoral students &amp; doctors (without Medical Faculty)</p>
    <p>Materials &amp; Procedure:</p>
    <p>Date: Tue, 11 Mar 2003 From: Yunfan Li To: the edoc survey mailing list Subject: Digital Dissertation Questionnaire for HU Doctoral Students and Doctors</p>
    <p>Dear doctoral student, dear doctor,</p>
    <p>Would you please take about 5 minutes to complete the HU Digital Dissertation Questionnaire. The goal of this investigation is to find out how the Digital publishing opportunity is known and used by HU doctoral students and doctors. With your help, we aim to continue to improve the service of the Document and Publication Server (http://edoc.hu-berlin.de). ...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Respondent characteristics mirror the targeted population (1)</p>
    <p>1180 emails sent out  approximately all HU doctoral students and doctors</p>
    <p>(without Medical Faculty)</p>
    <p>162 respondents started questionnaire (159 online)  response rate 13.7%</p>
    <p>101 respondents finished it  completion rate 64.2%</p>
    <p>69.3% doctoral students (population 98-01: 89.5%)  67.7% males (population: 57.3%)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Respondent characteristics mirror the targeted population (2)</p>
    <p>Faculties / institutes of respondents</p>
    <p>Biology</p>
    <p>Computer Science</p>
    <p>Physics</p>
    <p>Mathematics</p>
    <p>Geography</p>
    <p>Chemistry</p>
    <p>Psychology</p>
    <p>Economics / Business</p>
    <p>Social Sciences Inst.</p>
    <p>Law</p>
    <p>Education</p>
    <p>Languages</p>
    <p>History</p>
    <p>Agricultural Faculty</p>
    <p>other</p>
    <p>Natural Sciences</p>
    <p>Social Sciences</p>
    <p>Arts</p>
    <p>Agricultural Faculty</p>
    <p>All dissertation authors (98-01) by scientific area</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How would you like to publish your dissertation?</p>
    <p>book by a publishing house</p>
    <p>book by a copyshop</p>
    <p>microfiche</p>
    <p>online only</p>
    <p>Online? Yes, but ...</p>
    <p>online only</p>
    <p>online in addition to a book</p>
    <p>EDOC &amp; its QuestionsMethod  Results &amp; Discussion  Outlook Do authors not publish</p>
    <p>online because they  dont wish to?  do not feel</p>
    <p>capable / adequately supported?  are unaware of the possibility?Do authors not wish to publish online?</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>NO, BUT...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why ...</p>
    <p>Have you decided to publish online? (34.9%) o Its faster &amp; easier than traditional publishing. o Its cheap. o My documents can be accessed by more people.</p>
    <p>Have you decided not to publish online? (15.6%) o In my discipline, online publication is considered informal. o I would like to publish a real / physical book.</p>
    <p>Have you not made your decision yet? (49.5%) o I will make a decision after I finish writing. o My submission date is far from now; I will think about it later. o I know too little &amp; will make a decision when I know more.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EDOC &amp; its QuestionsMethod  Results &amp; Discussion  Outlook Do authors not publish</p>
    <p>online because they  dont wish to?  do not feel</p>
    <p>capable / adequately supported?  are unaware of the possibility?</p>
    <p>Authors need to format their dissertation using the dissertation template to enable DiML markup.</p>
    <p>Most authors feel adequately supported.  Most helpful in case of problems with the dissertation</p>
    <p>template: o author information (on the Web),</p>
    <p>o friends, o computing centre staff (email, personal, phone)</p>
    <p>~ 20% cant use and/or dont need training course.  cf. ~ 20% LaTeX users.</p>
    <p>Do authors feel incapable / inadequately supported?</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>SELDOM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BUT: Few concrete steps taken towards a digital diss. publication so far</p>
    <p>When did you / do you intend to start using the dissertation template?</p>
    <p>not decided yet after I finish writing in the middle at the beginning</p>
    <p>ACTIONS HAPPEN TOO LATE!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EDOC &amp; its QuestionsMethod  Results &amp; Discussion  Outlook Do authors not publish</p>
    <p>online because they  dont wish to?  do not feel</p>
    <p>capable / adequately supported?  are unaware of the possibility?</p>
    <p>28.3% wished they had learned earlier about EDOC.</p>
    <p>Are authors unaware of the digital diss. publishing opportunity?</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>How did you find out about the opportunity of publishing your dissertation online?</p>
    <p>from this questionnaire</p>
    <p>from a friend or colleague</p>
    <p>hyperlink from the library page</p>
    <p>from a professor</p>
    <p>YES! ... INFORMATION ARRIVES TOO LATE!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Suggestions for improving information flow and EDOC promotion</p>
    <p>Participants gave many suggestions  3 groups ... and we based our proposals on these suggestions:  Inform doctoral students when they start their</p>
    <p>dissertation project o Professors, examination offices, ... as informers &amp; promoters o Doctoral seminars etc., within or across scientific fields o Lectures and tutorials within the faculties o Stress the advantages and new opportunities of digital</p>
    <p>publication!</p>
    <p>Send a regular email newsletter  Offer more service with the formatting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outlook: Topics for further research</p>
    <p>Specific patterns in different faculties / institutes o authoring (up to 67% EDOC authors  in Mathematics)</p>
    <p>o use of EDOC services (e.g., training course)</p>
    <p>Structured use of metadata as a key competence o Authors experience problems when using the dissertation</p>
    <p>template</p>
    <p>o EDOC readers study: Users prefer searching (keyword type-in) to the use of metadata-based structured browsing lists (controlled vocabulary)</p>
    <p>Develop training &amp; education strategies further!</p>
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
