<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tracking context with usage and attention metadata in multilingual Technology Enhanced Learning</p>
    <p>Riina VuorikariRiina Vuorikari European Schoolnet / European Schoolnet / Open Univ. of the NetherlandsOpen Univ. of the Netherlands</p>
    <p>Bettina Berendt Bettina Berendt KU LeuvenKU Leuven</p>
    <p>www.berendt.dewww.berendt.de</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Learning Object Repositories Learning Object Repositories foster re-use and improve foster re-use and improve learning learning</p>
    <p>Really? Really?</p>
    <p>Ochoa (2008), Vuorikari &amp; Koper (2009): Ochoa (2008), Vuorikari &amp; Koper (2009): re-use ~ 20%re-use ~ 20%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A basic challenge: contextA basic challenge: context</p>
    <p>Political ScienceBiology</p>
    <p>Researching for a</p>
    <p>term paper in ...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MotivationMotivation (application goals)(application goals)</p>
    <p>Use case Use case  Technology Enhanced Learning / Learning Object Repositories Technology Enhanced Learning / Learning Object Repositories  teachers from different linguistic and country backgroundsteachers from different linguistic and country backgrounds</p>
    <p>Goal: foster re-use of resourcesGoal: foster re-use of resources  Assumption: understanding user context can improve Assumption: understanding user context can improve</p>
    <p>system behavioursystem behaviour  Approach:Approach:</p>
    <p>consider UAM as part of context measurement, specifically:consider UAM as part of context measurement, specifically:  Investigate different roles of social taggingInvestigate different roles of social tagging  Profit from parallel research in different areas Profit from parallel research in different areas</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation Motivation (general - workshop)(general - workshop)</p>
    <p>To exploit usage and attention metadata: need to  define what properties of usage to use and</p>
    <p>why  how to gather data on that property  what to do with that information</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MotivationMotivation (general  our work)(general  our work)</p>
    <p>Automatically gathered indicators of Automatically gathered indicators of contextcontext, , attention, ...attention, ...  Whats common across fields?Whats common across fields?  How can we communicate better?How can we communicate better?  Whats specific in T.E. Whats specific in T.E. learninglearning??</p>
    <p>How can How can tagstags help learning &amp; teaching? help learning &amp; teaching?  How to bridge (e.g. How to bridge (e.g. linguallingual) barriers?) barriers?  What are the best research methods for What are the best research methods for</p>
    <p>answering all these questions?answering all these questions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Types of context Types of context in TELin TEL</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is context?What is context?</p>
    <p>Context is any information that can be used to characterize the situation of an entity. An entity is a person, place, or object that is considered relevant to the interaction between a user and an application, including the user and applications themselves. (Dey, 2001)</p>
    <p>Any information not explicitly carried by the surface level of an interaction with a computational system</p>
    <p>Surface level:  user issues a query,  user accesses a resource, ...</p>
    <p>We will distinguish between  Macro-context  Micro-context</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Macro-contextMacro-context</p>
    <p>educational level  formal and informal learning  delivery setting (distance, blended, ...)  intended users and user roles  ...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Micro-contextMicro-context</p>
    <p>UserUser  traittrait  statestate</p>
    <p>InteractionInteraction  atomic vs. activity structureatomic vs. activity structure  implicit vs. explicit interest indicatorsimplicit vs. explicit interest indicators</p>
    <p>Background knowledge / semantic Background knowledge / semantic enrichment; often w.r.t. materialenrichment; often w.r.t. material</p>
    <p>(Berendt, 2007)(Berendt, 2007)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tags and contextTags and context</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Whats in a tag?Whats in a tag?</p>
    <p>tag</p>
    <p>item user  material</p>
    <p>user</p>
    <p>interaction  writing  reading</p>
    <p>Background knowledge</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tags as interest indicators (1)  Tags as interest indicators (1)  or: measuring and using or: measuring and using interaction-contextinteraction-context</p>
    <p>Comparative search efficiency:Comparative search efficiency:  Search option [A|B|...] Search option [A|B|...]  a target LO a target LO  Click-through rateClick-through rate aka aka confidenceconfidence (fraction of successful (fraction of successful</p>
    <p>searches)searches)  Path lengthPath length</p>
    <p>In LOR: Search with ...In LOR: Search with ...  explicit searchexplicit search (for resources w/o tags or ratings): 4.4 (for resources w/o tags or ratings): 4.4</p>
    <p>searches / resourcesearches / resource  community browsingcommunity browsing (tagclouds, lists, pivot browsing): 3.9 (tagclouds, lists, pivot browsing): 3.9</p>
    <p>searches / resourcessearches / resources  social informationsocial information (community browsing or explict search with (community browsing or explict search with</p>
    <p>interest indicators (tags, ratings)): 2.8 searches / resourceinterest indicators (tags, ratings)): 2.8 searches / resource</p>
    <p>Recommendation of search options?!Recommendation of search options?!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tags provide context to better Tags provide context to better utilize background knowledgeutilize background knowledge</p>
    <p>Can tags be used for enriching existing metadata of Can tags be used for enriching existing metadata of educational resources in a multilingual context?educational resources in a multilingual context?</p>
    <p>30% of tag applications matched with descriptors from a 30% of tag applications matched with descriptors from a multilingual thesaurus, which had also been used to multilingual thesaurus, which had also been used to index these learning resources (Vuorikari et al., 2009)index these learning resources (Vuorikari et al., 2009)  Thesaurus tagsThesaurus tags</p>
    <p>Thesaurus tags provide forThesaurus tags provide for  adding properties to tags (e.g., relation to a concept in a adding properties to tags (e.g., relation to a concept in a</p>
    <p>multilingual thesaurus, language)multilingual thesaurus, language)  linking resources to multilingual thesaurus descriptorslinking resources to multilingual thesaurus descriptors  can support retrieval of resources in a multilingual contextcan support retrieval of resources in a multilingual context</p>
    <p>Cf. convergence and quality tendencies in tagging in Cf. convergence and quality tendencies in tagging in general (Bollen &amp; Halpin, 2009; Hayes et al., 2007)general (Bollen &amp; Halpin, 2009; Hayes et al., 2007)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is user context  What is user context  the case of languagethe case of language</p>
    <p>User models have many different variablesUser models have many different variables  LanguageLanguage (first language, further languages, (first language, further languages,</p>
    <p>proficiency, preferences): an important proficiency, preferences): an important descriptor of usersdescriptor of users</p>
    <p>Language situationLanguage situation (interaction in a first or (interaction in a first or second language): an important descriptor second language): an important descriptor</p>
    <p>Linguistic trait and state context variables!Linguistic trait and state context variables!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measures / indicators of Measures / indicators of user languageuser language</p>
    <p>self-profiling that explicitly addresses the question self-profiling that explicitly addresses the question (your mother tongue?)(your mother tongue?)</p>
    <p>IP addressIP address  browser settingsbrowser settings  language of the currently used interfacelanguage of the currently used interface  language of search terms and tagslanguage of search terms and tags  known or inferred language of tagged resourcesknown or inferred language of tagged resources</p>
    <p>NB: indicator of the language situation: compare user NB: indicator of the language situation: compare user language with interface/resource language (e.g., language with interface/resource language (e.g., Berendt &amp; Kralisch, 2009)Berendt &amp; Kralisch, 2009)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tags as interest indicators (2)  Tags as interest indicators (2)  or: tags for measuring (re-)useor: tags for measuring (re-)use</p>
    <p>bookmarking and personal collections of digital bookmarking and personal collections of digital learning resources as a proxy for the use and learning resources as a proxy for the use and re-use of resourcesre-use of resources</p>
    <p>When coupled with user and resource When coupled with user and resource location / language:location / language:</p>
    <p>become proxy for (re-)use across national and become proxy for (re-)use across national and language boundarieslanguage boundaries</p>
    <p>(e.g., Vuorikari &amp; Koper, 2009)(e.g., Vuorikari &amp; Koper, 2009)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why support trans-lingual re-Why support trans-lingual reuse? (1): Situation on the use? (1): Situation on the WebWeb</p>
    <p>What would be an ideal language situation on What would be an ideal language situation on the Web?the Web?  One H0: ~ amount of materials proportional to One H0: ~ amount of materials proportional to</p>
    <p>number of first-language speakers of a languagenumber of first-language speakers of a language  Not the case  non-English languages are Not the case  non-English languages are</p>
    <p>severely under-represented on the Web due toseverely under-represented on the Web due to  Resource-creation behaviourResource-creation behaviour  Link-setting behaviourLink-setting behaviour  Link-following behaviourLink-following behaviour  Attitudes towards resources in different languagesAttitudes towards resources in different languages</p>
    <p>(Berendt &amp; Kralisch, 2009)(Berendt &amp; Kralisch, 2009)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why support trans-lingual Why support trans-lingual re-use? (2): User re-use? (2): User preferencespreferences</p>
    <p>Theoretical reasons (cognitive effort), supported by Theoretical reasons (cognitive effort), supported by implicit and explicit user preferences:implicit and explicit user preferences:</p>
    <p>Clear tendency to access materials in ones mother Clear tendency to access materials in ones mother tongue in a medical information systemtongue in a medical information system</p>
    <p>17% of users of a LOR had saved only content in their 17% of users of a LOR had saved only content in their native language in their Favourites native language in their Favourites</p>
    <p>LORs: pragmatic reasons (curricula)LORs: pragmatic reasons (curricula)  Search-engine give better results when queried with Search-engine give better results when queried with</p>
    <p>linguistically correct (rather than Latinized) spellingslinguistically correct (rather than Latinized) spellings  But: individual differences depending on proficiency in But: individual differences depending on proficiency in</p>
    <p>English!English!</p>
    <p>(Berendt &amp; Kralisch, 2009; Vuorikari &amp; Koper, 2009; Blanco &amp; Lioma, (Berendt &amp; Kralisch, 2009; Vuorikari &amp; Koper, 2009; Blanco &amp; Lioma, 2009)2009)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Using context for improving Using context for improving trans-lingual re-use: How? trans-lingual re-use: How? (1)(1)</p>
    <p>better-organised search result lists better-organised search result lists  first a ranked list in the preferred language, first a ranked list in the preferred language,  then a ranked list in a second language, etc. then a ranked list in a second language, etc.  done: Google for general search results and done: Google for general search results and</p>
    <p>by LeMill (lemill.net) for learning resources. by LeMill (lemill.net) for learning resources.</p>
    <p>organise tag clouds by language or organise tag clouds by language or country as in LRE country as in LRE (lreforschools.eun.iorg)(lreforschools.eun.iorg)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Using context for improving Using context for improving trans-lingual re-use: How? trans-lingual re-use: How? (2)(2)</p>
    <p>for users with weaker language preferences; for unknown for users with weaker language preferences; for unknown users; ...:users; ...:</p>
    <p>Make exceptions to the foregoing by recommendations Make exceptions to the foregoing by recommendations usingusing  travel-well tagstravel-well tags: :</p>
    <p>terms with the same or similar spelling in most languagesterms with the same or similar spelling in most languages  ex.: technical terms like mathematics, place and person namesex.: technical terms like mathematics, place and person names  How to identify them? How to identify them?</p>
    <p>via multi-lingual thesaurus or similarvia multi-lingual thesaurus or similar  tag has been assigned by users from different languagestag has been assigned by users from different languages  Tag has been assigned to resources in different languagesTag has been assigned to resources in different languages</p>
    <p>travel-well resourcestravel-well resources::  Have been bookmarked by people from different languages, country Have been bookmarked by people from different languages, country</p>
    <p>contexts, contexts,</p>
    <p>(Vuorikari &amp; Ochoa, 2009)(Vuorikari &amp; Ochoa, 2009)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Using context for improving Using context for improving trans-lingual re-use: How? trans-lingual re-use: How? (3)(3)</p>
    <p>Direct recommendations 1 (see above):Direct recommendations 1 (see above):  Recommend content or tags in a preferred languageRecommend content or tags in a preferred language</p>
    <p>Indirect recommendations:Indirect recommendations:  E.g., recommend bookmark lists of other users with a similar E.g., recommend bookmark lists of other users with a similar</p>
    <p>language preference profile language preference profile  Profile similarity: extensional and/or intensional: degree of Profile similarity: extensional and/or intensional: degree of</p>
    <p>tolerance for mixed-language resources, results, etc. tolerance for mixed-language resources, results, etc.</p>
    <p>Direct recommendations 2: Direct recommendations 2:  repositories could specifically encourage users who are repositories could specifically encourage users who are</p>
    <p>competent in smaller languages also to author content in competent in smaller languages also to author content in their language.their language.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OutlookOutlook</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some questionsSome questions</p>
    <p>How to best couple content and architecture How to best couple content and architecture researchresearch</p>
    <p>How to bring together research from Web analytics / e-How to bring together research from Web analytics / eCommerce, search-engine research, digital libraries, Commerce, search-engine research, digital libraries, TEL, ...TEL, ...</p>
    <p>How to complement the exploratory research with How to complement the exploratory research with experimental research effectively and efficientlyexperimental research effectively and efficiently</p>
    <p>How to best combine different methods (validate that How to best combine different methods (validate that the dependent variables used the dependent variables used meanmean something!) something!)</p>
    <p>Which privacy/security questions arise?Which privacy/security questions arise?  What is specific for TEL?What is specific for TEL?</p>
    <p>... and now yours! ... and now yours! (Thx!)(Thx!)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ReferencesReferences</p>
    <p>Most references can be found in the paper, available at Most references can be found in the paper, available at www.cs.kuleuven.be/~berendt/Papers/TEL_context_attention_vuorikari_berendt.pdfwww.cs.kuleuven.be/~berendt/Papers/TEL_context_attention_vuorikari_berendt.pdf</p>
    <p>In addition:In addition:</p>
    <p>Bollen, D., &amp; Halpin, H. (2009). Bollen, D., &amp; Halpin, H. (2009). An Experimental Analysis of An Experimental Analysis of Suggestions in Collaborative Tagging. In Suggestions in Collaborative Tagging. In Proc. Of WI-IAT09, Milan, Proc. Of WI-IAT09, Milan, Italy, 15-18 Sept 2009.Italy, 15-18 Sept 2009. IEEE Computer Society Press. IEEE Computer Society Press.</p>
    <p>Hayes, C. et al. (2007). ... In Berendt, B., Hotho, A., Mladeni\v{c}, D., Hayes, C. et al. (2007). ... In Berendt, B., Hotho, A., Mladeni\v{c}, D., &amp; Semeraro, G. (Eds.) (2007). &amp; Semeraro, G. (Eds.) (2007). From Web to Social Web: Discovering From Web to Social Web: Discovering and deploying user and content profiles. Workshop on Web Mining, and deploying user and content profiles. Workshop on Web Mining, WebMine 2006, Berlin, Germany, September 18, 2006, Revised WebMine 2006, Berlin, Germany, September 18, 2006, Revised Selected and Invited Papers.Selected and Invited Papers. LNAI 4737. Berlin etc.: Springer. LNAI 4737. Berlin etc.: Springer.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
