<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Understanding and Supporting Volunteer Contributors:</p>
    <p>The Case of Metadata and Document Servers</p>
    <p>Bettina Berendt</p>
    <p>Humboldt University Berlin, Institute of Information Systems www.wiwi.hu-berlin.de/~berendt</p>
    <p>AAAI 2005 Spring Symposium Knowledge Collection from Volunteer Contributors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The site: http://edoc.hu-berlin.de</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Knowledge contributions: data and metadata</p>
    <p>&lt;BIBLIOGRAPHY&gt;&lt;FLOAT&gt;&lt;PAGENUMBE R&gt;136&lt;/PAGENUMBER&gt;&lt;/FLOAT&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;HEAD&gt;Literaturverzeichnis&lt;/HEAD&gt; ...</p>
    <p>&lt;CITATION WORKTYPE=&quot;journal&quot; PUBLISHED=&quot;PUBLISHED&quot;&gt; &lt;CUT ID=&quot;bib-45-&quot;&gt;[2] &lt;/CUT&gt;&lt;WORKAUTHOR&gt;Albrecht, T. F.; Bott, K.; Meier, T.; Schulze, A.; Koch, M.; Cundiff, S. T.; Feldmann, J.; Stolz, W.; Thomas, P.; Koch, S. W.; G&amp;ouml;bel; E. O.&lt;/WORKAUTHOR&gt; &lt;ARTICLETITLE&gt;Disorder mediated biexcitonic beats in semiconductor quantum wells&lt;/ARTICLETITLE&gt;, &lt;WORKTITLE&gt;Phys. Rev. B&lt;/WORKTITLE&gt;, &lt;PUBDATE&gt;1996&lt;/PUBDATE&gt;, &lt;NUMBER&gt;54&lt;/NUMBER&gt;, &lt;PAGES&gt;4436&lt;/PAGES&gt;,</p>
    <p>&lt;/CITATION&gt; ...</p>
    <p>&lt;BIBLIOGRAPHY&gt;&lt;FLOAT&gt;&lt;PAGENUMBE R&gt;136&lt;/PAGENUMBER&gt;&lt;/FLOAT&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;HEAD&gt;Literaturverzeichnis&lt;/HEAD&gt; ...</p>
    <p>&lt;CITATION WORKTYPE=&quot;journal&quot; PUBLISHED=&quot;PUBLISHED&quot;&gt; &lt;CUT ID=&quot;bib-45-&quot;&gt;[2] &lt;/CUT&gt;&lt;WORKAUTHOR&gt;Albrecht, T. F.; Bott, K.; Meier, T.; Schulze, A.; Koch, M.; Cundiff, S. T.; Feldmann, J.; Stolz, W.; Thomas, P.; Koch, S. W.; G&amp;ouml;bel; E. O.&lt;/WORKAUTHOR&gt; &lt;ARTICLETITLE&gt;Disorder mediated biexcitonic beats in semiconductor quantum wells&lt;/ARTICLETITLE&gt;, &lt;WORKTITLE&gt;Phys. Rev. B&lt;/WORKTITLE&gt;, &lt;PUBDATE&gt;1996&lt;/PUBDATE&gt;, &lt;NUMBER&gt;54&lt;/NUMBER&gt;, &lt;PAGES&gt;4436&lt;/PAGES&gt;,</p>
    <p>&lt;/CITATION&gt; ...</p>
    <p>http://edoc.hu-berlin.de/diml/dtd/xdiml.dtd</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background &amp; Questions</p>
    <p>authors who publish on EDOC are volunteer contributors main document type: PhD theses, Habilitation theses advantages: o cost-free publication + high-quality archiving o long-term readability guarantee (50 years) o authenticity &amp; integrity o semantic searchability</p>
    <p>but: share of PhD theses published on EDOC has remained at ~20% (13% if medical faculty included)</p>
    <p>Why do so many authors not contribute? How can authors / contributors be supported better?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What kinds of knowledge can (not) be gathered from volunteer contributors?</p>
    <p>Large-scale questionnaire study of authors attitudes, experiences, and wishes Samples: o All non-medical faculties (study 1, 2003), medical faculty (study 2,</p>
    <p>working on their PhD or postdoctoral (usu. Habilitation) qualification o Response rates: 13.7%, 12% o Respondent characteristics mirror the target population (gender,</p>
    <p>disciplines, qualification sought)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EDOC non-/not-yet-authors</p>
    <p>Dont publish online because they</p>
    <p>dont wish to? do not feel capable / perceive barriers? are unaware of the possibility?</p>
    <p>EDOC authors (contributors)</p>
    <p>Publication on EDOC is a fast &amp; easy way to satisfy the German university publication requirements. I have learned about EDOC (too) late. The formatting requirements are difficult.</p>
    <p>Knowns and unknowns</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method</p>
    <p>Date: Tue, 11 Mar 2003 From: Yunfan Li To: the edoc survey mailing list Subject: Digital Dissertation Questionnaire for HU</p>
    <p>Doctoral Students and Doctors</p>
    <p>Dear doctoral student, dear doctor,</p>
    <p>Would you please take about 5 minutes to complete the HU Digital Dissertation Questionnaire. The goal of this investigation is to find out how the Digital publishing opportunity is known and used by HU doctoral students and doctors. With your help, we aim to continue to improve the service of the Document and Publication Server (http://edoc.hu-berlin.de). ...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How would you like to publish your dissertation?</p>
    <p>book by a publishing house</p>
    <p>book by a copyshop</p>
    <p>microfiche</p>
    <p>online only</p>
    <p>Online? Yes, but ...</p>
    <p>online in addition to a book</p>
    <p>Do authors not wish to publish online?</p>
    <p>NO, BUT...</p>
    <p>First study (similar results in second study)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Authors need to format their dissertation using the dissertation template to enable DiML markup. Most authors feel adequately supported. ~ 20% cant use and/or dont need training course.</p>
    <p>cf. ~ 20% LaTeX users. But the use of the dissertation template was the most-often described barrier. In the 2nd study, we asked for template use in education: o 76% : I have never used a template o 94% : Templates has never been discussed in courses I took.</p>
    <p>Do authors perceive barriers to contribution? If so, which one(s)?</p>
    <p>METADATA PROVISION</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AND: Few concrete steps taken towards a digital diss. publication so far</p>
    <p>When did you / do you intend to start using the dissertation template?</p>
    <p>not decided yet after I finish writing in the middle at the beginning</p>
    <p>ACTIONS HAPPEN TOO LATE!</p>
    <p>First study (similar results in second study)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Are authors unaware of the digital diss. publishing opportunity?</p>
    <p>How did you find out about the opportunity of publishing your dissertation online?</p>
    <p>from this questionnaire from a friend or colleague hyperlink from the library page from a professor</p>
    <p>YES! ... INFORMATION ARRIVES TOO LATE!</p>
    <p>First study (similar results in second study)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary: A marketing and service challenge</p>
    <p>Lack of information is a major problem that impedes contribution. Metadata contribution is perceived as a problem. Main recommendation: Inform doctoral students when they start their dissertation project o Professors, examination offices, ... as informers &amp; promoters</p>
    <p>educational challenge: practice structured writing! o Doctoral seminars etc., within or across scientific fields o Stress the advantages and new opportunities of digital</p>
    <p>publication! information and motivation (experience of competence)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Can useful knowledge collection be deployed as</p>
    <p>a side effect to users activities, e.g. searching or using the Web?</p>
    <p>= (1 option) Does the site turn readers into contributors?</p>
    <p>Data from Web server log sample: 10,992 sessions (210,655 requests) from one week in 2003 (near the end of the first survey) Methods: semantic enrichment, association rule and sequence mining (tools: WEKA, WUM); clustering and classification (not shown in poster)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data preparation: Semantic enrichment TOP</p>
    <p>AUTHOR SEARCH DOC OTHER</p>
    <p>OAI OTHERDISSFULLTEXT</p>
    <p>LIST</p>
    <p>DNB</p>
    <p>AUTHOR</p>
    <p>KEYWORD</p>
    <p>META PROJECTOTHER DOC</p>
    <p>MASTER</p>
    <p>ABSTRACT</p>
    <p>ADVICE</p>
    <p>TEMPLATE</p>
    <p>FAQ</p>
    <p>LATEX</p>
    <p>HINWEISE</p>
    <p>DIML</p>
    <p>README</p>
    <p>ACCESS</p>
    <p>CONFERENCE</p>
    <p>PUBLIC READ</p>
    <p>STUDY</p>
    <p>CMS</p>
    <p>ABSTRACT</p>
    <p>ACCESS</p>
    <p>RESULT</p>
    <p>regexpr.txt: mapping from URLs to concepts</p>
    <p>HOME edoc\.hu-berlin\.de\/$ AUTHOR-START \/e_autoren_en\/$ DISS-ABSTRACT \/abstract\.php3\/habilitationen\/ AUTHOR-ADVICE \/e_autoren\/hinweise\.php\?nav=.* AUTHOR-ADVICE \/e_rzm\/hinweise\.php.* ...</p>
    <p>regexpr.txt: mapping from URLs to concepts</p>
    <p>HOME edoc\.hu-berlin\.de\/$ AUTHOR-START \/e_autoren_en\/$ DISS-ABSTRACT \/abstract\.php3\/habilitationen\/ AUTHOR-ADVICE \/e_autoren\/hinweise\.php\?nav=.* AUTHOR-ADVICE \/e_rzm\/hinweise\.php.* ...</p>
    <p>HOME</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Content co-occurrence 6. DOC-DISS-ABSTRACT=1 4169 ==&gt; DOC-DISS-ACCESS=1 3107 conf:(0.75)</p>
    <p>supp:( 0.28) Reading an abstract will make you read a dissertation. lift(DISS-ABSTRACT DISS-ACCESS) = 0.75/0.44 = 1.69 2. DOC-DISS-ABSTRACT=1 externalReferrer=search-engine 3227 ==&gt; DOC</p>
    <p>DISS-ACCESS=1 2613 conf:(0.81) Even stronger than rule 6 above. (usually: people arriving from Google) 11. externalReferrer=search-engine 7166 ==&gt; DOC-DISS-ACCESS=1 3851</p>
    <p>conf:(0.54) Still some lift, but not as much. 8. DOC-DISS-ACCESS=1 4866 ==&gt; DOC-DISS-ABSTRACT=1 3107 conf:(0.64) Over 30% of people who access a dissertation have not read an abstract! 16. externalReferrer=other-external-referrer 1343 ==&gt; OTHER-PROJECT=1 571</p>
    <p>conf:(0.43) Lift = 0.43 / (2198/10992) = 2.15 17. externalReferrer=other-external-referrer 1343 ==&gt; OTHER-OTHER=1 554</p>
    <p>conf:(0.41) Lift = 0.41 / (2311/10992) = 1.95</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Popular entry points and first steps</p>
    <p>Readers go straight to dissertations and stay there.Readers go straight to dissertations and stay there.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Paths taken to the dissertation template</p>
    <p>Authors stay in author content.Authors stay in author content.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pattern 1</p>
    <p>Pattern 2</p>
    <p>Pattern 3</p>
    <p>Of the visitors starting at a Public reading paper, 50% will stay within this subject area. The same observation can be made regarding Other-Other and Other-Project.</p>
    <p>Of the visitors starting at a Public reading paper, 50% will stay within this subject area. The same observation can be made regarding Other-Other and Other-Project.</p>
    <p>Navigation around other content</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>When people use the internal search engine, they then</p>
    <p>The first two patterns indicate that user dont find their target or a clue leading them towards it. They do not continue with search function but go back to home and come back to search page again. Only the last pattern indicates a successful search.</p>
    <p>The first two patterns indicate that user dont find their target or a clue leading them towards it. They do not continue with search function but go back to home and come back to search page again. Only the last pattern indicates a successful search.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary: A broken cycle of knowledge?</p>
    <p>Readers and contributors are distinct groups; readers are not led to accessing contributor content (at least not in a single session). Only few people use the internal search engine, and they do not experience structured search as an effective or efficient search option. o Supporting evidence from a separate questionnaire study</p>
    <p>The use of external search engines makes access to dissertation full-texts more likely.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What programs and interfaces can support authors and turn them into</p>
    <p>contributors?</p>
    <p>... and how can further data be gained for understanding and supporting the authoring process?</p>
    <p>An Intelligent Authoring Tool for creating semantics Prototype: focus on bibliography markup o core &amp; most error-prone part of template use in EDOC o bibliographic errors haunt science: Cardona &amp; Marx, 2004</p>
    <p>MS Word macro + information extraction (TTT, Grover, Matheson, Mikheev, &amp; Moens, 2000), distributed system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation: An error resulting from the use of MS Word + template (example)</p>
    <p>&lt;BIBLIOGRAPHY&gt;&lt;FLOAT&gt;&lt;PAGENUMBER&gt;136&lt;/PAGENUMBER&gt;&lt;/ FLOAT&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;HEAD&gt;Literaturverzeichnis&lt;/HEAD&gt; &lt;CITATION WORKTYPE=&quot;journal&quot; PUBLISHED=&quot;PUBLISHED&quot;&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;CUT ID=&quot;bib-15-&quot;&gt;[1] &lt;/CUT&gt;&lt;WORKAUTHOR&gt;Agarwal, R.; Krueger, B. P.; Scholes, G. D.; Yang, M.; Yom, J.; Mets, L.; Fleming, G. R.&lt;/WORKAUTHOR&gt;U&lt;ARTICLETITLE&gt;ltrafast energy transfer in LHC-II revealed by three-pulse photon echo peak shift measurements&lt;/ARTICLETITLE&gt;, &lt;WORKTITLE&gt;J. Phys. Chem. B&lt;/WORKTITLE&gt;, &lt;PUBDATE&gt;2000&lt;/PUBDATE&gt;, &lt;NUMBER&gt;104&lt;/NUMBER&gt;, &lt;PAGES&gt;2908&lt;/PAGES&gt;,</p>
    <p>&lt;/CITATION&gt; ...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Server MS Word</p>
    <p>VBA Makro Informat. extraction</p>
    <p>System architecture &amp; interface</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary, conclusions, &amp; outlook</p>
    <p>To encourage volunteer contributions: consider computational &amp; motivational &amp; institutional aspects! Extend Intelligent Authoring Tool: o extend bibliography functionality (citation styles, ...) o as Web service o integration of further text and link mining o laboratory user studies for first evaluation of tool o usage mining for continuous evaluation of tool</p>
    <p>We believe that our setting, incentive structures, and thus also our findings transfer to other KCVC efforts.</p>
    <p>What do you think?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgements</p>
    <p>I wish to thank</p>
    <p>Nikolai Abrossov, Elke Brenstein, Noppawan Bunyonasegana, Thomas Dammeier, Gebhard Dettmar, Altug Kul, Yunfan Li, Thomas Posner, Bert Wendland, Zhan Wu, and the Web mining seminar groups</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
