<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Knowledge-based Approach to Citation Extraction</p>
    <p>Min-Yuh Day1,2, Tzong-Han Tsai1,3, Cheng-Lung Sung1, Cheng-Wei Lee1, Shih-Hung Wu4, Chorng-Shyong Ong2, Wen-Lian</p>
    <p>Hsu1</p>
    <p>myday@iis.sinica.edu.tw IEEE IRI 2005</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Introduction  Proposed Approach  Experimental Results and Discussion  Related Works  Conclusions and Future Research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction  Integration of the bibliographical information of</p>
    <p>scholarly publications available on the Internet is an important task in academic research.</p>
    <p>Accurate reference metadata extraction for scholarly publications is essential for the integration of information from heterogeneous reference sources.</p>
    <p>We propose a knowledge-based approach to literature mining and focus on reference metadata extraction methods for scholarly publications.</p>
    <p>INFOMAP: ontological knowledge representation framework</p>
    <p>Automatically extract the reference metadata.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proposed Approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reference Data Collection  Journal Spider (journal agent)</p>
    <p>collect journal data from the Journal Citation Reports (JCR) indexed by the ISI and digital libraries on the Web.</p>
    <p>Citation data source  ISI web of science  DBLP  Citeseer  PubMed</p>
    <p>Phase 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Knowledge Representation in INFOMAP</p>
    <p>Phase 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>INFOMAP  INFOMAP as ontological knowledge</p>
    <p>representation framework  extracts important citation concepts from a natural</p>
    <p>language text.  Feature of INFOMAP</p>
    <p>represent and match complicated template structures  hierarchical matching  regular expressions  semantic template matching  frame (non-linear relations) matching  graph matching</p>
    <p>Using INFOMAP, we can extract author, title, journal, volume, number (issue), year, and page information from different kinds of reference formats or styles.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reference Metadata Extraction Journal Reference</p>
    <p>styles Reference style example</p>
    <p>Bioinformatics style (BIOI)</p>
    <p>Davenport, T., DeLong, D., &amp; Beers, M. (1998) Successful knowledge management projects. Sloan Management Review, 39(2), 43-57.</p>
    <p>ACM style (ACM)</p>
    <p>IEEE style (IEEE)</p>
    <p>[1] T. Davenport, D. DeLong, and M. Beers, &quot;Successful knowledge management projects,&quot; Sloan Management Review, vol. 39, no. 2, pp. 43-57, 1998.</p>
    <p>APA style (APA)</p>
    <p>Davenport, T., DeLong, D., &amp; Beers, M. (1998). Successful knowledge management projects. Sloan Management Review, 39(2), 43-57.</p>
    <p>JCB style (JCB)</p>
    <p>Davenport, T., DeLong, D., &amp; Beers, M. 1998. Successful knowledge management projects. Sloan Management Review 39(2), 43-57.</p>
    <p>MISQ style (MISQ)</p>
    <p>Davenport, T., DeLong, D., and Beers, M. &quot;Successful knowledge management projects,&quot; Sloan Management Review (39:2) 1998, pp 43-57.</p>
    <p>Table 1. Examples of different journal reference styles</p>
    <p>Phase 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Knowledge-based Reference Metadata Extraction - Online Service</p>
    <p>Phase 4</p>
    <p>http://bioinformatics.iis.sinica.edu.tw/CitationAgent/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Citation Extraction From Text to BixTex</p>
    <p>W. L. Hsu, &quot;The coloring and maximum independent set problems on planar perfect graphs,&quot; J. Assoc. Comput. Machin., (1988), 535-563.</p>
    <p>W. L. Hsu, &quot;On the general feasibility test of scheduling lot sizes for several products on one machine,&quot; Management Science 29, (1983), 93-105.</p>
    <p>W. L. Hsu, &quot;The distance-domination numbers of trees,&quot; Operations Research Letters 1, (3), (1982), 96-100.</p>
    <p>@article{ Author = {W. L. Hsu}, Title = {The coloring and maximum independent set problems on planar perfect graphs,&quot;}, Journal = {J. Assoc. Comput. Machin.}, Volume = {}, Number = {}, Pages = {535-563}, Year = {1988 }} @article{ Author = {W. L. Hsu}, Title = {On the general feasibility test of scheduling lot sizes for several products on one machine,&quot;}, Journal = {Management Science}, Volume = {29}, Number = {}, Pages = {93-105}, Year = {1983 }} @article{ Author = {W. L. Hsu}, Title = {The distance-domination numbers of trees,&quot;}, Journal = {Operations Research Letters}, Volume = {1}, Number = {3}, Pages = {96-100}, Year = {1982 }}</p>
    <p>Figure 5. The system output of BibTex Format</p>
    <p>Figure 3. The system input of knowledge-based RME</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Output</p>
    <p>Syste m Input (Plain text)</p>
    <p>Output BibTex</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Results and Discussion  Experimental data</p>
    <p>We used EndNote to collect Bioinformatics citation data for 2004 from PubMed.</p>
    <p>A total of 907 bibliography records were collected from PubMed digital libraries on the Web.</p>
    <p>Reference testing data was generated for each of the six reference styles (BIOI, ACM, IEEE, APA, MISQ, and JCB).</p>
    <p>Randomly selected 500 records for testing from each of the six reference styles.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Accuracy of Citation Extraction Definition:  We consider a field to be correctly</p>
    <p>extracted only when the field values in the reference testing data are correctly extracted.</p>
    <p>The accuracy of citation extraction is defined as follows:</p>
    <p>fieldsofnumberTotal</p>
    <p>fieldsextractedcorrectlyofNumber Accuracy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental results of citation extraction from six reference styles</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis of the structure of reference styles</p>
    <p>Field Field Relation Structure Percentage%</p>
    <p>Author &lt;Author&gt;&lt;Year&gt; 54.29%</p>
    <p>&lt;Author&gt;&lt;Title&gt; 42.86%</p>
    <p>N/A 2.85%</p>
    <p>Year &lt;Author&gt;&lt;Year&gt;&lt;Title&gt; 48.57%</p>
    <p>&lt;Journal&gt;&lt;Year&gt;&lt;Volume&gt; 20.00%</p>
    <p>&lt;Issue&gt;&lt;Year&gt;&lt;Pages&gt; 14.29%</p>
    <p>&lt;Author&gt;&lt;Year&gt;&lt;Journal&gt; 5.71%</p>
    <p>&lt;Pages&gt;&lt;Year&gt; 2.86%</p>
    <p>&lt;Volume&gt;&lt;Year&gt;&lt;Pages&gt; 2.86%</p>
    <p>N/A 5.71%</p>
    <p>Title &lt;Year&gt;&lt;Title&gt;&lt;Journal&gt; 48.57%</p>
    <p>&lt;Author&gt;&lt;Title&gt;&lt;Journal&gt; 42.86%</p>
    <p>N/A 8.57%</p>
    <p>Journal &lt;Title&gt;&lt;Journal&gt;&lt;Volume&gt; 71.43%</p>
    <p>&lt;Title&gt;&lt;Journal&gt;&lt;Year&gt; 20.00%</p>
    <p>&lt;Year&gt;&lt;Journal&gt;&lt;Volume&gt; 5.71%</p>
    <p>N/A 2.86%</p>
    <p>Volume &lt;Journal&gt;&lt;Volume&gt;&lt;Pages&gt; 40.00%</p>
    <p>&lt;Journal&gt;&lt;Volume&gt;&lt;Issue&gt; 31.43%</p>
    <p>&lt;Year&gt;&lt;Volume&gt;&lt;Issue&gt; 14.29%</p>
    <p>&lt;Year&gt;&lt;Volume&gt;&lt;Pages&gt; 5.71%</p>
    <p>&lt;Journal&gt;&lt;Volume&gt;&lt;Volume&gt; 2.86%</p>
    <p>&lt;Journal&gt;&lt;Volume&gt;&lt;Year&gt; 2.86%</p>
    <p>N/A 2.85%</p>
    <p>Issue &lt;Volume&gt;&lt;Issue&gt;&lt;Pages&gt; 34.29%</p>
    <p>&lt;Volume&gt;&lt;Issue&gt;&lt;Year&gt; 14.29%</p>
    <p>N/A 51.42%</p>
    <p>Pages &lt;Volume&gt;&lt;Pages&gt; 42.86%</p>
    <p>&lt;Issue&gt;&lt;Pages&gt; 34.29%</p>
    <p>&lt;Year&gt;&lt;Pages&gt; 17.14%</p>
    <p>&lt;Volume&gt;&lt;Pages&gt;&lt;Year&gt; 2.86%</p>
    <p>N/A 2.85%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Works  Machine learning approaches</p>
    <p>Citeseer [8, 9, 12] take advantage of probabilistic estimation, which is based on the training sets of tagged bibliographical data, to boost performance.</p>
    <p>The citation parsing technique of Citeseer can identify titles and authors with approximately 80% accuracy and page numbers with approximately 40% accuracy.</p>
    <p>Seymore et al. [15] use the Hidden Markov Model (HMM) to extract important fields from the headers of computer science research papers</p>
    <p>Achieve an overall word accuracy of 92.9%  Peng et al. [14] employ Conditional Random Fields (CRF)</p>
    <p>to extract various common fields from the headers and citations of research papers.</p>
    <p>Achieve an overall word accuracy of 85.1%(HMM) compared to 95.37%(CRF) and an overall instance accuracy of 10%(HMM) compared to 77.33%(CRF) for paper references.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Works (Cont.)  Rule-based models</p>
    <p>Chowdhury [3] and Ding et al. [5], use a template mining approach for citation extraction from digital documents.</p>
    <p>Ding et al. [5] use three templates for extracting information from cited articles (citations) and obtain a quite satisfactory result (more than 90%) for the distribution of information extracted from each unit in cited articles.</p>
    <p>The advantage of their rule-based model is its efficiency in extracting reference information.</p>
    <p>However, they treat references in one style only from tagged texts (e.g., references formatted in HTML), whereas our method treats references in more than six reference styles from plain text.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparison with related works  Knowledge-based approach</p>
    <p>Our proposed knowledge-based RME method for scholarly publications can extract reference information from 907 records in various reference styles with a high degree of precision</p>
    <p>the overall average field accuracy is 97.87% for six major styles listed in Table 1</p>
    <p>98.20% for the MISQ style  87% for other 30 randomly selected styles</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions  Citation extraction is a challenging problem</p>
    <p>The diverse nature of reference styles  We have proposed a knowledge-based</p>
    <p>citation extraction method for scholarly publications.</p>
    <p>The experimental results indicate that, by using INFOMAP, we can extract author, title, journal, volume, number (issue), year, and page information from different reference styles with a high degree of precision.  The overall average field accuracy of citation</p>
    <p>extraction is 97.87% for six major reference styles.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Research  Integrate the ontological and the</p>
    <p>machine learning approaches to boost the performance of citation information extraction  Maximum-Entropy Method (MEM)  Hidden Markov Model (HMM)  Conditional Random Fields (CRF)  Support Vector Machines (SVM)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Q &amp; A A Knowledge-based Approach to</p>
    <p>Citation Extraction</p>
    <p>Min-Yuh Day1,2, Tzong-Han Tsai1,3, Cheng-Lung Sung1, Cheng-Wei Lee1, Shih-Hung Wu4, Chorng-Shyong Ong2, Wen-Lian Hsu1</p>
    <p>myday@iis.sinica.edu.tw</p>
    <p>IEEE IRI 2005</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
