<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HICSS 36HICSS 36</p>
    <p>On the e-Negotiation of On the e-Negotiation of Unmatched Logrolling ViewsUnmatched Logrolling Views</p>
    <p>Presenter Presenter S.C. Cheung S.C. Cheung scc@cs.ust.hkscc@cs.ust.hk</p>
    <p>Department of Computer ScienceDepartment of Computer Science Hong Kong University of Science and TechnologyHong Kong University of Science and Technology</p>
    <p>Co-authors Co-authors Patrick C.K. Hung Patrick C.K. Hung Patrick.Hung@csiro.auPatrick.Hung@csiro.au Dickson K.W. Chiu Dickson K.W. Chiu kwchiu@cse.cuhk.hkkwchiu@cse.cuhk.hk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OutlineOutline</p>
    <p>IntroductionIntroduction</p>
    <p>Motivating ExampleMotivating Example</p>
    <p>Offers MakingOffers Making</p>
    <p>Offers MatchingOffers Matching</p>
    <p>Tradeoff EvaluationTradeoff Evaluation</p>
    <p>Offer AcceptanceOffer Acceptance</p>
    <p>e-Negotiation Process Modele-Negotiation Process Model</p>
    <p>Conclusion &amp; Future WorkConclusion &amp; Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contract Template &amp; IssuesContract Template &amp; Issues Successful negotiation leads to a contract.Successful negotiation leads to a contract. Standard contract templates exist for common business Standard contract templates exist for common business interactions.interactions.</p>
    <p>A contract template defines the scope of a contract and A contract template defines the scope of a contract and summarizes the issues to be negotiated.summarizes the issues to be negotiated.</p>
    <p>This lease will start on &lt;DATE&gt; and last for &lt;PERIOD&gt; year(s). The This lease will start on &lt;DATE&gt; and last for &lt;PERIOD&gt; year(s). The property will be rented with/without* facilities. Tenant is required to pay property will be rented with/without* facilities. Tenant is required to pay landlord a monthly rent of &lt;RENT&gt;. The rent includes/excludes* the landlord a monthly rent of &lt;RENT&gt;. The rent includes/excludes* the management fee. management fee.  Example of a lease contract templateExample of a lease contract template</p>
    <p>Issues: DATE, PERIOD, RENT, facilities provision, management fee Issues: DATE, PERIOD, RENT, facilities provision, management fee inclusion, inclusion,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LogrollingLogrolling</p>
    <p>Negotiation is an iterative process deciding acceptable Negotiation is an iterative process deciding acceptable values of these issues.values of these issues.  In each iteration, a party performs tradeoff evaluation across In each iteration, a party performs tradeoff evaluation across</p>
    <p>various issues and make offers/counter-offers.various issues and make offers/counter-offers.  Tradeoff evaluation often requires logrolling  the exchange of Tradeoff evaluation often requires logrolling  the exchange of</p>
    <p>loss in some issues for gain in others.loss in some issues for gain in others.</p>
    <p>Problems:Problems:  What if utility functions that precisely define tradeoff evaluation What if utility functions that precisely define tradeoff evaluation</p>
    <p>are unavailable?are unavailable?  What if each negotiation party adopts a different tradeoff What if each negotiation party adopts a different tradeoff</p>
    <p>evaluation model, resulting in unmatched logrolling views?evaluation model, resulting in unmatched logrolling views?  How to match unmatched logrolling views?How to match unmatched logrolling views?  Can privacy of individual logrolling views be protected?Can privacy of individual logrolling views be protected?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivating Example - LeaseMotivating Example - Lease Period Facilities</p>
    <p>Facilities Allowance</p>
    <p>Start Date</p>
    <p>Basic Rent</p>
    <p>Period</p>
    <p>Facilities</p>
    <p>Facilities Allowance</p>
    <p>Start Date</p>
    <p>Basic Rent</p>
    <p>Landlord</p>
    <p>Tenant</p>
    <p>Mgt Fee</p>
    <p>Mgt Fee Allowance</p>
    <p>Mgt Fee</p>
    <p>Mgt Fee Allowance</p>
    <p>Logrolling Sets</p>
    <p>Rent</p>
    <p>Rent</p>
    <p>f: { Rent = Basic Rent + Facilities Allowance + Mgt Fee Allowance }</p>
    <p>L o</p>
    <p>g ro</p>
    <p>llin g V</p>
    <p>ie w</p>
    <p>o f T</p>
    <p>e n</p>
    <p>a n t</p>
    <p>L o</p>
    <p>g ro</p>
    <p>llin g V</p>
    <p>ie w</p>
    <p>o f L</p>
    <p>a n</p>
    <p>d lo</p>
    <p>rd</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Logrolling View of LandlordLogrolling View of Landlord</p>
    <p>The landlords primary concern is to let the flat as The landlords primary concern is to let the flat as early as possible.early as possible. Provision of facilities is negotiable subjected to a Provision of facilities is negotiable subjected to a longer lease and some increase in rent.longer lease and some increase in rent. The inclusion of estate management fee is The inclusion of estate management fee is negotiable subjected to some increase in rent.negotiable subjected to some increase in rent.</p>
    <p>Period Facilities</p>
    <p>Facilities Allowance</p>
    <p>Start Date</p>
    <p>Basic Rent</p>
    <p>Landlord</p>
    <p>Mgt Fee</p>
    <p>Mgt Fee Allowance</p>
    <p>Rent</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Logrolling View of TenantLogrolling View of Tenant</p>
    <p>The tenants primary concern is to have a The tenants primary concern is to have a shorter lease, leaving flexibility for potential job shorter lease, leaving flexibility for potential job relocation.relocation.</p>
    <p>Willing to pay a higher rent if facilities and/or Willing to pay a higher rent if facilities and/or estate management fee are included. estate management fee are included.</p>
    <p>Period</p>
    <p>Facilities</p>
    <p>Facilities Allowance</p>
    <p>Start Date</p>
    <p>Basic Rent</p>
    <p>Tenant</p>
    <p>Mgt Fee</p>
    <p>Mgt Fee Allowance</p>
    <p>Rent</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to Evaluate Tradeoffs?How to Evaluate Tradeoffs?</p>
    <p>Landlord</p>
    <p>Tenant</p>
    <p>logrolling sets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exchanging Offers in Unmatched ViewsExchanging Offers in Unmatched Views</p>
    <p>Period Basic Rent 1 yr 18K 2 yrs 17K</p>
    <p>Start Date Facilities Facilities Allowance</p>
    <p>Mgt Fee Mgt Fee Allowance Excluded 0 Included 1K</p>
    <p>Start Date Basic Rent 1M 19K 2M 20K 3M 21K</p>
    <p>Facilities Period Facilities Allowance Excluded 1 yr 0 Included 2 yrs 2K</p>
    <p>Mgt Fee Mgt Fee Allowance Excluded 0 Included 1K</p>
    <p>Start Date Facilities Lease Period Mgt Fee Rent</p>
    <p>Logrolling Sets Offer by means of Aggregated View</p>
    <p>e-Negotiation Support System (eNSS)</p>
    <p>Negotiation Party</p>
    <p>Negotiation Party</p>
    <p>e-Negotiation Support System (eNSS)</p>
    <p>Start Date Facilities Period Mgt Fee Rentlandlord Renttenant Rentdif=(Rentlandlord</p>
    <p>- Renttenant)</p>
    <p>Start Date Facilities Lease Period Mgt Fee Rent</p>
    <p>Aggregated View Aggregated View</p>
    <p>Logrolling Sets</p>
    <p>Offer Matching Table</p>
    <p>Logrolling Sets</p>
    <p>Logrolling Sets</p>
    <p>Tradeoff evaluation In Logrolling View</p>
    <p>Tradeoff evaluation In Logrolling View</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Construction of Aggregated ViewConstruction of Aggregated View</p>
    <p>Given N logrolling sets LGiven N logrolling sets L11, L, L22, , L, , LNN Aggregrated View = f(LAggregrated View = f(L11 x L x L22 x  x L x  x LNN))</p>
    <p>f: Rent = Basic Rent + Facilities Allowance + Mgt Fee Allowance</p>
    <p>An entry in aggregated view</p>
    <p>Cartesian Product</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Start Date Facilities Lease Period Mgt Fee Rent</p>
    <p>Aggregated View due to LandlordAggregated View due to Landlord</p>
    <p>Start Date Basic Rent 1M 19K 2M 20K 3M 21K</p>
    <p>Facilities Period Facilities Allowance Excluded 1 yr 0 Included 2 yrs 2K</p>
    <p>Mgt Fee Mgt Fee Allowance Excluded 0 Included 1K</p>
    <p>Logrolling Sets of Landlords Offer</p>
    <p>Aggregated View</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Aggregated View due to TenantAggregated View due to Tenant</p>
    <p>Period Basic Rent 1 yr 18K 2 yrs 17K</p>
    <p>Start Date Facilities Facilities Allowance</p>
    <p>Mgt Fee Mgt Fee Allowance Excluded 0 Included 1K</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Offer Matching TableOffer Matching Table Start Date Facilities Period Mgt Fee Rentlandlord Renttenant Rentdif=(Rentlandlord</p>
    <p>- Renttenant)</p>
    <p>Merging two aggregated</p>
    <p>views</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tradeoff Evaluation by TenantTradeoff Evaluation by Tenant</p>
    <p>Tradeoff evaluation is an Tradeoff evaluation is an iterative process.iterative process.</p>
    <p>In each iteration, party picks In each iteration, party picks the most concerned logrolling the most concerned logrolling set which has not yet set which has not yet evaluated.evaluated.</p>
    <p>Map entries in the offer Map entries in the offer matching table to the matching table to the logrolling set.logrolling set.</p>
    <p>Period</p>
    <p>Basic Rent</p>
    <p>Entries in the original logrolling set supplied by Tenants</p>
    <p>Minimum difference in each combination of template variables in offer matching table</p>
    <p>Most concerned logrolling set</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Revision of Reservation PricesRevision of Reservation Prices</p>
    <p>Revise reservation prices, if applicable.Revise reservation prices, if applicable.</p>
    <p>Proceed to further tradeoff evaluation Proceed to further tradeoff evaluation based on an entry, which has or has not based on an entry, which has or has not been revised.been revised.</p>
    <p>Period Basic Rent Min Diference 1 yr 18K  19K 2K  1K 2 yrs 17K 2K</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Further Tradeoff EvaluationFurther Tradeoff Evaluation</p>
    <p>Combinations not found in the original logrolling set</p>
    <p>Combinations not found in counterpartys offer</p>
    <p>Possible options</p>
    <p>Evaluation based on Period = 1 year and Basic Rent = 19K</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tradeoff Evaluation ScenarioTradeoff Evaluation Scenario</p>
    <p>A scenario of tradeoff A scenario of tradeoff evaluation can be evaluation can be represented in a tree.represented in a tree.</p>
    <p>A party evaluates A party evaluates his/her logrolling sets his/her logrolling sets in turn.in turn.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tradeoff Evaluation ScenariosTradeoff Evaluation Scenarios</p>
    <p>A party may A party may arbitrarily change arbitrarily change its evaluation order its evaluation order of logrolling sets.of logrolling sets. A party evaluates A party evaluates tradeoff and tradeoff and revises its revises its reservation prices reservation prices based on their based on their individual logrolling individual logrolling views.views.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Candidate Acceptable OfferCandidate Acceptable Offer</p>
    <p>Successful negotiation results in a set of acceptable Successful negotiation results in a set of acceptable offersoffers Selection of each offer leads to a contract.Selection of each offer leads to a contract.    The lease will start on June 20, 2002 and last for two The lease will start on June 20, 2002 and last for two</p>
    <p>years. The property will be rented with facilities. Tenant is years. The property will be rented with facilities. Tenant is required to pay landlord a monthly rent of $20,000. The required to pay landlord a monthly rent of $20,000. The rent excludes the management fee. rent excludes the management fee.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Candidate Acceptable OfferCandidate Acceptable Offer</p>
    <p>The first acceptable offer represents The first acceptable offer represents  Landlord compromises the rent (21KLandlord compromises the rent (21K20K) but enjoys the 20K) but enjoys the</p>
    <p>gain (1M early start date &amp; 2 yrs long lease).gain (1M early start date &amp; 2 yrs long lease).  Tenants compromises the lease period (1yrTenants compromises the lease period (1yr2yrs) but 2yrs) but</p>
    <p>enjoys the gain (comfortable rent).enjoys the gain (comfortable rent).</p>
    <p>This is a win-win situation after a logrolling process.This is a win-win situation after a logrolling process.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Negotiation ProcessNegotiation Process</p>
    <p>select e-Contract template</p>
    <p>identify logrolling issues</p>
    <p>define issues and criteria</p>
    <p>make offers &amp; counter offers</p>
    <p>validate consistency</p>
    <p>introduce auxiliary variables &amp;</p>
    <p>specify relations</p>
    <p>[all issues have been mapped]</p>
    <p>[consistent]</p>
    <p>[inconsistent]</p>
    <p>creation of e-Contract</p>
    <p>[reach consensus on all reservation prices]</p>
    <p>[quit]</p>
    <p>map issues to variables</p>
    <p>organize logrolling views</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ConclusionConclusion We have proposed a pragmatic approach to We have proposed a pragmatic approach to negotiation under unmatched logrolling views.negotiation under unmatched logrolling views. It does not require the use of utility functions and It does not require the use of utility functions and normative models.normative models. It does not require any exchanges of logrolling It does not require any exchanges of logrolling views between negotiation parties. This facilitates views between negotiation parties. This facilitates privacy of logrolling views, which represents privacy of logrolling views, which represents individuals tradeoff evaluation model.individuals tradeoff evaluation model. A prototype is being built based on the approach A prototype is being built based on the approach proposed.proposed.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future WorkFuture Work</p>
    <p>To investigate multi-lateral negotiations.To investigate multi-lateral negotiations.</p>
    <p>To support changes of logrolling views during To support changes of logrolling views during negotiation.negotiation.</p>
    <p>To apply the approach to other work [1,2,3,4,5]. To apply the approach to other work [1,2,3,4,5].</p>
    <p>(HICSS-36), January 2003.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions and AnswersQuestions and Answers</p>
    <p>scc@cs.ust.hkscc@cs.ust.hk</p>
    <p>Patrick.Hung@csiro.auPatrick.Hung@csiro.au</p>
    <p>kwchiu@cse.cuhk.hkkwchiu@cse.cuhk.hk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Meta-modelMeta-model</p>
    <p>Template Variable</p>
    <p>Party Negotiation Process</p>
    <p>Accepted Reservation Price</p>
    <p>Reservation Price</p>
    <p>makes</p>
    <p>holds</p>
    <p>*</p>
    <p>involves</p>
    <p>Issue 1</p>
    <p>Contract</p>
    <p>Auxiliary Variable</p>
    <p>relates to Variable</p>
    <p>Accepted Offer</p>
    <p>maps to</p>
    <p>Offer</p>
    <p>e-Contract Conceptual</p>
    <p>Model</p>
    <p>e-Negotiation Conceptual</p>
    <p>Model</p>
    <p>* *</p>
    <p>resolves 1..*Task 1</p>
    <p>Logrolling Set</p>
    <p>Logrolling View</p>
    <p>maps to 1 1</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
