<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Location Privacy Preservation in Collaborative Spe ctrum Sensing</p>
    <p>Shuai Li, Haojin Zhu, Zhaoyu Gao, Xinping Guan,</p>
    <p>Shanghai Jiao Tong University</p>
    <p>Kai Xing</p>
    <p>University of Science and Technology of China</p>
    <p>and Xuemin (Sherman) Shen</p>
    <p>University of Waterloo</p>
    <p>Presenter: Haojin Zhu</p>
    <p>Associate Professor</p>
    <p>Computer Science &amp; Engineering Department</p>
    <p>Shanghai Jiao Tong University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background  Cognitive Radio Networks  Spectrum Sensing  Collaborative Spectrum Sensing</p>
    <p>Existing Researches on Spectrum Sensing Security  Location Privacy Leaking Problem  Privacy Preserving Collaborative Spectrum Sensing  Experiment Results  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cognitive Radio</p>
    <p>Primary User (PU) PU uses the spectrum exclusively</p>
    <p>SUs can access the idle spectrum Secondary User (SU)</p>
    <p>Traditional Spectrum Allocation</p>
    <p>Cognitive Radio</p>
    <p>Cognitive Radio is proposed to increase the efficiency of channel utilization under the current static channel allocation policy.</p>
    <p>Cognitive Radio  access the spectrum dynamicallyCognitive Radio  access the spectrum dynamically</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spectrum Sensing</p>
    <p>Spectrum Sensing  In order to identify the idle spectrum, secondary users should sense the spectrum first.</p>
    <p>Spectrum 1</p>
    <p>Spectrum 2</p>
    <p>Spectrum n</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>Which one is idle?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Collaborative Spectrum Sensing</p>
    <p>But, spectrum sensing accuracy</p>
    <p>is often degraded by:</p>
    <p>Fading Shadowing</p>
    <p>Receiver Uncertainty</p>
    <p>Collaborative Spectrum Sensing is proposed to overcome these challenges.</p>
    <p>Step1: SUs sense the spectrum individually</p>
    <p>Step2: SUs submit the sensing reports to a fusion center</p>
    <p>Step3: Fusion center combines these reportsCollaborative sensing is also</p>
    <p>facing a series of security threats!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Existing Research in Spectrum Sensing Security</p>
    <p>1 Attack: Primary Emulation Attack</p>
    <p>(JSAC'08, Oakland S&amp;P'10, )  2 Attack: Sensing Data Falsification Attack</p>
    <p>(INFOCOM'08, TMC 2011, NDSS 2011)  3 Attack: Selfishness in Collaborative Sensing</p>
    <p>(ACM MC2R)</p>
    <p>None of existing works consider the privacy issues in CR networks before!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background  The Location Privacy Leaking Problem  Privacy Preserving collaborative Spectrum Sensing</p>
    <p>Privacy Preserving Sensing Report Aggregation  Distributed Dummy Report Injection Protocol</p>
    <p>Experiment Results  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exploiting Spectrum Sensing Reports for Involuntar y Geo-localization- An Attacker Point of View</p>
    <p>The Good Side: Exploit spatial diversity for spectrum sensing</p>
    <p>A Converse Question: Could we exploit correlation of CR sensing reports and their physical location to make an involuntary geo-localization of SU.</p>
    <p>SU</p>
    <p>SU</p>
    <p>SU</p>
    <p>SU</p>
    <p>Different Locations Correspond to Different Sensing Reports due to Spatial Diversity.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack I: Single Report Location Privacy (SRLP) Attack</p>
    <p>Test bed Setup and Experiment Approach: 1. Using USRP to detect the TV radio signal of 13 sampling regions. 2. The attacker using classification algorithm to obtain spectrum characteristics</p>
    <p>of each region (the cluster centroids). 3. Geo-localization a user by comparing the distance of the sensing data and the</p>
    <p>various cluster centroids.</p>
    <p>Single Report Location Privacy (SRLP) Attack: the adversary tries to compromise the location privacy of a CR user by correlating his sensing report and physical location.</p>
    <p>Single Report Location Privacy (SRLP) Attack: the adversary tries to compromise the location privacy of a CR user by correlating his sensing report and physical location.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attack II: Differential Location Privacy Attack in Aggregation Mode</p>
    <p>Inspired from database security concept, differential privacy. In the context of CR security: Untrusted Fusion Center (Aggregator), secondary users may frequently join or leave the networks</p>
    <p>Inspired from database security concept, differential privacy. In the context of CR security: Untrusted Fusion Center (Aggregator), secondary users may frequently join or leave the networks</p>
    <p>We could get , then based on SRLP attack, we could infer its location. We could get , then based on SRLP attack, we could infer its location.</p>
    <p>Aggregation Result: Aggregation Result: Even under the</p>
    <p>presence of privacy preserving</p>
    <p>aggregation solution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Results for the Attack</p>
    <p>Result I: Significant location-dependent fluctuation in the RSS sensing of three Digital TV (DTV) channels.</p>
    <p>Result I: Significant location-dependent fluctuation in the RSS sensing of three Digital TV (DTV) channels.</p>
    <p>Result II: the attackers could localize a user within 10-50 meters accuracy with 90% successful rate by choosing a proper parameter</p>
    <p>Result II: the attackers could localize a user within 10-50 meters accuracy with 90% successful rate by choosing a proper parameter</p>
    <p>How to enable the collaborative spectrum sensing without location privacy leaking? How to enable the collaborative spectrum sensing without location privacy leaking?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Formal Definition on Location Privacy in Collaborative Spectrum Sensing</p>
    <p>We define the uncertainty of the adversary and thus the location privacy level of a node involved in a successful privacy preserving spectrum sensing by adopting the entropy concept as follows:</p>
    <p>We define the uncertainty of the adversary and thus the location privacy level of a node involved in a successful privacy preserving spectrum sensing by adopting the entropy concept as follows:</p>
    <p>Total number of regions</p>
    <p>the probability that user a is located in the</p>
    <p>region b</p>
    <p>If the attacker could uniquely identify the location of the user, we can get and . Otherwise, the entropy is maximum for a uniform probability distribution .</p>
    <p>If the attacker could uniquely identify the location of the user, we can get and . Otherwise, the entropy is maximum for a uniform probability distribution .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background  The Location Privacy Leaking Problem  Privacy Preserving collaborative Spectrum Sensing</p>
    <p>Privacy Preserving Sensing Report Aggregation  Distributed Dummy Report Injection Protocol</p>
    <p>Experiment Results  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Preserving collaborative Spectrum Sensi ng (PPSS)</p>
    <p>Conceal each users sensing reports in aggregation (thwarting SRLP attack)</p>
    <p>Conceal the users sensing reports when he leaves or joins the aggregation (thwarting the DLP attack)</p>
    <p>Privacy Preserving Sensing Report Aggregation Protocol (PPSRA)</p>
    <p>Privacy Preserving Sensing Report Aggregation Protocol (PPSRA)</p>
    <p>Distributed Dummy Report Injection protocol (DDRI)</p>
    <p>Distributed Dummy Report Injection protocol (DDRI)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protocol I: PPSRA Objective: Allowing the aggregator to obtain the aggregation results without knowing the</p>
    <p>individual sensing report.</p>
    <p>E() is an homomorphic encryption such as Paillier or NDSS11[1].</p>
    <p>Each data is encrypted by multiplying to prevent aggregator from recovering the individual</p>
    <p>data. By letting , we obtain .</p>
    <p>Objective: Allowing the aggregator to obtain the aggregation results without knowing the</p>
    <p>individual sensing report.</p>
    <p>E() is an homomorphic encryption such as Paillier or NDSS11[1].</p>
    <p>Each data is encrypted by multiplying to prevent aggregator from recovering the individual</p>
    <p>data. By letting , we obtain .</p>
    <p>Phase II:</p>
    <p>Multiplying the encrypted data</p>
    <p>Aggregation Result</p>
    <p>Phase III:</p>
    <p>Decryption for the result</p>
    <p>Decrypt it for the aggregation result.</p>
    <p>Phase I:</p>
    <p>Individual Encryption</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protocol II: Distributed Dummy Report Injection protocol (DDRI)</p>
    <p>Differential Location Privacy Attack:</p>
    <p>Traditional differential privacy protection approach needs to add a large noise to the sensing reports, which will seriously degrade the collaborative sensing performance, obviously deviating from the original goal of collaboration.</p>
    <p>Traditional differential privacy protection approach needs to add a large noise to the sensing reports, which will seriously degrade the collaborative sensing performance, obviously deviating from the original goal of collaboration.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distributed Dummy Report Injection protocol</p>
    <p>Our Approach:</p>
    <p>Our dummy report based approach will not pollute the aggregation result. Our dummy report based approach will not pollute the aggregation result.</p>
    <p>Broadcast the fusion centers sensing results</p>
    <p>Send his own sensing results</p>
    <p>Send the centers sensing results</p>
    <p>LEAVE/JOIN</p>
    <p>Using some public available sensing data (dummy report) to replace the noises</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>i1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distributed Dummy Report Injection protocol</p>
    <p>The introduced randomness in aggregation result can successfully confuse the attacker.</p>
    <p>The introduced randomness in aggregation result can successfully confuse the attacker.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distributed Dummy Report Injection protocol</p>
    <p>Question 1: How much randomness has been introduced?</p>
    <p>Question 2: Whats the impact introduced to collaborative sensing (the actual number of the sensing nodes)?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distributed Dummy Report Injection protocol</p>
    <p>Question 3: Whats the impact introduced to collaborative sensing (the weight of the dummy report)?</p>
    <p>In general, we will demonstrate that our scheme can generate sufficient randomness to protect the users differential location privacy. It has limited impact on collaborative sensing performance</p>
    <p>In general, we will demonstrate that our scheme can generate sufficient randomness to protect the users differential location privacy. It has limited impact on collaborative sensing performance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background  The Location Privacy Leaking Problem  Privacy Preserving collaborative Spectrum Sensing</p>
    <p>Privacy Preserving Sensing Report Aggregation  Distributed Dummy Report Injection Protocol</p>
    <p>Experiment Results  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
    <p>After executing our PPSS protocol, the entropy rises to a high level. This demonstrate that PPSS can well protect the users location privacy.</p>
    <p>After executing our PPSS protocol, the entropy rises to a high level. This demonstrate that PPSS can well protect the users location privacy.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
    <p>It demonstrates that a small is enough to protect the users location privacy. Meanwhile, a small means little impact on collaborative sensing.</p>
    <p>It demonstrates that a small is enough to protect the users location privacy. Meanwhile, a small means little impact on collaborative sensing.</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>i</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
    <p>This experiment result further demonstrates the practicality of our PPSS protocol. This experiment result further demonstrates the practicality of our PPSS protocol.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background  The Location Privacy Leaking Problem  Privacy Preserving collaborative Spectrum Sensing</p>
    <p>Privacy Preserving Sensing Report Aggregation  Distributed Dummy Report Injection Protocol</p>
    <p>Experiment Results  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion and Future Work</p>
    <p>We identify and formulate a new security threat i n collaborative sensing</p>
    <p>We introduce PPSS to protect secondary users lo cation privacy in collaborative sensing.</p>
    <p>We evaluate the effectiveness and efficiency of P PSS by implementation in a real experiment.</p>
    <p>Our future work includes investigating the privac y issues in database-driven CR networks.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
