<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Finding Small Changes Using Sensor Networks</p>
    <p>Kaoru Hiramatsu, Takashi Hattori, Tatsumi Yamada, and Takeshi Okadome</p>
    <p>Communication Science Labs. hiramatu@cslab.kecl.ntt.co.jp</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background and Motivation Our Experiment</p>
    <p>Prototype sensor nodes Finding small changes using a sensor network</p>
    <p>Conclusion / Discussion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Ubiquitous Computing</p>
    <p>Next comes ubiquitous computing, or the age of calm technology, when technology recedes into the background of our lives. - M.Weiser</p>
    <p>Smart Environment Assists Daily Life actualized by small sensors and networks Not only factories and hospitals but also home and office.</p>
    <p>Target: context-aware applications in home and office</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation Context-aware applications need contexts</p>
    <p>In home and office, hard to abstract contexts because a system might observe various behaviors that relate to many objects.</p>
    <p>We describe contexts based on small changes of sensor data captured by sensor nodes attached to objects</p>
    <p>noise</p>
    <p>blocks movingdesk</p>
    <p>moving</p>
    <p>book openchairmoving</p>
    <p>desk work playing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>Sensor A</p>
    <p>Sensor B</p>
    <p>+th -th</p>
    <p>+th -th</p>
    <p>P(A),P(B)</p>
    <p>P(A,B)</p>
    <p>Small changes in Sensor Data Change within a time window exceeds threshold</p>
    <p>Small change</p>
    <p>Calculate change probabilities and co-change probabilities</p>
    <p>Apply several of time windows and check small changes</p>
    <p>- Easy calculation using low CPU power - Possible to pack data into small packets</p>
    <p>(better for network load)</p>
    <p>Advantages: Disadvantages:</p>
    <p>- Need to add knowledge to data (small changes and sets)</p>
    <p>- Discarding wave characteristics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Setting</p>
    <p>Sensor floor system</p>
    <p>Chair with sensor nodeDoor with sensor node</p>
    <p>m 1.</p>
    <p>Sensor nodeSensor nodeSensor nodeSensor node</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prototype Sensor Node</p>
    <p>m</p>
    <p>XPort Ethernet Controller</p>
    <p>Thermometer, Hygrometer</p>
    <p>Infrared Sensor</p>
    <p>Illuminometer</p>
    <p>Accelerometer</p>
    <p>Prototype Sensor Node</p>
    <p>with embedded CPU H8/36049HG (ROM 96 K, RAM 4K, 10MHz)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>m 1.</p>
    <p>(a) Sensor Data (Door) (b) Sensor Data (Floor)</p>
    <p>Sensor Data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Change Probabilities of One Sensor</p>
    <p>Time window (sec.)</p>
    <p>Changed sensor</p>
    <p>Change and co-change probabilities of chair sensor data</p>
    <p>A chair is moving. An individual is sitting</p>
    <p>A chair is moving. An individual is sitting</p>
    <p>Finding events by analyzing sequences: Infrared, then Acc. An individual sat. Acc., then Infrared An individual left.</p>
    <p>Finding events by analyzing sequences: Infrared, then Acc. An individual sat. Acc., then Infrared An individual left.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Co-change Probabilities among Sensors</p>
    <p>Time window (sec.)</p>
    <p>Changed Sensor</p>
    <p>Change and co-change probabilities of sensor data of chair, door, and floor</p>
    <p>Hints for contexts: - Door moved, then chair moved</p>
    <p>Individual started working - Chair moved, then door moved</p>
    <p>Individual left office</p>
    <p>Inferring distance between objects: distance(chair,door) &gt; distance(chair,floor)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion / Discussion Preliminary results:</p>
    <p>Small changes translated into contexts by adding object and situational knowledge</p>
    <p>Discussion Index of change probabilites Is small change sufficient? How large of knowledge is necessary? How many sensor nodes in an office?</p>
    <p>noise</p>
    <p>blocks moving</p>
    <p>desk moving</p>
    <p>book openchairmoving</p>
    <p>desk work playing</p>
    <p>Sensor network Signal processing</p>
    <p>Reasoning with knowledge</p>
    <p>Context-aware applications</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
