<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Relevance Feedback based on Parameter based on Parameter Estimation of Target Estimation of Target</p>
    <p>DistributionDistribution</p>
    <p>K. C. SiaK. C. Sia and Irwin King and Irwin King Department of Computer Science &amp; EngineeringDepartment of Computer Science &amp; Engineering</p>
    <p>The Chinese University of Hong KongThe Chinese University of Hong Kong</p>
    <p>IJCNN 2002IJCNN 2002</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>AgendaAgenda</p>
    <p>Introduction to content based image Introduction to content based image retrieval (CBIR) and relevance retrieval (CBIR) and relevance feedback (RF)feedback (RF)</p>
    <p>Former approachesFormer approaches  Tackling the problemTackling the problem</p>
    <p>Parameter estimation of target Parameter estimation of target distributiondistribution</p>
    <p>ExperimentsExperiments  Future works and conclusionFuture works and conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Content Based Image Content Based Image RetrievalRetrieval</p>
    <p>How to represent an image?How to represent an image?  Feature extractionFeature extraction</p>
    <p>Colour histogram Colour histogram (RGB)(RGB)  Co-occurrence matrix texture analysisCo-occurrence matrix texture analysis  Shape representationShape representation</p>
    <p>Feature vectorFeature vector  Map images to points in hyper-spaceMap images to points in hyper-space  Similarity is based on distance measureSimilarity is based on distance measure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Feature Extraction ModelFeature Extraction Model</p>
    <p>R</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>G</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Relevance FeedbackRelevance Feedback</p>
    <p>Relevance feedbackRelevance feedback  Architecture to capture users target of Architecture to capture users target of</p>
    <p>searchsearch  Learning processLearning process</p>
    <p>Two stepsTwo steps  FeedbackFeedback  how to learn from the  how to learn from the</p>
    <p>users relevance feedbackusers relevance feedback  DisplayDisplay  how to select the next set of  how to select the next set of</p>
    <p>documents and present to userdocuments and present to user</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>User Feedback</p>
    <p>Display</p>
    <p>Display</p>
    <p>User Feedback</p>
    <p>Estimation &amp; Display selection</p>
    <p>Feedback to system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Former ApproachesFormer Approaches</p>
    <p>Multimedia Analysis and Retrieval System Multimedia Analysis and Retrieval System (MARS)(MARS)  Yong Rui et al. Relevance feedback: A powerful tool for Yong Rui et al. Relevance feedback: A powerful tool for</p>
    <p>interactive content-based image retrieval. - 1998interactive content-based image retrieval. - 1998  Using weight to capture users preferenceUsing weight to capture users preference</p>
    <p>Pic-HunterPic-Hunter  Ingemar J. Cox et al. The Bayesian image retrieval system, Ingemar J. Cox et al. The Bayesian image retrieval system,</p>
    <p>pichunter, theory, implementation, and psychophysical pichunter, theory, implementation, and psychophysical experiments. - 2000experiments. - 2000</p>
    <p>Images are associated with a probability being Images are associated with a probability being the users targetthe users target</p>
    <p>Bayesian learningBayesian learning</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>ComparisonComparison</p>
    <p>MARSMARS Pic-HunterPic-Hunter Our approachOur approach</p>
    <p>Capturing Capturing users target users target of searchof search</p>
    <p>Weight on Weight on different feature different feature and dimensionand dimension</p>
    <p>Probability Probability associated associated with imageswith images</p>
    <p>Estimated Estimated parameter of parameter of target cluster target cluster</p>
    <p>UpdatingUpdating Counting and Counting and variancevariance</p>
    <p>Bayes ruleBayes rule EM algorithmEM algorithm</p>
    <p>DisplayDisplay Most likelyMost likely Maximum Maximum Entropy Entropy PrinciplePrinciple</p>
    <p>Maximum Maximum Entropy Entropy PrinciplePrinciple</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>The ModelThe Model</p>
    <p>Feature ExtractionFeature Extraction  II - raw image data - raw image data   - set of feature extraction method- set of feature extraction method  ff - feature extraction operation - feature extraction operation</p>
    <p>Images Images  data point in hyper-space data point in hyper-space (R(Rdd))  Problem scope is narrowed down to a particular Problem scope is narrowed down to a particular</p>
    <p>featurefeature</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FeedbackFeedback</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Inconsistence in FeedbackInconsistence in Feedback</p>
    <p>User tells liesUser tells lies</p>
    <p>Too many false positive or false Too many false positive or false negativenegative</p>
    <p>Conflict of feedback in each Conflict of feedback in each iteration by careless mistakeiteration by careless mistake</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Resolving ConflictsResolving Conflicts</p>
    <p>How to deal with inconsistent user How to deal with inconsistent user feedback?feedback?  Maintain a relevance measure for Maintain a relevance measure for</p>
    <p>each data pointseach data points  Relevance measure &gt; 0 counted as Relevance measure &gt; 0 counted as</p>
    <p>relevant and use in estimationrelevant and use in estimation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Estimating Target Estimating Target DistributionDistribution</p>
    <p>Users target is a cluster Users target is a cluster  Assume it follows a Gaussian Assume it follows a Gaussian</p>
    <p>distributiondistribution  Model a distribution that fits Model a distribution that fits</p>
    <p>the relevant data pointsthe relevant data points  Based on the parameterBased on the parameter</p>
    <p>of distribution, systemof distribution, system learns what user wantslearns what user wants</p>
    <p>Data points selected as relevant</p>
    <p>Red</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Expectation MaximizationExpectation Maximization</p>
    <p>Fitting a Gaussian distribution function using Fitting a Gaussian distribution function using feedback data pointsfeedback data points  By expectation maximizationBy expectation maximization</p>
    <p>Distribution represent users targetDistribution represent users target  Expectation function match the display modelExpectation function match the display model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Updating ParametersUpdating Parameters</p>
    <p>Estimated mean is the averageEstimated mean is the average  Estimated variance by Estimated variance by</p>
    <p>differentiationdifferentiation  Iterative approachIterative approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DisplayDisplay</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Maximum Entropy DisplayMaximum Entropy Display</p>
    <p>Why maximum entropy display?Why maximum entropy display?</p>
    <p>ReasonReason: fully utilize information : fully utilize information contained in user feedback to reduce contained in user feedback to reduce number of feedback iterationnumber of feedback iteration</p>
    <p>ResultResult: near boundary images will be : near boundary images will be selected to fine tune parametersselected to fine tune parameters</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Maximum Entropy DisplayMaximum Entropy Display</p>
    <p>How to simulate maximumHow to simulate maximum entropy display in ourentropy display in our model?model?  Data points 1.18 Data points 1.18  away away</p>
    <p>from from  are selected are selected  Why 1.18?Why 1.18?</p>
    <p>2P(2P(+1.18+1.18)=P()=P())</p>
    <p>Query target cluster center</p>
    <p>Selected by knn search</p>
    <p>Selected by Max. Entropy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>ExperimentExperiment</p>
    <p>Synthetic data generated by MatlabSynthetic data generated by Matlab</p>
    <p>Mixture of GaussiansMixture of Gaussians  Class label of data points shown for Class label of data points shown for</p>
    <p>reference to give feedbackreference to give feedback  Dose it works and works better?Dose it works and works better?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>ConvergenceConvergence</p>
    <p>Is the estimated parameter (mean Is the estimated parameter (mean and variance) converge to the and variance) converge to the actual parameter of target actual parameter of target distribution?distribution?</p>
    <p>Is the maximum entropy display Is the maximum entropy display correctly done?correctly done?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Estimated mean RMS error along each iteration</p>
    <p>iteration</p>
    <p>R M</p>
    <p>S e</p>
    <p>rr o</p>
    <p>r o</p>
    <p>f es</p>
    <p>ti m</p>
    <p>at ed</p>
    <p>m ea</p>
    <p>n 4 dimension 6 dimension</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Estimated standard deviation RMS error along iteration</p>
    <p>iteration</p>
    <p>R M</p>
    <p>S e</p>
    <p>rr o</p>
    <p>r o</p>
    <p>f es</p>
    <p>ti m</p>
    <p>at ed</p>
    <p>s ta</p>
    <p>n d</p>
    <p>ar d</p>
    <p>d ev</p>
    <p>ia ti</p>
    <p>o n</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>No. of feedback given along each iteration</p>
    <p>iteration</p>
    <p>N o</p>
    <p>. o f</p>
    <p>fe ed</p>
    <p>b ac</p>
    <p>k g</p>
    <p>iv en</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>PerformancePerformance</p>
    <p>Compares to Ruis intra-weight Compares to Ruis intra-weight updating modelupdating model  Nearest neighbour search performed Nearest neighbour search performed</p>
    <p>after several feedbacks (6-7 after several feedbacks (6-7 iterations)iterations)</p>
    <p>Data points outside 2 Data points outside 2  are discarded are discarded in our algorithmin our algorithm</p>
    <p>Precision-Recall graphPrecision-Recall graph</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Precision vs Recall</p>
    <p>Recall</p>
    <p>P re</p>
    <p>ci si</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>Expectation Maximization</p>
    <p>Rui's weight updating</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Precision vs Recall</p>
    <p>Recall</p>
    <p>P re</p>
    <p>ci si</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>Expectation Maximization</p>
    <p>Rui's weight updating</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Precision vs Recall</p>
    <p>Recall</p>
    <p>P re</p>
    <p>ci si</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>Expectation Maximization</p>
    <p>Rui's weight updating</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Precision vs Recall</p>
    <p>Recall</p>
    <p>P re</p>
    <p>ci si</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>Expectation Maximization</p>
    <p>Rui's weight updating</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Precision vs Recall</p>
    <p>Recall</p>
    <p>P re</p>
    <p>ci si</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>Expectation Maximization</p>
    <p>Rui's weight updating</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Precision vs Recall</p>
    <p>Recall</p>
    <p>P re</p>
    <p>ci si</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>Expectation Maximization</p>
    <p>Rui's weight updating</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>Future WorksFuture Works</p>
    <p>Modification to learn from information Modification to learn from information contained in non-relevant setcontained in non-relevant set</p>
    <p>To capture correlation in different To capture correlation in different featuresfeatures</p>
    <p>Apply in CBIR system for performance Apply in CBIR system for performance measurementmeasurement</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Relevance Feedback Based on Parameter Estimation of Target Distribution</p>
    <p>ConclusionConclusion</p>
    <p>Proposed an approach to interpret Proposed an approach to interpret the feedback information from user the feedback information from user and learn his target of searchand learn his target of search</p>
    <p>Compares our approach with Ruis Compares our approach with Ruis intra-weight updating methodintra-weight updating method</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ENDEND</p>
    <p>Presentation file available atPresentation file available at http://www.cse.cuhk.edu.hk/~kcsia/research/http://www.cse.cuhk.edu.hk/~kcsia/research/</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
