<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Using Taxonomies for Content-based Routing with Ants Workshop on Innovations in Web Infrastructure (IWI2) WWW2006, May 22, 2006</p>
    <p>Elke Michlmayr Women's Postgraduate College for Internet Technologies (WIT) Vienna University of Technology, Austria http://wit.tuwien.ac.at/people/michlmayr</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Ant algorithms for search in peer-to-peer networks</p>
    <p>Content-based approach Meta-data for annotating documents</p>
    <p>Content distribution influences performance</p>
    <p>To which extent? Can use of taxonomies improve performance?</p>
    <p>Query for WWW</p>
    <p>Query for WWW</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The SemAnt algorithm</p>
    <p>Ant algorithm for search in peer-to-peer networks Queries are ants Routing with pheromone trails</p>
    <p>Trail laying and trail following One type of pheromone for each keyword</p>
    <p>SemAnt combines features from Ant Colony System</p>
    <p>For graph-based optimization problems Trail laying and trail following</p>
    <p>AntNet For load-adaptive routing of data packets Forward and backward ants</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trail following and trail laying</p>
    <p>How do forward ants select the next peer? Exploiting strategy</p>
    <p>Select best link Exploring strategy</p>
    <p>Derive goodness value pj for each link Compute random value q in [0, 1] Select link if q &lt;= pj</p>
    <p>How do backward ants update pheromone trails? Amount depends on</p>
    <p>Number of documents found Number of hops</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Application scenario</p>
    <p>Network topology Small-world network with 1024 peers</p>
    <p>Test data: ACM Computing Classification System taxonomy Documents annotated with one leaf topic Queries consist of one leaf topic Research area</p>
    <p>sub-topics of a 3rd-level topic</p>
    <p>Query distribution is uniform Probability that a peer issues a query is 0.1 per time unit</p>
    <p>SemAnt parameters 85% exploiting strategy, TTL of 25</p>
    <p>A B C ...</p>
    <p>Research area</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Peer is an expert in one research area</p>
    <p>Comparison of k-random walker SemAnt maxResults (Ants use maximum TTL) SemAnt minResources (Ants stop after first result)</p>
    <p>Performance comparison with k-random walker</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Decrease coherence of content</p>
    <p>Peers store 100%, 80%, 60%, 40%, 20%, 0% of their documents related to one research area Remaining documents are instances of random topics</p>
    <p>and performance decreases as well! Can information from the taxonomy be used for enhancing it?</p>
    <p>How?</p>
    <p>Influence of content distribution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Using taxonomies</p>
    <p>Pheromone trails also for higher-level topics</p>
    <p>Backward ants drop same amount as for topic itself Forward ants consider these trails for exploiting strategy</p>
    <p>How many higher-level topics? Useful only for direct super-topic</p>
    <p>To which extent? Trail for topic: 100% Trail for super-topic: 25%</p>
    <p>A B C ...</p>
    <p>Research area</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Improvement by using underlying taxonomy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Content-based query routing in unstructured peer-to-peer networks based on the ant metaphor</p>
    <p>Successful queries leave small traces in the network Heuristics use traces to direct subsequent queries =&gt; Ants build a map of the content distribution</p>
    <p>Contribution of this paper Impact of content distribution Taxonomies for improvement</p>
    <p>Future work Conditional flooding 0.1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References</p>
    <p>M. Dorigo, L. M. Gambardella. Ant Colony System: A Cooperative Learning Approach to the Traveling Salesman Problem, 1997.</p>
    <p>G. Di Caro, M. Dorigo. AntNet: Distributed Stigmergy Control for Communications Networks, 1998.</p>
    <p>M. Dorigo, G. D. Caro. The Ant Colony Optimization Meta-Heuristic, 1999. M. Guntsch and M. Middendorf. Pheromone Modification Strategies for Ant</p>
    <p>Algorithms Applied to Dynamic TSP, 2001. O. Babaoglu, H. Meling, and A. Montresor. Anthill: A Framework for the</p>
    <p>Development of Agent-Based Peer-to-Peer Systems, 2002. B. Yang, H. Garcia-Molina. Improving Search in Peer-to-Peer Networks,</p>
    <p>for Peer-to-Peer Networks, 2002. D. Tsoumakos, N. Roussopoulos. Adaptive Probabilistic Search for Peer-to</p>
    <p>Peer Networks, 2003. B. F. Cooper. Guiding Queries to Information Sources with InfoBeacons,</p>
    <p>Peer-to-Peer Networks based on Social Metaphors, 2004. S. Rhea, D. Geels, T. Roscoe, J. Kubiatowicz. Handling Churn in a DHT, 2004</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
