<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ant Algorithms for Search in Unstructured Peer-to-Peer Networks ICDE06, Ph.D. Workshop, April 3, 2006</p>
    <p>Elke Michlmayr PhD student (advisors: Gerti Kappel, Wolfgang Nejdl) Women's Postgraduate College for Internet Technologies (WIT) Vienna University of Technology, Austria http://wit.tuwien.ac.at/people/michlmayr</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation Ant algorithms Research question Search in peer-to-peer networks</p>
    <p>The SemAnt algorithm Design Evaluation</p>
    <p>Contributions and future work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>nest</p>
    <p>food source</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>Pheromone for indirect communication Trail-laying and trail-following Evaporation</p>
    <p>Ant Colony Optimization Ant Colony System: graph-based optimization problems AntNet: adaptive routing in communication networks</p>
    <p>Research question: To which extent are ant algorithms feasible for query routing in peer-to-peer networks?</p>
    <p>Self-adaptation to changes in network topology (churn)</p>
    <p>Ant algorithms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Search in peer-to-peer networks</p>
    <p>Can be viewed as an optimization problem Maximize number of search results Minimize hop count</p>
    <p>Structured networks Efficient lookup by key Key space is distributed among peers Resource is relocated to the peer responsible for its key</p>
    <p>Unstructured networks Store information about queries in the past Use it to predict which peer can answer a query Based on the keywords of the query</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The SemAnt algorithm</p>
    <p>Combines adapted features from AntNet Ant Colony System</p>
    <p>Queries are ants No additional traffic</p>
    <p>Pheromone trails Multiple types of pheromone Probabilistic routing tables</p>
    <p>One row for each neighbouring peer One column for each keyword Initialize entries with small value</p>
    <p>Evaporation</p>
    <p>O ut</p>
    <p>go in</p>
    <p>g lin</p>
    <p>ks</p>
    <p>... ...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SemAnt: If a query is issued at peer PQ</p>
    <p>Create backward ant Terminate forward ant?</p>
    <p>Minimizes resource usage Backward ant travels back hop-by-hop to PQ</p>
    <p>Drops pheromone at each intermediate peer</p>
    <p>Else: terminate</p>
    <p>? ?</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>? ? Results?</p>
    <p>Results?</p>
    <p>Results?</p>
    <p>Results!</p>
    <p>? ?</p>
    <p>?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trail following and trail laying</p>
    <p>How to select the next peer? Exploiting strategy</p>
    <p>Select best link Exploring strategy</p>
    <p>Derive goodness value pj for each link Compute random value q 2 [0, 1] Select link if q &lt;= pj</p>
    <p>How to update pheromone trails? Amount depends on</p>
    <p>Number of results found Number of hops</p>
    <p>Compared to optimal values</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>Application scenario Metadata-based search</p>
    <p>Resources annotated with leaf concepts of ACM CCS taxonomy Small-world network with 1024 peers Static network topology and content distribution</p>
    <p>Content distribution Peer is an expert in one research area</p>
    <p>Query distribution Probability that a peer issues a query is 0.1 per time unit One keyword per query</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Metrics Hit rate Resource usage</p>
    <p>Parameter settings 85% exploiting strategy TTL of 25</p>
    <p>Comparison of k-random walker SemAnt maxResults</p>
    <p>Use maximum TTL SemAnt minResources</p>
    <p>Stop after first result</p>
    <p>Experimental results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions and future work</p>
    <p>SemAnt algorithm Content-based query routing in unstructured peer-to-peer networks Based on the ant metaphor</p>
    <p>Successful queries leave small traces in the network Heuristics use traces to direct subsequent queries</p>
    <p>Self-adaptation to dynamic network topologies Evaporation built-in Converged phase reached fast Trails reflect content distribution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References</p>
    <p>M. Dorigo, L. M. Gambardella. Ant Colony System: A Cooperative Learning Approach to the Traveling Salesman Problem, 1997.</p>
    <p>G. Di Caro, M. Dorigo. AntNet: Distributed Stigmergy Control for Communications Networks, 1998.</p>
    <p>M. Dorigo, G. D. Caro. The Ant Colony Optimization Meta-Heuristic, 1999. M. Guntsch and M. Middendorf. Pheromone Modification Strategies for Ant</p>
    <p>Algorithms Applied to Dynamic TSP, 2001. O. Babaoglu, H. Meling, and A. Montresor. Anthill: A Framework for the</p>
    <p>Development of Agent-Based Peer-to-Peer Systems, 2002. B. Yang, H. Garcia-Molina. Improving Search in Peer-to-Peer Networks,</p>
    <p>for Peer-to-Peer Networks, 2002. D. Tsoumakos, N. Roussopoulos. Adaptive Probabilistic Search for Peer-to</p>
    <p>Peer Networks, 2003. B. F. Cooper. Guiding Queries to Information Sources with InfoBeacons,</p>
    <p>Peer-to-Peer Networks based on Social Metaphors, 2004. S. Rhea, D. Geels, T. Roscoe, J. Kubiatowicz. Handling Churn in a DHT, 2004</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
