<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FOUNDATIONS OF WEB DATA MANAGEMENT Serge Abiteboul INRIA &amp; ENS Cachan</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Web</p>
    <p>hypertext</p>
    <p>universal library of text</p>
    <p>and multimedia</p>
    <p>personal/private data social data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A typical Web users data</p>
    <p>What kinds of data? -data: photos, music, movies, reports, email -metadata: photo taken by Alice in Paris on ... -ontologies: Alices ontology and mapping with</p>
    <p>other ontologies -localization: Alices pictures are on Picasa,</p>
    <p>back-ups are at INRIA -security: Facebook credentials (Alice, 123456) -annotations: Alice likes Elvis website -beliefs: Alice believes Elvis is alive -external knowledge: Bob keeps copies of Alices</p>
    <p>pictures -time, provenance, ...</p>
    <p>All kinds</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A typical Web users data</p>
    <p>What kinds of data? Where is the data?</p>
    <p>- laptop, desktop, smartphone, tablet, car computer</p>
    <p>- mail, address book, agenda - Facebook, LinkedIn, Picasa, YouTube, Tweeter - svn, Google docs - also access to data / information of family,</p>
    <p>friends, companies associations</p>
    <p>All kinds</p>
    <p>Everywhere</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A typical Web users data</p>
    <p>What kinds of data? Where is the data? What kind of organization? - terminology: different ontologies - systems: personal machines, social networks - distribution: different localization - security: different protocols - quality: incomplete / inconsistent information</p>
    <p>All kinds</p>
    <p>Everywhere</p>
    <p>Very heterogeneous</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A typical Web users data</p>
    <p>What kinds of data?</p>
    <p>Where is the data?</p>
    <p>What kind of organization?</p>
    <p>A typical user  Overwhelmed by the mass of information</p>
    <p>Cannot find the information needed</p>
    <p>Is not aware of important events</p>
    <p>Cannot manage/control how others access and use his/her own data</p>
    <p>All kinds</p>
    <p>Everywhere</p>
    <p>Very heterogeneous</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example of processing</p>
    <p>Sacha and Bob are getting engaged. Their friends want to offer them an album of photos where they are together</p>
    <p>To make such a photo album</p>
    <p>Find friends of Sacha &amp; Bob (say with Facebook)</p>
    <p>for each friend, find where she keeps her photos (say, Picassa)</p>
    <p>find the means to access her photos possibly via friends</p>
    <p>find the photos that feature them together</p>
    <p>possibly ask someone to verify the results</p>
    <p>Reasoning is needed to do that automatically</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>All this forms a distributed knowledge</p>
    <p>How can systems help?</p>
    <p>We need to move from a Web of text to a Web of knowledge</p>
    <p>- semantic Web</p>
    <p>We need to</p>
    <p>YOU need</p>
    <p>help!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Organization</p>
    <p>distributiondistribution</p>
    <p>verificationverification</p>
    <p>imprecisionimprecision</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distributed knowledge base</p>
    <p>S. Abiteboul 2/5/19 - 10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Webdamlog</p>
    <p>Extends datalog negation, updates, distribution, delegation, time</p>
    <p>Influenced by Active XML - for distribution &amp; intentional data Dedalus (UC Berkeley) - for time &amp; implementation</p>
    <p>Peer and relation names are data Delegation: possibility to send a rule to another peer</p>
    <p>Basis for distributed computing`  Basis for learning knowledge rules</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Peer and relation names are data</p>
    <p>$message@$peer($name, Happy birthday!) :today@my-iphone($d/$m/$y), birthday@my-iphone($name, $message, $peer, $d/$m)</p>
    <p>Extensional facts:</p>
    <p>today@my-iphone(6/3)</p>
    <p>birthday@my-iphone(Manon, sendmail, gmail.com, 6/3)</p>
    <p>sendmail@gmail.com(Manon, Happy birthday)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>S. Abiteboul 2/5/19 - 13</p>
    <p>Probabilistic data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Probabilistic trees</p>
    <p>Information on the Web is typically noisy: uncertain, incomplete, inconsistent</p>
    <p>Probabilistic trees: syntax for describing a set of trees with a probability distribution</p>
    <p>Attach probabilities to pieces of information Works</p>
    <p>Queries with aggregation</p>
    <p>Richer models based on recursive Markov chains</p>
    <p>Handle inconsistencies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ontology alignment</p>
    <p>Given some ontologies, try to align them</p>
    <p>In particular, align entities</p>
    <p>Also, align relationships and classes</p>
    <p>Probabilistic approach</p>
    <p>System Paris</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Active documents</p>
    <p>S. Abiteboul 2/5/19 - 16</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Active XML = evolving trees</p>
    <p>XML documents with embedded Web service calls</p>
    <p>Distributed data  Intentional data  Dynamic data Exchange streams of Active</p>
    <p>XML documents Efficient distributed query</p>
    <p>evaluation</p>
    <p>Query/ Updates</p>
    <p>AXML document</p>
    <p>Updates</p>
    <p>streams</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Active XML = business artifact</p>
    <p>Concept introduced by IBM [Nigam &amp; Caswell 03] Data-centric workflows A process is described by exchanges of documents With constraints on the evolution of documents</p>
    <p>Better adapted to a Web setting than transition-based</p>
    <p>workflows such as BPEL</p>
    <p>Works on the comparison of specifications based on</p>
    <p>business artifacts and other approaches</p>
    <p>Works on automatic verification of temporal constraints</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>S. Abiteboul 2/5/19 - 19</p>
    <p>A book on Web data management</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cambridge University Press Serge Abiteboul, Ioana Manolescu, Philippe Rigaux, Marie-Christine Rousset, Pierre Senellart</p>
    <p>http://webdam.inria.fr/Jorge</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modeling Web data XML, Xpath, Xquery, XML schema, Tree automata</p>
    <p>Modeling Web data XML, Xpath, Xquery, XML schema, Tree automata</p>
    <p>Web data semantics Ontologies RDF, RDFS, Owl Data integration</p>
    <p>Web data semantics Ontologies RDF, RDFS, Owl Data integration</p>
    <p>Web scale applications Web search, DHT, Hadoop, XML databases</p>
    <p>Web scale applications Web search, DHT, Hadoop, XML databases</p>
    <p>Web data management</p>
    <p>Cambridge University Press</p>
    <p>http://webdam.inria.fr/Jorge</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>S. Abiteboul 2/5/19 - 22</p>
    <p>The team</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Post Docs &amp; Docs  Y. Katsis, UCSD  F. Suchanek, MPI  D. Deutch, Ben Gurion  Y. Amsterdamer, Tel Aviv  B. Marnette, Oxford  P. Bourhis, Oxford  E. Kharlamov, Bolzano  M. Oita, Telecom ParisTech  A. Galland, Ministry Industry  B. Marinoiu, SAP</p>
    <p>S. Abiteboul, INRIA &amp;  P. Senellart, Telecom ParisTech  V. Vianu, UCSD</p>
    <p>Colleagues  B. ten Cate, UCSC  J. Stoyanovich, U. Penn  D. Gross-Amblart, Rennes  M.-C. Rousset, Grenoble  M. Bienvenu, Paris 11  P. Rigaux, Internet Memory</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
