<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simplifying Manageability, Scalability and Host Mobility in Large-Scale Enterprise Networks using VEIL-click</p>
    <p>Sourabh Jain and Zhi-Li Zhang  University of Minnesota-Twin Cities {sourj, zhzhang}@cs.umn.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current Trends and Future Networks</p>
    <p>Large number of mobile users and systems</p>
    <p>Large number of smart appliances</p>
    <p>High bandwidth core and edges</p>
    <p>Heterogeneous technologies</p>
    <p>More and more Virtual appliances:   Virtual Servers  Virtual PCs</p>
    <p>Home users Internet (or Future Networking Substrate)</p>
    <p>Banking &amp; e-commerce</p>
    <p>Cell &amp; smart phones</p>
    <p>POTS VoIP</p>
    <p>Multimedia Streaming</p>
    <p>Games</p>
    <p>Surveillance &amp; Security</p>
    <p>Online TV</p>
    <p>Web/emails</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges posed by These Trends  Scalability: capability to connect tens of thousands or</p>
    <p>more users and devices  routing table size, constrained by router memory, lookup speed</p>
    <p>Mobility: hosts are more mobile, virtual servers are also mobile  need to separate location (addressing) and identity (naming)</p>
    <p>Availability &amp; Reliability: must be resilient to failures  need to be proactive instead of reactive  need to localize effect of failures</p>
    <p>Manageability: ease of deployment, plug-&amp;-play  need to minimize manual configuration   self-configure, self-organize, while ensuring security and trust</p>
    <p>.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How Existing Technologies Meet these Challenges?</p>
    <p>Ethernet/Wireless LANs (L2)  Pluses:</p>
    <p>plug-&amp;-play, minimal configuration, better mobility</p>
    <p>Minuses:   (occasional) data plane</p>
    <p>flooding, sub-optimal routing (using spanning tree), not robust to failures</p>
    <p>Not scalable to large (wide-area) networks</p>
    <p>IPv4/IPv6 (L3)  Pluses:</p>
    <p>better data plane scalability, more optimal routing,</p>
    <p>Minuses:   control plane flooding, global</p>
    <p>effect of network failures  poor support for mobility  difficulty/complexity in</p>
    <p>network renaming   Esp., changing addressing</p>
    <p>schemes (IPv4 -&gt; IPv6 transition) requires modifications in routing and other network protocols</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IP address Management &amp; Mobility</p>
    <p>Subnet Prefix: 192.168.1.0 Mask: 255.255.255.0 Gateway: 192.168.1.1</p>
    <p>Subnet Prefix: 192.168.2.0 Mask: 255.255.255.0 Gateway: 192.168.2.1</p>
    <p>Interface IP address: 192.168.1.1</p>
    <p>Interface IP address: 192.168.2.1</p>
    <p>IP address 192.168.1.2 Gateway: 192.168.1.1</p>
    <p>To: 192.168.1.2</p>
    <p>IP address 192.168.1.2 Gateway: 192.168.1.1</p>
    <p>IP address (re)assignment creates management overhead:   Careful IP configurations</p>
    <p>DHCP servers need to maintain state  Static assignment requires manual effort</p>
    <p>Breaks the mobility  Firewall re-configurations</p>
    <p>How to enable live migrations of virtual machines?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recent Proposals  SEATTLE [SIGCOMM08] , VL2 [SIGCOMM09], TRILL, LISP</p>
    <p>Shortest path routing using link state routing protocol on Ethernet switches</p>
    <p>ID Location separation for better mobility  Seattle uses DHT style lookup, VL2 uses a directory service for flooding</p>
    <p>free lookup   No flooding on data plane  However, control plane still uses flooding!</p>
    <p>ROFL [SIGCOMM06], UIP [HotNets03]   DHT style routing for scalability  Uses flat labels for mobility  However, these may incur significant routing stretch due to no topology</p>
    <p>awareness  No fundamental support for advanced features such as:</p>
    <p>Multipath routing   Fast Failure Rerouting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of VEIL-Click   Prototype implementation of recently proposed VIRO</p>
    <p>routing framework   Enables benefits of VIRO for existing Ethernet</p>
    <p>networks  Creates Scalable, robust and efficient Ethernet networks  Built-in support for multipath routing &amp; fast failure rerouting</p>
    <p>Virtual Ethernet ID Layer  Re-use MAC addresses for topology-aware structured vids  vids act as the location for the hosts, while IP addresses are</p>
    <p>used as persistent identifiers  Enables a fully backward compatible design, with no</p>
    <p>modifications to existing host-devices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VEIL Design Elements  VEIL Switches  VEIL Centralized Controller (VCC)  [unchanged] Host Devices, and Ethernet/Wireless Routers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VEIL: Virtual Ethernet ID Layer</p>
    <p>Re-use 48-bit MAC addresses for vid   For backward compatibility with existing Ethernet protocols and</p>
    <p>devices  vid structure:</p>
    <p>switch vid (32 bits)  assigned to switches using the vcc  Host-device inherit the switch vid from the switch they directly</p>
    <p>connect to   host id (16 bits)</p>
    <p>assigned by host-switches   uniquely identify hosts directly connected to a switch.</p>
    <p>End hosts agnostic of their vids   Host switch performs vid/MAC address translation   Backward compatible w/ Ethernet, 802.11, etc.</p>
    <p>Switch vid Host-ID</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VEIL: &lt;IP/MAC, vid&gt; Mapping   Host-switch:</p>
    <p>a switch directly connected to the host   discover host MAC/IP through ARP, and assign vid to host   host-switch publishes IP  vid mappings at an access-switch</p>
    <p>Access-switch:   a switch whose vid is closest to hash (IP address of the host)</p>
    <p>Sx Sy</p>
    <p>Sz</p>
    <p>x y Host-switch for y</p>
    <p>IPy MACy VIDy</p>
    <p>IPy VIDy</p>
    <p>Access-switch for y</p>
    <p>Register mapping IPy  VIDy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Address/vid Lookup &amp; Data Forwarding   Use DHT look-up for address/vid resolution with local cache  vid to MAC address translation at last-hop</p>
    <p>Switch Sx Switch Sy</p>
    <p>Switch Sz</p>
    <p>x y</p>
    <p>Mapping Table at Sz</p>
    <p>IP Address VID</p>
    <p>IPy VIDy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Seamless Host Mobility</p>
    <p>Switch Sx</p>
    <p>Switch Sy</p>
    <p>Switch Sz</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>y</p>
    <p>Mapping Table at Sz IP</p>
    <p>Address VID</p>
    <p>IPy VIDy</p>
    <p>Switch Sw</p>
    <p>Host y is vid is VIDynew</p>
    <p>Host y is vid is VIDynew</p>
    <p>Mapping Table at Sz IP</p>
    <p>Address VID</p>
    <p>IPy VIDynew</p>
    <p>ARP reply packet containing the new vid of host y</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VEIL-Click: An initial prototype  Implementation of VEIL architecture using</p>
    <p>Click Modular Router framework   VEIL-Click enabled switch consists of:</p>
    <p>A linux machine  Multiple network interfaces  Click Modular Router  VEIL as Click elements</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VEIL-Click: Modules and Interaction  Input ports</p>
    <p>Output ports</p>
    <p>Router (actually</p>
    <p>Forwarder)</p>
    <p>Hello Generator</p>
    <p>Access Info Processor</p>
    <p>Access Info Publisher</p>
    <p>Hello Processor</p>
    <p>ARP Processor</p>
    <p>IP Processor</p>
    <p>RDV Processor</p>
    <p>Route Builder</p>
    <p>Classifier</p>
    <p>Spanning Tree</p>
    <p>Processor</p>
    <p>VID assignment Processor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A prototype switch</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>VEIL-Click: Host Mobility Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Throughput during the mobility Throughput remains more or less stable, with minimal disruptions during the transitions from one switch to another!</p>
    <p>Time (Seconds)</p>
    <p>Ra te</p>
    <p>(kb ps</p>
    <p>)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion &amp; on-going work   VEIL: Enables large-scale, efficient &amp; robust Ethernet</p>
    <p>networks  Practical realization of VIRO</p>
    <p>VIRO provides a scalable &amp; robust substrate for future networks  No flooding in both data and control planes</p>
    <p>Backward compatible   compatible with current host protocols (such as ARP etc)</p>
    <p>Enables (nearly) configuration-free networks  Essential for seamless mobility  Built-in support for Multi-path routing</p>
    <p>Ongoing work:   Prototype using OpenFlow based switches  Inter-domain routing issues</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks!</p>
    <p>Please visit http://networking.cs.umn.edu/veil for:  o Demo videos,  o List of related publications,  o Source code!</p>
    <p>Or simply search online for VIRO VEIL</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
