<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MovStream: An Efficient Algorithm for Monitoring Clusters Evolving in Data</p>
    <p>Streams</p>
    <p>Liang Tang, Chang-jie Tang, Lei Duan, Chuan Li, Ye-xi jiang, Chun-qiu Zeng</p>
    <p>and Jun Zhu</p>
    <p>Sichuan University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Introduction  Related Work  Monitoring Clusters Evolving  Experimental Study  Conclusions and Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction  Data stream is the source of continuous</p>
    <p>data collected from sensor network, satellite...</p>
    <p>The amount of data is unlimited, which cannot be entirely stored, and should be processed quickly.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction(motivation)  The evolution of data clusters can be used</p>
    <p>to analyze the trends of the continuous data streams.</p>
    <p>Each individual data cluster represents the distinct group of the data.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction(motivation)  The evolving behavior of each cluster is</p>
    <p>treated as a movement of the cluster</p>
    <p>We refer significant movements to movement events.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Fig.1 The drift to a cluster</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Fig.1 The drift to a cluster</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Fig.1 The drift to a cluster</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Fig.1 The drift to a cluster</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Fig.2 The expand to a cluster</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Fig.2 The expand to a cluster</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions  Propose the movement event with the</p>
    <p>measurement to the cluster</p>
    <p>We design a novel data stream clustering method : MovStream</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions  Propose the movement event with the</p>
    <p>measurement to the cluster</p>
    <p>We design a novel data stream clustering method : MovStream</p>
    <p>Refine the clusters through the detected movement event of each cluster during data streaming.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work  Guha et al. proposed a k-means based</p>
    <p>algorithm for clustering data streams.  OChalaghan et al proposed the STREAM</p>
    <p>algorithm to cluster data streams  Nasraoui et al. proposed an artificial</p>
    <p>immune system (AIS) based clustering approach TECNO-STREAMS.</p>
    <p>Aggarwal et al. proposed CluStream algorithm.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Guha et al. proposed a k-means based algorithm for clustering data streams.</p>
    <p>OChalaghan et al proposed the STREAM algorithm to cluster data streams</p>
    <p>Nasraoui et al. proposed an artificial immune system (AIS) based clustering approach TECNO-STREAMS.</p>
    <p>Aggarwal et al. proposed CluStream algorithm.</p>
    <p>Which is the comparative algorithm in our paper.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Monitoring Clusters Evolving</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>X NX</p>
    <p>Given a cluster C of data points {Xi}, where i = 1, 2, N, the centroid X0, the radius R and the diameter D of the cluster are defined as follows.</p>
    <p>N</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>R X X N</p>
    <p>1</p>
    <p>( 1)</p>
    <p>N N</p>
    <p>i j</p>
    <p>i j</p>
    <p>D X X N N</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Monitoring Clusters Evolving</p>
    <p>Given two clusters Ci and Cj, let X0i and X0j be the centroids of Ci and Cj. Then the mean distance of Ci and Cj is defined as</p>
    <p>dmean (Ci , Cj ) = | X0i X0j |</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sliding Window of individual cluster  Each cluster has a sliding window to</p>
    <p>maintain recent data points: SW</p>
    <p>Xi Xi+1 Xi+2  Xi+n-1 Xi+n Xi-1 Xi+n+1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sliding Window of individual cluster  Each cluster has a sliding window to</p>
    <p>maintain recent data points: SW</p>
    <p>Xi Xi+1 Xi+2  Xi+n-1 Xi+n Xi-1 Xi+n+1</p>
    <p>( ) = n</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>LS SW X</p>
    <p>( ) n</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>SS SW X</p>
    <p>Cluster Feature Variables:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sliding Window of individual cluster  Each cluster has a sliding window to</p>
    <p>maintain recent data points: SW</p>
    <p>Xi Xi+1 Xi+2  Xi+n-1 Xi+n Xi-1 Xi+n+1</p>
    <p>( ) = n</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>LS SW X</p>
    <p>( ) n</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>SS SW X</p>
    <p>Cluster Feature Variables:</p>
    <p>Time costs of updating are both O(1) when new data arrives.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sliding Window of individual cluster  Lemma 1: Get the centroid X0 and radius R</p>
    <p>from cluster feature variables.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sliding Window of individual cluster  Lemma 1: Get the centroid X0 and radius R</p>
    <p>from cluster feature variables.</p>
    <p>All the movement events are detected by centroid and radius of a cluster.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measurement of Cluster Movement  Given a sliding window SW of a cluster C and two</p>
    <p>time stamp t and t ,t &lt; t, let Rt and Rt be the radiuses of C(SW)t and C(SW)t.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Definition of Cluster Movement Event  Let the user-defined sensitivity parameter set be</p>
    <p>{i} (i &gt; 0) where i = 1  3, and Rt be the radius of cluster C at time stamp t.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Initial Clusters Creation  Cache the first InitNumber data points</p>
    <p>Adopt k-means to cluster the first InitNumber data points to k clusters.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Processing New Data  New arrived data point will be absorbed by</p>
    <p>the nearest cluster.</p>
    <p>New arrived data point</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Processing New Data  New arrived data point will be absorbed by</p>
    <p>the nearest cluster.</p>
    <p>Absorbed by cluster O4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Processing New Data  Algorithm 2 ProcessNewData (Xnew)  1 Find the nearest cluster i in ClusterTable to Xnew.  2 Add Xnew and Xnew  Xnew to LS and SS of ClusterTable[i]  3 Push Xnew in ClusterTable[i].SW  4 Find the cluster j contains Xlast in ClusterTable.  5 Pop out Xlast from ClusterTable[j].SW.  6 Subtract Xlast and Xlast  Xlast from LS and SS of</p>
    <p>ClusterTable[j]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Processing New Data  Algorithm 2 ProcessNewData (Xnew)  1 Find the nearest cluster i in ClusterTable to Xnew.  2 Add Xnew and Xnew  Xnew to LS and SS of ClusterTable[i]  3 Push Xnew in ClusterTable[i].SW  4 Find the cluster j contains Xlast in ClusterTable.  5 Pop out Xlast from ClusterTable[j].SW.  6 Subtract Xlast and Xlast  Xlast from LS and SS of</p>
    <p>ClusterTable[j]</p>
    <p>store all clusters information</p>
    <p>Pop out the oldest data point</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Maintaining clusters for streaming  Algorithm 3 Maintain({i}, MaxNumCluster,</p>
    <p>MinNumCluster)  for each cluster i do  while exist any movement event of cluster i is</p>
    <p>triggered do  event = the movement event triggered  Invoke corresponding operations to event  if the number of clusters &lt; MinNumCluster  Invoke split to the maximal radius cluster.  if the number of clusters &gt; MaxNumCluster  Invoke merge to the two closest clusters.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Refinement for evolution of clusters</p>
    <p>Refinement Condition Method</p>
    <p>Move drift event Update centroid by LS</p>
    <p>Stretch shrink event or expand event</p>
    <p>Update radius by LS and SS</p>
    <p>Delete die-out event Delete it from ClusterTable</p>
    <p>Split radius &gt; 4 Find out the farthest data point to make a seed for another new cluster</p>
    <p>Merge (Ri + Rj) 5 &gt; |X0i  X0j| Combine two sets of data points and recreate SW.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Split and Merge</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Split and Merge</p>
    <p>Choose the farthest point as the new seed to absorb points.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Split and Merge</p>
    <p>Sp lit</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Split and Merge</p>
    <p>Sp lit</p>
    <p>Merge</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Split and Merge</p>
    <p>Sp lit</p>
    <p>Merge</p>
    <p>Both split and Merge operations time complexity</p>
    <p>cost is at most O(N)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Study  1. Real datasets: the KDD-CUP99 Network</p>
    <p>Intrusion Detection data set, contains the network connection records.</p>
    <p>2. Synthetic datasets: generated several synthetic dataset which follows a series of Gaussian distributions. The size of dataset varies from 100K to 400K, the number of clusters varies from 5 to 20, and the dimensionality of data points varies from 4 to 50.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Study</p>
    <p>Fig.6 Network Intrusion dataset (horizon time=1000)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Study</p>
    <p>Fig.8 Network Intrusion dataset total Average SSQs on different lengths of</p>
    <p>horizon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Study</p>
    <p>Fig.9 Network Intrusion dataset (horizon time=2000, monitor-period=2000)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Study</p>
    <p>Fig.9 Network Intrusion dataset (horizon time=2000, monitor-period=2000)</p>
    <p>Calling maintain procedure per 2000 data points</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Study</p>
    <p>Fig.10 (B100C5 horizon time=2000, monitor</p>
    <p>period=2000)</p>
    <p>Fig.11 (B400C20 horizon time=5000, monitor</p>
    <p>period=5000)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Any Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
