<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theron Ji Eric Kim Raji Srikantan Alan Tsai Arel Cordero David Wagner</p>
    <p>UC Berkeley</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Widely used in todays elections</p>
    <p>Voters indicate choices by marking voting targets</p>
    <p>Scanner tabulates votes by detecting marks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Region where write-in candidates are written in by the voter</p>
    <p>Corresponding voting target must be filled for vote to count</p>
    <p>So does this happen?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lisa Murkowski wins the 2010 Alaska Senate election through a write-in campaign</p>
    <p>Donna Frye narrowly loses the 2004 San Diego mayoral election because people forgot to mark the write-in voting target</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voter writes in a candidates name, but doesnt fill in the corresponding voting target  vote is lost</p>
    <p>Questions: o How often does this occur? o What trends are there when this</p>
    <p>happens? o How do you detect this</p>
    <p>accurately, quickly, and with minimal human effort?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We were kindly given 248,334 scanned, double-sided ballot images from the 2008 Leon County General Election (thanks to Larry Moore, Ion Sancho, and Clear Ballot Group)</p>
    <p>These were in the Premier (Diebold) optical scan format</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We assume we are given blank templates</p>
    <p>We assume ballots have a regular and consistent structure</p>
    <p>(We dont assume to know write-in locations)</p>
    <p>(We dont assume scanned image will be perfect)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Align each ballot to a universal coordinate system</p>
    <p>Necessary for accuracy of further steps</p>
    <p>Robust against folds, skews, and tears in images</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Identify every hashmark along the side using template matching</p>
    <p>OK if some are missing or go undetected</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Linear regression along each edge using the hashmarks as points</p>
    <p>(Notice the slight leftwards skew in the image as shown by the lines)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Correspond every hashmark with the hashmark on the canonical ballot (template)</p>
    <p>Perform an affine transformation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We group all the ballots of the same style together</p>
    <p>We use the precinct number for this</p>
    <p>Match each style with one of the templates</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>First we look for the writein lines</p>
    <p>Notice that they are horizontal lines contained entirely within a contest box</p>
    <p>Use form extraction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Given the write-in lines, we scan upward until whitespace ends</p>
    <p>This gives us a rectangular box that becomes our write-in region</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Count the number of black pixels in the write-in region</p>
    <p>Threshold it at a conservative (low) number, and consider anything exceeding the threshold as a mark</p>
    <p>Black Pixels: 8</p>
    <p>Black Pixels: 908</p>
    <p>Black Pixels: 7203</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lastly, we classify the voting target for each write-in as filled or unfilled</p>
    <p>Do this through template matching the voting target</p>
    <p>Matched (Unfilled)</p>
    <p>Matched (Unfilled)</p>
    <p>Not Matched (Filled)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An example task for the participant to do</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Actual votes lost</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conflict votes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Non-serious votes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quantifying Votes?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Stray Marks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Marked Unmarked Total</p>
    <p>Filled 834</p>
    <p>(0.226%) 78</p>
    <p>(0.021%) 911</p>
    <p>(0.247%)</p>
    <p>Unfilled 784</p>
    <p>(0.213%) 366981</p>
    <p>(99.54%) 367766</p>
    <p>(99.75%)</p>
    <p>Total 1618</p>
    <p>(0.439%) 367059</p>
    <p>(99.56%) 368677</p>
    <p>Write-in Regions</p>
    <p>V o</p>
    <p>ti n</p>
    <p>g T</p>
    <p>a rg</p>
    <p>e t</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>1618 write-in votes (834 bubbled, 784 not)  453 emphasis votes (3 bubbled, 450 not)  17 conflict votes (0 bubbled, 17 not)  54 non-serious votes (41 bubbled, 13 not)  54 quantifying votes (27 bubbled, 27 not)  16 stray marks(0 bubbled, 16 not)</p>
    <p>Total Lost votes: 261 (16% of write-in votes)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We developed techniques to accurately detect write-in marks from optical scan ballots. We did this with only partial knowledge about the ballot, and minimal human assistance.</p>
    <p>We demonstrated its feasibility on a large, real-life data set from Leon County, and found surprising results  that in fact, up to 16% of write-in votes that could have been counted in the election were lost.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Disclaimer: This was not a real vote</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
