<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>Control Objectives for DP:j Digital Preservation as an</p>
    <p>Integrated Part of IT GovernanceIntegrated Part of IT Governance</p>
    <p>CChristoph Becker, Vienna Gonalo Antunes, Jos Barateiro, Ricardo Vieira, Jos Borbinha, Lisbon ASIS&amp;T Annual Meeting October 2011, New Orleans</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Agenda</p>
    <p>IT Governance  Digital longevity and reference models for DP  A capability-based Reference Architecture for DP</p>
    <p>Stakeholders, concerns, goals, influencers, capabilities</p>
    <p>Control Objectives for DP  How to integrate digital preservation into IT GovernanceHow to integrate digital preservation into IT Governance  Processes as enablers for capabilities</p>
    <p>How to assess and improve?  A Capability Maturity Model for Preservation Planning</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . IT Governance and COBIT</p>
    <p>IT Governance: decision making and communication within IT-supported organizations</p>
    <p>COBIT: Control Objectives for Information Technology  the leadership, organisational structures and processes that ensure</p>
    <p>that the enterprises IT sustains and extends the organisationsp g strategies and objectives</p>
    <p>goal-driven, process-oriented and control-based  How to leverage resources to achieve desired ends?  Goals  processes - activities</p>
    <p>Ensure systems security, Acquire and maintain application software, .</p>
    <p>Sophisticated, adaptable process model</p>
    <p>We integrate digital preservation goals and processes with IT Governance processeswith IT Governance processes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Digital Longevity</p>
    <p>Numerous reference models, frameworks and concepts  OAIS and trust: TRAC, RAC (ISO 16363), NESTOR  Records Management: MoReq, ISO 15489  Risk: DRAMBORA  Planning: PLATOPlanning: PLATO  Economics: BRTF, LIFE.</p>
    <p>Yet.  Maturity of the field is unclear and evolving  Integration into Information Systems and Information</p>
    <p>Technology fields is unclear  How does Digital Preservation relate to, e.g., IT Governance?  How can we assess and improve organizational capabilities?</p>
    <p>Integrate Digital Preservation into IT Governance Integrate Digital Preservation into IT Governance  Capability Model based on Enterprise Architecture approaches</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . A Capability-based Reference Architecture</p>
    <p>Domain Knowledge  SHAMANRA v1.0</p>
    <p>Standards and Best Practices</p>
    <p>OAIS  TRAC/RAC  TDR 2002 NESTOR</p>
    <p>Practices OMG UML OMG BMM  OMG SBVR OMG OSM NESTOR</p>
    <p>Planets Planning method  Planets Functional Model  PREMIS</p>
    <p>OMG OSM  ISO 27000: Security  ISO 31000: Risk Manag.  IEEE Std. 14712000</p>
    <p>BRTF Sustainability Report  DRAMBORA  PARSE.Insight</p>
    <p>Zachman Framework  COBIT  DoDAF</p>
    <p>Stakeholders Concerns Influencers Goals Capabilities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>Digital Preservation Capabilities</p>
    <p>A capability is an ability that an organization, person, or system possesses. Capabilities are typically expressed in general and high-level terms and typically require a combination of organization, people, processes, and technology to achieve</p>
    <p>A capability can control, inform, include, or depend on another capability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>DP Governance Capabilities</p>
    <p>Capability Key goals Compliance Verify and report compliance Community Relations Engage with designated community Certification Obtain and maintain certification status Mandate Negotiation Negotiate with governing institutionsMandate Negotiation Negotiate with governing institutions Business Continuity Assure mission-critical operations and manage capabilities Succession Planning Negotiate formal succession plans IT Governance Manage services, processes, technology solutions Manage Risks Control strategic and operational risks and opportunities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>Digital Preservation Capabilities</p>
    <p>A capability is an ability that an organization, person, or system possesses. Capabilities are typically expressed in general and high-level terms and typically require a combination of organization, people, processes, and technology to achieve</p>
    <p>Preserve Contents is the ability to maintain content authentic and understandable to the defined user community over time and assure itsunderstandable to the defined user community over time and assure its provenance.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Core Preservation Capabilities</p>
    <p>Preservation Planning Preservation Operation</p>
    <p>Monitor, steer and control the preservation operation of content</p>
    <p>Control the deployment and execution of preservation plans.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Core Preservation Capabilities</p>
    <p>Preservation Planning Preservation Operation</p>
    <p>Monitor, steer and control the preservation operation of content</p>
    <p>Control the deployment and execution of preservation plans.</p>
    <p>Influencers and Decision making Options diagnosis Specification and delivery Monitoring</p>
    <p>Analyze content Execute preservation actions Ensure adequate provenance trail Handle preservation metadataMonitoring Handle preservation metadata</p>
    <p>Conduct Quality Assurance Provide reports and statistics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Core Preservation Capabilities</p>
    <p>Preservation Planning Preservation Operation Monitor, steer and control the preservation operation of content</p>
    <p>Control the deployment and execution of preservation plans.</p>
    <p>Influencers and Decision making O ti di i</p>
    <p>Analyze content E t ti tiOptions diagnosis</p>
    <p>Specification and delivery Monitoring</p>
    <p>Execute preservation actions Ensure adequate provenance trail Handle preservation metadata Conduct Quality AssuranceQ y Provide reports and statistics</p>
    <p>Migrate this set of images (in TIFF-5) to JP2 using ImageMagick 6.3 with</p>
    <p>Analyse original Migrate, analyse output</p>
    <p>parameters a,b,c Conduct quality assurance Provenance, metadata, Reporting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . COBIT processes...</p>
    <p>Driven by specific goals and controls  Organized into activities with assigned responsibilities</p>
    <p>Related to other processes Related to other processes  Measured on all levels: Internal vs. external goals and metrics</p>
    <p>IT Goals Process goals Activity goals</p>
    <p>Key Performance I di t</p>
    <p>Process metrics</p>
    <p>Activity metricsIndicators metrics metrics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Preservation Planning example</p>
    <p>Ensure Manage Diagnose all understandability</p>
    <p>g obsolescence threats at logical level</p>
    <p>Diagnose all options against requirements</p>
    <p>Number of objects with breach of</p>
    <p>Number of obsolescence</p>
    <p>Options diagnosis: Efficiencywith breach of</p>
    <p>understandability during time horizon</p>
    <p>obsolescence issues successfully responded to</p>
    <p>Efficiency, completeness, correctness and timeliness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Preservation Planning Process</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . A Capability Maturity Model for Preservation Planning</p>
    <p>Coming from Software Engineering, the CMM has been shown to be a powerful instrument for assessment and improvement</p>
    <p>Awareness and Communication</p>
    <p>Policies, Plans and Procedures</p>
    <p>Tools and Automation</p>
    <p>Skills and Expertise</p>
    <p>Responsibility and Accountability</p>
    <p>Goal Setting and Measurement</p>
    <p>Initial / ad-hoc</p>
    <p>Repeatable, but Intuitive</p>
    <p>Defined</p>
    <p>Defined</p>
    <p>Managed and Measurable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>Awareness and Communicatio n</p>
    <p>Policies, Plans and Procedures</p>
    <p>Tools and Automatio n</p>
    <p>Skills and Expertise</p>
    <p>Responsibility and Accountability</p>
    <p>Goal Setting and Measurement</p>
    <p>Disorganised ad-hoc decisions</p>
    <p>Not defined</p>
    <p>Unclear goals, no measurement</p>
    <p>process emerges, but informal and incident-driven</p>
    <p>tool usage without Systematic integration.</p>
    <p>awareness of required skills, hands-on</p>
    <p>ownership of issues based on their own initiative on a</p>
    <p>issues experience reactive basis.</p>
    <p>Formal planning process in place some</p>
    <p>Automated tools, but processes</p>
    <p>Responsibilities assigned, documented</p>
    <p>approach is understood, accepted and communicated.</p>
    <p>place, some strategy takes place</p>
    <p>processes defined by available services</p>
    <p>documented and clearly communicated.</p>
    <p>Planning fully supported by well-specified methods; inter</p>
    <p>Automated planning system + operational</p>
    <p>culture nal best practice monitoring</p>
    <p>Industry best practice</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Thank you for your attention!</p>
    <p>Questions? www.ifs.tuwien.ac.at/~becker</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
