<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>Preservation Decisions: Terms and Conditions Apply</p>
    <p>Challenges, Misperceptions and Lessons Learned in Preservation Planning</p>
    <p>Christoph Becker, Andreas Rauber ACM/IEEE Joint Conference on Digital Libraries (JCDL 2011) Ott ON C dOttawa, ON, Canada June 14, 2011</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Digital Preservation decisions</p>
    <p>Digital Preservation arises from change organizational users technical legal contextual organizational, users, technical, legal, contextual</p>
    <p>Alignment of technology and business  Continuum between business and technologygy  User requirements vs. IT operations  Technology obsolescence vs. technological opportunities</p>
    <p>Reconciling Conflicts Reconciling Conflicts  between ends and means  between strategy and tactics</p>
    <p>Core decision: How to preserve content information  Preservation action: A concrete action (usually implemented by a</p>
    <p>software tool) performed on content in order to achieve preservation</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>software tool) performed on content in order to achieve preservation goals.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Preservation Planning</p>
    <p>Preservation Planning: is the ability to monitor, steer and control the preservation operation to meet preservation goals and manage obsolescence threatsobsolescence threats</p>
    <p>Systematic evaluation of candidate actions against scenario-specific requirements in a standardized, repeatable workflow using controlled experimentation on sample contentexperimentation on sample content</p>
    <p>A preservation plan defines a series of preservation actions to be taken by a responsible institution to address an identified risk for a given set of digital objects or records (called collection).set of digital objects or records (called collection).</p>
    <p>Plato: The Planning Tool - www.ifs.tuwien.ac.at/dp/plato  Growing user community  Series of case studies and productive decisions Series of case studies and productive decisions</p>
    <p>From to . 2011-2014</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Outline</p>
    <p>Preservation Planning  Planning method and Plato  Case studies  Decision criteria: What to measure and how</p>
    <p>Lessons LearnedLessons Learned  Necessity, Scope, Costs, Benefits  Prerequisites and Critical Success Factors  Common misperceptions Common misperceptions</p>
    <p>Observations and Future Challenges</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Preservation Planning: Key concepts</p>
    <p>Repeatable, standardized planning workflow A i ht d hi h f bj ti A weighted hierarchy of objectives  Measurable criteria on the leaf level of the tree  Utility functions make criteria comparabley p</p>
    <p>Controlled experimentation on sample content  Evidence-based decision making</p>
    <p>St d di d t t f l ifi ti Standardized structure for plan specification  Transparency and documentation  Comparability across scenariosp y  Integration with repository systems (ePrints; RODA, eSciDoc,)</p>
    <p>Plato guides, validates and documents planning</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>Automation: Reduce manual effort</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Case studies</p>
    <p>Case studies conducted with Plato Electronic documents Electronic documents</p>
    <p>Interactive art  Console video games  Scanned images  Relational databases  Interactive artInteractive art  Computer games  Born-digital photographs</p>
    <p>Doc ments Documents  Emails</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>And: Bitstream preservation (Zierau et al., IPRES 2010)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Four cases, three solutions: Scanned images</p>
    <p>Bavarian State Library, 72TB TIFF6: Leave and monitor British Library 80TB TIFF5: Migrate to JP2 (ImageMagick) British Library, 80TB TIFF5: Migrate to JP2 (ImageMagick)</p>
    <p>Royal Library of Denmark, ~10.000 aerial photographs in TIFF6: Leave and monitor</p>
    <p>State and University Library Denmark, scanned yearbooks in GIF: Migrate to TIFF 6</p>
    <p>Scenario Chosen action Main reasons</p>
    <p>Leave unchanged and it</p>
    <p>Color profile complications, lack of JP2 b t P tpages in TIFF6 monitor JP2 browser support, Process costs</p>
    <p>Migrate to JP2 Storage costs, Standardization</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Aerial photographs in TIFF6</p>
    <p>Leave unchanged and monitor</p>
    <p>Lack of JP2 browser support, Process costs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Scanned books requirements</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Scanned books requirements</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Addressing the evaluation gap</p>
    <p>Problems Manual evaluation is very effort intensive Manual evaluation is very effort intensive</p>
    <p>Need for sharing knowledge and comparing experiences</p>
    <p>Decision criteria  Analysis of &gt;600 criteria specified in 12 case studies  A taxonomy of criteria  Measurement devices for each category Measurement devices for each category  Integration with Plato through an extensible measurement</p>
    <p>framework</p>
    <p>Q tit ti l i f t Quantitative analysis of measurement coverage</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What to measure?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to measure?</p>
    <p>Category Example Data collection and t</p>
    <p>Tools measurement</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to measure?</p>
    <p>Category Example Data collection and t</p>
    <p>Tools measurement</p>
    <p>Outcome Object</p>
    <p>Image pixelwise identical Footnotes preserved</p>
    <p>Measurements of output and input, comparison</p>
    <p>FITS, JHove, ImageMagick...</p>
    <p>Footnotes preserved</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to measure?</p>
    <p>Category Example Data collection and t</p>
    <p>Tools measurement</p>
    <p>Outcome Object</p>
    <p>Image pixelwise identical Footnotes preserved</p>
    <p>Measurements of output and input, comparison</p>
    <p>FITS, JHove, ImageMagick...</p>
    <p>O F i ISO M f h DROID PRONOMOutcome Format</p>
    <p>Format is ISO standardised</p>
    <p>Measurements of the output, Trusted external data sources</p>
    <p>DROID, PRONOM, UDFR, P2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to measure?</p>
    <p>Category Example Data collection and t</p>
    <p>Tools measurement</p>
    <p>Outcome Object</p>
    <p>Image pixelwise identical Footnotes preserved</p>
    <p>Measurements of output and input, comparison</p>
    <p>FITS, JHove, ImageMagick...</p>
    <p>O F i ISO M f h DROID PRONOMOutcome Format</p>
    <p>Format is ISO standardised</p>
    <p>Measurements of the output, Trusted external data sources</p>
    <p>DROID, PRONOM, UDFR, P2</p>
    <p>Outcome Annual bitstream Measurements of the output, LIFE model effect preservation costs ()</p>
    <p>p , external data sources, models (LIFE)...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to measure?</p>
    <p>Category Example Data collection and t</p>
    <p>Tools measurement</p>
    <p>Outcome Object</p>
    <p>Image pixelwise identical Footnotes preserved</p>
    <p>Measurements of output and input, comparison</p>
    <p>FITS, JHove, ImageMagick...</p>
    <p>O F i ISO M f h DROID PRONOMOutcome Format</p>
    <p>Format is ISO standardised</p>
    <p>Measurements of the output, Trusted external data sources</p>
    <p>DROID, PRONOM, UDFR, P2</p>
    <p>Outcome Annual bitstream Measurements of the output, LIFE model effect preservation costs ()</p>
    <p>p , external data sources, models (LIFE)...</p>
    <p>Action ti</p>
    <p>Throughput (MB per illi d) M</p>
    <p>Measurements taken in t ll d i t ti</p>
    <p>MiniMEE runtime millisecond), Memory</p>
    <p>usage controlled experimentation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to measure?</p>
    <p>Category Example Data collection and t</p>
    <p>Tools measurement</p>
    <p>Outcome Object</p>
    <p>Image pixelwise identical Footnotes preserved</p>
    <p>Measurements of output and input, comparison</p>
    <p>FITS, JHove, ImageMagick...</p>
    <p>O F i ISO M f h DROID PRONOMOutcome Format</p>
    <p>Format is ISO standardised</p>
    <p>Measurements of the output, Trusted external data sources</p>
    <p>DROID, PRONOM, UDFR, P2</p>
    <p>Outcome Annual bitstream Measurements of the output, LIFE model effect preservation costs ()</p>
    <p>p , external data sources, models (LIFE)...</p>
    <p>Action ti</p>
    <p>Throughput (MB per illi d) M</p>
    <p>Measurements taken in controlled i t ti</p>
    <p>MiniMEE runtime millisecond), Memory</p>
    <p>usage experimentation</p>
    <p>Action static</p>
    <p>License costs per CPU (), Open Source</p>
    <p>Trusted external data sources, manual evaluation, sharing</p>
    <p>UDFR, Pronom, P2, manual( ), p</p>
    <p>License , g ,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to measure?</p>
    <p>Category Example Data collection and t</p>
    <p>Tools measurement</p>
    <p>Outcome Object</p>
    <p>Image pixelwise identical Footnotes preserved</p>
    <p>Measurements of output and input, comparison</p>
    <p>FITS, JHove, ImageMagick...</p>
    <p>O F i ISO M f h DROID PRONOMOutcome Format</p>
    <p>Format is ISO standardised</p>
    <p>Measurements of the output, Trusted external data sources</p>
    <p>DROID, PRONOM, UDFR, P2</p>
    <p>Outcome Annual bitstream Measurements of the output, LIFE model effect preservation costs ()</p>
    <p>p , external data sources, models (LIFE)...</p>
    <p>Action ti</p>
    <p>Throughput (MB per illi d) M</p>
    <p>Measurements taken in controlled i t ti</p>
    <p>MiniMEE runtime millisecond), Memory</p>
    <p>usage experimentation</p>
    <p>Action static</p>
    <p>License costs per CPU (), Open Source License</p>
    <p>Trusted external data sources, manual evaluation, sharing</p>
    <p>P2, manual ( ) p g</p>
    <p>Action judgement</p>
    <p>Configuration interface usability</p>
    <p>Manual judgement, sharing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Case studies</p>
    <p>Distribution in four case studies on scannedstudies on scanned images</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Measurement: Where are we now?</p>
    <p>The good news  We know the distribution of criteria in the taxonomy  We know what we need to measure  We have approaches to measuring things  We can measure simple properties reliably</p>
    <p>The not so good news  Confidence in the measures varies</p>
    <p>C f d d th bj t  f t Coverage of measures depends on the objects formats  We do normally not know much about the impact of a property</p>
    <p>Bad news  Many complex properties cannot be measured yet  Universal solutions for QA are not working well</p>
    <p>Piece by piece step by step is the way to go</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>Piece by piece, step by step is the way to go</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Is all this necessary?</p>
    <p>Challenges when evaluating preservation actions  Quality varies across tools  Properties vary across content  Usage varies across communities  Requirements vary across scenariosRequirements vary across scenarios  Risk tolerance varies across collections  Preferences and constraints vary across organisations</p>
    <p>C t t t d tibilit i i t Cost structures and compatibility varies across environments  Constraints, priorities and requirements shift constantly</p>
    <p>Trust requires evidenceq  Trust has to be evaluated in a realistic context  Controlled experimentation, repeatable documentation, and</p>
    <p>scenario-specific requirements assessment</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>scenario specific requirements assessment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Lessons learned</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . What are the costs and benefits of planning?</p>
    <p>Primary cost drivers for the planning activity Maturity of organizational framework: Maturity of organizational framework: Constraints, goals, drivers and responsibilities</p>
    <p>Degree of familiarity with the planning approach  Technical complexity of the content to be preserved  Technical proficiency of the staff assigned to do planning</p>
    <p>EffortEffort  First run generally effort-intensive: Learning curve, lack of context  Subsequent activities significantly easier and faster</p>
    <p>R t I t t Return on Investment  Hard to quantify   but shouldnt we rather ask: What are the costs of NOT planning?</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>p g  This is quite easy to quantify</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . What are the prerequisites of planning?</p>
    <p>Clear and concise documentation of the organization Constraints Constraints</p>
    <p>Drivers  Goals  Responsibilities  Infrastructure and technical capabilities  Cost structuresCost structures</p>
    <p>Understanding of the decision space  Properties of the content  Requirements of the stakeholders  Available options  Relationship between ends and means</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>p  Relationship between strategies and operations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Who is responsible for planning?</p>
    <p>A full understanding of the planning role has yet to be formedformed</p>
    <p>Combination of expertise and skills required  Understanding of business goals to achieveg g  Understanding of organizational environments and processes  In-depth knowledge of technical intricacies</p>
    <p>Not all planning activities should be carried out by the Not all planning activities should be carried out by the same person or role in an organization</p>
    <p>Preservation Planning needs to take place on an g p operational level</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . What is important?</p>
    <p>3 key levers influencing the decision outcome 1 Requirements definition1. Requirements definition 2. Utility functions 3. Importance weighting</p>
    <p>Weighting requirements  Assigns relative importance factors on all level of the tree  Low level changes in relative importance have little influence Low level changes in relative importance have little influence  Criteria often have a total weight of 1-5%</p>
    <p>Weighting vs. utility function  Key effects of criteria with low weight: Acceptance or rejection  Output range of utility function may include 0.0  Utility function is much more critical on the level of criteria</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>Utility function is much more critical on the level of criteria</p>
    <p>Measurements vs. Assessment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . The method, the tool, the services</p>
    <p>Method is very generally applicable From computer games to scanned images From computer games to scanned images</p>
    <p>From databases to born-digital art  From private photographs to national heritage institutions</p>
    <p>Tool support varies  Degree of automation strongly dependent on content and</p>
    <p>preservation actionspreservation actions  Manual evaluation is always possible</p>
    <p>Integrated services  Action services may or may not work on specific content  Failure of a service simply means that the service is not suitable  Planning and thorough evaluation is important</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>g g p</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Some Conclusions</p>
    <p>The planning method and Plato are broadly applicable, but need clear positioning in a well defined organizational context need clear positioning in a well-defined organizational context</p>
    <p>require clear understanding of the terms and conditions  Required expertise and skill set needs to be clarified  Tool support varies according to content type and action  Automation and Scalability:</p>
    <p>Integration into an organization's processes  understanding of processes, influences, interdependencies</p>
    <p>G Ri k d C li W d lik t Governance, Risk and Compliance: Wed like to see  An integration of DP into IT Governance  An integration of DP into Enterprise Risk Management</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
    <p>g g  A better understanding of the relationship with Governance, Risk</p>
    <p>and Compliance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Thank you for your attention!</p>
    <p>Questions? www.ifs.tuwien.ac.at/~becker www.ifs.tuwien.ac.at/dp/plato</p>
    <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
