<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>INTEGRATING META-PATH SELECTION WITH USER-GUIDED OBJECT CLUSTERING IN HETEROGENEOUS INFORMATION NETWORKS</p>
    <p>Yizhou Sun, Brandon Norick, Jiawei Han, Xifeng Yan, Philip S. Yu, and Xiao Yu</p>
    <p>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign University of California at Santa Barbara University of Illinois at Chicago</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Motivation and Problem Definition</p>
    <p>The PathSelClus Model and Algorithm</p>
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Information Networks Are Everywhere</p>
    <p>Social Networking Websites Biological Network: Protein Interaction</p>
    <p>Research Collaboration Network Product Recommendation Network via Emails</p>
    <p>They are all treated as Homogeneous Networks!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Heterogeneous Networks</p>
    <p>Multiple object types and/or multiple link types</p>
    <p>Venue Paper Author</p>
    <p>DBLP Bibliographic Network The IMDB Movie Network Actor</p>
    <p>Movie Director</p>
    <p>Movie Studio</p>
    <p>The Facebook Network</p>
    <p>Directly Mining information richer heterogeneous networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network Schema and Meta-Path [Sun et al., VLDB11]</p>
    <p>Network schema  Meta-level description of a network</p>
    <p>Meta-Path  Meta-level description of a path between two objects</p>
    <p>A path on network schema  Denote an existing or concatenated relation between two object types 5</p>
    <p>Jim-P1-Ann Mike-P2-Ann Mike-P3-Bob</p>
    <p>Author-Paper-Author</p>
    <p>Jim-P1-SIGMOD-P2-Ann Mike-P3-SIGMOD-P2-Ann Mike-P4-KDD-P5-Bob</p>
    <p>Author-Paper-Venue-Paper-Author</p>
    <p>Objects are connected together via different types of relationships!Objects are connected together via different types of relationships!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Motivation and Problem Definition</p>
    <p>The PathSelClus Model and Algorithm</p>
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Meta-Path Selection?</p>
    <p>Goal: Clustering authors based on their connection in the network</p>
    <p>{1,2,3,4} {5,6,7,8} {1,3,5,7}</p>
    <p>{2,4,6,8}</p>
    <p>{1,3} {2,4} {5,7} {6,8}</p>
    <p>Which meta-path to choose?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Role of User Guidance</p>
    <p>It is users responsibility to specify their clustering purpose  Say, by giving seeds in each cluster</p>
    <p>{1} {5}</p>
    <p>{1,2,3,4} {5,6,7,8}+</p>
    <p>{1} {2} {5} {6}</p>
    <p>{1,3} {2,4} {5,7} {6,8}</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p>Seeds Meta-path(s) Clustering Result</p>
    <p>Seeds Meta-path(s) Clustering Result</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problem of User-Guided Clustering with Meta-Path Selection</p>
    <p>Input:  The target type for clustering: T  Number of clusters: K</p>
    <p>Seeds in some of the clusters:  M Candidate meta-paths starting from T:</p>
    <p>Output:  The quality weight for each candidate meta-path in the clustering process</p>
    <p>The clustering results that are consistent with the user guidance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Existing Link-based User-Guided Clustering Approaches</p>
    <p>Link-based clustering algorithms on homogeneous networks  Treat all types of links equally important (Zhu et al., 2003)</p>
    <p>Distinguish different relations in HIN, but use ALL the relations in the network  Do not distinguish different clustering tasks with different semantic meanings (Long et al., 2007)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Motivation and Problem Definition</p>
    <p>The PathSelClus Model and Algorithm</p>
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Probabilistic Model</p>
    <p>Part 1: Modeling the Relationship Generation  A good clustering result should lead to high likelihood in observing existing relationships  Keep in mind: higher quality relations should count more in the total</p>
    <p>likelihood</p>
    <p>Part 2: Modeling the Guidance from Users  The more consistent with the guidance, the higher probability of the clustering result</p>
    <p>Part 3: Modeling the Quality Weights for Meta-Paths  The more consistent with the clustering result, the higher quality weight</p>
    <p>Objective Function</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part 1: Modeling the Relationship Generation</p>
    <p>For each meta path , let the relation matrix be :  The relationship is generated under a mixture of multinomial distributions   : the probability that belongs to Cluster k  : the probability that feature object appearing in Cluster k</p>
    <p>The probability to observing all the relationships in</p>
    <p>E.g.,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part 2: Modeling the Guidance from Users</p>
    <p>For each soft clustering probability vector :  Model it as generated from a Dirichlet prior  If is labeled as a seed in Cluster</p>
    <p>)  is an all-zero vector except for item , which is 1  is the user confidence for the guidance</p>
    <p>If is not labeled in any cluster</p>
    <p>The prior density is uniform, a special case of Dirichlet distribution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Part 3: Modeling the Quality Weights for Meta-Paths</p>
    <p>Model quality weight as the relative weight for each relationship in  Observation of relationships:</p>
    <p>Further assume relationship generation with Dirichlet Prior:</p>
    <p>The best : the most likely to generate current clustering-based parameters</p>
    <p>when is small, is more likely to be a uniform distribution  Random generated</p>
    <p>when is large, is more likely to be , what we observed  Consistent with the observation</p>
    <p>Dirichlet Distribution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Learning Algorithm</p>
    <p>An Iterative algorithm that the clustering result and quality weight vector mutually enhance each other  Step 1: Optimize given</p>
    <p>is determined by all the relation matrices with different weights , as well as the labeled seeds</p>
    <p>Step 2: Optimize given  In general, the higher likelihood of observing given , the higher</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Motivation and Problem Definition</p>
    <p>The PathSelClus Model and Algorithm</p>
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Datasets  DBLP</p>
    <p>Object Types: Authors, Venues, Papers, Terms  Relation Types: AP, PA, VP, PV, TP, PT</p>
    <p>Yelp  Object Types: Users, Businesses, Reviews, Terms  Relation Types: UR, RU, BR, RB, TR, RT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DBLP-Clustering Venues According to Research Areas</p>
    <p>Task:  Target objects: venues  Number of clusters: 4;  Candidate meta-paths: V-P-A-P-V, V-P-T-P-V</p>
    <p>Output:  Weights:</p>
    <p>V-P-A-P-V: 1576 (0.0017 per relationship)  V-P-T-P-V: 17001 (0.0003 per relationship)</p>
    <p>Clustering results:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Yelp-T2</p>
    <p>Task:  Target objects: restaurants  Number of clusters: 6;  Candidate meta-paths: B-R-U-R-B, B-R-T-R-B.</p>
    <p>Output:  Weights:</p>
    <p>B-R-U-R-B : 6000 (0.1716 per relationship, compared with 0.5864 for clustering shopping categories)</p>
    <p>B-R-T-R-B: 2.9522 (0.0138 per relationship)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Motivation and Problem Definition</p>
    <p>The PathSelClus Model and Algorithm</p>
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Meta-path selection  Unavoidable problem in information-rich heterogeneous information networks</p>
    <p>User guidance  Users responsibility to claim the mining purpose</p>
    <p>PathSelClus  An probabilistic model-based algorithm integrating meta-path selection with user-guided clustering</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgement</p>
    <p>Co-authors</p>
    <p>Funding Agencies  This research was supported by U.S. NSF, DHS, and ARL/NS-CTA</p>
    <p>Q &amp; A</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
