<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Unsupervised Framework for Extracting and Normalizing Product Attributes from Multiple Web Sites</p>
    <p>Tak-Lam Wong Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering The Chinese University of Hong Kong</p>
    <p>Wai Lam, Tik-Shun Wong Dept. of Systems Engineering and Engineering Management The Chinese University of Hong Kong</p>
    <p>@ SIGIR 2008  Singapore</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction  Problem Definition  Our Model  Inference Method  Experimental Results  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>(Source: http://www.superwarehouse.com)</p>
    <p>(Source: http://www.crayeon3.com)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Information Extraction</p>
    <p>To extract product attributes:  Prior knowledge about content</p>
    <p>Effective sensor resolution  Layout format</p>
    <p>White balance, shutter speed  Mutual influence</p>
    <p>Light sensitivity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attribute Normalization</p>
    <p>Samples of extracted text fragments from a page:  Cloudy, daylight, etc  What do they refer to?</p>
    <p>A text fragment extracted from another page:  white balance auto, daylight,</p>
    <p>cloudy, tungsten,    Attribute normalization:</p>
    <p>To cluster text fragments into the same group  Better indexing for product search  Easier understanding and interpretation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Existing Works</p>
    <p>Supervised wrapper induction  They need training examples.  The wrapper learned from a Web site cannot be applied</p>
    <p>to other sites.  Template-independent extraction (Zhu et al., 2007)</p>
    <p>They cannot handle previously unseen attributes.  Unsupervised wrapper learning (Crescenzi et al, 2001)</p>
    <p>Extracted data are not normalized.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction  Problem Definition  Our Model  Inference Method  Experimental Results  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Definition (1)</p>
    <p>A product domain,  E.g., Digital camera domain</p>
    <p>A set of reference attributes,  E.g., resolution, white balance, etc.  A special element, , representing not-an-attribute</p>
    <p>A collection of Web pages from any Web sites, , each of which contains a single product</p>
    <p>Let be any text fragment from a Web page</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Definition (2)</p>
    <p>&lt;TR&gt; &lt;TD&gt; &lt;P&gt; &lt;SPAN&gt; White balance &lt;/SPAN&gt; &lt;/P&gt; &lt;/TD&gt; &lt;TD&gt; &lt;P&gt; &lt;SPAN&gt; Auto, daylight, cloudy, tungstem, fluorescent, fluorescent H, custom &lt;/SPAN&gt; &lt;/P&gt; &lt;/TD&gt; &lt;/TR&gt; &lt;TR&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;TR&gt; &lt;TD&gt; &lt;P&gt; &lt;SPAN&gt; White balance &lt;/SPAN&gt; &lt;/P&gt; &lt;/TD&gt; &lt;TD&gt; &lt;P&gt; &lt;SPAN&gt; Auto, daylight, cloudy, tungstem, fluorescent, fluorescent H, custom &lt;/SPAN&gt; &lt;/P&gt; &lt;/TD&gt; &lt;/TR&gt; &lt;TR&gt;</p>
    <p>Line separator</p>
    <p>Line separator</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Definition (3)</p>
    <p>Information extraction:</p>
    <p>Attribute normalization:</p>
    <p>Joint attribute extraction and normalization:</p>
    <p>Attribute information</p>
    <p>Target information Layout information</p>
    <p>Content information</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Definition (4)</p>
    <p>White balance Auto, daylight, cloudy, tungstem, fluore scent, fluorescent H, custom  T=1  A=white balance</p>
    <p>Cloudy, daylight  T=1  A=white balance</p>
    <p>View larger image  T=0  A=not-an-attribute</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction  Problem Definition  Our Model  Inference Method  Experimental Results  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Model Dirichlet Process Prior (Infinite Mixture Model) N Text Fragment S Different Web Site</p>
    <p>k-th component proportion</p>
    <p>Content info. generation</p>
    <p>Target info. generation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Generation Process</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Generation Process</p>
    <p>The joint probability for generating a particular text fragment given the parameters, , , , and, :</p>
    <p>Inference:</p>
    <p>Intractable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction  Problem Definition  Our Model  Inference Method  Experimental Results  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Variational Method (1)</p>
    <p>Finding is intractable  Our goal: Design a tractable distribution</p>
    <p>such that should be as close to as possible.</p>
    <p>KL divergence:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Variational Method (2)</p>
    <p>Truncated stick-breaking process (Ishwaran and Jam es, 2001)  Replace infinity with a truncation level K</p>
    <p>Max:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Variational Method (3)</p>
    <p>One important variational parameters:</p>
    <p>How likely does come from the k-th component?  Attribute normalization!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Variational Method (4)</p>
    <p>Another important variational parameter:</p>
    <p>where</p>
    <p>How likely should be extracted?  Attribute extraction!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Unsupervised Approach</p>
    <p>What should be extracted?  Make use of the prior knowledge about a domain.</p>
    <p>Only a few terms about the product attributes  E.g., resolution, light sensitivity, shutter speed, etc.  Can be easily obtained, for example, by just</p>
    <p>highlighting the attributes of a Web page  Initialization</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction  Problem Definition  Our Model  Inference Method  Experimental Results  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>We have conducted experiments on four different domains:  Digital camera: 85 Web pages from 41 different sites  MP3 player: 96 Web pages from 62 different sites  Camcorder: 111 Web pages from 61 different sites  Restaurant: 29 Web pages from LA-Weekly Restaurant Guide</p>
    <p>In each domain, we conducted 10 runs of experiments.  In each run, we randomly selected a Web page and use</p>
    <p>the attributes inside as prior knowledge.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation on Attribute Normalization</p>
    <p>Baseline approach:  Agglomerative clustering  Edit distance between text fragments</p>
    <p>Evaluation metrics:  Pairwise recall (R)  Pairwise precision (P)  Pairwise F1-measure (F)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results of Attribute Normalization</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Visualize the Normalized Attributes</p>
    <p>The top five weighted terms in the ten largest normalized attributes in the digital camera domain:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation on Attribute Extraction</p>
    <p>Surprisingly, in the restaurant domain, our framework achieves a performance (0.95 F1-measure) which is c omparable to the supervised method (Muslea et al. 200 1)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction  Problem Definition  Our Model  Inference Method  Experimental Results  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions (1)</p>
    <p>We aim at simultaneously extracting and normalizing product attributes from Web pages collected from dif ferent sites.</p>
    <p>Our method considers page-independent content info rmation and the page-dependent layout information.</p>
    <p>We have developed a graphical model, which employ s Dirichlet process prior, to model the generation of t ext fragments in Web pages.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions (2)</p>
    <p>An unsupervised inference algorithm based on variati onal method is designed.</p>
    <p>We formally show that content and layout informatio n can collaborate and improve both extraction and no rmalization performance under our model.</p>
    <p>Experiments on four different domains have been co nducted to show the robustness and effectiveness of our approach.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions and Answers</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
