<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Epidemic Spreading in Real Networks: an Eigenvalue Viewpoint</p>
    <p>Yang Wang Deepayan Chakrabarti</p>
    <p>Chenxi Wang Christos Faloutsos</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Computer viruses are a prevalent threat</p>
    <p>Existing defense mechanisms (eg., scanning) focus on local behaviors only  like curing a contagious disease in one patient</p>
    <p>Global defense strategies require the understanding of global propagation behaviors  like prevention of spread of a contagious disease in a</p>
    <p>population  Epidemiological models can help us do exactly that</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Why do we care?  Understanding the spread of a virus is the first step in</p>
    <p>preventing it  How fast do we need to disinfect nodes so that the virus</p>
    <p>attack dies off?  How long will the virus take to die out?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem definition</p>
    <p>Question: How does a virus spread across an arbitrary network?</p>
    <p>Specifically, we want  a general analytic model for viral propagation  that applies to any network topology  and offers an easy-to-compute threshold condition</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Framework</p>
    <p>The network of computers consists of nodes (computers) and edges (links between nodes)</p>
    <p>Each node is in one of two states  Susceptible (in other words, healthy)  Infected</p>
    <p>Susceptible-Infected-Susceptible (SIS) model  Cured nodes immediately become susceptible</p>
    <p>Susceptible Infected</p>
    <p>Infected by neighbor</p>
    <p>Cured internally</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Framework (Continued)</p>
    <p>Homogeneous birth rate  on all edges between infected and susceptible nodes</p>
    <p>Homogeneous death rate  for infected nodes</p>
    <p>Infected</p>
    <p>Healthy</p>
    <p>XN1</p>
    <p>N3</p>
    <p>N2 Prob.</p>
    <p>Prob.</p>
    <p>Prob.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction  Classical models and their limitations  Modeling viral propagation in arbitrary</p>
    <p>network topologies  Epidemic threshold and eigenvalues  Experiments  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Homogeneous Model</p>
    <p>[Kephart-White 91, 93]  Homogeneous connectivity &lt;k&gt;</p>
    <p>Every node has equal probability of connecting to every other node</p>
    <p>Many real networks deviate from this!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power-law Networks</p>
    <p>Many real world networks exhibit power-law characteristics  Probability that a node has k links:</p>
    <p>P(k) = ck    = power law exponent  The Internet: 2    3and still</p>
    <p>evolving  [Faloutsos+ 99, Ripeanu+ 02]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power-law Networks</p>
    <p>Model for Barabsi-Albert networks (PL-3)  [Pastor-Satorras &amp; Vespignani, 01,</p>
    <p>02]  Prediction limited to BA type networks  which only allow power-laws of</p>
    <p>exponent  = 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power-law Networks</p>
    <p>Model for correlated (Markovian) networks  [Bogu-Satorras 02]  Additional distribution for neighbor degree</p>
    <p>correlation: P(k|k)  Difficult to find/produce P(k|k) in arbitrary</p>
    <p>networks  Such correlations have yet to be confirmed</p>
    <p>in real world networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction  Classical models and their limitations  Modeling viral propagation in arbitrary</p>
    <p>network topologies  Epidemic threshold and eigenvalues  Experiments  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Topology-independent epidemic model  Takes topological characteristics into</p>
    <p>account without being limited by them  Discrete time  A node is healthy at time t if it</p>
    <p>Was healthy before t and not infected at t</p>
    <p>Infected</p>
    <p>Healthy</p>
    <p>XN1</p>
    <p>N3</p>
    <p>N2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Topology-independent epidemic model  Takes topological characteristics into</p>
    <p>account without being limited by them  Discrete time  A node is healthy at time t if it</p>
    <p>Was healthy before t and not infected at t OR  Was infected before t, cured and not re-infected at t</p>
    <p>Infected</p>
    <p>Healthy</p>
    <p>XN1</p>
    <p>N3</p>
    <p>N2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Topology-independent epidemic model  Takes topological characteristics into</p>
    <p>account without being limited by them  Discrete time  A node is healthy at time t if it</p>
    <p>Was healthy before t and not infected at t OR  Was infected before t, cured and not re-infected at t OR  Was infected before t, therefore ignored re-infection attempts and was</p>
    <p>subsequently cured at t</p>
    <p>Infected</p>
    <p>Healthy</p>
    <p>XN1</p>
    <p>N3</p>
    <p>N2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Topology-independent epidemic model  Deterministic time evolution of infection</p>
    <p>1 - pi,t: probability node i is healthy at time t  k,t: probability a k-linked node will not receive infections from its</p>
    <p>neighbors at time t  Assume probability of curing before infection attempts 50%  Solve numerically</p>
    <p>neighbor: 1,,</p>
    <p>,1,2 1</p>
    <p>,1,,1,,</p>
    <p>,</p>
    <p>)1(</p>
    <p>)1()1(1</p>
    <p>j tjtk</p>
    <p>tktitktitktiti</p>
    <p>i tit</p>
    <p>p</p>
    <p>pppp</p>
    <p>p</p>
    <p>Equation 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation evaluation of model (1/2)</p>
    <p>network</p>
    <p>KW model</p>
    <p>Our model</p>
    <p>Simulation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Simulation evaluation of model (2/2)</p>
    <p>Our models predictions consistently equal or outperform predictions made by models designed for specific topologies</p>
    <p>PL-3 model</p>
    <p>Our model</p>
    <p>Simulation</p>
    <p>Real-world 10900-node</p>
    <p>Oregon network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction  Classical models and their limitations  Modeling viral propagation in arbitrary</p>
    <p>network topologies  Epidemic threshold and eigenvalues  Experiments  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Epidemic threshold  The epidemic threshold  is the value such that</p>
    <p>/ &lt;   there is no epidemic  where  = birth rate, and  = death rate</p>
    <p>What is this threshold for an arbitrary graph?  [Theorem 1]</p>
    <p>= 1/ 1,A</p>
    <p>where 1,A is the largest eigenvalue of the adjacency matrix A of the topology1,A alone captures the</p>
    <p>property of the graph!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Epidemic threshold for various networks  Our epidemic threshold condition is accurate</p>
    <p>and general  Homogeneous networks</p>
    <p>1,A = &lt;k&gt;;  = 1/&lt;k&gt;  where &lt;k&gt; = average degree  This is the same result as of Kephart &amp; White !</p>
    <p>Star networks  1,A = d;  = 1/ d  where d = the degree of the central node</p>
    <p>Infinite power-law networks  1,A = ;  = 0 ; this concurs with previous results</p>
    <p>Finite power-law networks   = 1/ 1,A</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Epidemic threshold  [Theorem 1] The epidemic threshold is</p>
    <p>given by</p>
    <p>= 1/ 1,A  How fast will an infection die out?  [Theorem 2] Below the epidemic threshold,</p>
    <p>the epidemic dies out exponentially  If / &lt;  ( = birth rate,  = death rate) then  any local breakout of infection dies out exponentially fast</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction  Classical models and their limitations  Modeling viral propagation in arbitrary</p>
    <p>network topologies  Epidemic threshold and eigenvalues  Experiments  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Epidemic threshold experiments (Star)</p>
    <p>/ =  (close to the threshold)</p>
    <p>/ &lt;  (below threshold)</p>
    <p>/ &gt;  (above threshold)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Epidemic threshold experiments (Oregon)</p>
    <p>/ &gt;  (above threshold)</p>
    <p>/ =  (at the threshold)</p>
    <p>/ &lt;  (below threshold)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our prediction vs. previous prediction</p>
    <p>When we do not subsume previous predictions, our predictions are much more accurate</p>
    <p>Oregon Star</p>
    <p>PL-3 PL-3</p>
    <p>Our Our</p>
    <p>N u</p>
    <p>m b</p>
    <p>er o</p>
    <p>f in</p>
    <p>fe ct</p>
    <p>ed n</p>
    <p>o d</p>
    <p>es</p>
    <p>/ /</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction  Classical models and their limitations  Modeling viral propagation in arbitrary</p>
    <p>network topologies  Epidemic threshold and eigenvalues  Experiments  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions</p>
    <p>We match our goals  A general analytic model for viral propagation</p>
    <p>(Equation 1)</p>
    <p>that applies to any network topology</p>
    <p>and offers an easy-to-compute threshold condition (Theorem 1)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions  We created new topology-independent</p>
    <p>epidemic model  More accurate than previous models  More general than previous models</p>
    <p>We derived new epidemic threshold condition  Only requires one parameter (1,A) that can be calculated with</p>
    <p>existing tools  Subsumes previous theories for epidemic threshold condition  When does not subsume, our theory is more accurate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Halting viruses</p>
    <p>Immunization strategies must concentrate on nodes that are statistically significant</p>
    <p>Statistically significant nodes are not necessarily limited to ones that are highly connected  We are building mathematical models to identify the most significant</p>
    <p>nodes in power-law models</p>
    <p>Other system parameters may also matter</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary and future work  &lt;cite the paper?&gt;</p>
    <p>Our models will provide a theoretical basis for global defense strategies for  intelligent immunization  mechanisms to guard against distributed denial-of-service (DDOS) attacks</p>
    <p>those that propagate via virus code</p>
    <p>&lt;Whatever you want to do about this entire bullet&gt;</p>
    <p>Phase transition phenomena at epidemic threshold</p>
    <p>Additional environmental factors that affect epidemic behavior</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic homogeneous model - KW</p>
    <p>Homogeneous connectivity &lt;k&gt;  Homogeneous birth rate  on all edges</p>
    <p>between infected and susceptible nodes  Homogeneous death rate  for infected</p>
    <p>nodes  Susceptible-Infected-Susceptible (SIS)</p>
    <p>model  Cured individuals immediately become susceptible</p>
    <p>Susceptible-Infected-Removed (SIR) model  Cured individuals are removed from the population</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Homogeneous model equations</p>
    <p>Deterministic time evolution of infected population t  Change = birth term - death term</p>
    <p>Equilibrium point of infection , = /(&lt;k&gt;)</p>
    <p>For homogeneous or Erds-Rnyi (random) networks</p>
    <p>ttt t k</p>
    <p>dt</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>)1(</p>
    <p>1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Homogeneous model</p>
    <p>= 1- = 1 -  /(&lt;k&gt;) = 1- 0.1 = 0.9</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power-law networks</p>
    <p>Discrepancy between simulation results and homogeneous model predictions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power-law networks</p>
    <p>There exist statistically significant nodes  Node 928 was infected 9473 times  Run #3 hits 928 around time 20  Both runs #1 and #2 hit 928 early in its run</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Models for power-law and correlated networks  Many real world networks exhibit power</p>
    <p>law characteristics  P(k) = k - --- probability that a node has k links  The Internet: 2    3and still evolving</p>
    <p>Model for Barabsi-Albert networks (SV)   = 3  Steady state:  = 2e-/m, m = minimum connectivity  Prediction limited to BA type networks</p>
    <p>Model for correlated (Markovian) networks  Additional distribution for neighbor degree correlation: P(k|k)  Difficult to find/produce P(k|k) in arbitrary networks  Such correlations have yet to be confirmed in real world networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Epidemic threshold  The epidemic threshold  = / (the ratio of</p>
    <p>birth rate to death rate) below which there is no epidemic</p>
    <p>Epidemic threshold for existing models:  Threshold of the basic homogeneous model: 1/&lt;k&gt;  Threshold of SV power-law model: &lt;k&gt;/&lt;k2&gt;</p>
    <p>We derive an epidemic threshold condition from our model   = 1/ 1,A  1,A: largest eigenvalue of the adjacency matrix A of the topology</p>
    <p>Power-law networks have extremely low threshold since connectivity variance is usually high, resulting in large 1,A</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
