<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Stephanie Jones, Christina Strong, Darrell Long, Ethan Miller</p>
    <p>June 21, 2011</p>
    <p>Tracking Emigrant Data via Transient Provenance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Data leaks are harmful for companies and government agencies</p>
    <p>Figuring out who leaked your data and how is hard  If a leak is found, information gathering is critical</p>
    <p>Who could have leaked the data?  When did the data leave the system?  What else did the user access at the time?</p>
    <p>Data provenance can be extended to track emigrant data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Assumptions</p>
    <p>All data is kept on a central storage system  Provenance store uses the PASS framework  High Performance Computing (HPC) environment  Clients connect over the network</p>
    <p>NFS, CIFS, SSH, FTP  Adversary is a trusted user with malicious intent</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Transient Provenance</p>
    <p>Data can leave central storage in two ways  Copied or moved to an directly connected external drive  Copied over a network connection</p>
    <p>Emigrant data is tracked via ghost objects  Ghost objects represent a period of time when</p>
    <p>data has left the central storage system  Ghost objects differ from regular provenance</p>
    <p>Do not track data ancestry  Are not meant to be immutable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tracking Data Leaks</p>
    <p>Ghost objects can be used to identify suspect users</p>
    <p>Each ghost represents a period of time during which data were accessible from outside the provenance systems control</p>
    <p>Querying over the provenance graph for leaked data will return all relevant ghost objects  Users who accessed the data  How the data left the central storage system  Where the leaked data went (external drive or IP address)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Data provenance can be extended to track emigrant data via ghost objects</p>
    <p>Ghost objects are used to track when data emigrates from a storage system</p>
    <p>Querying ghost objects can identify sources of data leaks  Identify potential suspects  Provide timeframe for the leak and the set of data</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
