<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link</p>
    <p>Signatures Neal Patwari Sneha Kasera</p>
    <p>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 2 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>What is location distinction?  Ability to know when a</p>
    <p>transmitter has changed position</p>
    <p>Enabled by the physical layer only</p>
    <p>Compared to localization  no coordinates  benefits from multipath  more sensitive, needs less</p>
    <p>coverage</p>
    <p>Each transmitter (i1, i2, i3) is distinguished at the two</p>
    <p>receivers (j1, j2)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 3 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Applications</p>
    <p>Efficient location estimation in WSN</p>
    <p>Physical security, management of objects</p>
    <p>Prevent impersonation in wireless networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 4 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Location Estimation in WSNs  Network self-localization expensive</p>
    <p>Ranging energy, bandwidth  Communication</p>
    <p>Only re-localize when sensor moves How do you know? Collaboration?</p>
    <p>WSN low-energy location distinction: detect movement w/o collaboration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 5 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Real-Time Location Service  Applications in Logistics</p>
    <p>Healthcare, distribution, manufacturing, mining, military,</p>
    <p>Idea: Detect Movement of Objects  most assets should be stationary  focus resources on rare moving assets</p>
    <p>However, existing methods are costly!  Accelerometers: add $3 to each tag  Doppler: require continuous transmission  both: energy, cost, communication inefficient</p>
    <p>Localization Issues: Coverage, Accuracy, Security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 6 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Wireless LAN Security</p>
    <p>Impersonation</p>
    <p>MAC-address spoofing [1]</p>
    <p>Traditional crypto methods subject to node compromise</p>
    <p>Image from HP, http://docs.hp.com/en/T1428-90017 /img/gfx2.gif, Three Levels of Wireless Security</p>
    <p>[1] D. B. Faria and D. R. Cheriton. Radio-layer security: Detecting identity-based attacks in wireless networks using signalprints. In Proc. 5th ACM Workshop on Wireless Security (WiSe'06), pages 43-52, Sept. 2006.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 7 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Goals &amp; Challenges</p>
    <p>Develop link signatures with key properties  uniqueness: as function of tx, rx locations  non-measurement: cant read from another place  spoof-proof: cant create from another place</p>
    <p>Efficiency: receivers, time</p>
    <p>Do not change transmitter</p>
    <p>Validate with real measurements</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 8 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Temporal link signatures</p>
    <p>Related work</p>
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Measurement apparatus</p>
    <p>Quantitative evaluation</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 9 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Physical Layer Filter</p>
    <p>Wireless channel from i to j is a filter</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>Sum of attenuated, delayed impulse functions</p>
    <p>hi;j ( ) = LX</p>
    <p>l=1</p>
    <p>le j l (  l)</p>
    <p>hi;j ( )</p>
    <p>jh i;</p>
    <p>j (</p>
    <p>)j</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 10 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Received Signal</p>
    <p>The signal is filtered by the channel</p>
    <p>hi;j (t) s(t) r(t) = s(t) ? hi;j (t)</p>
    <p>R(f ) = S(f )Hi;j (f ) Hi;j (f )</p>
    <p>S(f )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 11 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Calculation in Receiver</p>
    <p>Further convolve with known tx signal</p>
    <p>s(t) h(n)i;j (t) = s(t) ? hi;j (t) ? s</p>
    <p>(t)</p>
    <p>H(n)i;j (f ) = jS(f )j 2Hi;j (f )</p>
    <p>S(f) R(f)</p>
    <p>r(t)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 12 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Estimate of the Channel</p>
    <p>Typically |S(f)|2 largely flat in-band, very low out of band. (spectral efficiency)</p>
    <p>Figure: Spectral characteristic of an OFDM signal</p>
    <p>H (n)i;j (f ) = jS(f )j 2Hi;j (f )</p>
    <p>H (n)i;j (f )  Hi;j (f )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 13 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Temporal Link Signature</p>
    <p>In time domain, temporal link signature</p>
    <p>t</p>
    <p>Figure: Multipath (?) are approximated in the measurement (? )</p>
    <p>h(n)i;j (t)  hi;j (t)</p>
    <p>jh (n</p>
    <p>) i;</p>
    <p>j (t</p>
    <p>)j</p>
    <p>hi;j (t)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 14 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Use RSS only (multiple receivers) [1]  Power in received signal r(t)</p>
    <p>Use frequency-domain estimate [2]  Equivalent to at selected frequencies { f }</p>
    <p>[1] D. B. Faria and D. R. Cheriton. Radio-layer security: Detecting identitybased attacks in wireless networks using signalprints. In Proc. 5th ACM Workshop on Wireless Security (WiSe'06), pages 43-52, Sept. 2006.</p>
    <p>[2] Z. Li, W. Xu, R. Miller, and W. Trappe. Securing wireless systems via lower layer enforcements. In Proc. 5th ACM Workshop on Wireless Security (WiSe'06), pages 33-42, Sept. 2006.</p>
    <p>H (n)i;j (f )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 15 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Temporal Link Sig. Methodology</p>
    <p>Sampled temporal link signature</p>
    <p>Normalized link signature (NLS)</p>
    <p>h(n)i;j = [h (n) i;j (0); : : : ; h</p>
    <p>(n) i;j (Tr)]</p>
    <p>T</p>
    <p>~h(n)i;j = h(n)i;j</p>
    <p>kh(n)i;j k</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 16 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>New measurement</p>
    <p>Distance: normalized Euclidean (l2) to closest point</p>
    <p>Distance Between Signatures</p>
    <p>History for</p>
    <p>Size of history : avg. distance between points</p>
    <p>fh(n)i;j gn=1;:::;N 1</p>
    <p>i;j</p>
    <p>di;j = 1</p>
    <p>i;j min</p>
    <p>h2Hi;j kh  h(N )i;j k</p>
    <p>h(N )i;j</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 17 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Detection of Different Location</p>
    <p>Want to test two cases H0: New Meast at same location H1: New Meast at different location</p>
    <p>Two conditional densities for distance d</p>
    <p>PFA = Probability of false alarm PD = Probability of detection</p>
    <p>Choose a threshold ?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 18 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Measurement Experiment</p>
    <p>Meast set from Motorola office area</p>
    <p>Using 40 MHz direct sequence spreadspectrum (DSSS) Tx and Rx</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 19 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Measurement Experiment</p>
    <p>13 by 15 m area, and 44 devices</p>
    <p>5 measts per link (over 30 sec)</p>
    <p>44 x 43 x 5 = 9460 measurements</p>
    <p>Manual procedure, Mostly stationaryNode locations</p>
    <p>measured Cubicle Partitions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 20 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Leave-one-out Comparison</p>
    <p>Temporal Differences:</p>
    <p>Compare N = 5 meast from same link (i,j) to History for (i,j)</p>
    <p>Spatial Differences:</p>
    <p>Compare N = 5 meast from different link (k,j) to History for (i,j)</p>
    <p>i j</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>i j</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 21 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Example Link Signatures Li</p>
    <p>nk 1</p>
    <p>How different are they?  Temporal Differences:</p>
    <p>Li nk</p>
    <p>to 4</p>
    <p>h(n)i;j n = 1; : : : ; 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 22 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Link Signatures: Worst Case</p>
    <p>Temporal channel changes can cause changes  most widely varying set</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 23 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Comparing Results</p>
    <p>Three methods  RSS [Faria 2006]</p>
    <p>Link Signature</p>
    <p>Amplitude-Normalized Link Signature</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 24 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Performance with one Rx</p>
    <p>Adjustable results based on threshold Zoom in</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 25 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Heavy Tail on Worst Links</p>
    <p>Worst 5% of links cause 46% of missed detections  System could disable link signatures for</p>
    <p>highly varying links</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 26 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Multiple Receivers</p>
    <p>Can employ more than one receiver (access point)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 27 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Performance with Three Rx  Significantly higher reliability compared to one Rx</p>
    <p>Zoom in</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 28 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Multiple RX Summary</p>
    <p>Table 1: False Alarm Rates for Constant 95% Detection Rate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 29 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Robust location distinction can be achieved using temporal link signatures</p>
    <p>Significant improvement over RSS-only signature methods</p>
    <p>Future work  Comparison w/ freq-domain link signatures [Li 06]  Study other link characteristics, metrics  Real-time Implementation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 30 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Measurement Data Access</p>
    <p>SPAN Website  http://span.ece.utah.edu/  Under Data &amp; Tools</p>
    <p>To appear in CRAWDAD</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 31 Neal Patwari and Sneha Kasera, Robust Location Distinction Using Temporal Link Signatures, ACM MobiCom 2007.</p>
    <p>Threat Model</p>
    <p>Attacker can  listen to all wireless traffic  compromise encryption  use attenuators, amplifiers, directional antennas,</p>
    <p>software radios</p>
    <p>Attacker cannot  be at location of user  be at location of access points</p>
    <p>System deployment must have multiple coverage</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
