<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tradeoffs between Stretch Factor and Load Balancing Ratio in Routing on Growth Restricted Graphs</p>
    <p>Jie Gao Stanford University</p>
    <p>jgao@cs.stanford.edu</p>
    <p>Li Zhang Hewlett-Packard Labs</p>
    <p>l.zhang@hp.com</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Short paths and load balancing</p>
    <p>A routing algorithm delivers a packet with size i from source si to</p>
    <p>destination ti.</p>
    <p>Two desirable properties on routing algorithms:</p>
    <p>Short paths: e.g. shortest path routing.</p>
    <p>Load balancing: nodes are evenly loaded.</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Stretch factor and load balancing ratio</p>
    <p>Stretch factor: max{ routing path lengthshortest path length };</p>
    <p>A path is c-short if its length is at most c times the shortest path length.</p>
    <p>Load balancing ratio: max traffic on any node</p>
    <p>max traffic of the OPT off-line Alg .</p>
    <p>Question: Can we have good ratios under both measures simultaneously?</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>For general graphs, the answer is No</p>
    <p>These two properties are conflicting to some extent.</p>
    <p>c</p>
    <p>pi qi</p>
    <p>o p1 q1</p>
    <p>All the c-short paths from pi to qi have to pass though o. So the load</p>
    <p>balancing ratio for c-short routing is (n/c).</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Growth-restricted graphs</p>
    <p>A graph has growth rate k and density  if the number of nodes within</p>
    <p>distance r of any vertex is no more than rk.</p>
    <p>Graphs with restricted growth appear naturally:</p>
    <p>Meshes, VLSI layout networks.  Internet latencies embedded in geometric space, e.g., [Ng&amp;Zhang</p>
    <p>Peer-to-peer overlay networks;  Wireless ad hoc networks.</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ad hoc wireless networks</p>
    <p>Unit-disk Graphs: A set of wireless nodes in the plane, any two can</p>
    <p>communicate directly if they are within Euclidean distance 1.</p>
    <p>q p</p>
    <p>If node density (# nodes inside any unit disk)  , then a disk with radius r can only cover O(r2) nodes  the unit disk graph has density</p>
    <p>O() and growth rate 2.</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 6</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>For a graph with density  and growth rate k, the load balancing ratio of the optimal c-short routing is ((n/c)11/k1/k).</p>
    <p>Shortest path routing on unit disk graphs with constant density, or 2-d meshes has load balancing ratio (</p>
    <p>n).</p>
    <p>An online algorithm that produces (log n) approximate load balancing ratio by using only c-short paths.</p>
    <p>For unit disk graphs, if the average node density is , the load balancing ratio of shortest path routing is O(min(</p>
    <p>n log n, n)).</p>
    <p>The load balancing ratio of OPT routing on a c-spanner of a unit disk graph is (r2).</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>This talk</p>
    <p>For a unit disk graph with maximum node density , assume the optimal</p>
    <p>load balanced routing algorithm produces maximum load , shortest path</p>
    <p>routing produces maximum load 1.</p>
    <p>Theorem 0.1. The load balancing ratio of shortest path routing is 1/ = (</p>
    <p>n).</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lower bound</p>
    <p>m</p>
    <p>qk</p>
    <p>(cm)</p>
    <p>(cm)</p>
    <p>u v pk</p>
    <p>p1 q1</p>
    <p>Choose m =</p>
    <p>n/(c). The load balancing ratio of any c-short routing is</p>
    <p>(m) = (</p>
    <p>n/c).</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 9</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Upper bound proof</p>
    <p>Assume the requests are R = {(si, ti, i)} and p is the node with highest load by shortest path routing.</p>
    <p>W.l.o.g, assume all the requests R are routed through p by shortest path</p>
    <p>routing. 1 = (p) =  =</p>
    <p>i.</p>
    <p>We want to upper bound  = /.</p>
    <p>Intuition: if shortest path routing creates a high load on p, the OPT</p>
    <p>algorithm also has to create a high load.</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Upper bound proof, cont.</p>
    <p>Now we study how to route the requests Ri generated in each annulus Bi (with inner radius 2i1 and outer radius 2i) by the OPT routing algorithm.</p>
    <p>tj</p>
    <p>B0 sj</p>
    <p>p</p>
    <p>B2</p>
    <p>B1</p>
    <p>The shortest path from sj to tj goes through p. So the optimal routing path Pj has length at least 2</p>
    <p>i1. Take Aj as the first 2 i1 nodes on Pj .</p>
    <p>Si =</p>
    <p>sj Bi Aj .</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Upper bound proof, cont.</p>
    <p>p</p>
    <p>B1</p>
    <p>sj</p>
    <p>S1</p>
    <p>The total load on Si:</p>
    <p>vSi (v)</p>
    <p>sj Bi j|Aj| = 2i1</p>
    <p>sj Bi j .</p>
    <p>On the other hand, each node has maximum load .</p>
    <p>vSi (v)  |Si|  c0(2i1)2/.</p>
    <p>Therefore,</p>
    <p>sj Bi j /  c02i1/.</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Upper bound proof, cont.</p>
    <p>For each Bi,</p>
    <p>sj Bi j /  c02i1/.</p>
    <p>By summing up over all i, we have,</p>
    <p>Lemma 0.2. Suppose D is the disk with radius  centered at p, then</p>
    <p>sj D j /  c0 /, for some constant c0 &gt; 0.</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Upper bound proof, cont.</p>
    <p>p</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>sj</p>
    <p>Take   to be the smallest radius such that</p>
    <p>sj D j /  1/2. Then</p>
    <p>2c0 .</p>
    <p>On the other hand, for all the requests generated outside D , each i will</p>
    <p>contribute at least i  to the total load.    /(6n).</p>
    <p>Therefore,   min(2c0 , 6n/ )  O(</p>
    <p>n). QED</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Growth restricted graphs</p>
    <p>The proof can be extended to show,</p>
    <p>Theorem 0.3. For a graph with density  and growth rate k, , the load balancing ratio of the optimal c-short path routing is ((n/c)11/k1/k).</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 15</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Short path load balanced routing</p>
    <p>We propose an online algorithm with (log n)-approximate load</p>
    <p>balancing ratio using only c-short paths.</p>
    <p>Idea: Modify the online algorithm [Aspnes et al., 1993] for competitive</p>
    <p>online virtual circuit routing.</p>
    <p>Assign weights to edges.</p>
    <p>Find the lightest weight path among all c-short paths.</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 16</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Contribution: a thorough study on the tradeoffs between stretch factor and</p>
    <p>load balancing ratio for routing on growth restricted graphs.</p>
    <p>Tight bounds;  An online algorithm with competitive load balancing ratio by using</p>
    <p>only short paths.</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 17</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!</p>
    <p>July 27, 2004 J. Gao, L. Zhang @ PODC 2004 18</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
