<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Toward Risk Assessment as a Service in Cloud Environments</p>
    <p>Burton S. Kaliski Jr. and Wayne Pauley EMC Corporation HotCloud 10 June 22, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Risk Assessment: Definition</p>
    <p>Quantitative and/or qualitative valuation of risk in a specific context against a given threat with a probability of occurrence</p>
    <p>Includes system characterization, threat assessment, vulnerability analysis, impact analysis, and risk determination</p>
    <p>Many well-established standards for assessing security; some for privacy as well</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Risk Assessment in the Cloud: Challenges</p>
    <p>Cloud Characteristic (per NIST)</p>
    <p>Challenge</p>
    <p>On-Demand SelfService</p>
    <p>Human interaction is replaced with automated controls  which now must be trained to pass security audits</p>
    <p>Broad Network Access</p>
    <p>Endpoints can be any type, location, not just a pre-approved set</p>
    <p>Resource Pooling  Dynamic allocation, virtualization mean that resources are not known in advance  Multi-tenancy brings threats in house  Location independence introduces significant diversity in applicable laws</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Risk Assessment in the Cloud: Challenges</p>
    <p>Cloud Characteristic (per NIST)</p>
    <p>Challenge</p>
    <p>Rapid Elasticity  Cloud bursting engages multiple levels of sub-providers, who must also be assessed</p>
    <p>Measured Service  Metering information has more detail about multiple tenants  a higher-value target  Economics of the cloud also complicate assessments:</p>
    <p>cloud infrastructures will be constantly changing due to market growth, M&amp;A  risk assessments will rapidly become stale</p>
    <p>cost competition may discourage investment in risk assessments while increasing risk-taking</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proposal: Risk Assessment as a Service</p>
    <p>Approach: an automated risk score (e.g. like credit score)</p>
    <p>for a given tenant or application  or for general use  pre-assessment and on-demand</p>
    <p>Modes: provider self-assessment, third-party audit, consumer assessment (non-privileged)</p>
    <p>internal and external agents involved</p>
    <p>Policy-based IT management translates assessment of underlying dynamic resources into overall score</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Architecture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Topics for Further Research</p>
    <p>Automated measurement and analysis for risk assessment</p>
    <p>What sensors are needed? What language to use?  E.g., CloudAudit defines a dictionary based on common</p>
    <p>standards</p>
    <p>Automated adjustment based on the assessment  Trust assurances for measurements</p>
    <p>Who guards the guards?</p>
    <p>Effectiveness of automated assessment vs. traditional approaches</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contact Information</p>
    <p>Burt Kaliski Director, EMC Innovation Network Founding Scientist, RSA Laboratories kaliski_burt@emc.com community.emc.com/people/kalisb</p>
    <p>Wayne Pauley Director, Global Product Sales wayne.pauley@emc.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
