<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Constructivist Information Security Awareness</p>
    <p>M.Boujettif (Italtel, boujettif@yahoo.com) &amp; Y.Wang (UCCC)</p>
    <p>BWCCA 2010</p>
    <p>Fukuoka Institute of Technology, Fukuoka, Japan</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Abstract</p>
    <p>The application a unique approach to enhancing information security awareness amongst employees, in effort to improve information security</p>
    <p>Surveyed the current attitudes and awareness levels of 116 employees in 30 companies towards information security</p>
    <p>2 companies opted to implement our new approach (CISA) based on a highly-employee centred constructivist method</p>
    <p>The CISA approach aims to benefit the employees at</p>
    <p>different levels as it effects and encourages employee learning autonomy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Constructivist Information Security Awareness (CISA)</p>
    <p>CISA encourages CIOs and end users to improve their awareness regarding risks associated with utilising ICT</p>
    <p>CISA builds a conscious awareness of ones own</p>
    <p>attitude. This is deemed important in improving information security</p>
    <p>Attitudes play an important role in information security behaviour</p>
    <p>We confirm a positive correlation between poor/negative attitudes and low levels of information security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Interviewed CIOs;</p>
    <p>We established their current information security levels and  Conducted questionnaires to determine the employees attitudes</p>
    <p>Compared the results for any suspected correlations</p>
    <p>2 companies chosen which were established as having poor information security and whose employees exhibited negative and/or poor information security attitudes:</p>
    <p>We introduced them to our unique information security programme (CISA) based on constructive methods</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Questions  Research's main questions:</p>
    <p>Correlation between information security levels &amp; attitudes towards information security?</p>
    <p>Usefulness of constructivist training methodologies to improve information security awareness?</p>
    <p>Expected - Companies had security awareness campaigns but do they measure the effects of such campaigns on the employees attitudes and behaviour?</p>
    <p>How do we know that the campaigns are working?  Do the campaigns really improve users attitudes and behaviour</p>
    <p>towards information security?</p>
    <p>Results were used to establish effective security campaigns based on constructivist approach</p>
    <p>What is this approach?  Individualised, user-centred free learning environment where users are in</p>
    <p>control of their own learning process  Investigation has never been applied in the context of information security, IT</p>
    <p>security (even telecom security), and this makes this project unique</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Human Element</p>
    <p>Information Security : Traditionally conjures up images of complexity (HW &amp; SW)  Only implementable by a professional security firms!</p>
    <p>Previous researchers, like Stanton et al (2003), Schneier (2000), and Katsikas (2000) have warned that</p>
    <p>its not only the technical software or hardware aspects that introduce vulnerabilities into an information system, rather its the users of the system which pose the greatest and most serious information security risk.</p>
    <p>The human element needs to be dealt with first and foremost! Stephanou &amp; Dagada (2008)</p>
    <p>Procedures/ Policies are implemented to encourage people (Administrators/ Users/ Operators) how to use products to ensure information security within the organizations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Importance of Human Element</p>
    <p>Natural question: How do we deal with or influence the human aspect?</p>
    <p>Rules/Threats;  Punishment maybe? Fine?</p>
    <p>Imprisonment? Loss of Job?  Information! Training! Education!</p>
    <p>Training &amp; education in a subject  Better track record of effecting the perceptions/ attitudes towards that subject</p>
    <p>Environment and pedagogy (methods of training) have a lot to do with the individuals perception (Ann, Timothy and Laubach [2001])</p>
    <p>Changing or improving perceptions/attitudes towards something is rather challenging  Why?</p>
    <p>Avoiding? Moving Away?  Bad Perceptions &amp; Feelings!</p>
    <p>Exemplified in the fields of academia/training where peoples dislike of challenging subjects (such as Science and Mathematics)</p>
    <p>An effective ISA Programme needs to seek to influence and improve the users education training, and guide their understanding of IS concepts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Middle Eastern Companies</p>
    <p>Home grown Middle-Eastern companies pay little attention to ISA:</p>
    <p>Never existed  Little understood / appreciated</p>
    <p>Ambiguous and ineffective policies towards information security are due to:</p>
    <p>Genuine lack of awareness  Blas attitude by both senior</p>
    <p>management and senior security professionals</p>
    <p>Campaigns were basic (warnings via email/ posters)</p>
    <p>Increasing the appreciation of ISA programmes was done by ensuring the development of effective employee centred programmes:</p>
    <p>Entails imparting of knowledge whether in a training format or in a more academic format</p>
    <p>Information presented in a manner that is designed to change unfavourable perceptions and attitudes to desirable ones</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attitudes &amp; Perceptions</p>
    <p>What are perception and attitudes?</p>
    <p>Attitudes govern a persons personality beliefs, values, and motivations</p>
    <p>Three components:  1) Affect (feeling),  2) Cognition (thought or</p>
    <p>belief)  3) behaviour (an action)</p>
    <p>Individuals even try to employing interesting tactics in an attempt to reduce dissonance (conflict)</p>
    <p>Eliminating his/her responsibility or control over an act or decision</p>
    <p>Denying, distorting, or selectively forgetting information</p>
    <p>Minimizing the importance of the issue, decision, or act</p>
    <p>Develop an ISA programme that reduces the cognitive dissonance (conflict)</p>
    <p>Attitude formation: a result of learning, modelling others, direct experiences with people and situations</p>
    <p>Attitudes have different strengths, and are learned or influenced through experience and they can be changed!</p>
    <p>The method of measuring/assessing attitude via how strongly one agrees or disagrees (like or dislike) with a statement and ticking a 15 scale</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Constructivism</p>
    <p>Anything that may cause a sense of failure and/or negative feelings  Complexity is one of them</p>
    <p>Attitude change occurs  addressing cognitive and emotional components via new information</p>
    <p>Employing methods utilised in</p>
    <p>pedagogical circles. Have track record of yielding positive results</p>
    <p>One proven method in making positive changes to ones attitude and perceptions;  Constructivist methodology</p>
    <p>...commitment to the idea that the development of understanding requires active engagement on the part of the learner.</p>
    <p>Naylor and Keogh (1999)</p>
    <p>...principles of this approach ... learners can only make sense of new situations in terms of their existing understanding. Learning involves an active process ... learners construct meaning by linking new ideas with their existing knowledge.</p>
    <p>Active learning approaches were found to be beneficial and positive in improving academic achievement,/ attitude and concept learning (Anzai &amp; Simon [1979], Maria &amp; Rosetta [2005])</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CISA Programme</p>
    <p>Our CISA Programme entails:</p>
    <p>Elements of transfer of knowledge</p>
    <p>Conducive environment of learning</p>
    <p>Material is learner-friendly/learner-centric</p>
    <p>Little or no instruction or explanation</p>
    <p>Encourages active and engaging environment with virtual independence in learning</p>
    <p>CISA approach allow users to develop information security material and activities that would contain their own terminology and explanations which they themselves construct and understand</p>
    <p>Avoids passive learning</p>
    <p>Move towards active and interactive learning</p>
    <p>Learners relate information security to their daily lives and how it affects them and their colleagues</p>
    <p>The material: information security warnings, posters, emails and policies can sometimes be daunting and unwieldy therefore allow participants to feel more ownership in gaining a deeper understanding. Guaranteed since they constructed the material that they comprehend and understand</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Method and Realisation</p>
    <p>Sample size: 240 individuals, only 116 responded accurately and concisely</p>
    <p>30 CIOs interviewed  Survey attitudes and perceptions</p>
    <p>Questionpro (2007)  University of Florida IT Security</p>
    <p>Awareness (2009)  TCET (1997)</p>
    <p>Results were validated for consistence and disparate answers were removed leaving only consistent data outcomes</p>
    <p>Single case-study with a questionnaire administered in two companies (sample ISA material)</p>
    <p>Sample Size</p>
    <p>No Response Responded CIO</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Information Security Awareness  ISA</p>
    <p>Respondents indicate shocking low level of information security awareness for example their internet and email usage behaviours:</p>
    <p>Rather concerning results - Real lack of training ISA needs</p>
    <p>Current ISA programmes are ineffective and have profound consequences on information security</p>
    <p>No backup of w ork f ilesSimple passw ord structureWithout latest updates</p>
    <p>ISA Awareness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Employees ISA</p>
    <p>Information Security policies, procedures were little understood and rarely recognised or appreciated;</p>
    <p>Concerning situation: witnessed in the majority of KSA companies give us a reasonable microcosm of the possible state of information security awareness in and around the Middle East</p>
    <p>Levels of ISA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Respondents Attitudes</p>
    <p>Respondents Attitudes: Respondents attitudes towards interactive learning as indicated by the respondents were positive:</p>
    <p>Activities that may motivate the learning of new concepts were ones which required challenging, creating and Inventing activities as indicated by the results:</p>
    <p>Attitudes To Learning</p>
    <p>Uniqueness Doing Inventing Groups</p>
    <p>Learning New Concepts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Learning Environment</p>
    <p>When faced with a learning environment which either meant learning by oneself or in a team with colleagues the following results were garnered:</p>
    <p>In terms of the importance for there being an enjoying and fun environment:</p>
    <p>Learning Environment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Learning Preferences</p>
    <p>Respondents attitudes towards their thinking styles may indicate their preferences on how they approach challenges in learning etc.:</p>
    <p>Preferences</p>
    <p>Respondents attitudes towards visual stimuli were quite conclusive and were recorded as follows:</p>
    <p>Visual</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Constructivist ISA: Task 1</p>
    <p>Employees requested to construct an email message in 45 minutes (after CIO scrutiny)</p>
    <p>Access to resources (internet, written material on IS etc) requested to examine and identify important ISA aspects which needed to be transmitted in the email that they created. Requested to make it creative and funny. To encourage more fun, kinaesthetic</p>
    <p>Focus on convergent and divergent thinking by encouraging and balancing fact (actual ISA information) and feasibility (funny cartoon), and striking equilibrium between structure and flexibility</p>
    <p>Remarkable features:  Vocal and visible expressions of happiness and jubilation</p>
    <p>from the groups were experienced  Excited and animated on returning their created</p>
    <p>group effort email  Happy and cheerful for completing the task</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Constructivist ISA : Task 2,3,4,5...</p>
    <p>Sample Task 2: Videoed Presentation : Produce a 2 minute videoed presentation similar to a youtube.com</p>
    <p>Sample Task 3: Quiz Creation: Produce an ISA quiz written around a geometric shape that would be cut converted into a 3D shape e.g. a cube. displayed on their desk</p>
    <p>Sample Task 4: Poster Creation: Importance of Backup</p>
    <p>Sample Task 5: For and Against Discussion : Chose an ISA concept from set cards then instructed to think up arguments for and against later asked to defend the concept</p>
    <p>Sample Task 6: Approximations : Employees requested to guess as accurately as possible the volume capacity of two vessels (e.g. a cup and testtube) representing ISA statistics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation  Our survey shows that 91% preferred the</p>
    <p>CISA constructivist approached (App. 2)</p>
    <p>Traditional methods of disseminating and delivering ISA programmes maybe ineffective</p>
    <p>Negative effect on the intrinsic motivation/ attitude in learning ISA concepts</p>
    <p>Employees preferred to develop and construct their own material interactively</p>
    <p>CIOs should consider adopting constructivist methodologies to improve ISA awareness</p>
    <p>Employees attitudes had transformed when CISA was implemented</p>
    <p>Employees wanted freedom from the confines of formal passive learning (in keeping with previous research findings)</p>
    <p>Case Study Results</p>
    <p>Approach 2 Approach 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CONCLUSIONS  Employees can be blamed for traditional ISA paradigm as they tend to expect experts</p>
    <p>to transfer the knowledge to them</p>
    <p>Learners construct their own knowledge - interaction with environment</p>
    <p>At the heart of CISA approach: Employees must understand Information Security but also develop thinking skills (analysis, reasoning, problem solving) otherwise they gain only a superficial attitude and awareness towards ISA</p>
    <p>Security experts should employ constructivist methods</p>
    <p>This study made use of constructivist methods to enhance employee awareness of information security ideas and concepts through the interactive collaboration of employees in playing a more centric role developing and enthusing the company ISA program with interactive and enjoyable activities</p>
    <p>There was a perceived improvement in information security awareness. The significant findings and results of this study were;</p>
    <p>91% of the employees in the case-study preferred the new approach (Constructivist ISA) as opposed to traditional programs</p>
    <p>94% of the employees surveyed were dissatisfied with their companies current information security programs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
