<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>A Performance Study of Deployment Factors in Wireless Mesh Networks</p>
    <p>Joshua Robinson and Edward Knightly Rice University</p>
    <p>Rice Networks Group networks.rice.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>City-wide Wireless Deployments</p>
    <p>Many new city-wide wireless mesh networks being planned or deployed: Two-tier mesh networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Houston-wide Wireless Network</p>
    <p>620 square miles of coverage:</p>
    <p>95% Outside  90% Inside (window)</p>
    <p>Earthlink  $50 million estimated cost  15k mesh nodes and 3k</p>
    <p>gateways</p>
    <p>Operational by 2009  Miami-Dade Co. wants 2k</p>
    <p>sq. miles coverage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Deployment Strategies</p>
    <p>State of the art deployment strategies</p>
    <p>Exhaustive survey (WLAN, cellular) costly  Community networks do not cover efficiently  Rules of thumb in practice</p>
    <p>Problem: what deployment factors are important to mesh performance and why?</p>
    <p>For general network environments, not specific</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Deployment Factors and Mesh Performance</p>
    <p>We identify critical deployment factors and explore how they affect mesh performance</p>
    <p>Topology and Architecture</p>
    <p>Mesh topology structures  Multiple radios for access</p>
    <p>and backhaul</p>
    <p>Number of wired gateways</p>
    <p>Real-world limitations</p>
    <p>Placement perturbations  Unplanned deployments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Three Mesh Performance Criteria</p>
    <p>Goals for a high-performance mesh network?</p>
    <p>Focus on each part of the mesh: access tier, backhaul tier, and gateway nodes</p>
    <p>Ubiquitous coverage  High quality routes to a gateway  Fairly support many simultaneous flows</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Three Mesh Performance Criteria</p>
    <p>Goals for a high-performance mesh network?</p>
    <p>Ubiquitous coverage</p>
    <p>High quality routes to a gateway  Fairly support many simultaneous flows</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Three Mesh Performance Criteria</p>
    <p>Goals for a high-performance mesh network?</p>
    <p>Ubiquitous coverage  High quality routes to a gateway</p>
    <p>Fairly support many simultaneous flows</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Three Mesh Performance Criteria</p>
    <p>Goals for a high-performance mesh network?</p>
    <p>Ubiquitous coverage  High quality routes to a gateway  Fairly support many simultaneous flows</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Evaluating Mesh Performance</p>
    <p>Three mesh performance metrics</p>
    <p>Identify and study the deployment factors that control each metric</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Evaluation Methodology</p>
    <p>Calculating each performance metric</p>
    <p>Compute performance of each mesh node and client location  Use measurement data to drive study  Monte Carlo simulations for topologies  Infinite plane topology, no edge results reported  Performance of single-link fundamental</p>
    <p>Well-known pathloss model</p>
    <p>PdBm(d) = PdBm(d0)  10log10( d</p>
    <p>d0 ) +</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Technology-For-All (TFA) Mesh Testbed</p>
    <p>Operational mesh in pilot neighborhood in Houstons East End (Pecan Park)</p>
    <p>Status: 18 nodes with approximately 3 km2 of coverage and 2,000 users</p>
    <p>Operational since May 2005  More info at tfa.rice.edu  Results presented use TFA</p>
    <p>measurements for pathloss*</p>
    <p>* Measurement Driven Deployment of a Two-Tier Urban Mesh Access Network In Proceedings of MobiSys 2006.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Coverage Area</p>
    <p>Coverage area is the expected fraction of client locations which connect to a mesh node above a threshold signal strength</p>
    <p>Threshold value is 2 Mbps  Connect to at least one mesh node  Uniform user distribution</p>
    <p>Controlling topology factors: Mesh node density and configuration</p>
    <p>Figure: Two access nodes with poor coverage.</p>
    <p>Coverage = 1   i</p>
    <p>(1  Probdi [X &gt; Tmin])</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Coverage Area, Regular and Random</p>
    <p>Mesh Node Density (per km2)</p>
    <p>C ov</p>
    <p>er ag</p>
    <p>e A</p>
    <p>re a</p>
    <p>Square Triangular Hexagonal Random</p>
    <p>Ideal grid placement and 2-d Poisson point process  Compare mesh node densities, equivalent resources  95% coverage: random requires twice the density!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Perturbations from Ideal Grid Placement</p>
    <p>Regular Perturbed</p>
    <p>Not usually possible to deploy a perfect grid  Random angle and distance chosen from uniform distribution  Results from averaging 100 trials</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Mesh Node Perturbations</p>
    <p>Fix average node density at 20 nodes per km2</p>
    <p>Inter-node spacing for square grid is 225 meters</p>
    <p>Coverage declines only 3% up to 1</p>
    <p>spacing</p>
    <p>High perturbation better than coverage of random networks 0 50 100 1500.65</p>
    <p>Average Perturbation (meters)</p>
    <p>Fr ac</p>
    <p>tio n</p>
    <p>of C</p>
    <p>lie nt</p>
    <p>L oc</p>
    <p>at io</p>
    <p>ns C</p>
    <p>ov er</p>
    <p>ed</p>
    <p>Square Random</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Deploying with Perturbations</p>
    <p>Average Perturbation Distance (meters)</p>
    <p>R eq</p>
    <p>ui re</p>
    <p>d M</p>
    <p>es h</p>
    <p>D en</p>
    <p>si ty</p>
    <p>(n od</p>
    <p>es p</p>
    <p>er k</p>
    <p>m 2 )</p>
    <p>Coverages declines because of increasing dead spots  Resource demands for 95% coverage grow rapidly with</p>
    <p>perturbations above 40 meters</p>
    <p>Perturbations of 1 5</p>
    <p>inter-node distance correspond to 25% over-provisioning</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Fair Mesh Capacity</p>
    <p>Model a gateway node as alternating between:</p>
    <p>Rx/Tx to one-hop neighbors  Deferring to other neighbors within interference range</p>
    <p>Capacity is then found by the percentage of time doing Rx/Tx</p>
    <p>All flows receive fair time shares  Depends on gateway placement and routing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Calculating Fair Mesh Capacity</p>
    <p>Find routes first, then Tx/Rx and Defer times</p>
    <p>Uniform distribution of clients  Two-hop neighbors interfere  Single-radio system  Assume fair scheduling exists  Longer routes add more defer time Figure: Square grid</p>
    <p>network with wire ratio of 1 16</p>
    <p>= Tx/Rx Time</p>
    <p>Tx/Rx Time + Defer Time = 16</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Second Radio for the Access Tier</p>
    <p>Architectural Feature: dedicated radios for access and backhaul links</p>
    <p>Client to Mesh transmissions do not interfere on wireless backhaul</p>
    <p>Figure: With two radios, fair share is 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Calculating Capacity for Two Radios</p>
    <p>= 16 33</p>
    <p>= 48%</p>
    <p>Backhaul tier is 39% more efficient  Expect fair mesh capacity to increase proportionally  Spatial reuse decreases benefits</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Fair Mesh Capacity Results</p>
    <p>Mesh Node Density (nodes per km2)</p>
    <p>A dj</p>
    <p>us te</p>
    <p>d Fa</p>
    <p>ir M</p>
    <p>es h</p>
    <p>C ap</p>
    <p>ac ity</p>
    <p>(k bp</p>
    <p>s)</p>
    <p>Separate Access Unified Access</p>
    <p>Backhaul tier has more time available for useful transmissions  Fair mesh capacity increases by factor of almost 2  Adjusted capacity does not include the clients at a wired</p>
    <p>gateway</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Summary and Contributions</p>
    <p>Measurement-driven methodology for evaluating mesh network performance</p>
    <p>Coverage, connectivity, and capacity metrics  Topology, architecture, deployment factors</p>
    <p>Identified critical deployment factors and how they impact mesh performance, including</p>
    <p>Coverage Area: studies regular grids, random networks, and the impact of perturbations</p>
    <p>Connectivity: studied asymmetric links, redundant paths, and multiple backhaul radios</p>
    <p>Fair Mesh Capacity: studied regular grid topologies, random networks, and two-radio mesh architectures</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background Methodology Results Conclusion</p>
    <p>Ongoing and Future Work</p>
    <p>Continued Expansion of the TFA network</p>
    <p>Doubling the number of mesh nodes and gateways Deployment issues</p>
    <p>Selecting gateway placements  Optimal deployment strategies  Increasing capacity with additional radios</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
