<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bypassing Internet Censorship for News Broadcasters</p>
    <p>Karl Kathuria</p>
    <p>British Broadcasting Corporation and Canada Centre for Global Security Studies</p>
    <p>Munk School of Global Affairs, University of Toronto</p>
    <p>Abstract</p>
    <p>News organizations are often the targets of Internet censorship. This paper will look at two technical considerations</p>
    <p>for the BBC, based on its distribution of non-English content into countries such as Iran and China, where the news</p>
    <p>services are permanently unavailable from the official BBC websites: blocking detection and circumvention. This</p>
    <p>study examines an internal BBC prototype system built in 2010 to detect online censorship of its content, and eva</p>
    <p>luates potential improvements. It will also review the BBCs use of circumvention tools, and consider the impact and</p>
    <p>execution of pilot services for Iran and China. Finally, the study will consider the technical delivery of the BBCs</p>
    <p>news output, and the methods it employs to bypass Internet censorship.</p>
    <p>The British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC) provides</p>
    <p>programmes and content for radio, television, online,</p>
    <p>and mobile phones in English and 27 other languages.</p>
    <p>There is currently an increased focus on delivery of its</p>
    <p>services online, as the amount of radio content has re</p>
    <p>duced, both in terms of hours of output and infrastruc</p>
    <p>ture for shortwave delivery. However, some of the ser</p>
    <p>vices that are considered strategically important are for</p>
    <p>countries in which BBC news content has been blocked,</p>
    <p>either short term or persistently.</p>
    <p>This paper looks at two technical considerations for the</p>
    <p>BBC, based on its distribution of non-English content</p>
    <p>into countries such as Iran and China, where news ser</p>
    <p>vices are permanently unavailable from the official</p>
    <p>BBC websites: blocking detection and circumvention. It</p>
    <p>will then consider other ways in which content can be</p>
    <p>delivered where BBC web sites are inaccessible, and</p>
    <p>how the BBC can continue to reach its audience when</p>
    <p>its services are blocked.</p>
    <p>When the BBC knows that one of its web sites has been</p>
    <p>suddenly made unavailable due to a blocking event, it</p>
    <p>can put into place processes for dealing with that block.</p>
    <p>However, it first needs to gain an awareness of when</p>
    <p>and why its services are being blocked. To address this</p>
    <p>requirement, the BBC developed a software prototype</p>
    <p>Geostats  to detect blocking events.</p>
    <p>The development of Geostats was motivated by two</p>
    <p>factors. First, during the first half of 2010, there were</p>
    <p>several false alarms, where audience members had</p>
    <p>written to the BBC language services to report that con</p>
    <p>tent was being blocked in their country. When these</p>
    <p>claims were investigated, it was found that the inacces</p>
    <p>sibility was not due to filtering, but likely the result of</p>
    <p>various network conditions and outages that made con</p>
    <p>tent unavailable for short periods of time, or in some</p>
    <p>cases, improperly configured computers. Investigating</p>
    <p>each of these possibilities was taking up time and re</p>
    <p>sources for the team responsible for content distribu</p>
    <p>tion.</p>
    <p>Second, conversations with Google revealed that their</p>
    <p>Transparency Report [1] was nearing completion. The</p>
    <p>theories behind this project would form part of the brief</p>
    <p>for the BBC to create its own software to detect censor</p>
    <p>ship. The Geostats project was set up using technical</p>
    <p>experts from BBC World Service, who developed a</p>
    <p>system based on five key requirements:</p>
    <p>the BBCs own web bug-based software used</p>
    <p>publicly to display the current Most Read / Most</p>
    <p>Emailed stories on bbc.com/news and World Ser</p>
    <p>vice language web sites in near real-time; and</p>
    <p>server logs from the streaming media provider,</p>
    <p>showing technical details regarding the serving of</p>
    <p>streaming media.</p>
    <p>would generally report traffic along the zero-line of</p>
    <p>a graph regardless of the time and day. Extremes</p>
    <p>could then be attributed to either major news events</p>
    <p>or possible blocking of content. Any time the data</p>
    <p>was +/-60% of normal, an alert state would be re</p>
    <p>ported.</p>
    <p>query external data sources for more information</p>
    <p>when an alert state was reached.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>be used both for technical analysis and manage</p>
    <p>ment summary</p>
    <p>There are three main processes behind the Geostats</p>
    <p>implementation: database import, building the behav</p>
    <p>iour model, and displaying the results.</p>
    <p>Two sets of data were collected. First, Livestats data</p>
    <p>was received hourly via an API call to the system, and</p>
    <p>put into a database table. Data captured included coun</p>
    <p>try code, timestamp, number of hits and number of</p>
    <p>unique IP addresses.</p>
    <p>BBC streaming media is hosted by Akamai, the Content</p>
    <p>Delivery Network (CDN). Log data is collected hourly,</p>
    <p>and contains information about every piece of streaming</p>
    <p>media served by the BBC language sites, including the</p>
    <p>IP address of every computer accessing the audio and</p>
    <p>video. Approximately 30GB of uncompressed log data</p>
    <p>is collected daily.</p>
    <p>The data from Akamai is then taken per hour per log</p>
    <p>file and put into a similar table, with a country code,</p>
    <p>timestamp and number of hits.</p>
    <p>For both database tables in the prototype, the country</p>
    <p>codes were found with geographical IP lookups using</p>
    <p>software from Maxmind (maxmind.com). The next step</p>
    <p>is to normalise the data, and to identify the expected</p>
    <p>traffic at any given hour in the day. Scripts are sched</p>
    <p>uled to run hourly (using crontab), converting the new</p>
    <p>data into JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) objects.</p>
    <p>This data is presented using PHP and Open Flash</p>
    <p>Charts (OFC).</p>
    <p>Figure 1 shows the shape of processed data over a 3-day</p>
    <p>period for both collection methods, showing content</p>
    <p>served to Vietnam. Every day, there is a morning, after</p>
    <p>noon, and evening peak for traffica pattern that is</p>
    <p>repeated throughout the week, albeit with lower traffic</p>
    <p>levels at weekends.</p>
    <p>Figure 1: Shape of daily traffic to Vietnam over 3 days</p>
    <p>The simple calculation used to create a normal value</p>
    <p>was based on an average for any given hour and day of</p>
    <p>the week, built up over the life of the system. Therefore,</p>
    <p>the expected level of traffic for Monday at 10.00 would</p>
    <p>be defined by the average of all previous traffic levels</p>
    <p>for any given Monday at 10.00.</p>
    <p>This calculation is imperfect, and forms the basis of one</p>
    <p>of the improvements identified for the system, but pro</p>
    <p>vided a reasonable starting point. The resulting average</p>
    <p>is inserted into another database table for comparison</p>
    <p>against current levels. The fields are: hits; country code;</p>
    <p>hour of day (0-23); day of week (0-6).</p>
    <p>At this point, a graph can be created to show the level of</p>
    <p>traffic compared to its expected value, and for this de</p>
    <p>viation to be plotted around the zero-line, the level de</p>
    <p>fined as normal. After a month of data collection, the</p>
    <p>graphs were showing a large degree of variance, based</p>
    <p>mainly on the short period of time for which data had</p>
    <p>been collected.</p>
    <p>At this stage, the alert threshold was set to a deviation</p>
    <p>of +/- 70% to allow for the small amount of normalising</p>
    <p>data. If traffic at any given hour is found to be outside</p>
    <p>of this range, an alert state is generated. For example,</p>
    <p>the red lines displayed in figure 2 indicate a large dip in</p>
    <p>traffic for certain hours in Pakistan.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Figure 2: Four days of traffic deviation in Pakistan</p>
    <p>In the prototype Geostats system, an alert is displayed</p>
    <p>to the user when hovering over any red line displayed</p>
    <p>on the graph. The concept behind this alert is that the</p>
    <p>system would retrieve information from an external</p>
    <p>source with an API call. The click to see more mes</p>
    <p>sage reports any information related to that alert to bet</p>
    <p>ter inform users why the alert is being displayed (see</p>
    <p>figure 3). The system was set to retrieve any news re</p>
    <p>ports from the OpenNet Initiatives RSS feed related to</p>
    <p>the country being analysed. 1</p>
    <p>Figure 3: Geostats alert message</p>
    <p>The final component of Geostats is a calendar view,</p>
    <p>designed to be easily interpreted by non-technical users.</p>
    <p>This view took the same information, but presented a</p>
    <p>daily alert for each country (see figure 4). A country</p>
    <p>would show as having a problem if there was an hourly</p>
    <p>alert state for more than four hours in a 24-hour period.</p>
    <p>Figure 4: Calendar view</p>
    <p>http://opennet.net/taxonomy/term/41/feed</p>
    <p>Geostats was developed as a prototype with the inten</p>
    <p>tion to improve it based on lessons learned during de</p>
    <p>velopment. Areas for improvement were identified at</p>
    <p>the three stages of the system:</p>
    <p>Database import:</p>
    <p>- Log files are up to 24 hours behind real-time, which means the system cannot report effectively on a full</p>
    <p>set of live data.</p>
    <p>- The size of the log files requires the system be optimized for performance.</p>
    <p>- Malformed lines in log files are common and can skew the data. Refining the parsing methods could</p>
    <p>provide a more robust system.</p>
    <p>Building the behaviour model</p>
    <p>- Building the relationships places a huge load on the server, both in terms of processing power and data</p>
    <p>base calls.</p>
    <p>- The geographic lookup is imperfect, and also can take a long time. The ideal solution would give more</p>
    <p>granular views of outages, separating not just by</p>
    <p>country but by region and ISP. This would take ad</p>
    <p>ditional processing power, and also have a financial</p>
    <p>impact.</p>
    <p>- The normalisation process could be improved. One approach is to do more calculations to assess any</p>
    <p>given hour against the previous hour, previous day,</p>
    <p>and every seventh previous day in the system.</p>
    <p>Displaying the results</p>
    <p>- The graphs and calendar view are all created at the time of request, with queries being made to the da</p>
    <p>tabase.</p>
    <p>- The processing power required to deal with this request resulted in processing times of up to 5 minutes</p>
    <p>for the system to return results. Some form of cach</p>
    <p>ing could be introduced to improve this.</p>
    <p>Aside from these issues, there are two main challenges</p>
    <p>for the system: handling alerts and providing API ac</p>
    <p>cess. For handling alerts external APIs from reliable</p>
    <p>data sources can be queried, with the BBC able to pro</p>
    <p>vide three variables: country, date of alert, time of</p>
    <p>alert. The structure of the information that is returned</p>
    <p>from this query will need to be defined so that it can be</p>
    <p>imported into the BBCs Geostats system. The second</p>
    <p>challenge is to provide API access to Geostats for simi</p>
    <p>lar systems. A table in the database could be created,</p>
    <p>with an API to expose the country code, timestamp and</p>
    <p>percentage variance from normal.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Around the Iranian elections in June 2009, the BBC</p>
    <p>Persian web site was suddenly blocked in Iran. The site</p>
    <p>had been blocked on previous occasions [2], but this</p>
    <p>was the first block since the BBC Persian satellite tele</p>
    <p>vision station was launched several months earlier. BBC</p>
    <p>Persian TV was also blocked, prompting a blog piece</p>
    <p>from the BBCs Director of Global News claiming that</p>
    <p>such actions were against international treaties on sat</p>
    <p>ellite communications [3].</p>
    <p>During the block, the BBC noticed a huge increase in</p>
    <p>traffic to the BBC Persian TV Internet live stream of</p>
    <p>more than four times its usual levels. Geographical IP</p>
    <p>lookups of this traffic showed that the majority of</p>
    <p>streaming was from inside Iran. The BBC began to find</p>
    <p>ways to let the audience know that it could still access</p>
    <p>the streaming media.</p>
    <p>Psiphon Inc., a privately held Canadian corporation that</p>
    <p>develops circumvention technologies, provided proxy</p>
    <p>servers configured with bbcpersian.com as the first page</p>
    <p>that would be seen after logging in. The BBC used</p>
    <p>bit.ly, the URL shortening service, to set up links to</p>
    <p>Psiphon servers and to the direct media streams, and</p>
    <p>used all available channels to promote the availability</p>
    <p>of BBC content: Email newsletters, Twitter, Facebook</p>
    <p>and on-air promotions. The use of bit.ly allowed the</p>
    <p>BBC to look at near real-time statistics showing what</p>
    <p>country the shortcut URL was being accessed in. A</p>
    <p>separate web page was created to carry the BBC Persian</p>
    <p>TV stream through a non-BBC HTML player which</p>
    <p>was not being blocked in Iran.</p>
    <p>Having evaluated various tools prior to this incident,</p>
    <p>Psiphon was considered the most suitable for the or</p>
    <p>ganisation, as the BBC had no funds for development of</p>
    <p>new tools or additional technical support. Of the avail</p>
    <p>able off-the-shelf solutions, Psiphon had these advan</p>
    <p>tages:</p>
    <p>- Usability: The BBC would direct its audience to the tool, but not be responsible for hosting it.</p>
    <p>- No executable code: The BBC was not willing to provide software that had to be installed on the</p>
    <p>users PC, therefore a web-based proxy was chosen.</p>
    <p>- Appropriate information: The user of the circumvention solution would need an appropriate set of clear</p>
    <p>terms and conditions for use.</p>
    <p>- Hosting environment: The hosting of the solution had to be in a secure environment, provided by a</p>
    <p>trusted corporate entity, and not peer-to-peer based.</p>
    <p>- Exit strategy: If a web-based solution was compromised or if the BBC needed to withdraw from pro</p>
    <p>viding the service, it had to be able to do so.</p>
    <p>While the Psiphon service for BBC Persian grew or</p>
    <p>ganically from the sudden blocking of the web site, the</p>
    <p>service for BBC Chinese was introduced at a time when</p>
    <p>it was needed, and with the involvement of its produc</p>
    <p>tion team. At the end of September 2010, the BBC Chi</p>
    <p>nese service started to publicise Psiphon nodes, with the</p>
    <p>message If you are having trouble accessing our site in</p>
    <p>China, please try [node URL].</p>
    <p>Three nodes were set up by the Psiphon team, with their</p>
    <p>URLs propagated through different channels by the</p>
    <p>BBC: one through email newsletters; one through the</p>
    <p>BBC Chinese Twitter account, and one promoted on air</p>
    <p>and in direct email contact with individuals.</p>
    <p>The frequency of propagation differed for each of these</p>
    <p>channels. A message accompanied every radio broad</p>
    <p>cast (three times per day, with additional trails featuring</p>
    <p>the promotion), email newsletters were sent daily, and</p>
    <p>Tweets were sent on an ad hoc basis.</p>
    <p>Figure 5 shows the number of pages viewed through the</p>
    <p>BBC Chinese Psiphon service in comparison to BBC</p>
    <p>Persian during the first eight weeks. The active promo</p>
    <p>tion from BBC Chinese helped the service grow rapidly</p>
    <p>so that the number of pages served was matching those</p>
    <p>served by BBC Persians Psiphon implementation.</p>
    <p>Figure 5 Pages Served (000s) to BBC Psiphon servers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Shortly after the BBC Chinese service started propagat</p>
    <p>ing the availability of Psiphon nodes, a news event led</p>
    <p>to additional blocking of BBC content inside China.</p>
    <p>The Nobel Peace Prize ceremony to honour Liu Xiaobo</p>
    <p>was due to take place in Oslo on December 10, 2010.</p>
    <p>On the morning of December 9, 2010, the BBC pub</p>
    <p>lished a story with the headline Nobel: China blocks</p>
    <p>foreign web sites ahead of ceremony which reported</p>
    <p>on the blocking in China of a number of sites, also in</p>
    <p>cluding Norwegian broadcaster NRK [4]. BBC sites</p>
    <p>that were blocked included the English news site, and</p>
    <p>bbcukchina.com, an educational site with content about</p>
    <p>life and culture in the UK. The block also caused an</p>
    <p>increase in undeliverable email newsletters for BBC</p>
    <p>Chinese.</p>
    <p>The BBC worked with Psiphon to offer two extra proxy</p>
    <p>servers that would provide login screens in English, and</p>
    <p>bring visitors directly to the BBC News site in English.</p>
    <p>The first was promoted via Facebook and email news</p>
    <p>letters during the day, while the second node was</p>
    <p>brought online at night via Twitter promotion.</p>
    <p>Plans were made to provide a video feed of the live</p>
    <p>ceremony that would be BBC-branded, but not hosted</p>
    <p>on a BBC site. A bit.ly URL was created for this feed.</p>
    <p>Editorial teams were instructed to only propagate that</p>
    <p>message one hour before the start of the ceremony to</p>
    <p>minimise the likelihood of it being blocked.</p>
    <p>Of the two separate nodes brought online for the BBC</p>
    <p>News site in English, one was blocked almost immedi</p>
    <p>ately, while the other was available throughout the</p>
    <p>weekend. On the day of the ceremony, there were 387</p>
    <p>logins to this server.</p>
    <p>A live stream of the ceremony was also created on a</p>
    <p>non-BBC branded page, with bit.ly URLs promoted one</p>
    <p>hour before the ceremony. While there was no expecta</p>
    <p>tion of a huge audience for this stream, data from bit.ly</p>
    <p>shows that there were 4,236 clicks to that URL that day,</p>
    <p>with around 50% from China. This traffic accounted for</p>
    <p>about one-third of the total visitors to that stream, in</p>
    <p>cluding those accessing it from unfiltered locations.</p>
    <p>On December 13, the BBC news site in English was</p>
    <p>again available in China, which was reported with the</p>
    <p>conclusion, China appears to have done what it could</p>
    <p>to stop unfiltered news of the event reaching its own</p>
    <p>people[5].</p>
    <p>BBC sites are not always rendered correctly using Psi</p>
    <p>phon. Freedom House noted this issue in their review of</p>
    <p>circumvention software, pointing out that web-based</p>
    <p>proxies have an inability to properly translate flash and</p>
    <p>some other forms of dynamic content [6].</p>
    <p>There are two areas of concern for the BBC pages:</p>
    <p>- Page structure: There is a heavy reliance on JavaScript, particularly on the index pages of lan</p>
    <p>guage news sites such as bbcpersian.com. Content is</p>
    <p>fully displayed with correct links, but editorial plac</p>
    <p>ing of news stories can be obscured by incorrectly</p>
    <p>rendered JavaScript modules.</p>
    <p>- Audio and video: Audio and video on the BBCs language web sites is served using Flash Player or</p>
    <p>Windows Media Player, which will not be accessi</p>
    <p>ble through a web proxy.</p>
    <p>The BBC could work with Psiphon to improve content</p>
    <p>caching and JavaScript delivery. This approach has</p>
    <p>proven to be successful with Voice of America sites,</p>
    <p>which render properly using Psiphon. However, many</p>
    <p>modules on the BBC language news sites are used to</p>
    <p>render sites covering all of the BBCs entertainment</p>
    <p>output as well as its news. Changes made in this envi</p>
    <p>ronment to support serving content through web proxies</p>
    <p>would likely be considered low priority. An alternative</p>
    <p>is to consider changes that will only have an effect on</p>
    <p>the language news sites, such as modifying the CSS.</p>
    <p>The BBC is producing some audio and video content in</p>
    <p>formats that can be delivered via HTTP rather than</p>
    <p>RTMP. This standards-based approach allows content</p>
    <p>to be consumed on newer mobile devices, specifically</p>
    <p>those with support for HTML5, and will make BBC</p>
    <p>content more accessible through Psiphon and other web</p>
    <p>proxy tools. BBC sites with audio and video available</p>
    <p>over HTTP have been successfully tested over Psiphon.</p>
    <p>The BBCs international news services have distributed</p>
    <p>audio and video content through Akamai since 2003,</p>
    <p>and URLs for the streaming media do not include</p>
    <p>bbc.co.uk. Instead, Akamais edge network handles the</p>
    <p>stream request so that the server providing content to</p>
    <p>the end user is the one nearest to that computer on the</p>
    <p>network [7]. As the servers are not specific to the BBC,</p>
    <p>it makes URL and IP-based blocking more difficult than</p>
    <p>targeting *.bbc.co.uk. There have been reports of indi</p>
    <p>vidual machines on Akamais network being blocked,</p>
    <p>which has led to thousands of web sites also being</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>made unavailable [8]. The effects of such filtering are</p>
    <p>much wider than a blocking of an individual site.</p>
    <p>The BBC uses multiple CDNs to provide its streaming</p>
    <p>media. Live streams are available to mobile devices</p>
    <p>through non-BBC URLs such as iPhone video streams</p>
    <p>and SHOUTcast MP3 streams, while news clips for</p>
    <p>mobile devices are provided in discrete indices on the</p>
    <p>mobile version of the web site, with device detection</p>
    <p>and media hosting through a CDN. Clips are available</p>
    <p>through HTTP, so web proxy users can consume BBC</p>
    <p>language news videos through the mobile sites. How</p>
    <p>ever, the video index is only provided as a chronologi</p>
    <p>cal list and offers no editorial ordering of content.</p>
    <p>For most BBC language news sites, only headline and</p>
    <p>summary text is available for public syndication, with</p>
    <p>full text offers restricted to commercial deals. However,</p>
    <p>for BBC Persian, there is a full-text feed available</p>
    <p>publicly, as the BBC recognises the difficulty of serving</p>
    <p>content into Iran. This format, and its availability in</p>
    <p>multiple blogs and web sites, makes it difficult for Ira</p>
    <p>nian authorities to find and block BBC content.</p>
    <p>RSS feeds are also used for distributing content via</p>
    <p>iPhone apps that have been created by an enthusiast of</p>
    <p>the BBC Persian site. The developer uses the RSS feeds</p>
    <p>to recreate web content inside the app, and also links to</p>
    <p>the live audio and TV streams, and on-demand video</p>
    <p>files, carrying web content over HTTPS. The Chinese</p>
    <p>app is available in Chinas app store, and information</p>
    <p>from the developer suggests that downloads inside</p>
    <p>China count for over 50% of the total for the app.</p>
    <p>Audio and video content is also syndicated, and one of</p>
    <p>the BBCs partners for its language video content is</p>
    <p>YouTube. YouTube channels exist for BBC Persian and</p>
    <p>BBC Chinese, as well as several other BBC languages.</p>
    <p>Statistics from YouTube show that when YouTube itself</p>
    <p>is available, BBC videos can be viewed through the site</p>
    <p>inside both Iran and China.</p>
    <p>As the BBC focuses more of its efforts on online plat</p>
    <p>forms for news delivery, the need to detect and circum</p>
    <p>vent blocks becomes increasingly important. The pilot</p>
    <p>circumvention service and research into the distribution</p>
    <p>and blocking of its content has increased the under</p>
    <p>standing of its online environment. This has highlighted</p>
    <p>improvements that can be made and challenges that</p>
    <p>need to be overcome.</p>
    <p>The BBC has recognised that bypassing censorship in</p>
    <p>volves more than merely providing software that cir</p>
    <p>cumvents blocks of its content. There will be times</p>
    <p>when a complete throttling of internet traffic, such as</p>
    <p>recently experienced in Tunisia and Egypt, will make its</p>
    <p>content distribution more challenging, through circum</p>
    <p>vention tools as well as directly. The way its services</p>
    <p>are hosted will help BBC distribute its content into</p>
    <p>countries where it may otherwise be unavailable. Alter</p>
    <p>native methods of consuming news need to be promoted</p>
    <p>and constantly updated, and communicated to its audi</p>
    <p>ence through whatever channels are available.</p>
    <p>There is evidence through propagation of circumvention</p>
    <p>tools and multiple distribution channels that the BBC is</p>
    <p>able to reach people who want to access BBC news.</p>
    <p>The broadcaster needs to know when it is being cen</p>
    <p>sored, and that its role at these times is to direct its au</p>
    <p>dience to its content, wherever it is available.</p>
    <p>[1] Google, Transparency Report,</p>
    <p>http://www.google.com/transparencyreport/traffic/.</p>
    <p>[2] Iran Blocks BBC Persian Web Site, BBC News,</p>
    <p>January 24, 2006,</p>
    <p>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/464</p>
    <p>[3] Peter Horrocks, Stop the Blocking Now, June 14,</p>
    <p>http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/theeditors/2009/06/stop_</p>
    <p>the_blocking_now.html.</p>
    <p>[4] Nobel: China Blocks Foreign Websites Ahead of</p>
    <p>Ceremony, BBC News, December 9, 2010,</p>
    <p>http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-pacific</p>
    <p>[5] Michael Bristow, BBC Website Unblocked in Chi</p>
    <p>na, BBC News, December 13, 2010,</p>
    <p>http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-pacific</p>
    <p>[6] Freedom House, Leaping Over the Firewall: A Re</p>
    <p>view of Censorship Circumvention Tools, April 11,</p>
    <p>http://www.freedomhouse.org/template.cfm?page=383</p>
    <p>&amp;report=97.</p>
    <p>[7] Akamai, Streaming</p>
    <p>http://www.akamai.com/html/technology/products/</p>
    <p>streaming.html.</p>
    <p>[8] Akamai blocked in china cause thousands of web</p>
    <p>site also been blocked, Twit Browser,</p>
    <p>http://twitbrowser.net/33.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
