<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>New Direction in Wyner-Ziv Video Coding:New Direction in Wyner-Ziv Video Coding:</p>
    <p>On the Importance of Modeling On the Importance of Modeling Virtual Correlation Channel (VCC)Virtual Correlation Channel (VCC)</p>
    <p>Xin LiXin Li</p>
    <p>LDCSEE, WVULDCSEE, WVU</p>
    <p>Email: xin.li@ieee.orgEmail: xin.li@ieee.org</p>
    <p>If you cant solve a problem, then there is an easier problem you can solve: find it. - George Plya</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Formulation of a Simpler ProblemFormulation of a Simpler Problem</p>
    <p>x2tx2t-2</p>
    <p>x2t-1</p>
    <p>key frames</p>
    <p>WZ frames</p>
    <p>I frames</p>
    <p>B frames</p>
    <p>Conventional video coding (source coding)</p>
    <p>Wyner-Ziv video coding ( joint source-channel coding)</p>
    <p>x2t-1</p>
    <p>x2tx2t-2</p>
    <p>Assuming I or key frames are coded by the same intra-frame encoder, can we achieve comparable coding efficiency on WZ frames to H.264 (state-ofthe-art techniques of coding B frames)?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline of Our Attack Outline of Our Attack</p>
    <p>Motivating observationsMotivating observations  Characterizing the nonstationary virtual correlation channel Characterizing the nonstationary virtual correlation channel</p>
    <p>(VCC) by a mixture model(VCC) by a mixture model</p>
    <p>Theoretical derivationTheoretical derivation  Classification gain (dual to that in conventional source coding)Classification gain (dual to that in conventional source coding)</p>
    <p>Classification-based DVC algorithmClassification-based DVC algorithm  Approximate solution to the simplified problem Approximate solution to the simplified problem</p>
    <p>Experimental resultsExperimental results  Comparable R-D performance to H.264 JM11.0 (for certain type Comparable R-D performance to H.264 JM11.0 (for certain type</p>
    <p>of video sequences: slow motion)of video sequences: slow motion)</p>
    <p>Discussions and perspectivesDiscussions and perspectives  Dualities between conventional and distributed video codingDualities between conventional and distributed video coding  DVC=video modeling + DSC (Rate) + Estimation (Distortion)DVC=video modeling + DSC (Rate) + Estimation (Distortion)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MotivationsMotivations</p>
    <p>Learn from the conventional wisdom: What is the major Learn from the conventional wisdom: What is the major factor contributing to the success of existing image/video factor contributing to the success of existing image/video coding standards such as JPEG2000 and H.264?coding standards such as JPEG2000 and H.264?  It is the It is the source classificationsource classification principle and its principle and its subtle implicationssubtle implications</p>
    <p>rooted in the earlier pioneering works such as EZW/SPIHT and rooted in the earlier pioneering works such as EZW/SPIHT and multi-hypothesis MCPmulti-hypothesis MCP</p>
    <p>Therefore, by following the duality, it is natural to Therefore, by following the duality, it is natural to consider the idea of consider the idea of classifying the virtual correlation classifying the virtual correlation channelchannel in distributed source coding in distributed source coding  Unlike conventional video coding, Unlike conventional video coding, motion estimationmotion estimation (ME) is (ME) is</p>
    <p>done at the decoder instead of encoder side in WZ video coding done at the decoder instead of encoder side in WZ video coding (we have addressed this issue separately under a different (we have addressed this issue separately under a different contextcontext11))</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modeling Non-stationary VCCModeling Non-stationary VCC</p>
    <p>Why is the virtual correlation channel is non-Why is the virtual correlation channel is nonstationary?stationary?  Misaligned edges, deformable motion, illumination Misaligned edges, deformable motion, illumination</p>
    <p>variations are all spatio-temporally varying phenomena variations are all spatio-temporally varying phenomena</p>
    <p>Mixture modeling of Mixture modeling of virtual correlation channelvirtual correlation channel</p>
    <p>ttt zxy  WT of Interpolated</p>
    <p>WZ frames (side information)</p>
    <p>WT of original WZ frames</p>
    <p>additive errors</p>
    <p>(e.g., significant vs. insignificant wavelet coefficients)</p>
    <p>(e.g., significant vs. insignificant temporal interpolation errors)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary of Theoretical ResultsSummary of Theoretical Results Rate-Distortion optimization problem formulationRate-Distortion optimization problem formulation</p>
    <p>4</p>
    <p>min k</p>
    <p>kk DaD RRa k</p>
    <p>kk</p>
    <p>s.t.</p>
    <p>Conventional source coding Distributed source coding</p>
    <p>R-D function</p>
    <p>Rate allocation</p>
    <p>Classification gain</p>
    <p>],[log 2</p>
    <p>zx</p>
    <p>zx xz</p>
    <p>xz</p>
    <p>D DR</p>
    <p>)}(log,0max{][log</p>
    <p>],[log 2</p>
    <p>xx</p>
    <p>D DR x</p>
    <p>)(log10 2</p>
    <p>x c</p>
    <p>)(log10</p>
    <p>xzWZ</p>
    <p>c</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implications into WZ Video CodingImplications into WZ Video Coding In conventional source coding, In conventional source coding, classification gain implies that subsource classification gain implies that subsource of of largerlarger variance be assigned a higher variance be assigned a higher priority in rate allocationpriority in rate allocation</p>
    <p>In distributed source coding, similar In distributed source coding, similar conclusion can be made except that the conclusion can be made except that the variance of subsource is now determined variance of subsource is now determined by the virtual correlation channelby the virtual correlation channel</p>
    <p>zx</p>
    <p>zx xz</p>
    <p>02  xz</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion: the class of significant coefficients that are poorly motion compensated have the largest R-D slope (they should be coded first: where are they? and what are they?)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rate Control DilemmaRate Control Dilemma How can we estimate the second-order statistics How can we estimate the second-order statistics of VCC: of VCC: zz22 (the accuracy of side information y (the accuracy of side information ytt generated by temporal interpolation)?generated by temporal interpolation)?  At the encoder, we have access to xAt the encoder, we have access to xtt (original WZ (original WZ</p>
    <p>frames) but not yframes) but not ytt (side information) (side information)11</p>
    <p>At the decoder, we have access to yAt the decoder, we have access to ytt (side (side information) but not xinformation) but not xtt (original WZ frames) (original WZ frames)22</p>
    <p>We have adopted decoder-based approach based on We have adopted decoder-based approach based on a feedback channel and a feedback channel and scale invariancescale invariance assumption assumption about zabout zt t (an approximate but tractable solution)(an approximate but tractable solution)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Feedback via Scale Invariance of Feedback via Scale Invariance of Interpolation ErrorsInterpolation Errors</p>
    <p>x2t x2t+2 x2t-2</p>
    <p>x2t-1</p>
    <p>key frames</p>
    <p>WZ frames</p>
    <p>oracle actual</p>
    <p>hall</p>
    <p>foreman</p>
    <p>Block-based significance map of zt</p>
    <p>Fine-resolution:</p>
    <p>oracleS.I.</p>
    <p>Coarse-resolution:</p>
    <p>tttt xxxfz 222222 ),(</p>
    <p>Interpolated Key frame</p>
    <p>Key frame</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>wavelet transform</p>
    <p>advanced temporal</p>
    <p>interpolation</p>
    <p>Joint Exploitation</p>
    <p>WZ frames SW lossless</p>
    <p>coding of significance map</p>
    <p>SW lossless coding of</p>
    <p>significance coeff.</p>
    <p>SI</p>
    <p>CI decoded</p>
    <p>WZ frames</p>
    <p>decoded I frames</p>
    <p>Encoder Decoder block-based classification</p>
    <p>Classification-based WZ Video Classification-based WZ Video Coding SystemCoding System</p>
    <p>In a nutshell, we only allocate bits to the class of poorly motion compensated significant coefficients: both xx</p>
    <p>WT feedback channel</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Joint Exploitation of Side and Joint Exploitation of Side and Coded Information at the DecoderCoded Information at the Decoder</p>
    <p>zxy</p>
    <p>z~N(0,z 2)</p>
    <p>y</p>
    <p>SI</p>
    <p>CI=Q(x)</p>
    <p>Target of estimation: E[x|y,Q(x)] Latent variable: z (we dont know z</p>
    <p>x Update</p>
    <p>estimate of x</p>
    <p>Update estimate</p>
    <p>of z 2</p>
    <p>initial guess</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Justification of Distortion ReductionJustification of Distortion Reduction</p>
    <p>foreman-qcif, block size 1616, 18.3% blocks are coded</p>
    <p>SI alone</p>
    <p>SI+CI</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Coding Experiments SetupCoding Experiments Setup Parameter settingParameter setting  Block size: Block size: 1616, WT: Daubechies 9-7,</p>
    <p>Slepian-Wolf lossless encoder: LDPC-based1, uniform quantizer (=8)</p>
    <p>Rate control: thx, thz - significance thresholds for x and z respectively</p>
    <p>SI generation: Implicit MC vs. Explicit MC</p>
    <p>Benchmark: H.264 JM11.0 implementation Benchmark: H.264 JM11.0 implementation (QP of I frames is small and fixed )(QP of I frames is small and fixed )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Comparison of Temporal InterpolationComparison of Temporal Interpolation</p>
    <p>Foreman-qcif, ad-hoc fusion by simple averaging 1X. Li, Video processing via implicit and mixture motion model, IEEE Trans. on Cir. Sys. for Video Tech., vol. 17, no. 8, pp. 953-963, Aug. 2007.</p>
    <p>Implicit MC1 Explicit MC2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>R-D Performance Comparison (I)R-D Performance Comparison (I)</p>
    <p>Foreman-qcif, 30framesHall-qcif, 30frames</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>R-D Performance Comparison (II)R-D Performance Comparison (II)</p>
    <p>Container-qcif, 30frames Football-qcif, 30frames</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dualities between Conventional Dualities between Conventional and WZ Video Codingand WZ Video Coding</p>
    <p>Exploitation of motion-related temporal dependencyExploitation of motion-related temporal dependency  In traditional video coding, prediction is based on original frames In traditional video coding, prediction is based on original frames</p>
    <p>(overhead is involved)(overhead is involved)  In WZ video coding, interpolation is based on reconstructed key In WZ video coding, interpolation is based on reconstructed key</p>
    <p>frames (no overhead) frames (no overhead)  Importance of Importance of SI generationSI generation11</p>
    <p>R-D optimization shifted from encoder to decoderR-D optimization shifted from encoder to decoder  In traditional video coding, decoder is often fixed but encoder In traditional video coding, decoder is often fixed but encoder</p>
    <p>enjoys considerable flexibility enjoys considerable flexibility  In WZ video coding, rate control through the feedback channel In WZ video coding, rate control through the feedback channel</p>
    <p>offers great flexibility to the decoder without touching encoderoffers great flexibility to the decoder without touching encoder22</p>
    <p>Importance of Importance of matching SW lossless encoder with the statistics matching SW lossless encoder with the statistics of virtual correlation channelof virtual correlation channel (UEP is desirable) (UEP is desirable)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AcknowledgementAcknowledgement</p>
    <p>Ligang Lu and Dake He for inviting me to Ligang Lu and Dake He for inviting me to participate this special sessionparticipate this special session</p>
    <p>Zixiang Xiong for sharing with me his Zixiang Xiong for sharing with me his students implementation of LDPC-based students implementation of LDPC-based Slepian-Wolf coding algorithm Slepian-Wolf coding algorithm</p>
    <p>E. Simoncelli for stimulating discussions E. Simoncelli for stimulating discussions on distributed motion representationson distributed motion representations</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
