<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart, Vincent Aleven, Kevin Ashley, and Collin Lynch</p>
    <p>Clausthal University of Technology Carnegie Mellon University University of Pittsburgh</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>LARGO (Legal ARgument Graph Observer): ITS to engage students in analyzing &amp; reflecting about examples of expert Socratic reasoning</p>
    <p>US Supreme Court Oral Arguments as learning resources</p>
    <p>Diagrams to visualize argument as hypothesis testing: analysis and feedback</p>
    <p>Evaluation of LARGO</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>US Supreme Court Oral Arguments</p>
    <p>Important part of decision process  Attorneys propose a decision rule</p>
    <p>(test) to determine how to decide a case</p>
    <p>Justices challenge these tests by posing hypothetical scenarios (meaning, consistency with past cases, legal and policy implications)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>An Example Case  Example: Kathy Keeton v. Hustler Magazine, 465 U.S.</p>
    <p>US District Court in New Hampshire. Hustler is an Ohio corporation with its principal place of business in California. Ms. Keeton was not a New Hampshire resident and had almost no ties there. Each month, Hustler sold about 15,000 issues in New Hampshire, which was only state where Keeton was not time-barred under a statute of limitations.</p>
    <p>Question: Did the courts in New Hampshire have personal jurisdiction over Hustler Magazine?</p>
    <p>Conflicting principles: Fairness to defendant vs. right of state to redress in-state injury.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MR. GRUTMAN: The synthesis of those cases holds that where you have purposeful conduct by a defendant directed at the forum in question and out of which conduct the cause of action arises or is generated that satisfies the formula of those minimum contacts which substantial justice and reasonable fair play make it suitable that a defendant should be hailed into that court and be amenable to suit in that jurisdiction.</p>
    <p>JUSTICE: Would it apply in Alaska? MR. GRUTMAN: It would apply, Mr. Justice Marshall, wherever the magazine</p>
    <p>was circulated. It would apply in Honolulu if the publication were circulated there. It would apply theoretically and, I think, correctly wherever the magazine was circulated, however many copies were circulated.</p>
    <p>JUSTICE: What if the publisher had no intention of ever selling any magazines in New Hampshire?</p>
    <p>MR. GRUTMAN: A very different case, Mr. Justice White.  because in that case you could not say, as you do here, that you have purposeful conduct. There you have to look for other -- I think your phrase is affiliating circumstances, other connections, judicially cognizable ties -</p>
    <p>Example: Tests and Hypotheticals</p>
    <p>Test</p>
    <p>Hypo</p>
    <p>Response:</p>
    <p>Distinguish,</p>
    <p>Modify</p>
    <p>Hypo</p>
    <p>Response: Analogize</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Educational Value  Training in skills of argument important part</p>
    <p>of legal argumentation  Transcripts realistic and valuable examples</p>
    <p>of expert Socratic reasoning  Analysis of transcripts:</p>
    <p>can help learning these skills  provides opportunities for reflection</p>
    <p>But: complex material, hard to understand!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>A LARGO Argument Diagram</p>
    <p>LARGO Argument Diagram</p>
    <p>Palette</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Intelligent Support: How to interpret diagrams?</p>
    <p>Problem 1: legal argumentation is an illdefined domain  Different views possible  Difficult to define correctness in this</p>
    <p>interpretive field  Problem 2: arguments consist of natural</p>
    <p>language texts  NLP based approaches seem error-prone here</p>
    <p>LARGO approach: Attempt to find characteristics in argument diagram  Weaknesses (areas of potential problems) or  Opportunities for reflection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Diagram characteristics  Context: links between</p>
    <p>graph elements and important passages in the transcript.</p>
    <p>Structure: graph portions that correspond to pre-defined argument patterns.</p>
    <p>Content: adequateness of students` free-text descriptions in diagram boxes.</p>
    <p>Example: No test elements linked to transcript passage which contains important test</p>
    <p>Detected by graph grammar.</p>
    <p>Example: Diagram contains hypothetical not related to any fact or test element.</p>
    <p>Detected by graph grammar.</p>
    <p>Example: A description of a proposed test in a test diagram element is of poor quality.</p>
    <p>Detected by collaborative filtering.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Detection of Content Weaknesses through Collaborative Filtering</p>
    <p>Student A</p>
    <p>Student B</p>
    <p>Student C</p>
    <p>A rates the test descriptions provided by B and C after having entered his own.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Feedback: Self Explanation Prompts</p>
    <p>Principle: Use detected characteristics for self explanation prompts</p>
    <p>Research results: SE beneficial for learning, effective metacognitive strategy</p>
    <p>Offer opportunities for reflection about specific parts of Socratic reasoning examples:  the presumably weak parts of students</p>
    <p>argument analysis, and  the good parts still worth reflection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Feedback Example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>LARGO v. Cognitive Tutors  Study of expert argument examples  No cognitive model of diagram construction  LARGO does not insist that students create a correct</p>
    <p>graph  Because of ill-structure, it may not be feasible to</p>
    <p>identify a comprehensive set of correct graphs  Getting the diagram right is not the main thing: we</p>
    <p>want students to reflect on the quality of the arguments</p>
    <p>Student may be more deliberate and thoughtful without corrective feedback</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Experiment (Fall 2006)</p>
    <p>Goal: Evaluate LARGO, compared to standard note taking</p>
    <p>Hypothesis: Using LARGO improves  understanding hypothetical reasoning method,  ability to recognize/reason about examples in near and far transfer legal</p>
    <p>domains.</p>
    <p>Participants: 28 volunteer law students in 1st-semester Legal Process course.</p>
    <p>Task: Read SCOTUS oral arguments; represent hypothetical reasoning.</p>
    <p>Experimental condition: Use LARGO graphical argument representation and feedback to identify/relate elements of hypothetical reasoning.</p>
    <p>Control condition: Same oral arguments and focus on hypothetical reasoning, but use tool with text-based word-processing and highlighting (no feedback).</p>
    <p>Procedure: Over a four-week period: 1. (2h): Pre-test &amp; tool introduction 2. &amp; 3. (2x2h): Apply tools to Burnham &amp; Burger King (personal jurisdiction)</p>
    <p>arguments 4. (3h): Post-test</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Control Condition Tool</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Pre/post test measures</p>
    <p>Hypothetical reasoning</p>
    <p>General questions re hypotheticals</p>
    <p>Test general understanding of role of hypotheticals</p>
    <p>Hypothetical reasoning about tennis club policy</p>
    <p>Test hypothetical reasoning skills in everyday context</p>
    <p>Near transfer of hypothetical reasoning (Keeton, personal jurisdiction)</p>
    <p>Study new SCOTUS oral argument transcript without tool, answer questions about the relation between tests and hypotheticals</p>
    <p>Far transfer of hypothetical reasoning (Sony, copyright)</p>
    <p>Pre Post Question type Knowledge/skills tested</p>
    <p>Legal argumentation</p>
    <p>LSAT-type legal argument questions</p>
    <p>Test legal argumentation skills in a context that does not pre-suppose any specific legal knowledge</p>
    <p>Substantive legal knowledge</p>
    <p>Personal jurisdiction questions Test students knowledge of personal jurisdiction</p>
    <p>Copyright question Test students knowledge of copyright law</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Overall test scores</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Test scores by item</p>
    <p>Copyright LSAT Pers. Jurisd.</p>
    <p>Tennis General Pre-Test Total</p>
    <p>Keeton Sony Post-Test Total</p>
    <p>Pre-Test Diagram</p>
    <p>Pre-Test Text</p>
    <p>Post-Test Diagram</p>
    <p>Post-Test Text</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Divide sample by LSAT score</p>
    <p>Group LSAT score N Avg Scores Diagram Text Pre-Test* Post-Test*</p>
    <p>HIGH 162-165 2 6 .660 .622</p>
    <p>MED 161 8 1 .615 .549</p>
    <p>LOW 158-160 5 5 .599 .544</p>
    <p>*p&lt; .05</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Post-test scores in Low LSAT Group</p>
    <p>Copyright Pers. Jurisd.</p>
    <p>Tennis LSAT General Keeton Sony Total</p>
    <p>Post-Test Diagram</p>
    <p>Post-Test Text</p>
    <p>*p&lt; .05</p>
    <p>*</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Post-Hoc analysis: Classify questions in terms of argument model. One category: evaluating hypotheticals with respect to a proposed test</p>
    <p>Assume that Mr. Grutmans proposed test is as follows: .</p>
    <p>The following hypotheticals either were or could have been posed in the oral argument. Each of them is followed by four explanations why the hypothetical is or is not problematic for Mr. Grutmans proposed test. For each hypothetical, please check ALL of the explanations that are plausible.</p>
    <p>[First hypothetical:]  what if the plaintiff was totally unknown in the jurisdiction before the magazine was circulated?</p>
    <p>o The hypothetical is problematic for Mr. Grutmans proposed test. The decision rule applies by its terms, but arguably the publisher should not be subject to personal jurisdiction in the state under those circumstances.</p>
    <p>o The hypothetical is not problematic for Mr. Grutmans proposed test.  o  o</p>
    <p>[Second hypothetical:]</p>
    <p>Result: In near- and far-transfer problem questions of this type, LOW and MED students in experimental group scored higher than those in the control group, and the difference was significant (t(1,17)=2.73, d=1.00, p&lt;.05, 1-sided).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>LARGO advice usage  LARGO feedback is on-demand  Student requested help 10.1 times per transcript (1 hr).</p>
    <p>LOW 12.3  MED 6.2  HIGH 17.9</p>
    <p>Advice usage did not decrease over time:  7.3 and 9.8 in the first 2 transcripts  12.2 and 8.6 in the last 2 transcripts</p>
    <p>In 75% of requests, students selected one of the three short hints and read detailed feedback</p>
    <p>Conclusion: Feedback was appreciated</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Conclusion &amp; Outlook  LARGO: an ITS for the ill-defined domain of legal</p>
    <p>argumentation. Uses examples of expert Socratic reasoning to ask good questions about studentcreated argument diagrams.</p>
    <p>Experiment showed LARGO did not lead to better learning across the whole sample. But LARGO helps lower ability students learn argumentation skills and understanding the role of hypotheticals.</p>
    <p>Ongoing and future work:  Predictive value of argument graphs  Extend LARGO so students make arguments  Collaborative approach to argument construction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Niels Pinkwart AIED 2007</p>
    <p>Please visit our project website:</p>
    <p>http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~hypoform</p>
    <p>Email:</p>
    <p>niels.pinkwart@tu-clausthal.de</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
