<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Approximate Information Flows: Socially-based Modeling of Privacy in Ubiquitous Computing</p>
    <p>Xiaodong Jiang Jason I. Hong</p>
    <p>James A. Landay</p>
    <p>G r o u p f o r User Interface Research</p>
    <p>University of California Berkeley</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 2</p>
    <p>Designing for Privacy in Ubicomp</p>
    <p>What design goals?  How to implement?  Related work</p>
    <p>Fair Information Practices, Westin, Langheinrich  Transparent Society, David Brin  Design Framework for Ubicomp, Bellotti and Sellen</p>
    <p>This work  How privacy is affected by more pragmatic forces</p>
    <p>Market, Social, Legal, Technical (Lessig)</p>
    <p>Principle of Minimum Asymmetry  Approximate Information Flows (AIF) as a way of tying</p>
    <p>together asymmetry, privacy, and ubicomp systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 3</p>
    <p>Information Asymmetry</p>
    <p>Situations in which some actors hold private information relevant to everyone</p>
    <p>Akerlof (Nobel Prize 2001)  Ex. Used cars and &quot;Malfunctioning of Markets&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 4</p>
    <p>Alice (Data Owner)</p>
    <p>$ $ $</p>
    <p>Loc-based Advertiser (Data User)</p>
    <p>Map Service (Data Collector)</p>
    <p>Asymmetry in Ubicomp</p>
    <p>Large potential for asymmetries in information and power</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 5</p>
    <p>Forces on Privacy</p>
    <p>Privacy</p>
    <p>Social</p>
    <p>Market Legal</p>
    <p>Technology</p>
    <p>Lessig, Architecture of Privacy</p>
    <p>Practical privacy shaped by four forces  Asymmetry impedes Market, Social, and Legal  How to build Technology to enable other forces?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 6</p>
    <p>Operationalizing Privacy</p>
    <p>Technology</p>
    <p>Information Asymmetry</p>
    <p>Market Social Legal</p>
    <p>Privac y</p>
    <p>Values (Ex. FIP, Transparency)</p>
    <p>Approximate Information Flows: Describe and prescribe different levels of information asymmetry in ubicomp systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 7</p>
    <p>Principle of Minimum Asymmetry</p>
    <p>Minimize asymmetry of information between data owners and data collectors and data users, by:  Minimizing quality &amp; quantity of info going out  Maximizing quality &amp; quantity of info going back in</p>
    <p>Collectors / Users</p>
    <p>Owners Out</p>
    <p>In</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 8</p>
    <p>Minimizing Asymmetry in Ubicomp</p>
    <p>Alice (Data Owner)</p>
    <p>$ $ $</p>
    <p>Loc-based Advertiser (Data User)</p>
    <p>Map Service (Data Collector)</p>
    <p>Reduce accuracy  Anonymize</p>
    <p>Ask for consent  Notify  Log</p>
    <p>Aggregate  Reduce accuracy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 9</p>
    <p>Implications for Ubicomp</p>
    <p>Makes it easier to apply other forces  Market, ex. making informed decisions about</p>
    <p>personal data transactions  Social, ex. logging and notification to inform people</p>
    <p>about violations of social norms  Legal, ex. logs that serve as evidence for legal</p>
    <p>recourse</p>
    <p>Minimum asymmetry is a relative notion  Depends on the task, domain, and values</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 10</p>
    <p>Applying Minimum Asymmetry</p>
    <p>What are useful abstractions for thinking about and supporting minimum asymmetry?</p>
    <p>Approximate Information Flows  Where does the data live?  When does data flow to others?  What can people do to protect data?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 11</p>
    <p>Where Does the Data Live?</p>
    <p>Information Spaces, tied to boundaries  Privacy-sensitive data representation</p>
    <p>Persistence, how long does data live?  Confidence, sensor property</p>
    <p>Ex. 95% vs 25%</p>
    <p>Accuracy, usage property  Ex. &quot;Sweden&quot; vs &quot;Gteberg&quot; vs &quot;Draken Cinema&quot;</p>
    <p>Basic privacy-sensitive operations  Read / Write  Promote / Demote: persistence, confidence, accuracy  Aggregate: composition, fusion (inference)  Permissions and Logging association all operations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 12</p>
    <p>Example Usage of InfoSpaces</p>
    <p>Alice's InfoSpace</p>
    <p>Map Service InfoSpace</p>
    <p>Loc-based Advertiser InfoSpace</p>
    <p>Owner=&quot;Alice&quot; Loc=Draken Cinema&quot; Confidence=&quot;85%&quot; TTL=&quot;forever&quot;</p>
    <p>Owner=&quot;xyzzy&quot; Loc=Gteberg&quot; Confidence=&quot;80%&quot; TTL=&quot;1 week&quot; Notify=alice@anon.com&quot; Perm=map service&quot;</p>
    <p>Log</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 13</p>
    <p>When Does Data Flow to Others?</p>
    <p>Data Lifecycle  Collection</p>
    <p>The point when data is gathered  Ex. When Alice gets her location data (GPS)</p>
    <p>Access  The point when data is initially used  Ex. Map Service uses Alices location data</p>
    <p>Second use  Use and sharing of data after initial access  Ex. Location-based advertiser asks Map Service for</p>
    <p>location of Alice</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 14</p>
    <p>What Can People Do to Protect Data?</p>
    <p>Themes for Minimizing Asymmetry  Prevent privacy violations from occurring</p>
    <p>Ex. Anonymize Alice's data  Minimizing flow out</p>
    <p>Avoid potential privacy risks  Ex. Alice asks others if Map Service is reputable  Minimizing flow out &amp; maximizing flow in</p>
    <p>Detect privacy violations if there are any  Ex. A third party audits what Map Service is doing  Maximizing flow in</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 15</p>
    <p>Approximate Information Flows Putting it all together</p>
    <p>Information spaces define privacy zones  Incoming &amp; outgoing flows for an InfoSpace</p>
    <p>determine its degree of asymmetry  (Prevention, avoidance, detection) used to alter</p>
    <p>asymmetry for that InfoSpace  Apply at (collection, access, second use)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 16</p>
    <p>Minimizing Asymmetry at Different Times</p>
    <p>A vo</p>
    <p>id P</p>
    <p>re ve</p>
    <p>n t</p>
    <p>Collection Second UseAccess</p>
    <p>T h</p>
    <p>e m</p>
    <p>e s</p>
    <p>fo r</p>
    <p>M in</p>
    <p>im iz</p>
    <p>in g</p>
    <p>A sy</p>
    <p>m m</p>
    <p>e tr</p>
    <p>y</p>
    <p>Data Lifecycle</p>
    <p>Anonymization Pseudonymization</p>
    <p>P3P</p>
    <p>RBAC</p>
    <p>Location Support</p>
    <p>Privacy Mirrors</p>
    <p>Wearables</p>
    <p>User Interfaces for Feedback, Notification, and Consent</p>
    <p>Logging</p>
    <p>D e</p>
    <p>te ct</p>
    <p>io n</p>
    <p>Alice's InfoSpace</p>
    <p>D e</p>
    <p>te ct</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 17</p>
    <p>Current &amp; Future Work</p>
    <p>Model for privacy control: decentralized info space with unified privacy tagging  IEEE Pervasive Computing, July/Sept, 2002</p>
    <p>Integration into a context infrastructure  Ways to translate end-user privacy prefs to</p>
    <p>system-level asymmetry-based policies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oct 01 2002 18</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Asymmetry as a way of tying together Market, Legal, Social, and Technical forces</p>
    <p>Principle of Minimum Asymmetry  Approximate Information Flows as a model for</p>
    <p>implementing minimum asymmetry  Information Spaces  Data Lifecycle  Themes for minimizing asymmetry</p>
    <p>Approximate Information Flows for analyzing and minimizing asymmetry in ubicomp systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Xiaodong Jiang Jason I. Hong</p>
    <p>James A. Landay http://guir.berkeley.edu/groups/privacy</p>
    <p>G r o u p f o r User Interface Research</p>
    <p>University of California Berkeley</p>
    <p>Thanks to: John Canny Anind Dey Scott Lederer National Science Foundation ITR</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
