<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare:</p>
    <p>A case study</p>
    <p>Felipe Meneguzzi1</p>
    <p>felipe.meneguzzi@kcl.ac.uk Simon Miles1 Michael Luck1</p>
    <p>Camden Holt2 Malcolm Smith2</p>
    <p>and others 1Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>Kings College London</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 1 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>. . .1 Aerospace Aftercare</p>
    <p>. . .2 Background on Contracting</p>
    <p>. . .3 The CONTRACT Architecture</p>
    <p>. . .4 A Contract-Based System for the Aerospace Aftermarket</p>
    <p>. . .5 Concluding Remarks</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 2 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An Aerospace Aftercare Use Case</p>
    <p>Simplified version of Lost Waxs use case (previous presentation) Aircraft engine manufacturers:</p>
    <p>I Need to maintain an operational engine pool I Receive hourly rates for engine usage I Need to provide minimum service levels</p>
    <p>Electronic contracts established between manufacturers and airlines</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 3 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Aftercare contracts</p>
    <p>Complex agreements Include provisions for:</p>
    <p>I Restricting provenance of engines I Specifying a minimum number of spare engines I Maximum idle time for aircraft waiting maintenance I Penalties for violations</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 4 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background on Electronic Contracting</p>
    <p>Systems of self-interested agents: I Inherently unreliable I Require societal control</p>
    <p>We use norms to regulate agent behaviour: I Ensure compliance with societal goals I Usually expressed using deontic concepts</p>
    <p>Norms incorporated into a formal document  Contract</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 5 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The CONTRACT Project</p>
    <p>Explore multiple aspects of contract-based systems Aiming at an electronic contracting framework:</p>
    <p>I Facilitates design, enactment and management of contracts I Includes critical aspects of a contract life cycle I Instantiated here for aerospace aftercare</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 6 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Structure</p>
    <p>Framework describes: I Contracts I Target agents (contract</p>
    <p>parties) Architecture provides for:</p>
    <p>I Verification mechanisms I Monitoring of critical</p>
    <p>states I Administration processes</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 7 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contracts</p>
    <p>A contract contains clauses: I Obligations I Permissions I Prohibitions</p>
    <p>Contract parties bound by clauses Contract roles are fulfilled by contract parties</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 8 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contract Life Cycle</p>
    <p>Five stages: I Creation, finding partners,</p>
    <p>negotiating terms I Maintenance and update of a</p>
    <p>contract in a repository I Fulfilment of clauses by</p>
    <p>participants I Management, overseeing</p>
    <p>fulfillment, taking action I Termination or renewal when</p>
    <p>expired or violated</p>
    <p>&amp; Update Maintenance</p>
    <p>Creation Fulfilment</p>
    <p>Management</p>
    <p>Renewal Termination /</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 9 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contract Parties</p>
    <p>Business contract parties: I Agents targeted by the contract I Obligations largely concerned with business objectives</p>
    <p>Administrative contract parties: I Required to maintain system integrity:</p>
    <p>F Observer monitors critical state F Manager responds to notifications by observer</p>
    <p>I Obligations concerned with administering the system</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 10 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Agent Roles</p>
    <p>Airline operator Engine manufacturer Observer Manager</p>
    <p>CONTRACT</p>
    <p>S im</p>
    <p>u la</p>
    <p>to r</p>
    <p>Manufacturer Engine</p>
    <p>Environment</p>
    <p>Simulation Aftercare</p>
    <p>Airline</p>
    <p>Observer</p>
    <p>Manager</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 11 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Role: Airline Operator</p>
    <p>Goals: I Perform flights according to schedule I Notify manufacturer of unscheduled events I Schedule maintenance ahead of time</p>
    <p>Responsibilities: I Manage a fleet of aircraft I Clock engine cycles as flights are carried out I Inform observer of all communication</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 12 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Role: Engine Manufacturer</p>
    <p>Goals: I Perform scheduled maintenance before deadlines I Perform unscheduled maintenance ASAP</p>
    <p>Responsibility: I Inform observer of all communication</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 13 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Role: Observer Monitors activities of contract parties Detects whether or not violations take place In our system, intercepts communication between parties Notifies manager of violations</p>
    <p>Messages</p>
    <p>Manufacturer Engine Airline</p>
    <p>Observer Manager Notifications</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 14 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Role: Manager</p>
    <p>Receives violation notifications from Observer Takes action to remedy them In our system, informs human operator of violation</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 15 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AgentSpeak(L) and Jason</p>
    <p>AgentSpeak(L) is a procedural agent language Based on the BDI model Designer specifies plans in a library:</p>
    <p>I Plans encode procedures I Plans are characterised by trigger and context conditions I Goals are implicit in the plans</p>
    <p>Lends itself well to state-based monitoring mechanism Prototype implementation in the Java-based Jason</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 16 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Screenshot</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 17 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Shown an instantiated system based on the CONTRACT framework Examples of concrete Observer, Manager and Contract Parties</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 18 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Provide an observation mechanism that can be reused Linked a flexible agent model to an explicit contracting mechanism Proof of concept for a contracting architecture</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 19 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Expand the prototype Integrate XML contract format Incorporate monitoring</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 20 / 21</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>F. Meneguzzi (Kings College London) Electronic contracting in aircraft aftercare AAMAS 2008 21 / 21</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
