<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HICSS 36HICSS 36</p>
    <p>A Watermarking Infrastructure for A Watermarking Infrastructure for Enterprise Document ManagementEnterprise Document Management</p>
    <p>Presenter Presenter S.C. Cheung S.C. Cheung scc@cs.ust.hkscc@cs.ust.hk</p>
    <p>Department of Computer ScienceDepartment of Computer Science Hong Kong University of Science and TechnologyHong Kong University of Science and Technology</p>
    <p>Co-author Co-author Dickson K.W. Chiu Dickson K.W. Chiu kwchiu@cse.cuhk.hkkwchiu@cse.cuhk.hk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OutlineOutline</p>
    <p>Digital WatermarkingDigital Watermarking</p>
    <p>Document Distribution InfrastructureDocument Distribution Infrastructure</p>
    <p>Three Phases of Document Distribution Three Phases of Document Distribution ProtocolProtocol  Acquisition of Registration CertificatesAcquisition of Registration Certificates  Acquisition of DocumentsAcquisition of Documents  Resolution of Policy ViolationResolution of Policy Violation</p>
    <p>Conclusion &amp; Future WorkConclusion &amp; Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IntroductionIntroduction Enterprise document management across a large enterprise Enterprise document management across a large enterprise is difficult.is difficult.  Sensitive documents often found in photocopier rooms or public Sensitive documents often found in photocopier rooms or public</p>
    <p>folders at file serversfolders at file servers</p>
    <p>Why?Why?  It involves both digital and non-digital forms.It involves both digital and non-digital forms.  It covers both automated and manual procedures.It covers both automated and manual procedures.  It requires a truly distributed solution.It requires a truly distributed solution.  It supports multimedia format.It supports multimedia format.  It must be flexible, allowing individual group to refine its own policies.It must be flexible, allowing individual group to refine its own policies.  It should protect privacy wherever applicableIt should protect privacy wherever applicable..</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IntroductionIntroduction</p>
    <p>We propose the use of digital watermarking to We propose the use of digital watermarking to enforce enterprise document distribution enforce enterprise document distribution policy.policy.</p>
    <p>Document provider disseminates watermarked documents based on the</p>
    <p>registration certificate submitted by end user</p>
    <p>End User Document Provider</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Digital Watermarking (Overview)Digital Watermarking (Overview)</p>
    <p>Two common applications of digital Two common applications of digital watermarking:watermarking:</p>
    <p>Identify and claim the copyrights ownershipIdentify and claim the copyrights ownership</p>
    <p>Identify the origin of illegal distribution Identify the origin of illegal distribution</p>
    <p>Watermarks are exclusively owned by individualsWatermarks are exclusively owned by individuals..</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Digital Watermarking is originated from Steganography</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Principle of Digital WatermarkingPrinciple of Digital Watermarking insertion detection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Issues in Watermarked Document Key Issues in Watermarked Document Distribution ProtocolDistribution Protocol</p>
    <p>PhasesPhases IssuesIssues</p>
    <p>Registration Certificate Registration Certificate AcquisitionAcquisition</p>
    <p>- Secrecy of watermarks- Secrecy of watermarks</p>
    <p>Watermarked Document Watermarked Document AcquisitionAcquisition</p>
    <p>- End users cannot be trustedEnd users cannot be trusted - Document providers cannot be trustedDocument providers cannot be trusted</p>
    <p>Policy Violation ResolutionPolicy Violation Resolution - End users cannot be trustedEnd users cannot be trusted - Document providers cannot be trustedDocument providers cannot be trusted</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ProblemProblem</p>
    <p>Identify the origin of illegal distributionIdentify the origin of illegal distribution  End user owning the origin is liableEnd user owning the origin is liable  End users watermark is analogous to a End users watermark is analogous to a</p>
    <p>private keyprivate key  Could we protect end users watermark in Could we protect end users watermark in</p>
    <p>document distribution to prevent others document distribution to prevent others (including the document provider) from (including the document provider) from abusing the watermark?abusing the watermark?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solution SketchSolution Sketch</p>
    <p>End users need not release their watermarksEnd users need not release their watermarks</p>
    <p>Instead, end users release an encrypted Instead, end users release an encrypted version of their watermarksversion of their watermarks</p>
    <p>So, how does a document provider validate So, how does a document provider validate an encrypted watermark?an encrypted watermark?</p>
    <p>Trusted Enterprise Registration AuthorityTrusted Enterprise Registration Authority</p>
    <p>Use registration certificate to protect the Use registration certificate to protect the integrity of encrypted watermarkintegrity of encrypted watermark</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Watermarked Document Watermarked Document Distribution InfrastructureDistribution Infrastructure</p>
    <p>O b</p>
    <p>ta in</p>
    <p>O n ce</p>
    <p>Document provider disseminates watermarked documents based on the</p>
    <p>registration certificate submitted by end user</p>
    <p>Enterprise registration authority generates registration certificate for end user</p>
    <p>End User</p>
    <p>Enterprise Registration</p>
    <p>Authority</p>
    <p>Document Provider</p>
    <p>Policy enforcer collects evidence of policy violation from document provider</p>
    <p>Policy Enforcer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Object Model of Registration CertificateObject Model of Registration Certificate</p>
    <p>Registration Certificate Response</p>
    <p>Registration Certificate (RCertB)</p>
    <p>Watermark (W)</p>
    <p>Encrypted Watermark</p>
    <p>EKB(W)</p>
    <p>Registration Certificate</p>
    <p>Request</p>
    <p>PKI Certificate (CertB)</p>
    <p>Public Key (KB)</p>
    <p>End User 1</p>
    <p>Enterprise Registration</p>
    <p>Authority</p>
    <p>generated by1 *</p>
    <p>refers to refers to</p>
    <p>refers to</p>
    <p>encrypt 1</p>
    <p>aggregation binary association</p>
    <p>ternary association produces</p>
    <p>S ig</p>
    <p>n (R</p>
    <p>C ert</p>
    <p>B)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>apply for registration certificate</p>
    <p>Registration Certificate</p>
    <p>Request generate watermark</p>
    <p>Registration Certificate Response</p>
    <p>obtain PKI certificate</p>
    <p>store certificate</p>
    <p>End UserEnterprise Registration Authority</p>
    <p>Watermark AcquisitionWatermark Acquisition</p>
    <p>activities</p>
    <p>data objects</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Watermarked Document Acquisition</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Policy Violation Resolution</p>
    <p>encrypt X by EKB</p>
    <p>Evidence Response</p>
    <p>(, RCertB)</p>
    <p>discover a sensitive document (X)</p>
    <p>Policy Enforcer Document Provider</p>
    <p>retrieve the request identifier (V) from X</p>
    <p>retrieve permutation function  and registration certificate (RCertB)</p>
    <p>send evidence  &amp; RCertB</p>
    <p>Encrypted Document</p>
    <p>EKB(X)</p>
    <p>data objects</p>
    <p>activities</p>
    <p>Evidence Request</p>
    <p>(X)</p>
    <p>submit X</p>
    <p>retrieve public key EKB retrieve encrypted watermark EKB(W)</p>
    <p>apply permutation function</p>
    <p>Permutated Encrypted Watermark</p>
    <p>EKB(W)</p>
    <p>detect existence of EKB(W) in EKB(X)</p>
    <p>[no]</p>
    <p>X originates from the end user of RCertB</p>
    <p>[yes]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation ArchitectureImplementation Architecture</p>
    <p>Enterprise Registration</p>
    <p>Authority</p>
    <p>Request Registration Certificate</p>
    <p>Deliver Registration Certificate</p>
    <p>Encrypted</p>
    <p>watermarked</p>
    <p>document</p>
    <p>Document RegistryLook up</p>
    <p>document access information and policy</p>
    <p>Check out</p>
    <p>R eg</p>
    <p>is te</p>
    <p>r d o cu</p>
    <p>m en</p>
    <p>t ac</p>
    <p>ce ss</p>
    <p>i nf</p>
    <p>o rm</p>
    <p>at io</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>an d p</p>
    <p>o li</p>
    <p>cy</p>
    <p>End User Check in document with registration certificate</p>
    <p>Store and retrieve document access history</p>
    <p>Deliver permutation function and registration certificate</p>
    <p>Su bm</p>
    <p>it su</p>
    <p>sp ec</p>
    <p>te d</p>
    <p>do cu</p>
    <p>m en</p>
    <p>t</p>
    <p>re qu</p>
    <p>es t f</p>
    <p>or ev</p>
    <p>id en</p>
    <p>ce</p>
    <p>Document Access Log</p>
    <p>Document Server of the Provider</p>
    <p>Policy Enforcer</p>
    <p>Certificate Repository</p>
    <p>Maintain directories of valid and revoked Registration Certificates</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Version (of Registration Certificate Format)</p>
    <p>Registration Certificate Serial Number</p>
    <p>Signature Algorithm Identifier (for Certificate Issuers Signature)</p>
    <p>Issuer Name</p>
    <p>Validity Period (Start and Expiry Dates/Times)</p>
    <p>Subject Name</p>
    <p>Roles</p>
    <p>Subjects Public Key information (Algorithm Identifier &amp; Public Key Value)</p>
    <p>One-Way Hash Value of Encrypted Secret Text</p>
    <p>Encrypted Image Watermark &amp; Watermarking Algorithm Identifiers</p>
    <p>Encrypted Audio Watermark &amp; Watermarking Algorithm Identifiers</p>
    <p>Encrypted Video Watermark &amp; Watermarking Algorithm Identifiers</p>
    <p>Issuers Digital Signature</p>
    <p>O p</p>
    <p>tio n a</p>
    <p>l Format of Registration Certificate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ConclusionConclusion We have proposed a distribution protocol We have proposed a distribution protocol and its infrastructure for watermarked and its infrastructure for watermarked documentsdocuments  features with two roles: end users and features with two roles: end users and</p>
    <p>document providers;document providers;  does not require trusts on these parties in the does not require trusts on these parties in the</p>
    <p>protection and distribution of watermarks; protection and distribution of watermarks;  assumes a trusted enterprise registration assumes a trusted enterprise registration</p>
    <p>authority and the use of registration authority and the use of registration certificatescertificates</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future WorkFuture Work Study the effectiveness of our protocol with respect Study the effectiveness of our protocol with respect to various watermarking schemesto various watermarking schemes</p>
    <p>Adapt the techniques to digital contents in Adapt the techniques to digital contents in JPEG2000 formatJPEG2000 format</p>
    <p>Study the integration of watermarking protocols and Study the integration of watermarking protocols and inter-organizational workflows [2,3,4] and e-inter-organizational workflows [2,3,4] and emarketplace negotiations [1]marketplace negotiations [1]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions and AnswersQuestions and Answers</p>
    <p>scc@cs.ust.hkscc@cs.ust.hk</p>
    <p>kwchiu@cse.cuhk.hkkwchiu@cse.cuhk.hk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Supplementary Slides (Q&amp;A)Supplementary Slides (Q&amp;A) Permutation functionPermutation function void permutefunc(VLONG wmark[], int size, int seed)void permutefunc(VLONG wmark[], int size, int seed) {{</p>
    <p>int i, index1, index2;int i, index1, index2; srand(seed);srand(seed); for (i=0; i &lt; rand() % 100 + 50)for (i=0; i &lt; rand() % 100 + 50) // min. 50 times, max 150 times// min. 50 times, max 150 times {{ VLONG tmp;VLONG tmp; index1=rand()%size;index1=rand()%size; index2=rand()%size;index2=rand()%size; // swap the two watermark coefficient// swap the two watermark coefficient tmp = wmark[index1];tmp = wmark[index1]; wmark[index1]=wmark[index2];wmark[index1]=wmark[index2]; wmark[index2]=tmp;wmark[index2]=tmp; }}</p>
    <p>} }</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Supplementary Slides (Q&amp;A)Supplementary Slides (Q&amp;A)</p>
    <p>Watermark generation and insertion Watermark generation and insertion Privacy homomorphismPrivacy homomorphism</p>
    <p>If the watermark insertion operation is:If the watermark insertion operation is:  XXW = { xW = { x11(1+w(1+w11), x), x22(1+w(1+w22),, x),, x10001000(1+w(1+w10001000)})}</p>
    <p>Then we have,Then we have,  (E(E((xx))  E E((yy)) mod n = )) mod n = EE((x x  y y) )</p>
    <p>Therefore we can insert watermark in the Therefore we can insert watermark in the encrypted domain:encrypted domain:</p>
    <p>EEKBKB(X(X(W)) = E(W)) = EKBKB(X) (X)  (E(EKBKB(W)) (W))</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
