<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Question Classification in English-Chinese Cross-Language Question Answering: An Integrated Genetic Algorithm and</p>
    <p>Machine Learning Approach</p>
    <p>Min-Yuh Day 1, 2, Chorng-Shyong Ong 2, and Wen-Lian Hsu 1,*, Fellow, IEEE</p>
    <p>Taiwan</p>
    <p>{myday, hsu}@iis.sinica.edu.tw; ongcs@im.ntu.edu.tw IEEE IRI 2007, Las Vegas, Nevada, USA, Aug 13-15, 2007.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Introduction  Research Background  Methods</p>
    <p>Hybrid GA-CRF-SVM Architecture  Experimental Design  Experimental Results and Discussion  Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction  Question classification (QC) plays an</p>
    <p>important role in cross-language question answering (CLQA)  QC: Accurately classify a question in to a</p>
    <p>question type and then map it to an expected answer type</p>
    <p>What is the biggest city in the United States?  Question Type: Q_LOCATION_CITY  Extract and filter answers in order to improve</p>
    <p>the overall accuracy of a cross-language question answering system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction (cont.)  Question informers (QI) play a key role in</p>
    <p>enhancing question classification for factual question answering  QI: Choosing a minimal, appropriate contiguous</p>
    <p>span of a question token, or tokens, as the informer span of a question, which is adequate for question classification.</p>
    <p>What is the biggest city in the United States?  Question informer: city  city is the most important clue in the</p>
    <p>question for question classification.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction (cont.)  Feature Selection in Machine Learning</p>
    <p>Optimization problem that involves choosing an appropriate feature subset.</p>
    <p>Hybrid approach that integrates Genetic Algorithm (GA) and Conditional Random Fields (CRF) improves the accuracy of question informer prediction in traditional CRF models (Day et al., 2006)</p>
    <p>We propose an integrated Genetic Algorithm (GA) and Machine Learning (ML) approach for question classification in cross-language question answering.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Background  Cross Language Question Answering</p>
    <p>International Question Answering (QA) contests  TREC QA: 1999~</p>
    <p>Monolingual QA in English  QA@CLEF: 2003~</p>
    <p>European languages in both non-English monolingual and cross-language</p>
    <p>NTCIR CLQA: 2005~  Asian languages in both monolingual and cross-language</p>
    <p>Question Classification  Rule-based method  Machine Learning based method</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Background (cont.)  Two strategies for question classification in</p>
    <p>English-Chinese cross-language question answering 1) Chinese QC (CQC) for both English and Chinese</p>
    <p>queries.  English source language has to be translated into the</p>
    <p>Chinese target language in advance. 2) English QC (EQC) for English queries and Chinese</p>
    <p>QC (CQC) for Chinese queries.  We focus on question classification in</p>
    <p>English-Chinese cross-language question answering  Bilingual QA system for English source language</p>
    <p>queries and Chinese target document collections.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methods  Hybrid GA-CRF-SVM Architecture</p>
    <p>GA for CRF Feature Selection  GA-CRF Question Informer Prediction  SVM-based Question Classification using</p>
    <p>GA-CRF Question Informer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hybrid GA-CRF-SVM Architecture</p>
    <p>CRF-based Question Informer Prediction</p>
    <p>GA for CRF Feature Selection</p>
    <p>Near Optimal Feature Subset of CRF</p>
    <p>Near Optimal CRF Prediction Model</p>
    <p>Question</p>
    <p>GA-CRF Question Informer Prediction</p>
    <p>Question Informer</p>
    <p>SVM-based Question Classification</p>
    <p>Question Type</p>
    <p>SVM-based Question Classification</p>
    <p>GA : Feature Selection GA</p>
    <p>CRF</p>
    <p>SVM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Encoding a Feature Subset of CRF</p>
    <p>with the structure of chromosomes</p>
    <p>Initialization</p>
    <p>Evaluate (Fitness Function)</p>
    <p>Population</p>
    <p>CRF model 10-fold Cross Validation</p>
    <p>GA Operators: Reproduction,</p>
    <p>Crossover, Mutation</p>
    <p>x: Feature subset</p>
    <p>F(x):Fitness</p>
    <p>Function Stopping criteria</p>
    <p>Satisfied?</p>
    <p>Near Optimal Feature Subset of CRF</p>
    <p>Near Optimal CRF Prediction Model</p>
    <p>Training dataset</p>
    <p>Test dataset</p>
    <p>CRF-based Question Informer Prediction</p>
    <p>GA-CRF Learning</p>
    <p>Yes</p>
    <p>No</p>
    <p>GA-CRF Question Informer Prediction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment Design  Data set for English Question Classification</p>
    <p>Training dataset (5288E)  4,204 questions from UIUC QC dataset (E)  + 500 questions from the NTCIR-5 CLQA development set (E)  + 200 questions from the NTCIR-5 CLQA test set (E)  + 384 questions from TREC2002 questions (E)</p>
    <p>Test dataset (CLQA2T150E)  150 English questions from NTCIR-6 CLQAs formal run</p>
    <p>Data set for Chinese Question Classification  Training dataset (2322C)</p>
    <p>1238 question from IASL (C)  + 500 questions from the NTCIR-5 CLQA development set (C)  + 200 questions from the NTCIR-5 CLQA test set (C)  + 384 questions from TREC2002 questions (translated) (C)</p>
    <p>Test dataset (CLQA2T150C)  150 Chinese questions from NTCIR-6 CLQAs formal run</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment Design (cont.)  Features for English Question Classification</p>
    <p>Syntactic features  Word-based bi-grams of the question (WB)  First word of the question (F1)  First two words of the question (F2)  Wh-word of the question (WH)</p>
    <p>i.e., 6W1H1O: who, what, when, where, which, why, how, and other</p>
    <p>Semantic features  Question informers predicted by the GA</p>
    <p>CRF model (QIF)  Question informer bi-grams predicted by</p>
    <p>the GA-CRF model (QIFB)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment Design (cont.)  Features for Chinese Question Classification</p>
    <p>Syntactic features  Bag-of-Words</p>
    <p>character-based bi-grams (CB)  word-based bi-grams (WB).</p>
    <p>Part-of-Speech (POS)  Semantic Features</p>
    <p>HowNet Senses  HowNet Main Definition (HNMD)  HowNet Definition (HND).</p>
    <p>TongYiCi CiLin (TYC)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment Design (cont.)  Performance Metrics</p>
    <p>Accuracy</p>
    <p>MRR (mean reciprocal rank)</p>
    <p>questionsofnumberTotal</p>
    <p>typesquestioncorrectedofNumber Accuracy</p>
    <p>M</p>
    <p>i irankM MRR</p>
    <p>where ranki is the rank of the first corrected question type of the ith question, and M is total number of questions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Results  Question informer prediction</p>
    <p>Using GA to optimize the selection of the feature subset in CRF-based question informer prediction improves the F-score from 88.9% to 93.87%, and reduces the number of features from 105 to 40.</p>
    <p>Training dataset (UIUC Q5500)  Test dataset (UIUC Q500)</p>
    <p>The accuracy of our proposed GA-CRF model for the UIUC dataset is 95.58% compared to 87% for the traditional CRF model reported by Krishnan et al.(2005)</p>
    <p>The proposed hybrid GA-CRF model for question informer prediction significantly outperforms the traditional CRF model.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Results  English Question Classification (EQC) using SVM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Results of Chinese Question Classification (CQC) using SVM with different features</p>
    <p>Feature Used</p>
    <p>Top 1 Accuracy</p>
    <p>(Fine)</p>
    <p>Top 1 Accuracy (Coarse)</p>
    <p>Top 5 MRR (Fine)</p>
    <p>Top 5 MRR</p>
    <p>(Coarse)</p>
    <p>POS 53.33% 65.33% 0.5732 0.7533</p>
    <p>POSB 60.00% 74.00% 0.6469 0.7970</p>
    <p>HNMD 71.33% 81.33% 0.7480 0.8832</p>
    <p>CB 74.00% 84.67% 0.7934 0.9130</p>
    <p>HNMDB 74.00% 86.00% 0.7916 0.9117</p>
    <p>C 74.67% 84.67% 0.7979 0.9152</p>
    <p>TYCB 74.67% 86.00% 0.7880 0.9062</p>
    <p>HND 74.67% 86.67% 0.7860 0.9102</p>
    <p>W 76.00% 88.00% 0.7901 0.9208</p>
    <p>HNDB 76.67% 88.00% 0.8000 0.9162</p>
    <p>WB 77.33% 88.00% 0.8067 0.9162</p>
    <p>TYC 77.33% 88.67% 0.8019 0.9240</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Chinese Question Classification (CQC) using SVM</p>
    <p>Experimental Results (cont.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions  We have proposed a hybrid genetic algorithm and</p>
    <p>machine learning approach for cross-language question classification.</p>
    <p>The major contribution of this paper is that the proposed approach enhances cross-language question classification by using the GA-CRF question informer feature with Support Vector Machines (SVM).</p>
    <p>The results of experiments on NTCIR-6 CLQA question sets demonstrate the efficacy of the approach in improving the accuracy of question classification in English-Chinese cross-language question answering.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Applications: ASQA (Academia Sinica Question Answering System)</p>
    <p>ASQA (IASL-IIS-SINICA-TAIWAN)  ASQA is the best performing Chinese question</p>
    <p>answering system.  The first place in the English-Chinese (E-C)</p>
    <p>subtask of the NTCIR-6 Cross-Lingual Question Answering (CLQA) task.(2007)</p>
    <p>The first place in the Chinese-Chinese (C-C) subtask of the NTCIR-6 Cross-Lingual Question Answering (CLQA) task.(2007)</p>
    <p>The first place in the Chinese-Chinese (C-C) subtask of the NTCIR-5 Cross-Lingual Question Answering (CLQA) task.(2005)</p>
    <p>http://asqa.iis.sinica.edu.tw</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Q &amp; A Question Classification in English-Chinese</p>
    <p>Cross-Language Question Answering: An Integrated Genetic Algorithm and</p>
    <p>Machine Learning Approach</p>
    <p>Min-Yuh Day 1, 2, Chorng-Shyong Ong 2, and Wen-Lian Hsu 1,*, Fellow, IEEE</p>
    <p>Taiwan</p>
    <p>{myday, hsu}@iis.sinica.edu.tw; ongcs@im.ntu.edu.tw IEEE IRI 2007, Las Vegas, Nevada, USA, Aug 13-15, 2007.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
