<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Corroboration de vues discordantes fonde sur la confiance</p>
    <p>Alban Galland1 Serge Abiteboul1 Amlie Marian2 Pierre Senellart3</p>
    <p>October 21, 2009, Bases de Donnes Avances</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 1/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivating Example</p>
    <p>What are the capital cities of European countries? France Italy Poland Romania Hungary</p>
    <p>Alice Paris Rome Warsaw Bucharest Budapest Bob ? Rome Warsaw Bucharest Budapest Charlie Paris Rome Katowice Bucharest Budapest David Paris Rome Bratislava Budapest Sofia Eve Paris Florence Warsaw Budapest Sofia Fred Rome ? ? Budapest Sofia George Rome ? ? ? Sofia</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Introduction 2/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voting</p>
    <p>Information: redundance France Italy Poland Romania Hungary</p>
    <p>Alice Paris Rome Warsaw Bucharest Budapest Bob ? Rome Warsaw Bucharest Budapest Charlie Paris Rome Katowice Bucharest Budapest David Paris Rome Bratislava Budapest Sofia Eve Paris Florence Warsaw Budapest Sofia Fred Rome ? ? Budapest Sofia George Rome ? ? ? Sofia</p>
    <p>Frequence P. 0.67 R. 0.80 W. 0.60 Buch. 0.50 Bud. 0.43 R. 0.33 F. 0.20 K. 0.20 Bud. 0.50 S. 0.57</p>
    <p>B. 0.20</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Introduction 3/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluating Trustworthiness of Sources</p>
    <p>Information: redundance, trustworthiness of sources (= average frequence of predicted correctness)</p>
    <p>Decision Paris Rome Warsaw Bucharest Budapest France Italy Poland Romania Hungary Trust</p>
    <p>Alice Paris Rome Warsaw Bucharest Budapest 0.60 Bob ? Rome Warsaw Bucharest Budapest 0.58 Charlie Paris Rome Katowice Bucharest Budapest 0.52 David Paris Rome Bratislava Budapest Sofia 0.55 Eve Paris Florence Warsaw Budapest Sofia 0.51 Fred Rome ? ? Budapest Sofia 0.47 George Rome ? ? ? Sofia 0.45</p>
    <p>Frequence P. 0.70 R. 0.82 W. 0.61 Buch. 0.53 Bud. 0.46 weighted R. 0.30 F. 0.18 K. 0.19 Bud. 0.47 S. 0.54 by trust B 0.20</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Introduction 4/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Iterative Fixpoint Computation</p>
    <p>Information: redundance, trustworthiness of sources with iterative fixpoint computation</p>
    <p>France Italy Poland Romania Hungary Trust</p>
    <p>Alice Paris Rome Warsaw Bucharest Budapest 0.65 Bob ? Rome Warsaw Bucharest Budapest 0.63 Charlie Paris Rome Katowice Bucharest Budapest 0.57 David Paris Rome Bratislava Budapest Sofia 0.54 Eve Paris Florence Warsaw Budapest Sofia 0.49 Fred Rome ? ? Budapest Sofia 0.39 George Rome ? ? ? Sofia 0.37</p>
    <p>Frequence P. 0.75 R. 0.83 W. 0.62 Buch. 0.57 Bud. 0.51 weighted R. 0.25 F. 0.17 K. 0.20 Bud. 0.43 S. 0.49 by trust B 0.19</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Introduction 5/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Context and problem</p>
    <p>Context:  Set of sources stating facts  (Possible) functional dependencies between facts  Fully unsupervised setting: we do not assume any information</p>
    <p>on the truth values of facts or the inherent trust of sources  Problem: determine which facts are true and which facts are</p>
    <p>false  Real world applications: query answering, source selection,</p>
    <p>data quality assessment on the web, making good use of the wisdom of crowds</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Introduction 6/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Model</p>
    <p>Algorithms</p>
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Introduction 7/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Model</p>
    <p>Algorithms</p>
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Model 8/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General Model</p>
    <p>Set of facts F = ff1:::fng  Examples: Paris is capital of France, Rome is capital of</p>
    <p>France, Rome is capital of Italy  Set of views (= sources) V = fV1:::Vmg, where a view is a</p>
    <p>partial mapping from F to {T, F}  Example: : Paris is capital of France ^ Rome is capital of France</p>
    <p>Objective: find the most likely real world W given V where the real world is a total mapping from F to {T, F}</p>
    <p>Example: Paris is capital of France ^ : Rome is capital of France ^</p>
    <p>Rome is capital of Italy ^ ...</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Model 9/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Generative Probabilistic Model</p>
    <p>Vi , fj</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>'(Vi )'(fj ) 1  '(Vi )'(fj )</p>
    <p>:W(fj )</p>
    <p>&quot;(Vi )&quot;(fj )</p>
    <p>W(fj )</p>
    <p>'(Vi )'(fj ): probability that Vi forgets fj  &quot;(Vi )&quot;(fj ): probability that Vi makes an error on fj  Number of parameters: n + 2(n + m)  Size of data: 'nm with ' the average forget rate</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Model 10/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Obvious Approach</p>
    <p>Method: use this generative model to find the most likely parameters given the data</p>
    <p>Inverse the generative model to compute the probability of a set of parameters given the data</p>
    <p>Not practically applicable:  Non-linearity of the model and boolean parameter W(fj ) ) equations for inversing the generative model very complex</p>
    <p>Large number of parameters (n and m can both be quite large) ) Any exponential technique unpractical</p>
    <p>) Heuristic fix-point algorithms</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Model 11/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Model</p>
    <p>Algorithms</p>
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Algorithms 12/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Baselines</p>
    <p>Counting (does not look at negative statements, popularity) 8 &gt;&lt; &gt;:</p>
    <p>T if jfVi : Vi (fj ) = Tgj</p>
    <p>maxf jfVi : Vi (f ) = Tgj &gt;</p>
    <p>F otherwise</p>
    <p>Voting (adapted only with negative statements) 8 &gt;&lt; &gt;:</p>
    <p>T if jfVi : Vi (fj ) = Tgj</p>
    <p>jfVi : Vi (fj ) = T _ Vi (fj ) = Fgj &gt; 0:5</p>
    <p>F otherwise</p>
    <p>TruthFinder [YHY07]: heuristic fix-point method from the literature</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Algorithms 13/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fix-Point Algorithms</p>
    <p>Iterate until a fix-point is reached (and cross your fingers it converges!).</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Algorithms 14/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cosine</p>
    <p>The truth of a fact is what views state weighted by how error prone they are</p>
    <p>The error of a view is the correlation (= cosine similarity) between its statement of facts and the predicted truth of these facts</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Algorithms 15/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Assume all the fact have the same difficulty: &quot;(fj ) = 1  Statistical estimation of W(fj ) given &quot;(Vi ) and observations  Statistical estimation of &quot;(Vi ) given W(fj ) and observations  Quite instable ) tricky normalization</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Algorithms 16/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Similar in spirit to 2-Estimates but estimation of 3 parameters:</p>
    <p>truth value of facts  error rate or trustworthiness of sources  hardness of facts</p>
    <p>Also needs tricky normalization</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Algorithms 17/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Functional dependencies</p>
    <p>So far, the models and algorithms are about positive and negative statements, without correlation between facts</p>
    <p>How to deal with functional dependencies (e.g., capital cities)? pre-filtering: When a view states a value, all other values</p>
    <p>governed by this FD are considered stated false. If I say that Paris is the capital of France, then I say that neither Rome nor Lyon nor . . . is the capital of France.</p>
    <p>post-filtering: Choose the best answer for a given FD.</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Algorithms 18/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Model</p>
    <p>Algorithms</p>
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Experiments 19/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Datasets</p>
    <p>Synthetic dataset: large scale and higly customizable  Real-world datasets:</p>
    <p>General-knowledge quiz  Biology 6th-grade test  Search-engines results  Hubdub</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Experiments 20/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General-Knowledge Quiz (1/2)</p>
    <p>http://www.madore.org/~david/quizz/quizz1.html</p>
    <p>17 questions, 4 to 14 answers, 601 participants</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Experiments 21/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>General-Knowledge Quiz (2/2)</p>
    <p>Number of errors Number of errors (no post-filtering) (with post-filtering)</p>
    <p>Voting 11 6 Counting 12 6 TruthFinder - 2-Estimates 6 6 Cosine 7 6 3-Estimates 9 0</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Experiments 22/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>It does not always work!</p>
    <p>No magic!  Does not take into account dependencies between sources  Example: integration of search engine results  Usually, when it does not work, 3-Estimates gives results</p>
    <p>comparable to the baseline, Cosine is not bad, 2-Estimates is very unstable</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Experiments 23/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Model</p>
    <p>Algorithms</p>
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Conclusion 24/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In brief</p>
    <p>One of the first works in truth discovery among disagreeing sources</p>
    <p>Collection of fix-point methods, one of them (3-Estimates) performing remarkably and regularly well</p>
    <p>We believe this is an important problem, we do not claim we have solved it completely</p>
    <p>Cool real-world applications!</p>
    <p>All code and datasets available from http://datacorrob.gforge.inria.fr/</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Conclusion 25/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Merci.</p>
    <p>Foundations of Web data management</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 Conclusion 26/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Perspectives</p>
    <p>Exploiting dependencies between sources [DBES09]  Numerical values (1:77m and 1:78m cannot be seen as two</p>
    <p>completely contradictory statements for a height)  No clear functional dependencies, but a limited number of</p>
    <p>values for a given object (e.g., phone numbers)  Pre-existing trust, e.g., in a social network  Clustering of facts, each source being trustworthy for a given</p>
    <p>field</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 27/28</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References I</p>
    <p>Xin Luna Dong, Laure Berti-Equille, and Divesh Srivastava. Integrating conflicting data: The role of source dependence. In Proc. VLDB, Lyon, France, August 2009. Xiaoxin Yin, Jiawei Han, and Philip S. Yu. Truth discovery with multiple conflicting information providers on the Web. In Proc. KDD, San Jose, California, USA, August 2007.</p>
    <p>Corroboration A. Galland BDA 2009 28/28</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
