<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inapproximability of Combinatorial Public</p>
    <p>Projects</p>
    <p>Michael Schapira (Yale University and UC Berkeley)</p>
    <p>Joint work with Yaron Singer (UC Berkeley)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of the Talk</p>
    <p>The Combinatorial Public Project Problem.</p>
    <p>The Submodular Case  Background.</p>
    <p>A Trivial Truthful Approximation-Algorithm.</p>
    <p>Our Main Result.</p>
    <p>Conclusions and Open Questions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithmic Mechanism Design</p>
    <p>Algorithmic Mechanism Design deals with designing efficient mechanisms for decentralized computerized settings [Nisan-Ronen].</p>
    <p>Takes into account both the strategic behavior of the different participants and the usual computational efficiency considerations.</p>
    <p>Target applications: protocols for Internet environments.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Combinatorial Public Project</p>
    <p>Set of n users; Set of m resources;</p>
    <p>Each user i has a valuation function: vi : 2[m]  R0</p>
    <p>Objective: Given a parameter k, choose a set of resources S* of size k which maximizes the social welfare:</p>
    <p>S* = argmax i vi(S) S [m], |S|=k</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Assumptions Regarding Each Valuation Function</p>
    <p>Normalized: v( ) = 0</p>
    <p>Non-decreasing: v(S)  v(T) S T</p>
    <p>Subadditive: v( S) + v(T)  v( S  T)</p>
    <p>[ Submodular: v( S  { j }) v(S)  v( T  { j }) v(T) S T ]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivating Examples</p>
    <p>Elections for a committee: The agents are voters, resources are potential candidates.</p>
    <p>Overlay networks: We wish to select a subset of nodes in a graph that will function as an overlay network. [http://nms.csail.mit.edu/ron/]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Access Models</p>
    <p>How can we access the input ?</p>
    <p>One possibility: succinct valuations computational complexity approach.</p>
    <p>The black box approach: each bidder is represented by an oracle which can answer certain queries. Communication complexity approach.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What Do We Want?</p>
    <p>Quality of the solution: As close to the optimum as possible.</p>
    <p>Computationally tractable: Polynomial running time (in n and m).</p>
    <p>Truthful: Motivate (via payments) agents to report their true values regardless of other agents reports.  The utility of each user is ui = vi(S) - pi</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Submodular Case [Papadimitriou-SSinger]</p>
    <p>Computational Perspective: A 1-1/e approximation ratio is achievable due to the submodularity of the valuations (but not truthful)  A tight lower bound exists [Feige].</p>
    <p>Strategic Perspective: A truthful solution is achievable via VCG payments (but NP-hard to obtain)</p>
    <p>What about achieving both simultaneously?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Submodular Case: Truth and Computation Dont Mix</p>
    <p>Theorem [Papadimitriou-S-Singer]:</p>
    <p>Any truthful algorithm for the combinatorial public project problem which approximates better than m requires exponential communication in m.</p>
    <p>Even for n=2.</p>
    <p>Implications for AMD: A huge gap between truthful&amp;polynomial algorithms, and truthful/polynomial algorithms.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A trivial m-approximation Algorithm for Subadditiver Agents</p>
    <p>The algorithm:</p>
    <p>If km, simply choose the single resource j for which the social-welfare is maximized.</p>
    <p>If k&gt;m, divide the m resources to m disjoint sets of equal size and choose the one that maximizes the social welfare.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Algorithm is Truthful</p>
    <p>Fact: Maximal-in-range algorithms are truthful (VCG).</p>
    <p>-&gt; The trivial approximation algorithm is (essentially) the best truthful algorithm for the submodular case. Also for the subadditive case.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Upper and Lower Bounds</p>
    <p>Submodular m</p>
    <p>truthful upper bound</p>
    <p>constant non- truthful upper bounds exist</p>
    <p>Subadditive m</p>
    <p>truthful upper bound</p>
    <p>?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>High Hopes</p>
    <p>Twin problem: combinatorial auctions.</p>
    <p>Theorem (Informal): There is a 2approximation algorithm for combinatorial auctions with subadditive bidders. [Feige]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Main Result</p>
    <p>Theorem: Any approximation algorithm for the combinatorial public project problem with subadditive agents which approximates better than O(m1/4) requires exponential communication in m.</p>
    <p>Implications: The trivial truthful approximation algorithm is nearly tight even from a purely computational perspective.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other Results and an Open Question</p>
    <p>A communication complexity lower bound for general valuations.</p>
    <p>A computational complexity lower bound for general valuations.</p>
    <p>Open question: prove a computationalcomplexity analogue of our result.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
