<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Speech Assisted Radiology System for Retrieval, Reporting and Annotaiton</p>
    <p>Tim Weninger, Daniel Greene, Jack Hart, William H. Hsu and Surya Ramachandran*</p>
    <p>Department of Computing and Information Sciences Kansas State University, Manhattan KS</p>
    <p>*AIdentity Matrix Inc, Elmhurst, IL</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction  Motivation  Example</p>
    <p>Voice Directed Search  Prerequisites  Parsing Spoken Text  Search  Findings and Impressions</p>
    <p>Merit Case Client  Experiments</p>
    <p>Metrics  Results</p>
    <p>Conclusions and Future Work  Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Motivation  Paradigm: Radiology  Healthcare is expensive</p>
    <p>Why?</p>
    <p>Errors  2004-2006 Medicare study</p>
    <p>Errors cost US$8.8 billon  University of Baylor study:</p>
    <p>Out of 113 errors studied  Transcription was the base-cause for 46%</p>
    <p>(Seely et al. 2004)</p>
    <p>Inefficiencies  Medical Transcription</p>
    <p>Adds cost  Adds complexity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Status quo (simplified)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Status quo (simplified)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Definitions</p>
    <p>Define our Terms:  Paradigm: Radiology</p>
    <p>MRI  Finding/Impression</p>
    <p>Medical diagnostic interpretation of particular abnormalities as seen by the radiologist</p>
    <p>Annotation  The expression of a medical opinion related to a specific image.</p>
    <p>Drawn Arrow  Circle  Etc</p>
    <p>Merit Case Client:  Speech directed PACS system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Voice Directed Search</p>
    <p>Current PACS systems  Example: find men with slipped discs</p>
    <p>Search. sex equals male. diagnosis equals herniated disc.  [Search] is a command  [male] is a menu option in list [sex]  [Herniated disc] is option in list [diagnosis]</p>
    <p>Disadvantages:  Narrow speech scope  Voice recognition systems are not foolproof</p>
    <p>Example: Homonyms  Search. Sex equals mail. Diagnosis equals herniated disk.</p>
    <p>Does not compute!</p>
    <p>Main advantage:  Capable of standardizing naturally spoken medical terminologies with</p>
    <p>significant degrees of variance.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Voice Directed Search  Example:</p>
    <p>Find all male patients between the ages of 55 and 60 with a slipped disc in the L4/L5 region with no previous history of disc injury.</p>
    <p>Find men with a slipped disc in the L4/L5 region  [Find] is a command along with others  [male] is a interpreted to be [male] within [sex]  [between 55 and 60] is [55-60] within [age]  [slipped disc] is interpreted to be [herniated disc] within [disease]  [disc injury] looks for any [disc] within [disease]</p>
    <p>Moreover:  This widens the search scope  Voice recognition systems are not foolproof</p>
    <p>Example: Homonyms and formatting  Find men with a slipped disk in the El four slash El five region.</p>
    <p>This works as well.</p>
    <p>How?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Parsing Spoken Text</p>
    <p>Operating Assumptions:  The system maintains a complete list of all ages, sexes, diseases, etc.</p>
    <p>i.e. type enumeration  Valid responses are available in lists</p>
    <p>Homonyms do not coexist in a list  If so, then its hard to make a decision</p>
    <p>Goal  Map what is dictated to the appropriate descriptor</p>
    <p>Sliding window approach: There is moderate disc bulging at L5/S1</p>
    <p>Size Small Small to Moderate Moderate Moderate to Large Large</p>
    <p>There is moderate disc bulging at L5/S1</p>
    <p>Diagnosis Disc bulging Herniated disc Degenerative disc disease</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Voice Directed Search</p>
    <p>Synonym Learning  How does the system know:</p>
    <p>Slipped Disc = Herniated Disc = Disc Herniation  The system will make an initial guess.</p>
    <p>System will not initially recognize Slipped Disc</p>
    <p>System remembers corrections  Correction process is easy  Learns speakers word choice preference</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Structured Reporting</p>
    <p>Image Embedding  Findings  Impressions  Annotations</p>
    <p>Text, descriptors, drawings  Become linked with the image(s)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Data points  (1) Text read by the radiologist  (2) Text output by speech recognition engine  (3) Descriptors filled in by Merit Case Client  (4) Correct state of the descriptor (ground truth)</p>
    <p>Metrics  Speech Recognition Metric (SRM)</p>
    <p>Word-Edit distance between original text (1) and output by the speech recognition system (2).</p>
    <p>Parsing Engine Metric (PEM)  Word-Edit distance between menus filled in by Merit Case Client (3) and</p>
    <p>the correct answer (4)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Experiments</p>
    <p>Reporting and Analysis  Some errors are more costly than others  3 reporting methods:</p>
    <p>Word distance  Weighted errors</p>
    <p>Disease descriptor= 60%  Location descriptor = 20%  All others descriptors = 20%</p>
    <p>All or not  Was it completely correct or not?</p>
    <p>Experiment  Radiologist (Dr. Schekall, MD) made 100 dictations based on real-world</p>
    <p>cases  25 search queries  75 findings and impressions dictations</p>
    <p>No re-dos allowed  Speech recognition system was NOT pre-trained</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Data points and their linear regression lines</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Change in accuracy for each paradigm Method: (SRM-PEM)/SRM</p>
    <p>Paradigm Test Accuracy (area) Change in Accuracy</p>
    <p>Distance Speech (SRM) 87.65 +10.0285%</p>
    <p>Parsing (PRM) 96.44</p>
    <p>Weighted Speech (SRM) 66.93 +41.8945%</p>
    <p>Parsing (PRM) 94.97</p>
    <p>All-or-Not Speech (SRM) 35.81 +96.7607%</p>
    <p>Parsing (PRM) 70.46</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Current domains of implementation (ongoing)</p>
    <p>Branded under - Virtual Integrity in Medicine TM (VIM)</p>
    <p>Electronic Medical Records  VIM Radiology</p>
    <p>PET, CT, MRI, Nuclear, X-Ray, Ultrasound, etc  VIM Cardiology</p>
    <p>ECG, Ultrasound, CT, Nuclear, Cath lab, Vitals, Resting, Exercise, Stress, Ambulatory BP and Spirometry</p>
    <p>VIM Neurology  From out-patient clinical through surgery</p>
    <p>Front &amp; Back Office  Scheduling, Patient profile, Insurance, Rule-outs ICD9/10, Referring Physician,</p>
    <p>Reporting, Billing &amp; Accounts bridge, Clinical messaging, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Demo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IEEE CBMS Conference August 3-4, 2009</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Special thanks</p>
    <p>Dr. Michael Schekall, MD Deborah Templeton, BS, CNMT, RT(R), LRT</p>
    <p>Hutchinson Clinic PA, Hutchinson, KS</p>
    <p>Jeff Barber, Andrew Walters Kansas State University</p>
    <p>Industry Contact for more information</p>
    <p>Surya Ramachandran AIdentity Matrix Medical Inc. surya@aidentitymatrix.com</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
