<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quantifying Maintainability in Quantifying Maintainability in Feature Oriented Product LinesFeature Oriented Product Lines</p>
    <p>G. Aldekoa1, S.Trujillo2, G.Sagardui1, O.Daz3 1: Universidad de Mondragon 2: IKERLAN 3: Universidad del Pas Vasco</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Problem Statement: Product-Line Maintenance Work Done Lessons Learned and Ongoing Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Software Product Line (SPL) is a set of software-intensive systems that share a common, managed set of features satisfying the specific needs of a particular market segment or mission and that are developed from a common set of core assets in a prescribed way Clements and Northrop, 2001 FOP is a paradigm to SPL development where features are the building blocks of products Features are units incrementing application functionality by which different products can be distinguished and defined within an SPL.</p>
    <p>Software Product Line Definition</p>
    <p>plus</p>
    <p>memory</p>
    <p>minus</p>
    <p>multiply</p>
    <p>division</p>
    <p>color</p>
    <p>base plus</p>
    <p>memory</p>
    <p>scientific</p>
    <p>minus</p>
    <p>multiply</p>
    <p>division</p>
    <p>color</p>
    <p>These are features!</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>The ease with which a software system can be modified to correct faults, improve performance, or adapt to a changing environment The capability of the software product to be modified. [IEEE Standard Computer Dictionary ]</p>
    <p>Maintainability index (SEI), Using Polynomial regression model A greater MI means more maintainable. Case Studies: [Coleman 94], [Welker 95],[Zhuo 93], [Pearse 95] Tools to measure C, Java (Semantic Designs, Understand)</p>
    <p>aveV is the average Halstead Volume V per module.  aveV(g') is the average extended Cyclomatic Complexity per module.  aveLOC is the average count of Lines Of Code (LOC) per module.  perCM is the average percent of Lines of Comments per module.</p>
    <p>Maintainability Definition</p>
    <p>( ) ( ) ( ) perCMaveLOCgaveVaveVMI += 4.2sin50ln2.16'23.0ln2.5171</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem Statement</p>
    <p>Maintainability for Software Product Lines</p>
    <p>Distinct quality dimensions SPL quality &lt;&gt; Products quality</p>
    <p>P1 P2 P3 PN</p>
    <p>SPL Infrastructure</p>
    <p>Quality</p>
    <p>Quality Quality Quality Quality</p>
    <p>Problem Statement</p>
    <p>Maintainability for Software Product Lines</p>
    <p>Distinct quality dimensions SPL quality &lt;&gt; Products quality</p>
    <p>Change probability Probability of Change (SPL) &gt; Probability of Change (Product)</p>
    <p>P1 P2 P3 PN</p>
    <p>SPL Infrastructure</p>
    <p>Change</p>
    <p>Change Change Change Change</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Problem Statement: Product-Line Maintenance Work Done Lessons Learned and Ongoing Work</p>
    <p>Work Done</p>
    <p>Measure Software Product Line Maintainability</p>
    <p>P1 P2 P3 PN</p>
    <p>SPL Infrastructure</p>
    <p>Remind existing problems</p>
    <p>We have: Jak code Override existing code</p>
    <p>Problem: 1) Tooling unavailable 2) Measurement of refinements need further study</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>But</p>
    <p>Remind a single product has MI Each product has a set of features (belonging to the SPL) Should be possible to get features MI from products? Stay tuned</p>
    <p>P1 P2 P3 Pn</p>
    <p>SPL Infrastructure</p>
    <p>Fa Fb Fc Fn</p>
    <p>Fa Fb Fc</p>
    <p>base</p>
    <p>Fc</p>
    <p>base</p>
    <p>Fa Fb</p>
    <p>base From</p>
    <p>Products</p>
    <p>To Features</p>
    <p>Mi</p>
    <p>base Mi</p>
    <p>Work Done</p>
    <p>Help</p>
    <p>Feature Model Case Studies A simple SPL was developed</p>
    <p>Basic Windows-GUI calculator</p>
    <p>Problems  was developed by us  consisted only of a few</p>
    <p>classes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Work Done</p>
    <p>Help</p>
    <p>Feature Model Case Studies A simple SPL was developed</p>
    <p>Basic Windows-GUI calculator</p>
    <p>An SPL provided by AHEAD Tool Suite was used Graph Product Line</p>
    <p>Work Done</p>
    <p>Measure products MI and extrapolating feature impact</p>
    <p>(1) All possible products were build (147)</p>
    <p>(2) MI for each product was measured using available (SemanticDesigns) tooling</p>
    <p>MIFeaturesProduct</p>
    <p>(3) A system of equations with these results was created A matrix where the rows contain equations One row per product and One column per feature</p>
    <p>omittedequationsmore</p>
    <p>xyvsb xypsc</p>
    <p>xyqsd xyosb</p>
    <p>base</p>
    <p>base</p>
    <p>base</p>
    <p>base</p>
    <p>__//</p>
    <p>BFS esOnlyVerticUndirectedNumberlyVerticesWeightedOn</p>
    <p>BFS thEdgesDirectedWiNumberthEdgesWeightedWi</p>
    <p>BFS rsthNeighbouDirectedWiNumberrsthNeighbouWeightedWi</p>
    <p>BFS lyVerticesDirectedOnNumberlyVerticesWeightedOn</p>
    <p>++++=</p>
    <p>++++=</p>
    <p>++++=</p>
    <p>++++=</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Work Done</p>
    <p>(4) MatLab was used to resolve the matrix equation system</p>
    <p>Entries (MI_vector and PF) where</p>
    <p>MI_vector is a vector with all the MI values of products  PF is a matrix specifying product features</p>
    <p>MI_vector=[153.96,146.62,149.50,153.23, 150.32,148.71,153.46]</p>
    <p>PF=[1,1,0,0,0,1,0,0,0,1,0,0,0,0,0,1,0,0; 1,1,0,0,0,0,0,1,0,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,1; // content omitted 1,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,1,0,0,1,0,0,0,0,0]</p>
    <p>x=solveAxb (PF, MI_vector)</p>
    <p>MatLab commands</p>
    <p>Work Done</p>
    <p>(5) The resolution of the equation provides the maintainability values for each feature</p>
    <p>Pr</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>= = =</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>= =</p>
    <p>= =</p>
    <p>= =</p>
    <p>rsthNeighbouWeightedWi</p>
    <p>thEdgesWeightedWi</p>
    <p>lyVerticesWeightedOn</p>
    <p>oursWithNeighbUndirected</p>
    <p>WithEdgesUndirected</p>
    <p>esOnlyVerticUndirected</p>
    <p>Transpose</p>
    <p>nnectedStronglyCo</p>
    <p>Number</p>
    <p>imMST</p>
    <p>rsthNeighbouDirectedWi</p>
    <p>thEdgesDirectedWi</p>
    <p>lyVerticesDirectedOn</p>
    <p>DFS</p>
    <p>Cycle</p>
    <p>Connected</p>
    <p>BFS</p>
    <p>Base</p>
    <p>d c b</p>
    <p>a w v</p>
    <p>u t s r q p</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>m z y x</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Benefits</p>
    <p>Developers can improve specific features (depending on the MI impact)</p>
    <p>Developers and Customers can use automated reasoning to establish SPL or Product quality levels</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Problem Statement: Product-Line Maintenance Work Done Lessons Learned and Ongoing Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons Learned</p>
    <p>Dependencies among Features Impact of Order</p>
    <p>Monotonicity Overriding different code, impact is different.</p>
    <p>Artefact Heterogeneity Not only code is maintained, there are other artefacts.</p>
    <p>Generality of Experiences What happens with other paradigms?</p>
    <p>Range of Maintainability Index</p>
    <p>Ongoing Work</p>
    <p>Quantification of Feature Maintainability Provides a number of benefits:  Identification of risk areas</p>
    <p>Quantification of Software Product Lines Maintainability Provides a number of benefits:</p>
    <p>Compare different global-SPL Maintainability  Establish maintainability risk limits  Predict maintenance cost of individual product  Support of design decisions  Reasoning on maintenance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks for your attention !</p>
    <p>Can we improve this talk? Contact us at galdekoa@eps.mondragon.edu Drop by our site at www.mondragon.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
