<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges in Access Right Assignment for Secure Home Networks</p>
    <p>Tiffany Hyun-Jin Kim, Lujo Bauer, James Newsome, Adrian Perrig (CMU) Jesse Walker (Intel)</p>
    <p>August 10, 2010</p>
    <p>HotSec10 (5th Usenix Workshop on Hot Topics in Security)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Smart Home Vision</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bob &amp; Alice</p>
    <p>Carol &amp; her boyfriend Marvin</p>
    <p>David &amp; his babysiIer Anna Chapman</p>
    <p>Year 2020</p>
    <p>* hIp://www.electroluxdesignlab.com/</p>
    <p>*</p>
    <p>*</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Issues</p>
    <p>Security concern  Individual &amp; family privacy</p>
    <p>PotenRal physical harm</p>
    <p>QuesOon  How to control access in home environment?</p>
    <p>Diversity of visitors</p>
    <p>Complexity &amp; diversity of devices and resources</p>
    <p>Low sophisRcaRon of administrators</p>
    <p>Social context</p>
    <p>Poten&amp;al Home Network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Problem DefiniOon</p>
    <p>Unique CombinaOon of Challenges</p>
    <p>Preliminary Policy Assignment</p>
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem DefiniOon</p>
    <p>Access control mechanisms from a users perspec&amp;ve  Assist non-expert home owners for access assignment to visitors</p>
    <p>Protect resources against unauthorized use</p>
    <p>Adversary Model  Visitor with unintended (over-permissive) access privileges</p>
    <p>Curious Anna</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Unique CombinaOon of Challenges</p>
    <p>Appliances, media storage, network-related, safety devices</p>
    <p>Types of resources each device supports</p>
    <p>Data stored on each device</p>
    <p>service workers, first responders, elderly care providers  Each party requires different access</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Unique CombinaOon of Challenges 4. Devices: mixed ownership</p>
    <p>No single owner for all devices (e.g., personal laptops)  Shared devices with mulRple owners (e.g., TV)</p>
    <p>Anna</p>
    <p>Bob &amp; Alice</p>
    <p>Carol</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Preliminary Policy Assignment</p>
    <p>Small user study  Interview on 20 people (8 males &amp; 12 females)  Age range of 20 to 60</p>
    <p>Interview instrucOons  List 8 people</p>
    <p>Contact on semi-regular basis</p>
    <p>May be potenRal future home visitors</p>
    <p>Imagine future electronics &amp; appliances in their future home  Ask access policy assignments for each device for each person</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ObservaOons from Interview  ValidaOon of some challenges</p>
    <p>Non-expert administrators</p>
    <p>Complexity of home environments</p>
    <p>Diversity of visiRng parRes</p>
    <p>Concerned about distrust revelaRon</p>
    <p>3 types of policies  Sufficient to capture desired policies</p>
    <p>Fixed groups of access-control policies to visitors  DuraRon of relaRonship</p>
    <p>Level of trust</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User must be inside home to gain access  User presence (PU)</p>
    <p>Owner &amp; user presence (POU)</p>
    <p>Logging (PL)  Devices maintain detailed audit logs</p>
    <p>Ask for permission (PA)  Lazy evaluaRon approach</p>
    <p>Owner is contacted when visitors aIempt to use</p>
    <p>Always deny (PX)</p>
    <p>Hybrid policies  CombinaRon of any dimensions (e.g., PUA)</p>
    <p>Ask</p>
    <p>Log</p>
    <p>Presence</p>
    <p>PU</p>
    <p>POU</p>
    <p>PUA</p>
    <p>PX PL</p>
    <p>PA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Complete control &amp; full access to all devices  Owners, close relaRves, household members</p>
    <p>Restricted control  Full access control except: entertainment &amp; security systems  Teenagers in family</p>
    <p>ParOal control  Full access control on sharable devices (e.g., home telephone)  Trusted friends</p>
    <p>Minimal control  Most restricRve  Casual visitors</p>
    <p>Bob &amp; Alice</p>
    <p>Carol</p>
    <p>Marvin</p>
    <p>Anna</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Suggested Basic Policy Assignment</p>
    <p>Policy Meaning</p>
    <p>PU User present</p>
    <p>POU User &amp; owner present</p>
    <p>PL Logging</p>
    <p>PA Ask for permission</p>
    <p>PX Always deny</p>
    <p>Bob &amp; Alice</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Home environment  Carl Ellison: home network security  Johnson &amp; Stajano: permission to guests</p>
    <p>Argyroudis &amp; Omahony: foundaRon architecture for security relaRonships</p>
    <p>KosRaninen et al.: access control for family members</p>
    <p>Marin et al.: access control middleware for family members  Brush &amp; Inkpen: results from empirical study of 15 families</p>
    <p>Egelman et al.: user account model for shared home computers</p>
    <p>Seingneur et al.: adjust trust based on reputaRon  Mazurek et al.: access control for home data sharing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions  Access policy to home resources to visitors</p>
    <p>Difficult to address all challenges  Danger: inappropriate access permission</p>
    <p>Liberal assignment: visitor accesses sensiRve personal data</p>
    <p>RestricRve assignment: visitor cannot use light switch</p>
    <p>Preliminary approach to address some challenges  3 policy types</p>
    <p>4 groups of access rights</p>
    <p>Future work  Full evaluaRon with larger set of parRcipants</p>
    <p>Address remaining challenges (e.g., mulRple administrators)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
    <p>hyunjin1@ece.cmu.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion QuesOons</p>
    <p>Issue with logging  How to prioriRze entries with illegiRmate accesses while prevenRng entries with legiRmate accesses?</p>
    <p>Mental models  Compelling mental models for consumers?  Would 3 classes &amp; 4 groups be natural way of thinking?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
