<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Verified by Visa and</p>
    <p>MasterCard SecureCode  or, How Not to Design Authentication</p>
    <p>Steven Murdoch and Ross Anderson Cambridge</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Single Sign-on Systems</p>
    <p>Since mid-80s, weve seen products that let you use one password for multiple systems</p>
    <p>What do you think is the most successful single sign-on system ever?  Microsoft Passport / InfoCard?  OpenID?  Liberty Alliance?</p>
    <p>Actually, its none of these</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SecureCode; hereinafter 3DS  Lets you use a password with your credit card to</p>
    <p>pay at many merchant websites  Like Passport, OpenID etc, it redirects you to a</p>
    <p>central login service  It was the card industrys answer to a big rise in</p>
    <p>card-not-present (CNP) fraud that followed the introduction of the Europay-Mastercard-VISA (EMV) smartcard payment system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fraud in the UK since EMV</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How 3DS Works  Customer presents card to merchant  Merchant passes card number to its bank (the</p>
    <p>acquirer) who supplies a URL for logon  The URL is often to a third-party service such as</p>
    <p>RSA  The logon page was originally presented as popup  Because of popup blockers, the standard now</p>
    <p>recommends that the merchant embeds it in an iframe</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Interface (1)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>User Interface (2)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How 3DS Works (2)</p>
    <p>If successful, auth code is returned for merchant using TLS and client certificate</p>
    <p>Similar systems are being introduced (or are planned) for more and more payment systems  VISA original credits  Single European Payment Area (SEPA) e-Mandates</p>
    <p>The latter will replace cheques in Europe!  So how secure is all this?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technical Security (1)</p>
    <p>Implementation is left to individual banks and their contractors</p>
    <p>Some make truly shocking choices  like reusing ATM PINs as online 3DS passwords</p>
    <p>Best practice is to authenticate the bank too  with a memorable phrase from the customer</p>
    <p>But this is still open to man-in-the-middle attack  So were now seeing a variety of phishing attacks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phishing (1)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Technical Security (2)  Banks should mail out passwords  but to save</p>
    <p>money most do Activation During Shopping (ADS)  So a merchant website suddenly enrols you!  Weak auth  e.g. date of birth (Bank of Scotland)  Banks are not supposed to compel registration until</p>
    <p>after three transactions, but many ignore this  Also, if you forget your password, many banks just</p>
    <p>rerun the enrolment protocol  All this also gets used in phishing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phishing (2)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Usability</p>
    <p>Users should only enter bank credentials at bank URL to which they have navigated (or at least which theyve checked)</p>
    <p>Our industry introduced cues such as extended validation certs and browser toolbar colour</p>
    <p>The banking industry via 3DS has trashed this completely!</p>
    <p>Our first encounter with securesuite.co.uk  So why should the computer industry be helpful to</p>
    <p>the banks in future?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy</p>
    <p>SET gave the bank and the merchant only the data they needed; InfoCard prevents profiling at all</p>
    <p>3DS collects full transaction data  And its mostly run by contractors like RSA who</p>
    <p>accumulate huge databases of transactions  We might then worry about FBI national security</p>
    <p>letters, spear phishing, corrupt employees...  Will there be a big bust-up as with SWIFT?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Economics</p>
    <p>3DS is easily the worst secure signon protocol ever; why did it succeed?  Merchants are no longer as liable for transactions they</p>
    <p>push through 3DS  Users lose statutory protection of signatures; typical</p>
    <p>contract says customer liable for all uses</p>
    <p>While InfoCard and OpenID had good engineering but no incentives for adoption, 3DS had bad engineering but strong incentives</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Policy</p>
    <p>3DS is abusive  customers get little or no protection but a huge increase in liability</p>
    <p>Whats needed is transaction authentication  e.g. modify 3DS to include SMS, Cronto (Commerzbank, Germany) or CAP interaction (Ogone, Belgium)</p>
    <p>Regulation: at present, a liability shift is allowed under Europes e-signature directive if the customer has a secure signature creation device</p>
    <p>The missing word is only!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions  Single sign-on provides a telling case study in</p>
    <p>security engineering  Previous offerings like OpenID and InfoCard got</p>
    <p>the engineering right but the economics wrong  3D Secure got the engineering wrong but the</p>
    <p>economics right (at least for the banks)  Its the one that succeeded  The outcome is abusive to customers (and</p>
    <p>merchants hate it too). Regulators ought to fix it  It contributes to growing systemic risk (recall the</p>
    <p>hassles of registering and booking!)</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
