<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Samuli Aalto (HUT), Urtzi Ayesta (FranceTelecom and INRIA) and Eeva Nyberg-Oksanen (HUT)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mice and elephants: 80% of the flows are short, 5% of largest flows make up for 95% of the load.</p>
    <p>TCP point of view, short connections are more vulnerable against losses. Motivation for the differentiation between Short and Long TCP</p>
    <p>flows.</p>
    <p>Flow level analysis: Interest in the analysis of age based scheduling disciplines.</p>
    <p>Mean delay analysis of Kleinrocks Multi-level Processor Sharing.</p>
    <p>Comparison with ordinary Processor Sharing.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Review of known Scheduling results. Two-level Processor Sharing</p>
    <p>Framework for mean delay comparison of scheduling disciplines.</p>
    <p>Results</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!&quot;</p>
    <p>Two important set of disciplines depending on whether or not the size of jobs is known.</p>
    <p>The size is known: Shortest-Remaining-Processing-Time SRPT is optimal with respect to the average response time of the system.</p>
    <p>The size is not known, but we know the age (attained service) of jobs. The most appropriate scheduling discipline depends on the service time distribution characteristics.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!&quot;  Hazard rate of a distribution function. h(x)=P[x&lt; size of the job</p>
    <p>x+dx | size of the job &gt; x]</p>
    <p>The hazard-rate of several distributions of practical interest show monotonous behaviour: Constant for Exponential, decreasing for Pareto &amp; hyperexponential and increasing for uniform.</p>
    <p>Foreground-Background (FB): The job(s) who has attained the least amount of service is served. FB is optimal with respect to the mean delay when the hazard rate is decreasing.</p>
    <p>FB might be difficult to implement. We consider the MLPS disciplines that can be thought of an approximation of FB.</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>( ) ( )</p>
    <p>( )</p>
    <p>=</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Low Priority: Connections that have already obtained threshold units of service.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!&quot;</p>
    <p>High Priority empty</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>!&quot;</p>
    <p>Low priority: Service interrupted.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An example. Let be the unfinished work truncated at x for arbitrary time t. There is a job of total length 10 and it has obtained 3 units of service. Consider we truncate at x=5, then this job contributes to the unfinished truncated work with 2 units.</p>
    <p>For age based scheduling disciplines, the expected value of the mean unfinished truncated work is</p>
    <p>For all work conserving disciplines,</p>
    <p>( ) ( )=</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>( ) ( ) ( ) =</p>
    <p>( )</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>#$     $</p>
    <p>Mean delay is given by</p>
    <p>The difference of the mean delay of two scheduling disciplines is given by</p>
    <p>[ ] ( ) ( ) ( ) ( )</p>
    <p>==</p>
    <p>[ ] [ ]</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>( ) ( ) ( )</p>
    <p>=</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>#$     $</p>
    <p>Integrating by parts, and noting that and we have</p>
    <p>If for all x0, and the hazard rate h(x) is decreasing,</p>
    <p>[ ] [ ]</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>==</p>
    <p>==</p>
    <p>[ ] [ ]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>%$   $</p>
    <p>$</p>
    <p>( )</p>
    <p>( ) ( ) ( ) ( )</p>
    <p>There exists some x*0 such that</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>x  x* ,</p>
    <p>x &gt; x* ,</p>
    <p>If 1,2 are work conserving</p>
    <p>x0,</p>
    <p>( ) ( ) ( )</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>( ) ( )=</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>&amp;'    $</p>
    <p>( !&quot;</p>
    <p>( )( ) ( ) ( ) ( )</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p>&lt; =</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p>!</p>
    <p>&quot;#</p>
    <p>&quot;#&quot;#</p>
    <p>Batch Processor-Sharing: Explicit expression for exponential file size distribution (Kleinrock et al.75, Rege and Sengupta 93).</p>
    <p>For a general distribution (Kleinrock et al. 75)</p>
    <p>( ) ( ) ( )</p>
    <p>+=</p>
    <p>&quot;#</p>
    <p>&quot;#</p>
    <p>( ) ( ) ( )</p>
    <p>+++</p>
    <p>&quot;#</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>( ) ( )</p>
    <p>( ) ( )</p>
    <p>&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;</p>
    <p>&lt;</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p>&quot;#&quot;#</p>
    <p>&quot;#&quot;#</p>
    <p>Since PS+PS is work conserving discipline , there exists</p>
    <p>For all x x*,</p>
    <p>( ) ( )</p>
    <p>&gt;=</p>
    <p>+</p>
    <p>&quot;#&quot;#&quot;#</p>
    <p>PS PS+PS(a)</p>
    <p>( ) ( )</p>
    <p>==</p>
    <p>( ) ( ) ( ) &quot;#&quot;#&quot;#</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>+</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>For all x0,</p>
    <p>If the hazard rate of the distribution function is decreasing:</p>
    <p>( )[ ] [ ]&quot;#&quot;#&quot;#  +</p>
    <p>#$   ) ( !&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;#</p>
    <p>&quot;#&quot;#</p>
    <p>+</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>#$</p>
    <p>$    *'  Let A(t) denote the number of jobs who have arrived up to time t</p>
    <p>and let Si be the service time requirement of the i-th job</p>
    <p>FB minimizes Ux(t) in sample path sense since</p>
    <p>and thus  x0</p>
    <p>( ) ( ) ( ) = =</p>
    <p>$</p>
    <p>#</p>
    <p>( ) ( ) ( )</p>
    <p>&gt; =</p>
    <p>=</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Let MLPS(a1,, aN) denote the set of MLPS disciplines with thresholds 0= a0&lt; a1 &lt;  &lt;aN &lt; aN+! =. Let n{FB,PS} denote the scheduling discipline used at level n, where n{1,,N+1}.</p>
    <p>We define the order relation between {FB,PS}:</p>
    <p>Let ,   MLPS(a1,, aN), then, we say that , if for all n{1,,N+1}.</p>
    <p>Let an-1  x  an,  if n = n,, then for all t 0 if , , then for all t 0 in particular if</p>
    <p>n =FB, then n is locally optimal, i.e.,</p>
    <p>( ) ( )    =</p>
    <p>&quot;#&quot;#&quot;#</p>
    <p>( ) ( )</p>
    <p>( ) ( )   =</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>#$</p>
    <p>Let ,   MLPS(a1,, aN), then, if and the hazard rate is decreasing</p>
    <p>In particular</p>
    <p>[ ] [ ]</p>
    <p>[ ] [ ] [ ] [ ]&quot;#&quot;#&quot;#&quot;#    ++  [ ] [ ] [ ] [ ]&quot;#&quot;#&quot;# &quot;#   ++</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>$</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>#</p>
    <p>Mean-wise and path-wise framework for comparing the mean delay of age based scheduling disciplines.</p>
    <p>Future work and open issues Generalizing the result for more than two levels. More general job arrival process. Quantitative evaluation of the reduction of the mean delay Optimal choice of the thresholds...</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
