<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Silk Server Adding missing Links while</p>
    <p>consuming Linked Data</p>
    <p>Robert Isele , Freie Universitt Berlin</p>
    <p>Anja Jentzsch, Freie Universitt Berlin</p>
    <p>Christian Bizer, Freie Universitt Berlin</p>
    <p>Proceedings Of The First International Workshop On Consuming Linked Data</p>
    <p>Shanghai, China, November 8, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A bad thing about Links</p>
    <p>The Semantic Web is a single global data space because data sources are connected by Links</p>
    <p>Many links are missing</p>
    <p>Setting links is effort for data publishers</p>
    <p>Tools enable data publishers to set links</p>
    <p>Number of linked</p>
    <p>datasets</p>
    <p>Number of</p>
    <p>datasets</p>
    <p>more than 10 28 (13.79 %)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Silk Link Discovery Framework</p>
    <p>Open source tool for discovering relationships between entities within different Linked Data sources.</p>
    <p>Main Features</p>
    <p>platforms</p>
    <p>- Reduction of network load by caching and reusing of SPARQL</p>
    <p>result sets</p>
    <p>- Multi-threaded computation of the data item comparisons</p>
    <p>- Optional blocking of data items</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Silk Versions</p>
    <p>Silk Single Machine</p>
    <p>Generate links on a single machine</p>
    <p>Local or remote data sets</p>
    <p>Silk MapReduce</p>
    <p>Generate RDF links using a cluster of multiple machines</p>
    <p>Based on Hadoop (Can be run on Amazon Elastic MapReduce)</p>
    <p>Silk Server</p>
    <p>Provides an HTTP API for matching instances from an incoming</p>
    <p>stream of RDF data while keeping track of known entities</p>
    <p>Can be used as an identity resolution component within applications</p>
    <p>that consume Linked Data from the Web</p>
    <p>Can be used for instance together with a Linked Data crawler to</p>
    <p>populate a local duplicate-free cache with data from the Web</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Link Conditions</p>
    <p>Specify which conditions two entities must fulfill in order to be interlinked.</p>
    <p>A Link Condition is expressed as a combination of:</p>
    <p>RDF paths</p>
    <p>Similar to SPARQL 1.1 Property Paths</p>
    <p>Examples:</p>
    <p>?movie/dbpedia:director/rdfs:label</p>
    <p>?person/label[@lang=en]</p>
    <p>Transformations</p>
    <p>Transforms the result set of an RDF paths</p>
    <p>Variety of built-in transformations</p>
    <p>Examples:</p>
    <p>LowerCase</p>
    <p>RegexReplace</p>
    <p>Stem</p>
    <p>Similarity Metrics</p>
    <p>Similarity of two inputs based on a userdefined metric.</p>
    <p>Examples:</p>
    <p>Various string similarity metrics</p>
    <p>Geographic similarity</p>
    <p>Date similarity</p>
    <p>Aggregations</p>
    <p>Aggregates multiple similarity metrics</p>
    <p>Examples:</p>
    <p>Min, Max, Average</p>
    <p>Quadratic Mean</p>
    <p>Geometric Mean</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Linking Persons</p>
    <p>&lt;LinkCondition&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Aggregate type=&quot;average&quot;&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Aggregate type=&quot;max&quot; required=&quot;true&quot;&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Compare metric=&quot;jaroWinkler&quot;&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;TransformInput function=&quot;lowerCase&quot;&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Input path=&quot;?a/foaf:name&quot;/&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/TransformInput&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;TransformInput function=&quot;lowerCase&quot;&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Input path=&quot;?b/foaf:name&quot;/&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/TransformInput&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/Compare&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/Aggregate&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Aggregate type=&quot;max&quot; weight=&quot;2&quot; required=&quot;true&quot;&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Compare metric=&quot;levenshtein&quot;&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Input path=&quot;?a/foaf:homepage&quot;/&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Input path=&quot;?b/foaf:homepage&quot;/&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/Compare&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Compare metric=&quot;equality&quot;&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Input path=&quot;?a/foaf:mbox_sha1sum&quot;/&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;Input path=&quot;?b/foaf:mbox_sha1sum&quot;/&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/Compare&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/Aggregate&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/Aggregate&gt;</p>
    <p>&lt;/LinkCondition&gt;</p>
    <p>Compare names</p>
    <p>using JaroWinkler Similarity</p>
    <p>Ignore character case Aggregate</p>
    <p>results</p>
    <p>Compare homepages</p>
    <p>Compare mailboxes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Linking Workflow</p>
    <p>Blocking</p>
    <p>Partitions the instances into clusters. Only instances from the same cluster will be matched.</p>
    <p>This avoids matching the complete Cartesian product.</p>
    <p>Matching</p>
    <p>Computes a similarity value for each pair of instances from the same cluster.</p>
    <p>The similarity value is based on a user-defined link condition.</p>
    <p>Filtering</p>
    <p>Removes all links with a lower confidence than the userdefined threshold</p>
    <p>Only a limited number of links from the same subject are yielded</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Evaluation</p>
    <p>Finding links between cities in a dataset consisting of 10,500 settlements from DBpedia and 59,000 cities and towns from</p>
    <p>LinkedGeoData.</p>
    <p>Silk Version Link Generation Time Number of Links</p>
    <p>Silk Single Machine1 54 hours 9283</p>
    <p>Silk MapReduce2 6.7 hours 9283</p>
    <p>Silk Version Link Generation Time Number of Links</p>
    <p>Silk Single Machine1 155.5 min 9224 (&lt; 1 % loss)</p>
    <p>Silk MapReduce2</p>
    <p>CPU Medium Instance Profile)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Silk Server</p>
    <p>Silk Single Machine and Silk MapReduce create links from static datasets.</p>
    <p>Silk Server generates links from an incoming stream of RDF data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The big picture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Silk Server Architecture</p>
    <p>Enables applications to commit newly discovered resources and receive the generated links</p>
    <p>Multiple requests can be processed in parallel</p>
    <p>REST Interface</p>
    <p>Generates the links based on a set of link specifications</p>
    <p>Silk Linking Engine</p>
    <p>Holds all known instances and keeps track of newly discovered instances.</p>
    <p>Currently held in memory, but can be replaced by a persistent cache in future versions</p>
    <p>Instance Cache</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Silk Server</p>
    <p>Setup Phase</p>
    <p>Service Phase</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Semantic Web Conference Corpus</p>
    <p>Database of persons and papers from Semantic Web conferences</p>
    <p>For some persons, it contains links to the corresponding FOAF profile</p>
    <p>Many links are missing!</p>
    <p>Solution: LDSpider + Silk to get additional Links</p>
    <p>To FOAF profiles</p>
    <p>To Twitter accounts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Setup</p>
    <p>The previously shown link condition has been used to identify duplicate person descriptions</p>
    <p>The following steps have been executed:</p>
    <p>the Server</p>
    <p>All crawled documents are forwarded to Silk Server</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Results</p>
    <p>In total, we have crawled 6730 FOAF profiles and 1160 Twitter accounts</p>
    <p>Silk Server identified the FOAF profiles of 228 persons</p>
    <p>Generated links have been evaluated</p>
    <p>Sematic Web Conference Corpus links to 56 FOAF profiles</p>
    <p>Silk Server reconstructed 51 profiles correctly</p>
    <p>For some persons, Silk Server identified multiple profiles correctly</p>
    <p>Silk Server identified the Twitter profiles of 89 persons</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Silk provides a Link Specification language which is expressive enough to cover all common use cases</p>
    <p>Silk provides a blocking feature as well as a MapReduce version to interlink big datasets.</p>
    <p>Silk Server matches instances from an incoming stream of RDF data and thus can be used as an identity resolution</p>
    <p>component within Linked Data applications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks!</p>
    <p>Get Silk from: http://www4.wiwiss.fu-berlin.de/bizer/silk</p>
    <p>This work was supported in part by Vulcan Inc. as part of its Project Halo</p>
    <p>(www.projecthalo.com) and by the EU FP7 project LOD2 - Creating Knowledge out of</p>
    <p>Interlinked Data (http://lod2.eu/, Ref. No. 257943).</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
