<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Steven Y. Ko (SUNY at Buffalo), Kyungho Jeon (SUNY at Buffalo), Ramses Morales (Xerox Research Center Webster)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What if we dont trust clouds?</p>
    <p>Or more specifically,</p>
    <p>To what extent can we utilize clouds with partial trust?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some people just dont trust.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Threats do exist.  Research: A. Armando et al. (ACM FMSE,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>However, cloud computing offers benefits.  Elasticity: dynamic scale-up and down  Pay-as-you-go: less (or no) up-front infra</p>
    <p>investment  (Arguably) better maintenance &amp;</p>
    <p>availability  Etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some people dont trust clouds, threats do exist, but there are benefits.</p>
    <p>Can we still utilize clouds without full trust? If so, to what extent?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>(Typically) forced to choose between extremes</p>
    <p>Full Trust Full Utilization</p>
    <p>No Trust No Utilization</p>
    <p>Whats in the middle???</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>HybrEx is one (or our very first) attempt.  Question: what if the only concern is</p>
    <p>confidential or private data leakage? How much can we still utilize clouds?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Partitioning &amp; info. flow tracking (tainting)</p>
    <p>Public Cloud</p>
    <p>Private Cloud</p>
    <p>HybrEx Storage</p>
    <p>HybrEx Execution Framework</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>App</p>
    <p>Disk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why?  A good start: popular, relatively easy to</p>
    <p>partition (massively-parallel)</p>
    <p>Public Cloud Private Cloud</p>
    <p>Map</p>
    <p>Reduce</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Applications  Opportunities do exist (e.g., PigLatin &amp; Hive)</p>
    <p>Declassification  how to enable private to public shuffle?  New sanitize phase</p>
    <p>Performance  wide-area MapReduce  Catch: were adding resources  Localize communication whenever possible</p>
    <p>Integrity checking  how to verify computation correctness  Random insertion of inspection points</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Please come find me for more details!</p>
    <p>Full Trust Full Utilization</p>
    <p>No Trust No Utilization</p>
    <p>Whats in the middle???</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
