<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CivitasCivitas Toward a Secure Voting SystemToward a Secure Voting System</p>
    <p>Michael Clarkson, Stephen Chong, Andrew Myers Cornell University</p>
    <p>IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy May 21, 2008</p>
    <p>Coin Crawford 413, ca. 63 B.C., commemorates secret ballot introduced 137 B.C.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas2</p>
    <p>State of Secure Electronic VotingState of Secure Electronic Voting</p>
    <p>Major commercial voting systems are insecure  California top-to-bottom reviews [Wagner,</p>
    <p>Wallach, Blaze, et al.]</p>
    <p>Much pessimism about secure voting  SERVE report [Jefferson et al.]</p>
    <p>How secure a voting system can we build?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas3</p>
    <p>CivitasCivitas</p>
    <p>Civitas: Electronic voting system we built  Publicly available  21,000 LOC (Jif, Java, and C)</p>
    <p>Started with abstract voting protocol  Extended design to improve security and</p>
    <p>performance  Implemented in security-typed language</p>
    <p>(Jif)  Evaluated security and performance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas4</p>
    <p>CaveatCaveat</p>
    <p>This work is about advancing the science  Not about selling a particular system</p>
    <p>Civitas isnt suitable for running a national election (yet)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas5</p>
    <p>Civitas Security Requirements</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas6</p>
    <p>Security ModelSecurity Model</p>
    <p>No trusted supervision of polling places  Including voters, procedures, hardware, software  Voting could take place anywhere  Thus, remote voting</p>
    <p>Generalization of Internet voting and postal voting</p>
    <p>Interesting problem to solve:  More general than supervised voting  Trusted supervision is the source of many</p>
    <p>vulnerabilities  Trend toward remote interactions</p>
    <p>Public elections (absentee ballots, Oregon, Washington, Estonia)</p>
    <p>Organizational elections (Debian, ACM, IEEEall on Internet)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas7</p>
    <p>Security ModelSecurity Model</p>
    <p>Adversary  May corrupt all but one of each type of election</p>
    <p>authority  Agents who conduct the election</p>
    <p>May coerce voters, demanding secrets or behavior, remotely or physically</p>
    <p>But voter isnt under constant surveillance  May control network</p>
    <p>With one exception during registration  May perform any polynomial time computation</p>
    <p>Security properties  Strong, in tension  Confidentiality, integrity, availability</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas8</p>
    <p>IntegrityIntegrity</p>
    <p>Verifiability:</p>
    <p>Including:  Voter verifiability: Voters can check</p>
    <p>that their own vote is included  Universal verifiability: Anyone can</p>
    <p>check that only authorized votes are counted, no votes are changed during tallying [Sako and Killian 1995]</p>
    <p>The final tally is correct and verifiable.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas9</p>
    <p>ConfidentialityConfidentiality</p>
    <p>Voter coercion  Employer, spouse, etc.  Coercer can demand any behavior</p>
    <p>Particular vote, random vote, abstain  Generalizes vote buying</p>
    <p>Coercer can observe and interact with voter during remote voting</p>
    <p>Must prevent coercers from trusting their own observations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas1 0</p>
    <p>ConfidentialityConfidentiality</p>
    <p>Stronger than receipt-freeness, which is stronger than anonymity  [Delaune, Kremer, and Ryan]  Which are too weak for remote voting</p>
    <p>The adversary cannot learn how voters vote, even if voters collude and interact</p>
    <p>with the adversary.</p>
    <p>Coercion resistance:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas1 1</p>
    <p>AvailabilityAvailability</p>
    <p>We assume that this holds  To guarantee, would need to make system</p>
    <p>components highly available  Use reliable systems techniques</p>
    <p>Byzantine fault tolerance, threshold cryptography  Civitas designed, but not implemented, with this in mind</p>
    <p>We do not assume that votes remain available</p>
    <p>The final tally of the election is produced.</p>
    <p>Tally availability:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas1 2</p>
    <p>Civitas Voting Scheme</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas1 3</p>
    <p>JCJ SchemeJCJ Scheme</p>
    <p>Civitas is based on JCJ scheme  [Juels, Catalano, and Jakobsson, WPES 2005]</p>
    <p>JCJ:  Formally defined coercion resistance and</p>
    <p>verifiability  Constructed voting scheme</p>
    <p>Not implemented</p>
    <p>Proved scheme satisfies coercion resistance and verifiability</p>
    <p>I wont discuss why it works in this talk</p>
    <p>Verified in ProVerif [Backes, Hritcu, and Maffei, CSF 2008]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas1 4</p>
    <p>JCJ Protocol ArchitectureJCJ Protocol Architecture</p>
    <p>bulletin board</p>
    <p>voter client</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>registrar</p>
    <p>Issue credentials</p>
    <p>Tabulate, using mix network</p>
    <p>Verifiability: Tellers post zeroknowledge proofs during tabulation</p>
    <p>Coercion resistance:</p>
    <p>Voters can undetectably fake</p>
    <p>credentials</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas1 5</p>
    <p>Problem #1Problem #1</p>
    <p>bulletin board</p>
    <p>voter client</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>registrar</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas1 6</p>
    <p>Problem #1: Trusted RegistrarProblem #1: Trusted Registrar</p>
    <p>JCJ: Trusts single agent to issue credentials to voters  Could violate coercion resistance  Could vote on behalf of voters</p>
    <p>Civitas: Distributes trust over set of registration tellers  We extended JCJ security proof to prove</p>
    <p>Civitas is still coercion resistant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas1 7</p>
    <p>Distributed RegistrarDistributed Registrar</p>
    <p>bulletin board</p>
    <p>voter client</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas1 8</p>
    <p>Civitas Registration ProtocolCivitas Registration Protocol</p>
    <p>voter client</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
    <p>credential share</p>
    <p>credential</p>
    <p>also: designated-verifier ZK proof to convince voter</p>
    <p>without allowing transfer of credential</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas1 9</p>
    <p>Problem #2Problem #2</p>
    <p>bulletin board</p>
    <p>voter client</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas2 0</p>
    <p>Problem #2: Vote StorageProblem #2: Vote Storage</p>
    <p>JCJ: Trusts single bulletin board to store all the votes  Could lose votes</p>
    <p>Unavailable votes not universally verifiable  So implement with BFT?</p>
    <p>Could scale poorly</p>
    <p>Civitas: Distributes vote storage over set of ballot boxes</p>
    <p>Votes are available for tabulation.</p>
    <p>Vote availability:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas2 1</p>
    <p>Distributed Vote StorageDistributed Vote Storage</p>
    <p>bulletin board</p>
    <p>voter client</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
    <p>ballot box ballot box ballot box</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas2 2</p>
    <p>Civitas Vote Storage ProtocolCivitas Vote Storage Protocol</p>
    <p>voter client</p>
    <p>ballot box</p>
    <p>ballot box</p>
    <p>ballot box tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>Transmit all votes</p>
    <p>using simple commitment</p>
    <p>protocol</p>
    <p>Win: Vote availability, scales easily</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas2 3</p>
    <p>Problem #3Problem #3</p>
    <p>bulletin board</p>
    <p>voter client</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>tabulation teller</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
    <p>registration teller</p>
    <p>ballot box ballot box ballot box</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas2 4</p>
    <p>Problem #3: Tabulation ScalabilityProblem #3: Tabulation Scalability</p>
    <p>JCJ: Tabulation protocol is quadratic in number of voters</p>
    <p>Civitas: Divide voters into blocks  Block is a virtual precinct</p>
    <p>Each voter assigned to one block  Each block tallied independently of other</p>
    <p>blocks, even in parallel</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas2 5</p>
    <p>BlocksBlocks</p>
    <p>Tabulation time is:</p>
    <p>Quadratic in block size</p>
    <p>Linear in number of voters  If using one set of machines for many blocks</p>
    <p>Or, constant in number of voters  If using one set of machines per block</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas2 6</p>
    <p>BlocksBlocks</p>
    <p>Coercion resistance  Voters no longer anonymous within whole</p>
    <p>population  But still anonymous within block  Also true in real precincts</p>
    <p>Assignment to blocks  Based on physical location</p>
    <p>Leads to risk of reprisal, as in real precincts</p>
    <p>Based on random assignment  Mitigates risk  Made possible by remote voting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas2 7</p>
    <p>Civitas Implementation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas2 8</p>
    <p>ProtocolsProtocols</p>
    <p>JCJ: Un- or partially-specified  Implementation requires concrete</p>
    <p>protocols</p>
    <p>Civitas: Full protocol details, and code  Uses many protocols from the literature:</p>
    <p>El Gamal; distributed [Brandt]; non-malleable [Schnorr and Jakobsson]  Proof of knowledge of discrete log [Schnorr]  Proof of equality of discrete logarithms [Chaum &amp; Pederson]  Authentication and key establishment [Needham-Schroeder-Lowe]  Designated-verifier reencryption proof [Hirt &amp; Sako]  1-out-of-L reencryption proof [Hirt &amp; Sako]  Signature of knowledge of discrete logarithms [Camenisch &amp; Stadler]  Reencryption mix network with randomized partial checking [Jakobsson, Juels &amp; Rivest]  Plaintext equivalence test [Jakobsson &amp; Juels]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas2 9</p>
    <p>Secure ImplementationSecure Implementation</p>
    <p>Civitas implemented in Jif Java + Information Flow [Myers 1999, Chong and Myers 2005, 2008]</p>
    <p>Security-typed language  Types contain information-flow policies</p>
    <p>Policies express confidentiality and integrity requirements on information</p>
    <p>Jif compiler and runtime enforce policies</p>
    <p>If policies in code express correct requirements  (And Jif compiler is correct)  Then code is secure w.r.t. requirements</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas3 0</p>
    <p>Civitas Policy ExamplesCivitas Policy Examples</p>
    <p>Confidentiality:  Information: Voters credential share  Policy: RT permits only this voter to learn this</p>
    <p>information  Jif syntax: RT  Voter</p>
    <p>Confidentiality:  Information: Tellers private key  Policy: TT permits no one else to learn this information  Jif syntax: TT  TT</p>
    <p>Integrity:  Information: Random nonces used by tellers  Policy: TT permits only itself to influence this information  Jif syntax: TT  TT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas3 1</p>
    <p>Civitas Policy ExamplesCivitas Policy Examples</p>
    <p>Declassification:  Information: Bits that are committed to then</p>
    <p>revealed  Policy: TT permits no one to read this information</p>
    <p>until all commitments become available, then TT declassifies it to allow everyone to read.</p>
    <p>Jif syntax: TT  [TT commAvail  ]</p>
    <p>Erasure:  Information: Voters credential shares  Policy: Voter requires, after all shares are</p>
    <p>received and full credential is constructed, that shares must be erased.</p>
    <p>Jif syntax: Voter  [Voter credConst T ]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas3 2</p>
    <p>Civitas LOCCivitas LOC</p>
    <p>Component Approx. LOC</p>
    <p>Tabulation teller 5,700</p>
    <p>Registration teller 1,300</p>
    <p>Bulletin board, ballot box</p>
    <p>Voter client 800</p>
    <p>Other (incl. common code)</p>
    <p>Total Jif LOC 13,400</p>
    <p>Low-level crypto and I/O (Java and C)</p>
    <p>Total LOC 21,400</p>
    <p>Policy Distin ct</p>
    <p>annot a</p>
    <p>tions</p>
    <p>Confidentiality 20</p>
    <p>Integrity 26</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas3 3</p>
    <p>Evaluation: Civitas Security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas3 4</p>
    <p>Civitas Trust AssumptionsCivitas Trust Assumptions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas3 5</p>
    <p>Civitas Trust AssumptionsCivitas Trust Assumptions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas3 6</p>
    <p>Registration Trust AssumptionsRegistration Trust Assumptions</p>
    <p>One way to discharge is with in-person registration  Not an absolute requirement</p>
    <p>Though for strong authentication, physical presence (something you are) is reasonable</p>
    <p>Need not register in-person with all tellers</p>
    <p>Works like real-world voting today:  Registration teller trusted to correctly authenticate voter  Issue of credential must happen in trusted registration booth  But doesnt need to happen on special day</p>
    <p>Con: System not fully remote  Pro: Credential can be used remotely for many</p>
    <p>elections</p>
    <p>Insight: Reusing real-world mechanism, can bootstrap into a system offering stronger security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas3 7</p>
    <p>Civitas Trust AssumptionsCivitas Trust Assumptions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas3 8</p>
    <p>Voting Client Trust AssumptionVoting Client Trust Assumption</p>
    <p>Civitas voting client is not a DRE  Voters are not required to trust a single</p>
    <p>(closed-source) implementation  Civitas allows open-source</p>
    <p>(re)implementations of the client  Voters can obtain or travel to</p>
    <p>implementation provided by organization they trust</p>
    <p>Possibility to discharge:  Distribute trust in client</p>
    <p>[Benaloh, Chaum, Joaquim and Ribeiro, Kutyowski et al., Zquete et al., ]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas3 9</p>
    <p>Evaluation: Civitas Cost and Performance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas4 0</p>
    <p>Real-World CostReal-World Cost</p>
    <p>Society makes a tradeoff on  Cost of election, vs.  Security, usability,</p>
    <p>Current total costs are $1-$3 / voter [International Foundation for Election Systems]</p>
    <p>We dont know the total cost for Civitas  But with our implementation, we can</p>
    <p>investigate one piece:  Computational cost of employing cryptography</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas4 1</p>
    <p>Tabulation Time vs. AnonymityTabulation Time vs. Anonymity</p>
    <p># voters = K, # tab. tellers = 4, security strength  112 bits [NIST 20112030]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas4 2</p>
    <p>Tabulation Time vs. # VotersTabulation Time vs. # Voters</p>
    <p>K = 100</p>
    <p>sequential</p>
    <p>parallel</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas4 3</p>
    <p>CPU Cost for TabulationCPU Cost for Tabulation</p>
    <p>CPU time is 39 sec / voter / authority  If CPUs are bought, used (for 5 hours),</p>
    <p>then thrown away:  $1500 / machine = $12 / voter</p>
    <p>If CPUs are rented:  $1 / CPU / hr = 4 / voter</p>
    <p>For this extra cost, we get increased security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas4 4</p>
    <p>Ranked Voting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas4 5</p>
    <p>Ranked Voting MethodsRanked Voting Methods</p>
    <p>Voters submit ranking of candidates  E.g. Condorcet, Borda, STV  Help avoid spoiler effects  Defend against strategic voting</p>
    <p>Tricky because rankings can be used to signal identity (Italian attack)</p>
    <p>Civitas implements coercion-resistant Condorcet, approval and plurality voting methods  Could do any summable method  New construction [in TR] for efficient Condorcet</p>
    <p>tabulation  Based on homomorphic encryption</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas4 6</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas4 7</p>
    <p>SummarySummary</p>
    <p>Civitas is an implemented remote voting system</p>
    <p>Civitas contributes to:  Protocols (theory of voting):</p>
    <p>Distributed trust in registration for confidentiality  Distributed vote storage for availability  Introduced blocks (virtual precincts) for scalability  Articulated and analyzed trust assumptions  Efficient coercion-resistant Condorcet voting</p>
    <p>Systems (practice of voting):  Developed full protocols  Implemented system  Studied performance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas4 8</p>
    <p>Related WorkRelated Work</p>
    <p>Abstract voting schemes: [Adida and Rivest; Baudron et al.; Benaloh; Benaloh and Tuinstra; Boyd; Chaum; Chaum, Ryan, and Schneider Chen and Burminster; Cohen and Fischer; Cramer, Gennaro, and Schoenmakers; Fujioka, Okamoto, and Ohta; Hirt and Sako; Iversen; Kiayias and Yung; Magkos et al.; Merrit; Neff; Niemi and Renvall; Sako and Killian; Ohkubo et al.; Ohta; Okamoto; Park et al.; Rivest]</p>
    <p>Implemented voting systems:  Adder [Kiayias, Korman, Walluck]  ElectMe [Shubina and Smith]  EVOX [Herschberg, DuRette]  Prt  Voter [Schneider, Heather, et al.; Ryan; Chaum]  Punchscan [Stanton, Essex, Popoveniuc, et al.; Chaum]  REVS [Joaquim, Zquette, Ferreira; Lebre]  Sensus [Cranor and Cytron]  VoteHere [Neff]  W-Voting [Kutyowski, Zagrski, et al.]  Civitas: Strongest coercion resistance, first to offer</p>
    <p>security proofs plus information-flow analysis</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas4 9</p>
    <p>Web SiteWeb Site</p>
    <p>http://www.cs.cornell.edu/projects/civitas</p>
    <p>Technical report with concrete protocols</p>
    <p>Source code of our prototype</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CivitasCivitas Toward a Secure Voting SystemToward a Secure Voting System</p>
    <p>http://www.cs.cornell.edu/projects/civitas</p>
    <p>Michael Clarkson, Stephen Chong, Andrew Myers Cornell University</p>
    <p>Coin Crawford 413, ca. 63 B.C., commemorates secret ballot introduced 137 B.C.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas5 1</p>
    <p>Extra SlidesExtra Slides</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas5 2</p>
    <p>Unresolved IssuesUnresolved Issues</p>
    <p>Distribute trust in voter client  Eliminate in-person registration</p>
    <p>Still need untappable channel</p>
    <p>Study credential management  UI for faking</p>
    <p>Implement high availability  App-level DOS is a problem.</p>
    <p>Improve performance/anonymity trade-off  Replace plaintext equivalence tests with</p>
    <p>group signatures? [Traore and Araujo 2007]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas5 3</p>
    <p>PaperPaper</p>
    <p>What paper does:  Convince voter that his vote was captured</p>
    <p>correctly  What paper does next:</p>
    <p>Gets dropped in a ballot box  Immediately becomes insecure</p>
    <p>Chain-of-custody, stuffing, loss, recount attacks  Hacking paper elections has a long and (in)glorious</p>
    <p>tradition [Steal this Vote, Andrew Gumbel, 2005]  20% of paper trails are missing or illegible [Michael</p>
    <p>Shamos, 2008]</p>
    <p>What paper doesnt:  Guarantee that a vote will be counted  Guarantee that a vote will be counted correctly</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas5 4</p>
    <p>CryptographyCryptography</p>
    <p>The public wont trust cryptography.  It already does  Because experts already do</p>
    <p>I dont trust cryptography.  You dont trust the proofs, or  You reject the hardness assumptions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas5 5</p>
    <p>Resisting CoercionResisting Coercion</p>
    <p>Key idea:</p>
    <p>Voters invent fake credentials</p>
    <p>To adversary, fake  real</p>
    <p>Votes with fake credentials are removed during tabulation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas5 6</p>
    <p>Resisting CoercionResisting Coercion</p>
    <p>If the adversary demands that the voter</p>
    <p>Then the voter</p>
    <p>Submits a particular vote Does so with a fake credential.</p>
    <p>Sells or surrenders a credential</p>
    <p>Supplies a fake credential.</p>
    <p>Abstains Supplies a fake credential to the adversary and votes with a real one.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clarkson: Civitas5 7</p>
    <p>Selling VotesSelling Votes</p>
    <p>Requires selling credential  Which requires:</p>
    <p>Adversary tapped the untappable channel, or</p>
    <p>Adversary authenticated in place of voter</p>
    <p>Which requires: Voter transferred ability to authenticate to</p>
    <p>adversary; something voter  Has: too easy  Knows: need incentive not to transfer  Is: hardest to transfer</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
