<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Power and Bandwidth Allocation in Cooperative Dirty Paper Coding</p>
    <p>Chris T. K. Ng1, Nihar Jindal2</p>
    <p>Andrea J. Goldsmith3, Urbashi Mitra4</p>
    <p>ICC May 21, 2008. Beijing, China</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Wireless ad hoc network: nodes may cooperate by joint encoding or processing.</p>
    <p>Cooperation consumes power and bandwidth.</p>
    <p>Benefits of cooperation: Need to optimize resource allocation.</p>
    <p>Two cooperating transmitters: Orthogonal cooperation channel. Exchange messages, then perform dirty paper coding (DPC). Interference channel (in the absence of the cooperation channel). Investigate power and bandwidth allocation to characterize the cooperative DPC rate region.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dirty Paper Coding (DPC)</p>
    <p>Gaussian channel Transmitter has power P, unit-variance Gaussian noise N. Without interference S, capacity =  log (1+P).</p>
    <p>Dirty paper coding (DPC) [Costa 83] Interference non-causally known to the transmitter. Capacity =  log (1+P), same as if no interference. Codewords orthogonal to S, instead of attempting to cancel the interference.</p>
    <p>X Y++</p>
    <p>S N</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Works</p>
    <p>Achievable rate regions Two cooperative transmitters and one receiver [Sendonaris et al. 03, Yazdi et al. 03].</p>
    <p>Cooperative diversity Forward parity bits [Hunter et al. 03] Orthogonal protocols achieve full spatial diversity [Laneman et al. 04].</p>
    <p>Information theoretical bounds Multiplexing gain, diversity [Host-Madsen et al. 05, 06]. Achievable rates and capacity upper bounds [Khojastepour et al. 04, Jindal et al. 04]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Channel Model</p>
    <p>Two cooperating transmitters Close together (G is large). Cooperation channel: Orthogonal, static, full-duplex additive white Gaussian noise (AWGN).</p>
    <p>Channel state information (CSI) h1,, h4 known at all terminals. 5</p>
    <p>R1</p>
    <p>R2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Channel Model: Power and Bandwidth</p>
    <p>System-wide cost of cooperation: Network power constraint : P1 + P2 + Pt  P (short-term).</p>
    <p>Bandwidth assumptions: 1) Separate bands: B = Bt = 1 (spatial reuse). 2) Bandwidth allocation: B + Bt = 1 (no reuse).</p>
    <p>R1</p>
    <p>R2</p>
    <p>P1</p>
    <p>P2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cooperative Dirty Paper Coding (DPC)</p>
    <p>Transmitter exchange messages through cooperation channel.</p>
    <p>Network becomes equivalent to a broadcast channel (BC) with a two-antenna transmitter.</p>
    <p>Transmitters jointly encode using dirty paper coding. Capacity-achieving for multi-antenna BC [Weingarten 04].</p>
    <p>Cooperative DPC rate region: Convex hull of rates (R1,R2) achievable by cooperative DPC. Optimize power and bandwidth allocation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Duality: Broadcast Channel and Multiple Access Channel</p>
    <p>Gaussian BC: Dual MAC: reverse channel inputs and outputs [Jindal et al. 04, Vishwanath et al. 03].</p>
    <p>For every (R1,R2) in BC region under power constraint P: Dual MAC achieves same (R1,R2) with a suitable power allocation P1, P2 such that P1 + P2 = P. Allocation of P1, P2 in MAC is convex; can be calculated efficiently.</p>
    <p>Broadcast Channel (BC) Dual Multiple Access Channel (MAC)</p>
    <p>(R1,R2) (R1,R2)</p>
    <p>P P1 + P2 = P</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimal MAC Sum Power Allocation</p>
    <p>Multiple access channel: Two single-antenna transmitters and a two-antenna receiver, sum power constraint : P1 + P2  Ps .</p>
    <p>Capacity region:</p>
    <p>(R1,R2) on capacity region boundary: Concave in P1, P2. Found by applying Karush-Kuhn-Tucker (KKT) conditions on the Lagrangian.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MAC Decode Order</p>
    <p>Dual MAC capacity region corner points Achieved by different decoder orders.</p>
    <p>BC capacity region has three segments; from dual MAC: Decode order (1) Decode order (2) Time sharing</p>
    <p>R1</p>
    <p>R2</p>
    <p>(1) : Tx 2, Tx 1</p>
    <p>(2) : Tx 1, Tx 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cooperative DPC Rates</p>
    <p>Transmitters need to know each others codewords. Cooperation channel (with power Pt) rates  DPC rates.</p>
    <p>Duality: Cooperation channel:</p>
    <p>Capacity of an AWGN channel:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Numerical Allocation of Power and Bandwidth</p>
    <p>Rates monotonically increasing with power P and bandwidth B.</p>
    <p>Reject (R1,R2) in the interior of CBC or Cco. Numerically compute the intersection of boundaries of Cco and CBC (three segments).</p>
    <p>Bandwidth assumption 1) Bt = B = 1 One-dimensional numerical optimization to find Pt .</p>
    <p>Bandwidth assumption 2) Bt + B = 1 Local optimum: numerically search over Pt and Bt. Conjecture: DPC rates concave over Pt and Bt. Convexity not readily verified as objective function is numerically computed.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Numerical Results</p>
    <p>Channels h1,, h4: independent Rayleigh fading. Ergodic rate region:</p>
    <p>Network power constraint P = 10 dB.</p>
    <p>Cooperation channel: Weak: G = 0 dB Strong: G = 10 dB</p>
    <p>Comparisons: BC (transmitters co-located, G = ). Non-cooperation: time-division (TD) between transmitters.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cooperative DPC Rate Regions</p>
    <p>Cooperation better than TD only when G is large. Cooperation more advantageous at sum-rate. Separate cooperation bands: close to BC when G is large. Equal bandwidths Bt = B = 0.5 close to optimal allocation.</p>
    <p>G = 0 dB G = 10 dB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Two cooperating transmitters: Exchange messages over orthogonal cooperation channel. Cooperative dirty paper coding.</p>
    <p>Power and bandwidth allocation. Optimal sum power allocation in multi-antenna MAC. BC-MAC capacity duality.</p>
    <p>Cooperative DPC improves capacity when cooperation channel is strong.</p>
    <p>Cooperative DPC offers better performance near sum-rate.</p>
    <p>Only considered transmitter cooperation. Further gains may be obtained if receivers as well as transmitters cooperate.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
