<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>School of Computer Science Carnegie Mellon University</p>
    <p>The dynamics of viral marketing</p>
    <p>Jure Leskovec, Carnegie Mellon University</p>
    <p>Lada Adamic, University of Michigan</p>
    <p>Bernardo Huberman, HP Labs</p>
    <p>School of Information</p>
    <p>University of Michigan</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Using online networks for viral marketing</p>
    <p>Burger Kings subservient chicken</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  prior work on viral marketing &amp; information diffusion  incentivised viral marketing program  cascades and stars  network effects  product and social network characteristics</p>
    <p>The dynamics of Viral Marketing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Information diffusion</p>
    <p>Studies of innovation adoption  hybrid corn (Ryan and Gross, 1943)  prescription drugs (Coleman et al. 1957)</p>
    <p>Models (very many)  Rogers, Diffusion of Innovations  Watts, Information cascades, 2002</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation for viral marketing</p>
    <p>viral marketing successfully utilizes social networks for adoption of some services  hotmail gains 18 million users in 12 months,</p>
    <p>spending only $50,000 on traditional advertising  gmail rapidly gains users although referrals are the only way to</p>
    <p>sign up</p>
    <p>customers becoming less susceptible to mass marketing</p>
    <p>mass marketing impractical for unprecedented variety of products online  Google AdSense helps sellers reach buyers with targeted</p>
    <p>advertising  but how do buyers get good recommendations?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The web savvy consumer and personalized recommendations</p>
    <p>&gt; 50% of people do research online before purchasing electronics</p>
    <p>personalized recommendations based on prior purchase patterns and ratings  Amazon, people who bought x also bought y  MovieLens, based on ratings of users like you</p>
    <p>Is there still room for viral marketing?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Is there still room for viral marketing next to personalized recommendations?</p>
    <p>We are more influenced by our friends than strangers</p>
    <p>68% of consumers consult friends and family before purchasing home electronics (Burke 2003)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Incentivised viral marketing (our problem setting)</p>
    <p>Senders and followers of recommendations receive discounts on products</p>
    <p>Recommendations are made to any number of people at the time of purchase</p>
    <p>Only the recipient who buys first gets a discount</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Product recommendation network</p>
    <p>purchase following a recommendation</p>
    <p>customer recommending a product</p>
    <p>customer not buying a recommended product</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>the data</p>
    <p>large anonymous online retailer (June 2001 to May 2003)</p>
    <p>15,646,121 recommendations  3,943,084 distinct customers  548,523 products recommended  Products belonging to 4 product groups:</p>
    <p>books  DVDs  music  VHS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>summary statistics by product group</p>
    <p>products customers recommendations</p>
    <p>edges buy + get discount</p>
    <p>buy + no discount</p>
    <p>Book 103,161 2,863,977 5,741,611 2,097,809 65,344 17,769</p>
    <p>DVD 19,829 805,285 8,180,393 962,341 17,232 58,189</p>
    <p>Music 393,598 794,148 1,443,847 585,738 7,837 2,739</p>
    <p>Video 26,131 239,583 280,270 160,683 909 467</p>
    <p>Full 542,719 3,943,084 15,646,121 3,153,676 91,322 79,164</p>
    <p>high</p>
    <p>low</p>
    <p>people recommendations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>viral marketing program not spreading virally</p>
    <p>94% of users make first recommendation without having received one previously</p>
    <p>size of giant connected component increases from 1% to 2.5% of the network (100,420 users)  small!</p>
    <p>some sub-communities are better connected  24% out of 18,000 users for westerns on DVD  26% of 25,000 for classics on DVD  19% of 47,000 for anime (Japanese animated film) on DVD</p>
    <p>others are just as disconnected  3% of 180,000 home and gardening  2-7% for childrens and fitness DVDs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>medical study guide recommendation network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>measuring cascade sizes</p>
    <p>delete late recommendations  count how many people are in a single cascade  exclude nodes that did not buy</p>
    <p>steep drop-off</p>
    <p>very few large cascades</p>
    <p>books</p>
    <p>= 1.8e6 x-4.98</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>cascades for DVDs</p>
    <p>shallow drop off  fat tail</p>
    <p>a number of large cascades</p>
    <p>DVD cascades can grow large  possibly as a result of websites where people sign up to</p>
    <p>exchange recommendations</p>
    <p>~ x-1.56</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>simple model of propagating recommendations (ignoring for the moment the specific mechanics of the recommendation</p>
    <p>program of the retailer)</p>
    <p>Each individual will have pt successful recommendations. We model pt as a random variable.</p>
    <p>At time t+1, the total number of people in the cascade,</p>
    <p>Nt+1 = Nt * (1+pt)</p>
    <p>Subtracting from both sides, and dividing by Nt, we have</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>simple model of propagating recommendations (continued)</p>
    <p>Summing over long time periods</p>
    <p>The right hand side is a sum of random variables and hence normally distributed.</p>
    <p>Integrating both sides, we find that N is lognormally distributed</p>
    <p>if  large resembles power-law</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>participation level by individual</p>
    <p>Number of recommendations</p>
    <p>C o</p>
    <p>un t</p>
    <p>= 3.4e6 x-2.30 R2=0.96</p>
    <p>very high variance</p>
    <p>The most active person made 83,729 recommendations</p>
    <p>and purchased 4,416 different items!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network effects</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>does receiving more recommendations increase the likelihood of buying?</p>
    <p>BOOKS DVDs</p>
    <p>Incoming Recommendations</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>ba bi</p>
    <p>lit y</p>
    <p>of B</p>
    <p>uy in</p>
    <p>g</p>
    <p>Incoming Recommendations</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>ba bi</p>
    <p>lit y</p>
    <p>of B</p>
    <p>uy in</p>
    <p>g</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>does sending more recommendations influence more purchases?</p>
    <p>Outgoing Recommendations</p>
    <p>N um</p>
    <p>be r</p>
    <p>of P</p>
    <p>ur ch</p>
    <p>a se</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Outgoing Recommendations</p>
    <p>N um</p>
    <p>be r</p>
    <p>of P</p>
    <p>ur ch</p>
    <p>as es</p>
    <p>BOOKS DVDs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>the probability that the sender gets a credit with increasing numbers of recommendations</p>
    <p>consider whether sender has at least one successful recommendation</p>
    <p>controls for sender getting credit for purchase that resulted from others recommending the same product to the same person</p>
    <p>Outgoing Recommendations</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>ba bi</p>
    <p>lit y</p>
    <p>of C</p>
    <p>re di</p>
    <p>t probability of receiving a credit levels off for DVDs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multiple recommendations between two individuals weaken the impact of the bond on purchases</p>
    <p>-3</p>
    <p>Exchanged recommendations</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>ba bi</p>
    <p>lit y</p>
    <p>of b</p>
    <p>uy in</p>
    <p>g</p>
    <p>Exchanged recommendations</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>ba bi</p>
    <p>lit y</p>
    <p>o f b</p>
    <p>u yi</p>
    <p>ng</p>
    <p>BOOKS DVDs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>product and social network characteristics influencing</p>
    <p>recommendation effectiveness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>recommendation success by book category</p>
    <p>consider successful recommendations in terms of  av. # senders of recommendations per book category  av. # of recommendations accepted</p>
    <p>books overall have a 3% success rate  (2% with discount, 1% without)</p>
    <p>lower than average success rate (significant at p=0.01 level)  fiction</p>
    <p>romance (1.78), horror (1.81)  teen (1.94), childrens books (2.06)  comics (2.30), sci-fi (2.34), mystery and thrillers (2.40)</p>
    <p>nonfiction  sports (2.26)  home &amp; garden (2.26)  travel (2.39)</p>
    <p>higher than average success rate (statistically significant)  professional &amp; technical</p>
    <p>medicine (5.68)  professional &amp; technical (4.54)  engineering (4.10), science (3.90), computers &amp; internet (3.61)  law (3.66), business &amp; investing (3.62)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>anime DVDs</p>
    <p>47,000 customers responsible for the 2.5 out of 16 million recommendations in the system</p>
    <p>29% success rate per recommender of an anime DVD</p>
    <p>giant component covers 19% of the nodes</p>
    <p>Overall, recommendations for DVDs are more likely to result in a purchase (7%), but the anime community stands out</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>regressing on product characteristics</p>
    <p>Variable transformation Coefficient</p>
    <p>const -0.940 ***</p>
    <p># recommendations ln(r) 0.426 ***</p>
    <p># senders ln(ns) -0.782 ***</p>
    <p># recipients ln(nr) -1.307 ***</p>
    <p>product price ln(p) 0.128 ***</p>
    <p># reviews ln(v) -0.011 ***</p>
    <p>avg. rating ln(t) -0.027 *</p>
    <p>R2 0.74</p>
    <p>significance at the 0.01 (***), 0.05 (**) and 0.1 (*) levels</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>products most suited to viral marketing</p>
    <p>small and tightly knit community  few reviews, senders, and recipients  but sending more recommendations helps</p>
    <p>pricey products</p>
    <p>rating doesnt play as much of a role</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Overall  incentivized viral marketing contributes marginally to</p>
    <p>total sales  occasionally large cascades occur</p>
    <p>Observations for future diffusion models  purchase decision more complex than threshold or</p>
    <p>simple infection  influence saturates as the number of contacts expands  links user effectiveness if they are overused</p>
    <p>Conditions for successful recommendations  professional and organizational contexts  discounts on expensive items  small, tightly knit communities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>For more information</p>
    <p>the paper:  http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~jure/pubs/viral-market.pdf</p>
    <p>my publications:  http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~jure/pubs/</p>
    <p>Ladas publications:  http://www-personal.umich.edu/~ladamic</p>
    <p>Bernardo Hubermans Information Dynamics Lab at HP:  http://www.hpl.hp.com/research/idl</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extras</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>pay it forward</p>
    <p>product category number of buy bits forward recommendations</p>
    <p>percent</p>
    <p>Book 65,391 15,769 24.2</p>
    <p>DVD 16,459 7,336 44.6</p>
    <p>Music 7,843 1,824 23.3</p>
    <p>Video 909 250 27.6</p>
    <p>Total 90,602 25,179 27.8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hour of the Day</p>
    <p>R ec</p>
    <p>om m</p>
    <p>en dt</p>
    <p>io ns</p>
    <p>when recommendations are sent</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>when purchases are made</p>
    <p>Hour of the Day</p>
    <p>A ll</p>
    <p>P u</p>
    <p>rc ha</p>
    <p>se s</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>when discounts are to be had</p>
    <p>Hour of the Day</p>
    <p>D is</p>
    <p>co un</p>
    <p>te d</p>
    <p>P ur</p>
    <p>ch as</p>
    <p>es</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>lag between time of recommendation and time of purchase</p>
    <p>Lag [day]</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>p o rt</p>
    <p>io n</p>
    <p>of P</p>
    <p>u rc</p>
    <p>h a se</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Lag [hours]</p>
    <p>C o u nt</p>
    <p>Lag [day]</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>po rt</p>
    <p>io n o</p>
    <p>f P u rc</p>
    <p>h as</p>
    <p>es</p>
    <p>Lag [hours]</p>
    <p>C ou</p>
    <p>nt Book DVD</p>
    <p>but &gt; 15% wait more than a week</p>
    <p>daily periodicity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>observations</p>
    <p>purchases and recommendations follow a daily cycle</p>
    <p>customers are most likely to purchase within a day of receiving a recommendation</p>
    <p>acting on a recommendation at atypical times increases the likelihood of receiving a discount</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
