<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Leakage in Mobile Online Social Networks</p>
    <p>Balachander Krishnamurthy, AT&amp;T Labs  Research</p>
    <p>Craig E. Wills, Worcester Polytechnic Institute</p>
    <p>Workshop on Online Social Networks</p>
    <p>Boston, MA USA</p>
    <p>June 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Previously studied the leakage of personally identifiable information via</p>
    <p>Online Social Networks (OSNs) to third-party aggregators.</p>
    <p>Trend towards use of mobile devices to access OSNs (Facebook reports</p>
    <p>Also development of new OSNsmobile OSNs (mOSNs)that</p>
    <p>primarily cater to mobile users. Examples include Brightkite,</p>
    <p>Foursquare, Gowalla, Loopt, Urbanspoon, Whrrl.</p>
    <p>Mobile access to Web sites designed specifically for mobile devices and</p>
    <p>through the development of apps that are specific to a site and to a</p>
    <p>mobile platform.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>New Privacy Concerns</p>
    <p>Mobile devices potentially introduce new privacy concerns for mOSNs.</p>
    <p>These include:</p>
    <p>user presence and geographic location</p>
    <p>information shared with a mOSN connected to a traditional OSN is</p>
    <p>also shared with that OSN</p>
    <p>unique device identifiers</p>
    <p>Examine the degree to which leakage of private information is</p>
    <p>occurring via mOSNs.</p>
    <p>Related work by Chen&amp;Rahman08 on analyzing privacy designs of</p>
    <p>social networking apps focusing on location.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interfaces and Interconnections for mOSNs</p>
    <p>Mobile Apps</p>
    <p>Mobile OSN 1 Mobile OSN 2</p>
    <p>Server Server 3rdParty 3rdParty</p>
    <p>Server Server</p>
    <p>Providing API OSN</p>
    <p>Connect</p>
    <p>API Connect API Connect</p>
    <p>Mobile Browser</p>
    <p>Mobile Web Site</p>
    <p>Mobile Browser</p>
    <p>Traditional Browser</p>
    <p>Full Web Site</p>
    <p>Mobile Web Site</p>
    <p>Traditional Browser</p>
    <p>Full Web Site</p>
    <p>Interfaces include full Web site, mobile Web site and mobile app.</p>
    <p>Connections with OSNs and third-parties.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Potential Privacy Leakage Vectors in mOSNs</p>
    <p>mOSN</p>
    <p>Server1</p>
    <p>L O C A T I</p>
    <p>O N</p>
    <p>P R E S E N C E</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>Friends of user1u2 u3 u9</p>
    <p>u4</p>
    <p>u5</p>
    <p>u6</p>
    <p>u7</p>
    <p>u8</p>
    <p>U D I D</p>
    <p>User1s Pieces of [Private] Information Friends of user1</p>
    <p>OSN1</p>
    <p>Friends of user1</p>
    <p>OSN2</p>
    <p>OSN1connection</p>
    <p>OSN2connection</p>
    <p>Server2</p>
    <p>P H O T O</p>
    <p>G E N D E R</p>
    <p>N A</p>
    <p>M</p>
    <p>E</p>
    <p>R I E N D S</p>
    <p>F</p>
    <p>... ...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy Issues</p>
    <p>Many mOSNs have a check-in mechanismboth establishes a users</p>
    <p>presence on the mOSN and the users current location.</p>
    <p>Mobile devices typically have a unique device identifier, which is often</p>
    <p>used as verification for installing approved apps on a users mobile</p>
    <p>device.</p>
    <p>If this unique identifier is leaked to a third-party via an application and</p>
    <p>can be associated with a users identity, this becomes a privacy</p>
    <p>problem.</p>
    <p>Linkage between mOSNs and traditional OSNs.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mobile OSNs for Study</p>
    <p>Focused on mOSNs requiring accounts by users, supporting concept of</p>
    <p>friends, and providing at least one interface with content tailored for</p>
    <p>mobile devices.</p>
    <p>Used popularity metrics as a secondary criterion to establish a study</p>
    <p>set of 20 mOSNs.</p>
    <p>Re-examined seven mOSNs with roots as a traditional OSN:</p>
    <p>Bebo, Facebook, Hi5, Linkedin, Livejournal, MySpace and Twitter.</p>
    <p>Added two special-purpose social networks: Flickr, Yelp.</p>
    <p>Added 11 mOSNs not in existence prior to the widespread use of</p>
    <p>mobile devices: Brightkite, Buzzd, Dopplr, Foursquare, Gowalla,</p>
    <p>Gypsii, Loopt, Radar, Urbanspoon, Wattpad and Whrrl.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mobile Device Applications</p>
    <p>Not a specific criterion for inclusion in our study, but found the</p>
    <p>following count of applications (out of 20) for each device:</p>
    <p>Apple iPhone19</p>
    <p>Blackberry10</p>
    <p>Google Android6</p>
    <p>Palm6</p>
    <p>Microsoft Windows Phone3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Issues</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Examined each available interface for 19 of the mOSNs (all but Hi5)</p>
    <p>using the Apple iPhone application as the app interface.</p>
    <p>Used a Web proxy to capture HTTP traffic for full and mobile Web</p>
    <p>sites.</p>
    <p>Almost all applications also used HTTP for communication, which was</p>
    <p>capturable with proxy. Network sniffer revealed no leakage for</p>
    <p>non-HTTP traffic.</p>
    <p>Recorded multiple sessions for each mOSN interface while performing</p>
    <p>actions appropriate for the given interface.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Availability of PII Pieces to Users in 13 mOSNs Level of Availability</p>
    <p>Always Available Unavailable Always Piece of PII Available by default by default Unavailable Personal Photo 10 3 0 0 Home Location 3 4 1 1 Gender 2 3 1 3 Name 5 5 1 2 Friends 6 6 0 1 Activities 3 7 1 0 Photo Set 0 3 0 0 Age/Birth Year 1 3 0 2</p>
    <p>We note that these 13 mOSNs request and make available less</p>
    <p>information about each user in comparison to OSNs previously studied.</p>
    <p>Each mOSN allows the sharing of information to be controlled by a</p>
    <p>user via the full Web site interface of the mOSN.</p>
    <p>Only a minority of these mOSNs provide any privacy settings via the</p>
    <p>mobile and mobile application interfaces.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Location and Presence</p>
    <p>Seven traditional OSNs: 5 provide means to post public comments</p>
    <p>(presence), but only one allow a user to establish a current location.</p>
    <p>Of the 13 others: Level of Availability</p>
    <p>Always Available Unavailable Always Information Available by default by default Unavailable Check-In Location 3 3 2 5 Comments 4 7 1 1</p>
    <p>Location available by default to all mOSN users for roughly half of the</p>
    <p>mOSNs with comments available by default for most mOSNs.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interconnectedness of mOSNs</p>
    <p>Number of mOSNs with Connections to Twitter, Facebook and Flickr</p>
    <p>(out of 12 excluding seven traditional plus Flickr):</p>
    <p>Twitter10</p>
    <p>Facebook8</p>
    <p>Flickr2</p>
    <p>Actions in mOSNs passed through to these OSNs, but not privacy</p>
    <p>controls.</p>
    <p>A users location may now be posted to all on Facebook or Twitter.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Leakage of OSN Identifier</p>
    <p>GET /e0?rt=1&amp;amp;...</p>
    <p>Host: p.admob.com</p>
    <p>Referer: http://buzzd.com/m/buzz/.../id/OSN-ID Cookie: uuid=ef07qb76f47b19173389f27a9ae1d391</p>
    <p>Via Referer Field of Buzzd Mobile Web Site</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example of Direct PII Leakage</p>
    <p>GET /ad_source.php?d[gender]=m... Host: r.admob.com</p>
    <p>X-Admob-Isu: IPHONE-UDID Cookie: uuid=ef07qb76f47b19173389f27a9ae1d391</p>
    <p>Direct PII Leakage to a Third-Party Via Request-URI of Radar App</p>
    <p>(since deceased).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Leakage of User Location</p>
    <p>POST http://beacon.pinchmedia.com/</p>
    <p>Host: beacon.pinchmedia.com</p>
    <p>User-Agent: buzzd/2.2.0 CFNetwork/459</p>
    <p>Darwin/10.0.0d3</p>
    <p>beacons=&quot;did&quot;:&quot;IPHONE-UDID&quot;,.. lat : 20.00, lon : -70.00</p>
    <p>Location Leakage to a Third-Party Via POST from Buzzd App</p>
    <p>Observe that the location is shared with a map service by the</p>
    <p>application interface of eight mOSNs, the mobile Web site of four</p>
    <p>mOSNs and the full Web site of one mOSN.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Counts of Known Third-Party Privacy Leakage via 20</p>
    <p>mOSNs</p>
    <p>What is Leakage Interface</p>
    <p>Leaked? Mobile App Full</p>
    <p>OSN Identifier 6 2 18</p>
    <p>Piece of PII 1 2 5</p>
    <p>Location 0 2 0</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Type of Leakage: Explicit Vs. Implicit</p>
    <p>Do not know intention when leakage occurs, but can classify leakage</p>
    <p>into two types:</p>
    <p>unless done so on a per-server basis.</p>
    <p>prevent.</p>
    <p>Explicit leakage for 9 of 26 instances of OSN identifier leakage.</p>
    <p>All leakage instances of PII pieces and location are explicit leakage.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Leakage of Unique Device Identifier to</p>
    <p>Third-Parties</p>
    <p>GET /?i=xxxxxxxx-xxxx-...&amp;u=IPHONE-UDID Host: ads.mobclix.com</p>
    <p>User-Agent: Wattpad/1.6.1 CFNetwork/459</p>
    <p>Darwin/10.0.0d3</p>
    <p>Observed such explicit leakage for six mOSNs.</p>
    <p>Some type of private information is leaked to a third-party via all 20 of</p>
    <p>the mOSNS in our study.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Leakage problems found earlier in traditional OSNs continue to be a</p>
    <p>problem with new mOSNs.</p>
    <p>New leakages foundlocation, device identifiers.</p>
    <p>Multi-dimensional privacy protection problem for the user: including</p>
    <p>duration of privacy settings, transitive closure of information arising</p>
    <p>from connections with traditional OSNs, what information is shared</p>
    <p>with different OSNs and third parties.</p>
    <p>Needs continued monitoring as sites evolve.</p>
    <p>Also need to extend app study to a broader set of devices.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
