<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Are Nonblocking Networks Needed for High-End Computing Workloads?</p>
    <p>N. Desai, P. Balaji, P. Sadayappan, M. Islam</p>
    <p>Narayan Desai</p>
    <p>desai@mcs.anl.gov</p>
    <p>Cluster '08</p>
    <p>September 29th, 2008</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Switch-based Interconnect Networks</p>
    <p>Provide high-performance communication to parallel jobs  Low latency  High bandwidth</p>
    <p>Constructed from non-blocking switch ASICs into multi-stage switch complexes  Clos Networks  Fat Trees</p>
    <p>Dominant interconnect architecture  Except for high-end systems (Blue Gene, Cray)</p>
    <p>Bisection bandwidth cost grows non-linearly with port count  Is this cost justified?  What is the impact of reduced bisection bandwidth?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multi-stage Switch Networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Approach</p>
    <p>Build a demand model for bisection bandwidth  Worst case (100% communication)  Probabilistic model</p>
    <p>Reduce available uplink capacity  Model performance impact on jobs</p>
    <p>Process real-world workloads using these models  Jazz (production system at ANL)  Atlas (capability system at LLNL)</p>
    <p>Thunder (capacity system at LLNL)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Probabilistic View of Contention</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demand Model</p>
    <p>Assumption: nodes only communicate with other nodes in the same job  Demand computed on a per-switch ASIC basis  Each job has an uplink demand per ASIC</p>
    <p>min (local job nodes, sum(remote job nodes))  Demand aggregated for simultaneous jobs</p>
    <p>Yields a single uplink demand for each switch ASIC for each time interval</p>
    <p>Describes which ASIC/time intervals would be impacted by uplink reduction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Uplink Reduction</p>
    <p>Remove individual uplinks for each switch ASIC  Will reduce performance if uplink demand is higher than reduced supply</p>
    <p>Reduced performance is the ratio of demand to supply</p>
    <p>i.e., if demand is 6 and supply is 4, interval runtime is extended by 50%  Jobs are slowed down at a uniform pace</p>
    <p>Factor depends on most contended switch  A workload can be analyzed in terms of individual job slowdowns</p>
    <p>Can show overall system impact of uplink removal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contended Architecture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Input Workloads</p>
    <p>Jazz system at Argonne  350 node production cluster  Capacity workload</p>
    <p>1 core per node  Atlas system at Livermore</p>
    <p>1152 nodes  Capability workload  8 cores per node</p>
    <p>Thunder system at Livermore  1024 nodes  Capacity workload  4 cores per node</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis</p>
    <p>Contention as uplinks are removed  System-wide impact  Impact on jobs experiencing contention</p>
    <p>Impact of multicore nodes on workloads  Impact of increasing switch size</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Slowdowns</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Impact of Multi-core Growth</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions and Future Work</p>
    <p>Most workloads don't show much sensitivity to bisection bandwidth reduction  Most workloads show modest (&lt; 5%) aggregate performance penalty</p>
    <p>for substantial bisection bandwidth reduction  Even counting worst-case communication</p>
    <p>As switch sizes increase, this penalty decreases on a per-uplink basis  Multi-core systems result in fatter nodes, spreading jobs across fewer</p>
    <p>nodes and hence fewer network ports  All of these trends suggest that bisection bandwidth will decrease in</p>
    <p>importance for common workloads over time  Future Work</p>
    <p>Need to take I/O into consideration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
