<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Channel Allocation in 802.11-based Mesh Networks</p>
    <p>Bhaskaran Raman Department of CSE, IIT Kanpur</p>
    <p>India 208016 http://www.cse.iitk.ac.in/users/braman/</p>
    <p>Presentation at Infocom 2006 Barcelona, Spain</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation and Background</p>
    <p>The 2P MAC protocol</p>
    <p>Channel allocation, channel subgraphs  Optimal channel allocation</p>
    <p>NP-completeness  Heuristics</p>
    <p>Discussion: P2MP links, further work  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Directional antenna  MAC modifications</p>
    <p>Example deployments:  www.Djurslands.Net  Nepal wireless  Ashwini project, A.P., India</p>
    <p>Src: http://nepalwireless.net/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Ashwini Centre at Kasipadu,</p>
    <p>West Godavari,</p>
    <p>Andhra Pradesh,</p>
    <p>India</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network Model</p>
    <p>Point-to-point links  Multiple interfaces (radios) per node  One directional antenna per link</p>
    <p>To link-1</p>
    <p>To link-2 To link-3</p>
    <p>Ethernet hub</p>
    <p>Link-1</p>
    <p>Link-2 Link-3</p>
    <p>Point-topoint</p>
    <p>Radio1</p>
    <p>Radio2 Radio3</p>
    <p>Landline node</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The 2P MAC Protocol  Two phases: each node switches between</p>
    <p>SynRx and SynTx</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B C</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>SynTx SynRx</p>
    <p>SynTx SynRx</p>
    <p>a) Links: A--&gt;B, A--&gt;D, C--&gt;B, C--&gt;D</p>
    <p>b) Links: B--&gt;A, B--&gt;C, D--&gt;A, D--&gt;C Note: diagram ignores system and propogation delays</p>
    <p>Single channel operation  Topology has to be bipartite</p>
    <p>Design and Evaluation of a new MAC Protocol for Long-Distance 802.11 Mesh Networks , Bhaskaran Raman and Kameswari Chebrolu, Mobicom 2005</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bipartite graph, or a  channel subgraph</p>
    <p>V 1</p>
    <p>V 2</p>
    <p>f</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Channel Subgraphs</p>
    <p>Non-overlapping channels 1 6 11</p>
    <p>Mhz</p>
    <p>Channel subgraph: maximal subgraph with all links on the same channel</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BP-proper Channel Allocation  BP-proper channel allocation: such that all</p>
    <p>channel subgraphs are bipartite  Question: given a graph, does it have a BP</p>
    <p>proper 3-edge colouring?  If 6-edge-colourable, provably yes</p>
    <p>6-edge colouring using Vizing's approach  Merge alternate colours  Channel subgraphs will be paths or even cycles</p>
    <p>If graph is 8-vertex-colourable, provably yes  Thanks to Sundar Vishwanathan, CSE, IITB</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Link Capacities</p>
    <p>Assumption: all links operate at max. rate  Traffic on links may be asymmetric  Focus of our work: accommodating this</p>
    <p>asymmetry  Model: operator specifies a desired fraction</p>
    <p>(DF) of capacity in a particular direction  Note:</p>
    <p>The actual fraction of capacity an edge is allocated: achieved fraction (AF)</p>
    <p>DF v 1  v</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Channel Allocation and Link Capacities</p>
    <p>Edges in a channel subgraph have the same AF</p>
    <p>V 1</p>
    <p>V 2</p>
    <p>f</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Zero-Mismatch ChannelAllocation (ZMCA)</p>
    <p>ZMCA definition:  Given a network and edge DFs,  BP-proper 3-channel allocation such that:</p>
    <p>That is: all edges in each channel subgraph have the same</p>
    <p>DF ei= AF ei edges ei</p>
    <p>ei DF ei</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NP-Completeness of ZMCA  NP-Complete even if:</p>
    <p>Delta &lt;= 4  DFs chosen from {1/4, 1/3, 1/2, 2/3, 3/4}</p>
    <p>Proof outline:  Reduce 3SAT to ZMCA  Mimics proof of NP-Completeness of optimal edge</p>
    <p>colouring problem  Ian Holyer,  The NP-Completeness of Edge-Colouring ,</p>
    <p>SIAM J. COMPUTING, vol. 10, no. 4, Nov 1981.  Construct inverting, replicating, clause-testing</p>
    <p>components</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Minimum-Mismatch ChannelAllocation (MMCA)</p>
    <p>MMCA definition: minimize</p>
    <p>ZMCA NP-Complete =&gt; MMCA NP-hard  Note: given a channel allocation, minimizing</p>
    <p>mismatch is trivial  Within a channel subgraph with edge DFs  Optimal is one of  Optimal for each channel subgraph is determined</p>
    <p>independently</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>i E DF ei AF ei</p>
    <p>f f i , i=1. . k f i , i=1. . k</p>
    <p>f</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Heuristics for MMCA</p>
    <p>Steps: 6-edge-colouring, AF assignment  Approach:</p>
    <p>Heuristic for edge-colouring, edge-ordering in Vizing's algorithm</p>
    <p>Get initial set of channel subgraphs  Uncolour channel subgraphs with large mismatch  Local exhaustive search to colour that subgraph</p>
    <p>Performance close to optimum</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Packet radio network scheduling, bluetooth  Single channel of operation  Use STDMA scheduling (not 2P)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion: Point-to-MultiPoint (P2MP) Links</p>
    <p>Bhimavaram</p>
    <p>Ashwini network deployment (partial)</p>
    <p>Each village has a bandwidth reqmt.: 384 Kbps</p>
    <p>Specific times known too</p>
    <p>Can use this info to set DFs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion: Further Work</p>
    <p>What if only two channels available?  One channel may be required for local coverage</p>
    <p>Practical complications:  Inter-link interference &amp; channel assignment</p>
    <p>Inter-link interference an important factor  Inefficiencies in 2P with large channel subgraph</p>
    <p>size  Minimize channel subgraph size</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>802.11 mesh networks becoming popular  We focus on planned networks with long-distance</p>
    <p>links  This work: channel allocation for desired link</p>
    <p>capacity  Practical considerations add new dimensions to</p>
    <p>the problem  Experience will tell which direction is important to</p>
    <p>explore</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
