<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  Motivation</p>
    <p>Our System</p>
    <p>Evaluation Evaluation</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Botnet</p>
    <p>A botnet is a collection of bots controlled by a botmaster via a command and control (C&amp;C) channel  Centralized C&amp;C, P2P-based C&amp;C</p>
    <p>Botnets serve as the infrastructures for a variety of attacks</p>
    <p>Exploiting, scanning, spamming, phishing, DDoS, etc.</p>
    <p>Botnet detection is of great importance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  Current detection approaches are based on Deep Packet Inspection (DPI)  BotHunter [Security 07]</p>
    <p>BotSniffer [NDSS 07]</p>
    <p>BotMiner [Security 08] (malicious activity plane)</p>
    <p>TAMD [DIMVA 08] TAMD [DIMVA 08]</p>
    <p>Not Scalable for high-speed and high-volume networks!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our system  A layered traffic analysis approach</p>
    <p>Botnet-aware packet sampling algorithm (B-Sampling)</p>
    <p>Scalable spatial-temporal flow-correlation algorithm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Architecture Scalable spatial-temporal flow-correlation</p>
    <p>PerExp : expected percentage of suspicious hosts</p>
    <p>Flow Capture: 1.B-Sampling: Botnet-Aware Adaptive Packet Sampling 2.Flow-Assembler</p>
    <p>Fine-Grained Botnet Detectors</p>
    <p>DPI</p>
    <p>SRT : target sampling rate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow Capture Indexed by Hash(SrcIP||DstIP) Record # of pkts for an interval T (15 min)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow Capture: Synchronized IPs Detector  homo-servers</p>
    <p>Hosts outside the monitored networks whose clients show small variance of connections in a time interval (T=15 min)</p>
    <p>similar-clients  Hosts within the monitored networks that generate similar connections to a large number of destination IPs in a time interval (T=15 min)</p>
    <p>a large number of destination IPs in a time interval (T=15 min)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow Capture: Synchronized IPs Detector  From homo-servers and similar-clients, we identify:</p>
    <p>syn-servers  C&amp;C servers for centralized-based botnets</p>
    <p>syn-clients  Bots of P2P-based botnets</p>
    <p>Bots of P2P-based botnets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow Capture: Synchronized IPs Detector  Identify syn-server/client based on home-server/similar-client</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow Capture: Sampling Probability Calculation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why we need a new sampling algorithm?</p>
    <p>Uniform sampling or periodic sampling  Prune to capturing packets in large flows and missing small flows (e.g. netflow)</p>
    <p>FlexSample [IMC 08]  Samples more packets from specific traffic subpopulations based  Samples more packets from specific traffic subpopulations based on programmable conditions (e.g. small and medium flows)</p>
    <p>The diversity of C&amp;C communications of different botnets makes it challenging to set conditions for FlexSample to sample packets from a wide range of botnets.</p>
    <p>Requirement  Let the real sampling rate be close to target sampling rate.</p>
    <p>Sample more packets from C&amp;C communication flows. 11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow Capture: Sampling Probability Calculation</p>
    <p>The Priority-based Sampling Algorithm</p>
    <p>Priority Set of IPs Sampling Rate</p>
    <p>Cnt</p>
    <p>Sampling Sketch</p>
    <p>Pt: the pre-defined target sampling rate  fi: the packet fraction for a priority out of all</p>
    <p>the packets  budgeti: the fraction of the sampled packets</p>
    <p>we would like to give to a particular priority  budget: available budget</p>
    <p>Estimate fi currEstimate fi curr</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow Capture: Flow Assembler  Assemble each sample packet, together with its sampling rate (pi), to 5</p>
    <p>tuple flows identified by (SrcIP, SrcPort, DstIP, DstPort, Proto)</p>
    <p>Timestart/end: the start/end time of this flow</p>
    <p>sizeactual: flow size,</p>
    <p>byteactual: the # of bytes observed,</p>
    <p>sizeest: the estimated flow size,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow Correlation: Get C-flows</p>
    <p>C-flow  Aggregates a set of 5-tuple flows sharing the same tuple of (SrcIP, DstIP, DstPort, Proto) in a certain epoch (12 hours).</p>
    <p>Represents the communication pattern from a host to a remote host and port in a certain epoch.host and port in a certain epoch.</p>
    <p># of flows per hour  # of packets per flow  # of packets per second  # of bytes per packet</p>
    <p>fphmax: the maximum number of flows per hour timem: the median time interval of two consecutive flows</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow Correlation: Cross-Epoch Correlation</p>
    <p>If a pair of hosts share similar communication patterns for at least M out of N epochs (M&lt;=N), they are suspicious.</p>
    <p>Birch, a streaming clustering algorithm with good scalability</p>
    <p>Increase the diameter for discovering clusters to identify up to PerExp hosts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fine-Grained Detectors  Fine-Grained detectors only focus on traffic of PerExp hosts for deep packet inspection  If a pair of hosts share persistently similar communication patterns and commit similar attacks, they are identified as bots.(a modified version of BotMiner)</p>
    <p>BotSniffers IRC-based C&amp;C detection component</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation  Experimental Data  Experimental Setup</p>
    <p>12 hours for each epoch; totally 7 epochs</p>
    <p>If a pair of hosts share similar communication patterns 3</p>
    <p>communication patterns 3 epochs out of 7 epochs, they are identified to share persistently similar communication patterns.</p>
    <p>Both-IRC-A: TR/Agent.1199508.A Bot-HTTP-A: Swizzor.gen.c Bot-P2P-Storm: storm Bot-P2P-Waledac: waledac Others from RuBot</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation  Packet Sampling Algorithm</p>
    <p>p ac</p>
    <p>k et s am</p>
    <p>p li n g r at es</p>
    <p>target sampling rates</p>
    <p>IRC-A</p>
    <p>IRC-A, BSampling</p>
    <p>IRC-A, Flex</p>
    <p>StormHTTP-A</p>
    <p>The actual packet sampling rate is close to the target sampling rate  High sampling rates for botnet C&amp;C traffic  Outperform another recent packet sampling algorithm (FlexSample)</p>
    <p>k et s am</p>
    <p>p li n g r at es</p>
    <p>target sampling rates</p>
    <p>Storm</p>
    <p>Storm, BSampling</p>
    <p>Storm, Flex 0</p>
    <p>p ac</p>
    <p>k et s am</p>
    <p>p li n g r at es</p>
    <p>target sampling rates</p>
    <p>HTTP-A</p>
    <p>HTTP-A, BSampling</p>
    <p>HTTP-A, Flex</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation  Cross-Epoch Correlation</p>
    <p>Cross-epoch correlation together with B-Sampling can detect all the bots for most of the combinations of SRT (target sampling rate) and PerExp (expected percentage of suspicious hosts)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cross-Epoch Correlation  Time consumption of cross-epoch correlation compared to BotMiners clustering algorithm (X-means + hierarchical clustering)</p>
    <p>Evaluation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation  Fine-Grained Detectors</p>
    <p>Detection Results</p>
    <p>Eliminate all the false positives  Achieve high detection</p>
    <p>Fine-grained detectors only need to investigated less than 5% traffic and use much less time.</p>
    <p>with our approach direct deployment</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion  High-Speed Networks</p>
    <p>Given 2 hr process time of cross-epoch correlation and t=0.0035 * # of cflows , our system can process 2M c-flows (i.e., # of c-flows)</p>
    <p>College network: 200K c-flows extracted from 200Mbps traffic</p>
    <p>2M c-flows would result from 2Gbps, indicating that the cross-epoch</p>
    <p>2M c-flows would result from 2Gbps, indicating that the cross-epoch correlation can be used in 2 Gbps networks</p>
    <p>Evasion  Randomize communication patterns to decrease the packet sampling rates and evade cross-epoch correlation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  A botnet-aware adaptive sampling algorithm</p>
    <p>Keep the actual packet sampling rate close to the target sampling rate</p>
    <p>High sampling rates for botnet C&amp;C related packets compared</p>
    <p>Cross-epoch correlation</p>
    <p>Effectively and efficiently identify bots by investigating their persistently similar communication patterns</p>
    <p>A new botnet detection system employing layered traffic analysis approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks!</p>
    <p>Questions?Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
