<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mathematical Modeling of Competition in Sponsored Search Market</p>
    <p>Jerry Jian Liu and Dah Ming Chiu Department of Information Engineering The Chinese University of Hong Kong NetEcon10, October 3rd, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>The monopoly market model</p>
    <p>The duopoly market model</p>
    <p>Competition for end users</p>
    <p>Competition for advertisers</p>
    <p>Simulation results</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>Internet advertising becomes a main source of revenue for primary search engines nowadays.</p>
    <p>Major search engines, like Google, Yahoo! and Microsoft all employ sponsored links to display advertisement when users submit their searching keywords.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example of Sponsored Search</p>
    <p>Sponsored Links</p>
    <p>Algorithmic Links</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Most of previous works on sponsored search focused on mechanism design and analysis within the scope of one search engine.</p>
    <p>In practice, we notice that multiple search engines compete with each other for end users as well as advertisers in the market.</p>
    <p>How would the market evolve in the future? Will the leading company (like Google in US and Baidu in China) become the monopolist? Can small competitors still survive and co-exist?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>The monopoly market model</p>
    <p>The duopoly market model</p>
    <p>Competition for end users</p>
    <p>Competition for advertisers</p>
    <p>Simulation results</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Monopoly Market Model</p>
    <p>One search engine;</p>
    <p>A fixed set of end users;</p>
    <p>A fixed set of advertisers denoted by ;</p>
    <p>Search engine can infer users interest via the submitted keywords, and sell users attentions to advertisers in the form of sponsored search.</p>
    <p>: the supply of attentions for a particular keyword in a given time interval.</p>
    <p>Search engine needs to determine the price per attention to maximize its revenue:</p>
    <p>I (jIj = m)</p>
    <p>R = p  min(S; D(p)) = min(p  S; pD(p))</p>
    <p>S</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some explanations</p>
    <p>S: determined by end users.</p>
    <p>D: determined by advertisers.</p>
    <p>Regarded as an auction process:</p>
    <p>Price starts from zero. All advertisers stay in the auction.</p>
    <p>More demand than supply  price increases gradually.</p>
    <p>More advertisers choose to quit, demand drops.</p>
    <p>At the point when demand equals supply, items were cleared at that price.</p>
    <p>R = p  min(S; D(p)) = min(p  S; pD(p))</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Aggregate Demand</p>
    <p>In practice, each advertiser would submit two parameters to the advertising system: value for each attention and budget in the given time interval.</p>
    <p>Reorder the index of advertisers such that</p>
    <p>The aggregate demand is then:</p>
    <p>where we define .</p>
    <p>Thus, is also non-increasing over p since shrinks as price p increases. Furthermore, its piece-wise constant.</p>
    <p>vj  vj+1</p>
    <p>D(p) = X</p>
    <p>i2I+(p)</p>
    <p>Bi p</p>
    <p>I+(p) , fi 2 I : vi &gt; pg p  D(p) =</p>
    <p>P i2I+(p) Bi</p>
    <p>I+(p)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Revenue as the Function of Price</p>
    <p>We can depict the revenue figures:</p>
    <p>For the undetermined advertiser scenario, we assume the search engine would allocate all the remaining supply to advertiser 2 as long as the current price doesnt exceed its value and the budget is not exhausted yet.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimal Price</p>
    <p>A polynomial step algorithm for calculating the optimal price:</p>
    <p>Input:</p>
    <p>Output:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>The monopoly market model</p>
    <p>The duopoly market model</p>
    <p>Competition for end users</p>
    <p>Competition for advertisers</p>
    <p>Simulation results</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Duopoly Market Model</p>
    <p>Two horizontally and vertically differentiated search engines competing for users and advertisers.</p>
    <p>Horizontal difference means the different design of home pages and diversity of extra services like news, email.</p>
    <p>Different users may have different tastes and preferences.</p>
    <p>Vertical difference means the quality of search results.</p>
    <p>For users, the higher quality the better.</p>
    <p>We model the competition as a three-stage game:</p>
    <p>Stage I, two engines provide various services to attract users;</p>
    <p>Stage II, two engines determine their prices to advertisers;</p>
    <p>Stage III, advertisers choose the engine which brings them higher utility.</p>
    <p>J = f1; 2g</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Assuming users are spread uniformly on the circumference of a unit circle. Each user is characterized by an address t on the circle, denoting his specific taste.</p>
    <p>Each engine chooses a location in the characteristic space denoting the specific feature of service it provides.</p>
    <p>For user t searches at engine at location x, it will involve quadratic transportation cost .</p>
    <p>Utility of user :</p>
    <p>: vertical difference in quality;</p>
    <p>: horizontal difference in design.</p>
    <p>Stage I: Classic Location Model</p>
    <p>(t  x)2</p>
    <p>t 2 [0; 1)</p>
    <p>2 [0; 1] C(t; x)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Division of User Market</p>
    <p>By letting , we get the address of two indifferent users as .</p>
    <p>Then the market share of engine 2 is:</p>
    <p>By applying first-order condition , we can get the optimal address for engine 2:</p>
    <p>i.e., the maximum differentiation.</p>
    <p>u1(t) = u2(t)</p>
    <p>1; 2</p>
    <p>n2(x2) = 2  1 dn2 dx2</p>
    <p>= 0</p>
    <p>x2 = 1 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Competition for Advertisers</p>
    <p>The utility of advertiser in either search engine is:</p>
    <p>is a discount factor denoting advertiser s perceived disability of engine 2 to convert users attentions to clicks (or actual sales of products).</p>
    <p>: more sensitive  Performance advertisers.</p>
    <p>: less sensitive</p>
    <p>Brand advertisers.</p>
    <p>i 2 I</p>
    <p>i 2 [0; 1] i</p>
    <p>i  1 i  0</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Division of Advertisers</p>
    <p>By letting , we derive the condition under which advertiser i would choose engine 1:</p>
    <p>Reorder advertisers according to , then the division of advertisers is as follows:</p>
    <p>: set of advertisers preferring engine 1;</p>
    <p>: set of advertisers preferring engine 2.</p>
    <p>i1   i 2</p>
    <p>i  p2 p1</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>I1(p1; p2) = fi 2 I : i  p2</p>
    <p>p1 g</p>
    <p>I2(p1; p2) = fi 2 I : i &gt; p2</p>
    <p>p1 g</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Nash Equilibrium Price Pair</p>
    <p>After initial price and are set in the market, advertisers are divided into and . Each engine then compute its optimal price and independently as the monopoly case and price ratio gets updated.</p>
    <p>If it happens the new ratio divides the advertisers into and , then this is a Nash equilibrium price pair</p>
    <p>The formal definition is as follows: A price pair is called Nash equilibrium (NE) price pair if and where is calculated according to algorithm 1.</p>
    <p>p1 p2 I1 I2</p>
    <p>p1(I1) p  2(I2)</p>
    <p>p2=p  1</p>
    <p>I1 I2 (pNE1 ; p</p>
    <p>N E 2 )</p>
    <p>(p1; p2)</p>
    <p>p1 = p (I1(p1; p2)) p2 = p(I2(p1; p2)) p(I)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Existence of NE price pair</p>
    <p>Theorem 1: Assuming advertisers can purchase service from both search engines simultaneously, Nash equilibrium price pair would always exist for any set of advertisers and supplies of search engines.</p>
    <p>The above assumption is necessary. Otherwise, the system would suffer from oscillation problem and no NE may exist.</p>
    <p>A counter-example is when there is only one advertiser. No matter which engine it chooses, the price in the other engine is always zero. The advertiser would keep switching.</p>
    <p>Theorem 2: Denoted by the NE price pair and the optimal price when engine 1 monopolizes the market, it must hold that .</p>
    <p>(pNE1 ; p N E 2 )</p>
    <p>p</p>
    <p>pNE2  p  pNE1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>The monopoly market model</p>
    <p>The duopoly market model</p>
    <p>Competition for end users</p>
    <p>Competition for advertisers</p>
    <p>Simulation results</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Four Major Criteria</p>
    <p>SW = X i2I1</p>
    <p>viqi1 + X i2I2</p>
    <p>iviqi2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Baseline Setting</p>
    <p>We consider two search engines equally dividing the market. Suppose the total supply is normalized to one, the supplies of either engine is ;</p>
    <p>Value : uniformly distributed over (18, 20);</p>
    <p>Budget : uniformly distributed with ;</p>
    <p>Discount factor : uniformly distributed over (0.5,0.9) with expectation .</p>
    <p>To be exact, we define advertisers with as brand advertisers.</p>
    <p>The rest advertisers are all performance advertisers.</p>
    <p>S1 = S2 = 0:5</p>
    <p>v B E(B) = 4</p>
    <p>E() = 0:7</p>
    <p>E()</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prices in Baseline Setting</p>
    <p>Approach maximal v</p>
    <p>Approach maximal v</p>
    <p>Saturate at round five since E(B)=E(v) = 4=19 t 0:2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Revenues in Baseline Setting</p>
    <p>R1 = p1  S1 R2 = p2  S2</p>
    <p>R = p  (S1 + S2)</p>
    <p>t R1 + p1</p>
    <p>p2 R2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Aggregate Utility in Baseline Setting</p>
    <p>Far more than half of the square line! Brand advertisers have higher and benefit from lower price of engine 2.</p>
    <p>Exactly half of the triangular line!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Social Welfare in Baseline Setting</p>
    <p>Realized values get discounted due to the effect of :</p>
    <p>SW = X i2I1</p>
    <p>viqi1 + X i2I2</p>
    <p>iviqi2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>The monopoly market model</p>
    <p>The duopoly market model</p>
    <p>Competition for end users</p>
    <p>Competition for advertisers</p>
    <p>Simulation results</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary of this work</p>
    <p>We propose an analytical framework to analyze the interaction of search engines, advertisers and end users in sponsored search market.</p>
    <p>A three-stage dynamic game is formulated to model the competition between search engines; furthermore, we prove the existence of Nash equilibrium of the game.</p>
    <p>We show some initial results of revenue and welfare of the advertising system by simulations.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Directions</p>
    <p>Throughout the work, we implicitly assume advertisers would reveal their true parameters. How would strategies of rational advertisers affect our conclusions?</p>
    <p>Associating our result of revenue from one keyword with practical scenario when revenue is aggregated from numerous keywords queried by different end users.</p>
    <p>Incorporating the generalized second-price (GSP) auction prevailing in major search engines.</p>
    <p>Investigating competition among multiple search engines analytically besides the duopoly scenario.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>~The end~</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
