<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges in managing implicit and abstract provenance data: experiences with ProvManager</p>
    <p>Anderson Marinho, Marta Mattoso, Cludia Werner, Vanessa Braganholo, Leonardo Murta</p>
    <p>Workshop on the Theory and Practice of Provenance 2011</p>
    <p>Federal University of Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), Brazil Fluminense Federal University (UFF), Brazil</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem/Motivation  Some challenges in managing provenance</p>
    <p>Which provenance data should be gathered?  Open Provenance Model is a possible solution</p>
    <p>How to capture provenance data?  Three levels: Workflow, Operating System, Activity</p>
    <p>How to manage provenance in workflows that are executed by different execution environments (distributed environments)?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ProvManager - Overview of provenance gathering strategy</p>
    <p>ProvManager</p>
    <p>Taverna</p>
    <p>Kepler</p>
    <p>VisTrails</p>
    <p>Experiment</p>
    <p>Scientist</p>
    <p>[SWF 2009; IPAW, 2010]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workflow instrumentation</p>
    <p>A B Original workflow</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workflow instrumentation</p>
    <p>A BPGA PGAPGA</p>
    <p>A B Original workflow</p>
    <p>Instrumenting workflow PGA</p>
    <p>PGA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workflow instrumentation</p>
    <p>A BPGA PGAPGA</p>
    <p>A BPGA PGAPGA</p>
    <p>A B Original workflow</p>
    <p>Instrumenting workflow</p>
    <p>Wrapping activities</p>
    <p>PGAPGA</p>
    <p>A B</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workflow instrumentation</p>
    <p>A BPGA PGAPGA</p>
    <p>A BPGA PGAPGA</p>
    <p>A B</p>
    <p>A B</p>
    <p>Original workflow</p>
    <p>Instrumenting workflow</p>
    <p>Wrapping activities</p>
    <p>Adapted workflow</p>
    <p>PGAPGA</p>
    <p>A B</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>There are still some problems  Implicit provenance data</p>
    <p>Difficulty in gathering provenance data when these are not explicitly declared in the workflow specification</p>
    <p>Lack of higher provenance abstraction levels  Concrete workflow related provenance data are not</p>
    <p>enough to help scientists in the experiment analysis  Some scientists may not be used to such information</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implicit provenance data</p>
    <p>A B</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>OS domain</p>
    <p>SWfMS domain</p>
    <p>D im g. jp g</p>
    <p>C:\data</p>
    <p>re s. zi p</p>
    <p>C:\data C:\res.zip{1,3,5}</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis of Movements of</p>
    <p>Platform Prosim</p>
    <p>Conceptual Abstract Concrete</p>
    <p>Lack of higher provenance abstraction levels</p>
    <p>Problem: scientist does not easily relate data from one abstraction level to the other</p>
    <p>Questions such as what is the result data of the analysis of platform movements activity? can not be</p>
    <p>easily answered</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some ideas  Implicit data</p>
    <p>Adopt a OS level provenance gathering mechanism to work together with the PGA in the ProvManager</p>
    <p>There is a similar initiative in VisTrails (Koop et al. (2010))</p>
    <p>Lack of higher provenance abstraction levels  Create a conceptual provenance data model</p>
    <p>Salayandia and da Silva (2010) propose something similar  Map this model to the existing concrete provenance data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges in managing implicit and abstract provenance data: experiences with ProvManager</p>
    <p>Anderson Marinho, Marta Mattoso, Cludia Werner, Vanessa Braganholo, Leonardo Murta</p>
    <p>Workshop on the Theory and Practice of Provenance 2011</p>
    <p>Federal University of Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), Brazil Fluminense Federal University (UFF), Brazil</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
