<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Embedded Firmware Diversity for Smart Electric</p>
    <p>Meters</p>
    <p>Stephen McLaughlin, Dmitry Podkuiko, Adam Delozier, Sergei Miadzvezhanka, and Patrick McDaniel</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Smart Meters</p>
    <p>Smart MeterElectromechanical Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fraud - Hacking meters to reduce energy bill</p>
    <p>Privacy - Using detailed load profiles to determine behavior</p>
    <p>Blackout - Exploiting large numbers of meters and cutting power</p>
    <p>Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problem of Meter Monocultures</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>.</p>
    <p>Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problem of Meter Monocultures</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problem of Meter Monocultures</p>
    <p>Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problem of Meter Monocultures</p>
    <p>Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Known Mitigation: Diversity</p>
    <p>Software Diversity: Uniqueness added to the implementation, but not interfaces of a program.</p>
    <p>Caveat: Uniqueness must depend on good randomness</p>
    <p>Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations of Embedded Systems</p>
    <p>Firmware Type Processor Type MMU Privileged Mode NX Bit RAM Repeater Controller Renesas M16C No No No 20KB</p>
    <p>Wireless Mesh Renesas H8S No No No N/A</p>
    <p>Embedded TCP/IP Lantronix DSTni-EX 186 No No No 256KB</p>
    <p>Gateway Controller Intel i386EX Yes Yes No 8MB</p>
    <p>Address Space Layout Randomization No MMU</p>
    <p>Software Fault Isolation No protected supervisor mode</p>
    <p>Non-Executable Stacks No NX bit</p>
    <p>Stack Cookies Check code not segmented</p>
    <p>Address Encryption Works, but failed exploits can cause</p>
    <p>random errors</p>
    <p>DiversityTechnique Limitation</p>
    <p>Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More Embedded Challenges</p>
    <p>Diversity scheme hardness depends on secret size, which is related to machine word size.</p>
    <p>Smart meter components range from 32- down to 8-bit MCUs.</p>
    <p>This will affect the layout of some data structures in 8and 16-bit systems, where multiple machine words will be needed to store the diversified value.</p>
    <p>Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Address Encryption</p>
    <p>R K</p>
    <p>Stack Registers</p>
    <p>Local Variables</p>
    <p>Previous Frame</p>
    <p>R K</p>
    <p>R</p>
    <p>K</p>
    <p>ret, jmp, etc.</p>
    <p>Normal Dereference</p>
    <p>R'</p>
    <p>Stack Registers</p>
    <p>Local Variables</p>
    <p>Previous Frame</p>
    <p>R'</p>
    <p>R' K</p>
    <p>ret, jmp, etc.</p>
    <p>Exploit Dereference</p>
    <p>EXPLOIT</p>
    <p>K</p>
    <p>FAULTWhat is normally a fault will cause unpredictable errors in embedded</p>
    <p>architectures with single, real-mode address spaces.</p>
    <p>Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Redundant Address Encryption</p>
    <p>R K2</p>
    <p>R K1</p>
    <p>R K3</p>
    <p>Local Variables</p>
    <p>Previous Frame</p>
    <p>Stack Registers</p>
    <p>R K1 R K2</p>
    <p>R K3</p>
    <p>R R R</p>
    <p>K1 K2 K3</p>
    <p>Compare</p>
    <p>ret, jmp, etc.</p>
    <p>Fail Stop</p>
    <p>==</p>
    <p>!=</p>
    <p>For three keys on a 16 bit MCU:  248 probes to compromise  232 probes to random error</p>
    <p>A 15,000 node deployment that is rate limited to 3 request/second for each meter requires approx. 10 years to fully compromise when using three keys.</p>
    <p>Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Binary Instrumentation</p>
    <p>Feasible for embedded smart meters:</p>
    <p>Statically linked code</p>
    <p>Explicit call and return instructions</p>
    <p>Loose performance constraints</p>
    <p>Code size must be minimized!</p>
    <p>Original function call:</p>
    <p>push A ; Save address</p>
    <p>jmp B ; Perform branch</p>
    <p>Instrumented function call:</p>
    <p>mov D [key1_addr] ; D = K_1</p>
    <p>mov C A ; C = A</p>
    <p>xor C D ; C = C XOR D</p>
    <p>push C ; Save encrypted address</p>
    <p>mov D [key2_addr] ; D = K_2</p>
    <p>mov C A ;</p>
    <p>xor C D ; Second redundant encryption</p>
    <p>push C ;</p>
    <p>mov D [key3_addr] ; D = K_3</p>
    <p>mov C A ;</p>
    <p>xor C D ; Third redundant encryption</p>
    <p>push C ;</p>
    <p>jmp B ; Perform branch</p>
    <p>Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Meter Configuration</p>
    <p>Issues Dashboard</p>
    <p>Priority Description Comments</p>
    <p>Critical Change Data Capture in Oracle (CDC) Performance</p>
    <p>Change Data Capture application was not scaling to required performance. Waiting to test a fix from Oracle that is Oracle RAC compatible. 4/30 update  Per Lungile M  System refreshed on 4/29 back to 2/27 in order to run billing with CDC enabled and with full infrastructure (Data Guard included). CDC performance results satisfactory; awaiting RSS initial results to be available by EOD 5/1.</p>
    <p>Critical Meter discover and initialization process for installed meters in Bakersfield area delayed due to project slip.</p>
    <p>The project has been using interfaces which have not completed testing (60, 50, 104, 66, 67) to enable AMS Ops to discover and initialize installed meters. The conversion approach for the MDMS needs to be revisited to determine if the right approach is to initialize the MEM go live weekend, or use ORT to enable cut-over.</p>
    <p>Critical RSS critical defect impacts</p>
    <p>FSTE environment preparation to be completed; Oracle had delivered a fix for the critical null value defect which addressed the defect but was not compatible with other code. Awaiting updated fix from Oracle. Per T. Tang, sev 2 issue opened with Oracle; no estimated resolution date yet. Need as soon as possible; cannot go live with re-platform without this fix.</p>
    <p>High Establishment of Substation connectivity with automated discovery process</p>
    <p>Currently the process of establishing connectivity and discovery process is labor intensive. Automated mechanism must be provided by DCSI to make this process less error prone and reliable. Tickets have been opened with DCSI for this specific requested feature in TNG.</p>
    <p>High Agreement with Southern California Edison for streetlights &amp; poles in Area4</p>
    <p>Agreement with Southern California Edison for streetlights and poles in Area4 is overdue. Fifty-six gas data collector towers (DCUs) are being stalled. 4/26 update  SCE Sr. Mgmt unwilling to set precedent prior to deciding on policy for Wi-Fi installations. Team attempting to contact SCE AMI Project.</p>
    <p>High Dates for ClimateSmart Issue to be described by CC&amp;B at meeting.</p>
    <p>SmartMeter Project Release</p>
    <p>Critical and High Impact Issues Issues are categorized as CRITICAL and HIGH by the following definitions: Critical: Major threat to success (as measured against balance of quality, schedule, and budget). High: Significant disruption to successful delivery of objectives, products, and benefits.</p>
    <p>Confidential  Submitted Pursuant to PU Code Section 583</p>
    <p>Public Version</p>
    <p>Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Meter monocultures</p>
    <p>Highly exposed nodes</p>
    <p>Hard to configure</p>
    <p>Same pandemic problem as other monocultures</p>
    <p>Diversity</p>
    <p>Well understood exploit mitigation</p>
    <p>Significantly slows large scale exploit attempts</p>
    <p>Embedded diversity schemes will present their own challenges while facing less stringent performance requirements than traditional diversity techniques</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You</p>
    <p>http://www.cse.psu.edu/~smclaugh http://siis.cse.psu.edu</p>
    <p>Seed Questions</p>
    <p>Are there suggestions for approaches besides diversity for mitigating large-scale meter exploitation?</p>
    <p>How could we reduce meter TCB, thus reducing the amount of code that needs to be diversified?</p>
    <p>Should we build redundant address encryption or explore additional diversity techniques?</p>
    <p>Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Systems and Internet Infrastructure Security Laboratory (SIIS) Page 17 Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Considerations</p>
    <p>Sensors MCU</p>
    <p>Storage Networking</p>
    <p>Meter</p>
    <p>Utility Server</p>
    <p>Utility Technician</p>
    <p>Tuesday, August 10, 2010</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
