<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Investigating Energy and Security Trade-offs in the Classroom With the Atom LEAP Testbed</p>
    <p>Peter A. H. Peterson Digvijay Singh William J. Kaiser Peter L. Reiher</p>
    <p>{pahp, reiher}@cs.ucla.edu digvijay@ucla.edu kaiser@ee.ucla.edu</p>
    <p>August 8, 2011</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>We present a new measurement tool and describe its use for an undergraduate research seminar investigating energy and security tradeoffs.</p>
    <p>I Introducing the Atom LEAP</p>
    <p>I Undergraduate Research: Security vs. Energy</p>
    <p>I Lessons Learned</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introducing Atom LEAP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introducing Atom LEAP</p>
    <p>The Atom LEAP is an energy measurement platform which is...</p>
    <p>I Component Level (HDD, RAM, CPU, USB, PSU)</p>
    <p>I High granularity (10,000 floating point samples per second)</p>
    <p>I Event Synchronized with Energy Calipers</p>
    <p>The LEAP is flexible and portable:</p>
    <p>I Off the shelf hardware</p>
    <p>I Open-source/Free Software stack</p>
    <p>I Easy to construct (Even I can do it!)</p>
    <p>I Inexpensive  about $1,500 (mostly the DAQ)</p>
    <p>I Self-contained</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Atom LEAP Components</p>
    <p>I Intel Atom N330 and Motherboard</p>
    <p>I Risers and sense resistors</p>
    <p>I National Instruments USB DAQ</p>
    <p>I Synchronization instrumentation</p>
    <p>I Software stack</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Atom LEAP: Exploded View</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Synchronized Energy Calipers</p>
    <p>Energy calipers allow energy measurement of very small time spans.</p>
    <p>I A sync signal is linked to the CPUs Time Stamp Counter (TSC)</p>
    <p>I This signal is sampled while workload is measured</p>
    <p>I Workload instrumentation records the TSC before and after an event with inline assembly or a command line utility</p>
    <p>I Post-hoc analysis identifies energy samples taken during named events</p>
    <p>I Data can be averaged or viewed as a time series</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Synchronized Energy Calipers</p>
    <p>Calipers are available for user and kernel code:</p>
    <p>I Kernel prints TSC values to the syslog</p>
    <p>I User code prints TSC values to a log file</p>
    <p>I All logging is done to a RAM disk to reduce overhead (although this obviously increases RAM usage)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Software Stack</p>
    <p>Familiar and powerful environment:</p>
    <p>I Runs on Linux I Can test virtually any software with minimum instrumentation</p>
    <p>I Inline assembly compiled into source code I Or, getticks utility executed between binary workloads</p>
    <p>I Testing scripts facilitate consistent repetitions and batched jobs with reboots</p>
    <p>I Report format named by workload, separated into job components, and easily imported into analysis tools</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Portable and Flexible Framework</p>
    <p>The LEAP model is applicable to a wide variety of hardware. It requires only:</p>
    <p>I Stable, accessible clock source like a TSC</p>
    <p>I Instrumentation harness (wires, resistors, and DAQ)</p>
    <p>I Software tools  automating workloads, scripting, etc.</p>
    <p>We have already constructed:</p>
    <p>I Atom LEAP</p>
    <p>I Mobile LEAP</p>
    <p>I DSP LEAP</p>
    <p>I Dual Xeon LEAP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Active Testing and Development</p>
    <p>Ongoing research:</p>
    <p>I analysis of self-measurement cost</p>
    <p>I analysis of sample rate effects</p>
    <p>I improved instrumentation code</p>
    <p>I calibration workloads</p>
    <p>Stay tuned for information about a pilot program.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Undergraduate Research with Atom LEAP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Undergraduate Research with Atom LEAP</p>
    <p>Case study:</p>
    <p>I UCLA CS 188: Undergraduate Research Seminar</p>
    <p>I 25 graduates and undergraduates</p>
    <p>I 10-week quarter</p>
    <p>I Security-oriented projects</p>
    <p>I Atom LEAP</p>
    <p>Our goals:</p>
    <p>I Using LEAP to investigate Security vs. Energy Trade-offs</p>
    <p>I Teach performance measurement and analysis</p>
    <p>I Interactive group meetings instead of lectures</p>
    <p>I Emphasis on overall process and experience rather than novel results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introducing the Atom-Powered zPad by Banana Computer</p>
    <p>As employees of Banana Computers Development Lab, students were assigned to workgroups performing introductory investigations into five energy and security related concept areas for the new device:</p>
    <p>I Disk Encryption</p>
    <p>I Network Encryption</p>
    <p>I Power/Security Posture</p>
    <p>I Virtualization/Isolation</p>
    <p>I Offloading Computation</p>
    <p>Ill briefly discuss each area, along with some limited quantitative results.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>But First, A Disclaimer</p>
    <p>The following nuggets are meant more as teasers than solid gold results. Several issues combined to affect outcomes:</p>
    <p>I Experiment design and workload choice</p>
    <p>I Time constraints of quarter</p>
    <p>I Varying expertise of students</p>
    <p>I Experimental practice</p>
    <p>Well discuss some of these issues in the Lessons Learned portion of the talk.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I How much energy does Full Disk Encryption cost?</p>
    <p>I Should it be done in hardware or software?</p>
    <p>FDE disk did not arrive in time, so students investigated whether compression could reduce the cost of disk encryption.</p>
    <p>I Compared various filesystems and compression algorithms</p>
    <p>I Against various workloads</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CPU (J) HDD (J) RAM (J)</p>
    <p>Jo u le</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Hardware Component</p>
    <p>Energy Use of Kernel String Search by Compression Algorithm</p>
    <p>None LZO gzip</p>
    <p>xz</p>
    <p>Does compression save energy? If so, how much?</p>
    <p>I Compression significantly reduces cost of encrypted filesystem</p>
    <p>I Middle ground algorithm (gzip) is best</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I How much does encryption cost change by algorithm?</p>
    <p>I What if we chose algorithm based on current threat?</p>
    <p>I Students chose to engineer cipher changing in SSH</p>
    <p>I Workloads included basic microbenchmarks as well as expect-scripted interactive sessions and file transfers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CPU (J) HDD (J) RAM (J)</p>
    <p>Jo u le</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Hardware Component</p>
    <p>Energy Use of scp Encryption Cost by Cipher</p>
    <p>Does SCP cipher choice have an energy cost?</p>
    <p>I Both AES and Blowfish are significantly cheaper than 3DES</p>
    <p>I Blowfish is the winner (but this was only significant for RAM)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I How much energy do various sandboxing techniques cost? I VirtualBox I User-Mode Linux I chroot jails</p>
    <p>I What isolation is provided by each technique?</p>
    <p>I Students ran file utilities and GUI workloads scripted with the Linux Desktop Testing Project (LDTP)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Atom N330 Does not have hardware virtualization support!</p>
    <p>I 60-600% penalty to use VirtualBox! (Even with kernel plugin and multiple cores)</p>
    <p>I chroot jails inexpensive, but of limited value</p>
    <p>I Students could not get User-Mode Linux to work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I What if OS added energy dimension to Security and Data Sensitivity zones?</p>
    <p>I In high-security areas, the zPad could cut back on paranoid security</p>
    <p>I Or reschedule latency-tolerant tasks for later</p>
    <p>I Would this save energy?</p>
    <p>I What would such a facility look like?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CPU (J) HDD (J) RAM (J)</p>
    <p>Jo u le</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Hardware Component</p>
    <p>Energy Savings of Omitting Scan Option in ClamAV</p>
    <p>All No Archives No Images</p>
    <p>No Algorithms</p>
    <p>Energy-aware virus scanning</p>
    <p>I Students created the PowerSecZone daemon and API</p>
    <p>I Modified ClamAV to behave differently based on status</p>
    <p>I Number of files scanned more significant (in their test) than content or algorithm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I Can the zPad extend battery life by offloading security tasks?</p>
    <p>I Or does the offloading cost more than it saves?</p>
    <p>I Tested email signing, bittorrent, and more</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CPU (J) HDD (J) RAM (J) NETWORK (J)</p>
    <p>Jo u le</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Hardware Component</p>
    <p>Energy Savings of Offloading RSA-Signature of 256k Email</p>
    <p>No Offloading Offloading</p>
    <p>Offloading cryptographic signing to a compute server via WiFi</p>
    <p>I Saved a tremendous amount of power  around 40-50%</p>
    <p>I Even while paying to encrypt wifi with SSH</p>
    <p>I Not just shorter runtime  disk, RAM, and net (USB) used less watts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons Learned</p>
    <p>The course and Atom LEAP are a success, but there is much work to do!</p>
    <p>I Course design and management</p>
    <p>I Research value vs. practical issues</p>
    <p>I Statistics and experimental practice</p>
    <p>I LEAP Development</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons: Course Design</p>
    <p>I Atom LEAP technology worked really well</p>
    <p>I Designing projects and assigning students was a good choice</p>
    <p>I Group meetings a lot like actual grad school experience</p>
    <p>I Five different groups require a lot of oversight</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons: Research Value vs. Practical Issues</p>
    <p>I Help students prepare to succeed despite major setbacks</p>
    <p>I Decide if you want rock solid results or broader educational experience</p>
    <p>I Quarters are short and students (allegedly) have other classes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons: Statistics and Experimental Practice</p>
    <p>I The class definitely taught why evaluation is hard</p>
    <p>I We worked hard to try and control parameters and use real software</p>
    <p>I Not all students learned good experimental practice and this wasnt obvious until it was too late</p>
    <p>I Be explicit about experimental requirements: I require students to script workloads for repeatability I require analysis of workload scripts with students (not just</p>
    <p>experimental plan) I require statistical analysis, dont just recommend it</p>
    <p>I Test early, test often!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Atom LEAP Pilot Program</p>
    <p>We are improving LEAP technology and are preparing a distribution of the platform so that other researchers can build their own. Were creating documentation, packaging our tools, and preparing some community resources. To help iron out some kinks, we are considering a small pilot program. Interested? Email: pahp@cs.ucla.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgments</p>
    <p>I Intel, NSF</p>
    <p>I Sean Peisert (shepherd)</p>
    <p>I CSET committee, reviewers, USENIX</p>
    <p>I Dr. William J. Kaiser and Digvijay Singh (primary LEAP developers)</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
