<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Exercises for the Online Classroom with DETER</p>
    <p>Peter A. H. Peterson and Dr. Peter L. Reiher {pahp, reiher}@cs.ucla.edu</p>
    <p>Laboratory for Advanced Systems Research (LASR) University of California Los Angeles</p>
    <p>The 3rd Workshop on Cyber Security Experimentation and Test (CSET'10)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Points</p>
    <p>education.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Points</p>
    <p>security curriculum.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Project motivation  DETER as an educational platform  Our labs as a case study  Lessons Learned  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Project Motivation</p>
    <p>Homework for the online classroom  Requirements</p>
    <p>Same value as traditional homework  Easy to use without much face time</p>
    <p>Possibilities  Research Projects  Pen and paper coursework  Hands-on labs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Hands-on?</p>
    <p>Theory alone does not provide security  Real security is theory and practice, together</p>
    <p>The real world is complicated  Give a person a fish...  Real-world scenarios and tools add relevancy  Fundamental issues exemplified in real</p>
    <p>systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hands-on Approaches</p>
    <p>Applications  OWASP WebGoat, custom demonstrations, etc.  We wanted to use real software systems  Some topics hard to put in application form</p>
    <p>Virtualization  QEMU, VirtualBox, VMware</p>
    <p>Testbeds  In-house, Emulab, DETER</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Not Virtualization?</p>
    <p>Remote software support  Multi-gigabyte download  Bugfixes  Virtual networking  Cheating  Overhead of multiple hosts</p>
    <p>MITM Topology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DETER</p>
    <p>Dynamic physical networks</p>
    <p>Based on Emulab  ~300 machines  Internet-accessible  Public  Grouped resources  Security focused</p>
    <p>DETER Homepage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DETER Experiments</p>
    <p>Network Topology  Machines  Software</p>
    <p>DETER Topology designer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DETER Customization</p>
    <p>Boot-time customization</p>
    <p>Packages install from course archive on DETER</p>
    <p>Single repository  Stable platform and</p>
    <p>interface DETER customization scripts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DETER for Students</p>
    <p>Individual, private logins  Simple web control panel  Requires only a web browser and SSH  Built-in redundancy  Backups  Testbed support</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Any DETERrents?</p>
    <p>Shared testbed with finite resources  Only a minor inconvenience in practice</p>
    <p>Not local hardware  Overkill for some uses  Installation media not 100% secure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study</p>
    <p>Hands-on, practical online exercises  Courseware components</p>
    <p>DETER  Lab Manual  Lab software</p>
    <p>Five labs  Supporting a class on DETER</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lab Manual</p>
    <p>Wiki for CMS  Remote Access  Easy to update</p>
    <p>Read-only for students</p>
    <p>Internal/External links</p>
    <p>Lab manual homepage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lab Template</p>
    <p>Self-contained unit:  Overview  Technical discussion  External reading  The Story So Far...  Assignment</p>
    <p>Permissions Lab Table of Contents</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lab Descriptions</p>
    <p>Topics  Permissions and Firewalls  Exploits  Computer Forensics  Man-in-the-middle  Network intrusion detection systems</p>
    <p>All freely available open-source software  Most are standard security/networking tools</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Permissions &amp; Firewalls</p>
    <p>POSIX file system permissions  Including special permissions and sudo</p>
    <p>Stateful firewalls with iptables  Principle of Least Privilege  Deny by Default Design  Emphasis on unexpected interactions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exploits</p>
    <p>Buffer overflows  Pathname attacks  SQL Injection  Find, Exploit, Patch,</p>
    <p>Debrief  No Security in</p>
    <p>Obscurity  Failure or Works As</p>
    <p>Designed?</p>
    <p>/etc/shadow is not a memo!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Computer Forensics</p>
    <p>Security involves detective work  Three scenarios and disk images  Data recovery  Log analysis  Analysis and written report  Talk about exploratory learning!  Two sides to every story</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Man-in-the-middle</p>
    <p>ARP poisoning  Eavesdropping  Replay  Injection  Canonical MITM  Nonce design  The liability of</p>
    <p>abstraction The scene of the crime</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NIDS</p>
    <p>Intrusion Detection  Craft signatures  Real data  Security tuning  Highly context</p>
    <p>sensitive task  TCP trace analysis</p>
    <p>BASE interface</p>
    <p>(http://base.secureideas.net/)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Supporting DETER Classes</p>
    <p>Email is the #1 support tool, by far  Live office hours with</p>
    <p>Instant messaging  SSH tunneling  GNU screen</p>
    <p>Low-tech and works like a charm!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DETER Lessons</p>
    <p>We feel DETER superior to VMs for our needs  Especially:</p>
    <p>For online courses  For multi-node scenarios  When physical networks are important  For security-oriented projects</p>
    <p>Also great for brick and mortar classes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hands-on Lessons</p>
    <p>Excellent interest and response  Unexpected and creative answers  Exploration reaps rewards  Novices and experts both succeed  Theory illuminated by practice</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Work</p>
    <p>Flexibility and Repeatability issues  Reducing development cost</p>
    <p>Forensic Image Creator</p>
    <p>New labs  DETER-specific issues</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Q&amp;A</p>
    <p>Labs available at: http://lasr.cs.ucla.edu/classes/seclabs/</p>
    <p>{pahp, reiher}@cs.ucla.edu</p>
    <p>Contact us for more information.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
