<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Staging Package Deployment via</p>
    <p>Repository Management Chris St. Pierre</p>
    <p>Matt Hermanson</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background (Mostly) homogeneous environment Organizational structure Bcfg2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach Control what packages are available in the</p>
    <p>repository Define classes of repositories Upstream/Stable/Unstable Infra/HPSS/clusters</p>
    <p>Clients are always up-to-date with repository Centralized management</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other solutions Yum excludes Spacewalk Bcfg2 version specification Yum versionlock</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A solution: Pulp Part of Red Hats CloudForms Repos can be cloned efficiently Sync mediated by filters Manual manipulation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workflow Tiered repositories Upstream  daily sync from upstream Unstable  filtered sync from upstream Stable  filtered sync from unstable</p>
    <p>Custom repositories branched from upstream Package promotion separated by time and/or</p>
    <p>manual intervention</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workflow How do we implement filters Whitelist and blacklist packages</p>
    <p>Manual package promotion and removal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workflow Patches are promoted to stable after at least a</p>
    <p>week in unstable Security patches receive immediate attention Choosing Impactful packages Kernel and kernel-space Impacts customers Lustre and Infiniband related</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results Improved automation results in less overhead Increased compartmentalization</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Updates</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vulnerabilities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What's next? Sponge</p>
    <p>Web frontend for pulp  Django  More intuitive repository management  http://github.com/stpierre/sponge</p>
    <p>Apply an age attribute to individual packages Other packaging formats</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
