<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interdomain Routing as Socia l Choice</p>
    <p>Ronny R. Dakdouk, Semih Salihoglu, Hao Wang, Haiyong Xie, Yang Richard</p>
    <p>Yang</p>
    <p>Yale University</p>
    <p>IBC06</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>A social choice model for interdomain routin g</p>
    <p>Implications of the model</p>
    <p>Summary &amp; future work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Importance of Interdomain Routing  Stability</p>
    <p>excessive churn can cause router crash  Efficiency</p>
    <p>routes influence latency, loss rate, network congestion, etc.</p>
    <p>Why policy-based routing?  Domain autonomy: Autonomous System (AS)  Traffic engineering objectives: latency, cost, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BGP</p>
    <p>The de facto interdomain routing protocol of the c urrent Internet</p>
    <p>Support policy-based, path-vector routing  Path propagated from destination  Import &amp; export policy  BGP decision process selects path to use</p>
    <p>Local preference value  AS path length  and so on</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Policy Interactions Could Lead to Oscillations</p>
    <p>The BAD GADGET example: - 0 is the destination - the route selection policy of each AS is to prefer its counter clockwise neighbor</p>
    <p>Policy interaction causes routing instability !</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Previous Studies</p>
    <p>Policy Disputes (Dispute Wheels) may caus e instability [Griffien et al. 99]</p>
    <p>Economic/Business considerations may lea d to stability [Gao &amp; Rexford 00]</p>
    <p>Design incentive-compatible mechanisms [F eigenbaum et al. 02]</p>
    <p>Interdomain Routing for Traffic Engineering [Wang et al. 05]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Whats Missing</p>
    <p>Efficiency (Pareto optimality) Previous studies focus on BGP-like protocols</p>
    <p>Increasing concern about extension of BGP or replacement (next-generation protocol)</p>
    <p>Need a systematic methodology  Identify desired properties  Feasibility + Implementation</p>
    <p>Implementation in strategic settings  Autonomous System may execute the protocol</p>
    <p>strategically so long as the strategic actions do not violate the protocol specification!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our approach - A Black Box View of Interdomain Routing</p>
    <p>An interdomain routing system defines a m apping (a social choice rule)</p>
    <p>A protocol implements this mapping Social choice rule + Implementation</p>
    <p>Interdomain Routing Prot</p>
    <p>ocol</p>
    <p>.....</p>
    <p>..... AS 1 Preference</p>
    <p>AS N Preference</p>
    <p>AS 1 Route</p>
    <p>AS N Route</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In this Talk</p>
    <p>A social choice model for interdomain routin g</p>
    <p>Implications of the model  Some results from literature  A case study of BGP from the social choice p</p>
    <p>erspective</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>A social choice model for interdomain routin g</p>
    <p>Implications of the model</p>
    <p>Summary &amp; future work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Social Choice Model for Inter domain Routing</p>
    <p>Whats the set of players?  This is easy, the ASes are the players</p>
    <p>Whats the set common of outcomes?  Difficulty</p>
    <p>AS cares about its own egress route, possibly some other s routes, but not most others routes</p>
    <p>The theory requires a common set of outcomes  Solution</p>
    <p>Use routing trees or sink trees as the unifying set of outc omes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Routing Trees (Sink Trees)</p>
    <p>Each AS i = 1, 2, 3 has a route to the destination (AS 0) T(i) = AS is route to AS 0 Consistency requirement:</p>
    <p>If T(i) = (i, j) P, then T(j) = P A routing tree</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Realizable Routing Trees</p>
    <p>Not all topologically consistent routing trees are realizable</p>
    <p>Import/Export policies</p>
    <p>The common set of outcomes is the set of realizable routing trees</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Local Routing Policies as Preference Relations</p>
    <p>Why does this work?  Example: The preference of AS i depends on i</p>
    <p>ts own egress route only, say, r1 &gt; r2  The equivalent preference: AS i is indifferent t</p>
    <p>o all outcomes in which it has the same egre ss route</p>
    <p>E.g: If T1(i) = r1, T2(i) = r2, T3(i) = r2, then T1 &gt;i T2 =i T3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Local Routing Policies as Preference Relations (cont)</p>
    <p>Not just a match of theory Can express more general local policies</p>
    <p>Policies that depend not only on egress routes of the AS itself, but also incoming traffic patterns</p>
    <p>AS 1 prefers its customer 3 to send traffic through it, so T1 &gt;1 T2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Preference Domains</p>
    <p>All possible combinations of preferences of individual ASes  Traditional preference domains:</p>
    <p>Unrestricted domain  Unrestricted domain of strict preferences</p>
    <p>Two special domains in interdomain routing  The domain of unrestricted route preference  The domain of strict route preference</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Preference Domains (cont)</p>
    <p>The domain of unrestricted route preference  Requires: If T1(i) = T2(i), then T1 =i T2  Intuition: An AS cares only about egress routes</p>
    <p>The domain of strict route preference  Requires: If T1(i) = T2(i), then T1 =i T2  Also requires: if T1(i)  T2(i) then T1 i T2  Intuition: An AS further strictly differentiates</p>
    <p>between different routes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interdomain Social Choice Rule (S CR)</p>
    <p>An interdomain SCR is a correspondence: F: R=(R1,...,RN)  P  F(R)  A</p>
    <p>F incorporates the criteria of which routing t ree(s) are deemed optimal  F(R)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some Desirable Properties of In terdomain Routing SCR Non-emptiness</p>
    <p>All destinations are always reachable</p>
    <p>Uniqueness  No oscillations possible</p>
    <p>Unanimity (Strong) Pareto optimality</p>
    <p>Efficient routing decision</p>
    <p>Non-dictatorship  Retain AS autonomy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protocol as Implementation</p>
    <p>No central authority for interdomain routing  ASes execute routing protocols</p>
    <p>Protocol specifies syntax and semantics of me ssages  May also specify some actions that should be ta</p>
    <p>ken for some events  Still leaves room for policy-specific actions &lt;- str</p>
    <p>ategic behavior here! Therefore, a protocol can be modeled as imple</p>
    <p>mentation of an interdomain SCR</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>A social choice model for interdomain routin g</p>
    <p>Implications of the model</p>
    <p>Summary &amp; future work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some Results from Literature</p>
    <p>On the unrestricted domain  No non-empty SCR that is non-dictatorial, strate</p>
    <p>gy-proof, and has at least three possible routing trees at outcomes [Gibbards non-dominance the orem]</p>
    <p>On the unrestricted route preference domain  No non-constant, single-valued SCR that is Nas</p>
    <p>h-implementable  No strong-Pareto optimal and non-empty SCR th</p>
    <p>at is Nash-implementable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Case Study of BGP</p>
    <p>Assumption 1: ASes follow the greedy BGP r oute selection strategy</p>
    <p>Assumption 2: if T1(i) = T2(i) then either T1 (i) or T2(i) can be chosen</p>
    <p>BGP</p>
    <p>.....</p>
    <p>..... AS 1 Preference</p>
    <p>AS N Preference</p>
    <p>Routing Tree</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reverse engineering BGP</p>
    <p>Non-emptiness: X</p>
    <p>Uniqueness: X</p>
    <p>Unanimity:</p>
    <p>Strong Pareto Optimality:  only on strict route preference domain</p>
    <p>Non-dictatorship: X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BGP in strategic settings</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BGP is manipulable! If AS 1 and 3 follow the default BGP</p>
    <p>strategy, then AS 2 has a better strategy  If (3,0) is available, selects (2, 3, 0)  Otherwise, if (1, 0) is available, selects (2, 1, 0)  Otherwise, selects (2, 0)  The idea: AS 2 does not easily give AS 3 the</p>
    <p>chance of exploiting itself! Comparison of strategies for AS 2 (AS 1, 3</p>
    <p>follow default BGP strategy)  Greedy strategy: depend on timing, either (2,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Possibility of fixing BGP</p>
    <p>BGP is (theoretically) Nash implementable (actually, also strong implementable)</p>
    <p>But, only in a very simple game form The problem: the simple game form may no</p>
    <p>t be followed by the ASes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Viewed as a black-box, interdomain routing i s an SCR + implementation</p>
    <p>Strategic implementation impose stringent constraints on SCRs</p>
    <p>The greedy BGP strategy has its merit, but i s manipulable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Whats next?</p>
    <p>Design of next-generation protocol (the goal!)  Stability, optimality, incentive-compatible  Scalability  Scalability may serve as an aide (complexity</p>
    <p>may limit viable manipulation of the protocol)</p>
    <p>What is a reasonable preference domain to consider?</p>
    <p>A specialized theory of social choice &amp; implementation for routing?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Backup Slides</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Social Choice Rules (SCR)</p>
    <p>A set of players V = { 1,...,N } A set of outcomes  = { T1,,TM } Player i has its preference Ri over</p>
    <p>a complete, transitive binary relation</p>
    <p>Preference profile R = (R1,,RN)  R completely specifies the world state</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Preference Domains</p>
    <p>Preference domain P : a non-empty set of potential preference profiles  Why a domain?  The preference profile</p>
    <p>that will show up is not known in advance</p>
    <p>Some example domains:  Unrestricted domain  Unrestricted domain of strict</p>
    <p>preferences</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Social Choice Rule (SCR)</p>
    <p>An SCR is a correspondence: F: R=(R1,...,RN)  P  F(R)  A</p>
    <p>F incorporates the criteria of which outcomes are deemed optimal  F(R)</p>
    <p>Some example criteria:  Pareto Optimal (weak/strong/indifference)  (Non-)Dictatorship  Unanimity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SCR Implementation</p>
    <p>The designer of a SCR has his/her criteria of what outcomes should emerge given players preferences</p>
    <p>But, the designer does not know R  Question: What can the designer do to</p>
    <p>ensure his criteria get satisfied?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SCR Implementation</p>
    <p>Implementation: rules to elicit designers de sired outcome(s)</p>
    <p>Game Form (M,g)  M: Available action/message for players (e.g,</p>
    <p>cast ballots)  g: Rules (outcome function) to decide the out</p>
    <p>come based on action/message profile (e.g, majority wins)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SCR Implementation</p>
    <p>Given the rules, players will evaluate their s trategies (e.g, vote ones second favorite may be better, if the first is sure to lose)</p>
    <p>Solution Concepts: predict players strategic behaviors  Given (M,g,R), prediction is that players will pl</p>
    <p>ay action profiles S  A</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SCR Implementation</p>
    <p>The predicted outcome(s) OS(M,g,R) = { a  A |  m  S(M,g,R), s.t. g(m) =</p>
    <p>a }</p>
    <p>Implementation: predicted outcomes satisfy criteria OS(M,g,R) = F(R), for all R  P</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Protocol as Implementation FeasibilityDominant Strategy implementation</p>
    <p>Gibbards non-dominance theorem: No dominant strategy implementation of n on-dictatorial SCR w/ &gt;= 3 possible outco mes on unrestricted domain</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some Results from Literature</p>
    <p>On the unrestricted route preference domain)  Almost no non-empty and strong Pareto optimal SC</p>
    <p>R can be Nash implementable  If we want a unique routing solution (social choice fu</p>
    <p>nction, SCF), then only constant SCF can be Nash im plementable</p>
    <p>2nd result does not hold on a special domain which m ay be of interest in routing context (counter-example, dictatorship)</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
