<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reference Reference Reconciliation in Reconciliation in</p>
    <p>Complex Complex Information Information</p>
    <p>SpacesSpaces</p>
    <p>Erin GkdenizErin Gkdeniz 20047213752004721375</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reference ReconciliationReference Reconciliation  Introduction  Overview  Reconciliation Algorithm</p>
    <p>Dependency Graph  Exploiting the Dependency Graph  Enriching the References  Enforcing constraints</p>
    <p>Computing Similarity Scores  Experimantal Results  Related Work &amp; Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IntroductionIntroduction  Reference Reconciliation is the problem of</p>
    <p>different references in a dataset corresponding to the same real-world entity</p>
    <p>Because of mis-spellings,use of abbreviations, different naming conventions, naming variations over time.</p>
    <p>Mainly a matter for data integration concept</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IntroductionIntroduction  Most of the previous work considers,</p>
    <p>techniques for reconciling references to a single class.</p>
    <p>the data contains many attributes.</p>
    <p>In practice,  Complex Information spaces where instances</p>
    <p>of multiple classes  Rich relationships between the instances  Classes may have only few attributes  References typically have unknown att. values</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proposed Reconciliation Proposed Reconciliation AlgorithmAlgorithm</p>
    <p>Main motivation is Personal Information Management</p>
    <p>Supporting higher level browsing of information on ones desktop.(PIM)</p>
    <p>Examines data from sources on the desktop(e.g. Mails,files, spreadsheets)</p>
    <p>Rec. Algo. addresses several shortcomings of existing reference reconciliation algorithms that preclude their use in applications such as PIM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Personal Information Personal Information ManagementManagement</p>
    <p>Extract instances of multiple classes:  Person, Message, Article, Conference</p>
    <p>Extract associations :  senderOf, authorOf, publishedIn..</p>
    <p>Also, (aside from PIM)  Publications  Online product catalogs involves complex relationships between</p>
    <p>multiple entities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proposed Reconciliation Proposed Reconciliation AlgorithmAlgorithm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reconciliation AlgorithmReconciliation Algorithm  The key ideas of the algorithm :</p>
    <p>Extensive use of context information to provide evidence for reconciliation decisions  Example : for given 2 references algorithm</p>
    <p>also considers their co-authors and emails to decide whether to reconcile them</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reconciliation AlgorithmReconciliation Algorithm  Propagation of information between</p>
    <p>reconciliation decisions for different pairs of references  Example : when we decide to reconcile two</p>
    <p>papers , we obtain additional evidence for reconciling the person references to their authors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reconciliation AlgorithmReconciliation Algorithm  Addressing the lack of information in</p>
    <p>each reference by reference enrichment  Example : when we reconcile two person</p>
    <p>references, we gather different representations of the persons name , different mail addresses and can enlarge the co-author list.</p>
    <p>This enrichment can lead us to another reconciliations.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem DefinitionProblem Definition  A domain is modelled with a schema  Schema includes classes with</p>
    <p>attributes  Attributes :</p>
    <p>Atomic : Simple type like String, int  Associations : whose values are links</p>
    <p>to other instances.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SchemaSchema</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ReferencesReferences</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reconciliation ResultsReconciliation Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measures of QualityMeasures of Quality  Recall</p>
    <p>Measures the percentage of correctly reconciled pairs of references over all pairs of references that refer to the same entity.</p>
    <p>Precision  Measures the percentage of correctly</p>
    <p>reconciled pairs over all reconciled pairs of references</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reconciliation Algorithm Reconciliation Algorithm DetailsDetails</p>
    <p>First, costruct the dependency graph that captures the relationships between different reconciliation decisions</p>
    <p>Iteratively re-compute scores that are assigned to reconciliation decision nodes in the graph until a fixed point is reached.</p>
    <p>Finally, compute the transitive closure for the final reconciliation results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dependency GraphDependency Graph  We need to compute the similarity for</p>
    <p>every pair of references of the same class,  Therefore, atomic and association</p>
    <p>attributes similarities  A node in the graph represents the</p>
    <p>similarity between a pair of references  An edge represents the dependency</p>
    <p>between a pair of similarities</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Definitions of GraphDefinitions of Graph</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some DefinitionsSome Definitions  We call n an incoming neighbor of m,</p>
    <p>and m an outgoing neighbor of n .  If the similarity of a node n depends</p>
    <p>only whether the references in the node m are reconciled, then we say m is a boolean-valued neighbor of n</p>
    <p>If the similarity of n depends on the actual similarity value of node m, we call m is a real-valued neighbor of n</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Some DefinitionsSome Definitions  If the reconciliation of ms two references</p>
    <p>implies that the two references in n should also be reconciled, m is called ns strongboolean-valued neighbor.</p>
    <p>If the reconciliation of ms references only increases the similarity score of n, but does not directly imply reconciliation, m is called ns weak-boolean-valued neighbor.  e.g..The similarity score of 2 persons will increase given</p>
    <p>that they have email correspondence with the same person</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Graph Construction Graph Construction Step 1 Step 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Graph Construction Graph Construction Step 2 Step 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exploiting the Dependency Exploiting the Dependency GraphGraph</p>
    <p>Algorithm is based on propogating similarity decisions from node to node.</p>
    <p>e.g.. After deciding to reconcile articles a1 and a2 we should reconcile their associated conferences c1 and c2,</p>
    <p>Further, re-computation of the similarities of other papers that mention the conferences c1 and c2 is required</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NodesNodes  Merged : when a nodes similarity score is above a</p>
    <p>merge-threshold (it represents reconciled references)</p>
    <p>Active : if a nodes similarity is reconsidered  Inactive : the rest..  Initially all nodes representing the similarity</p>
    <p>between references are marked active  The nodes representing the similarity between</p>
    <p>atomic attribute values are marked merged or inactive depending on their associated similarity score</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NodesNodes  At a time one active node is selected</p>
    <p>and its similarity score is recomputed  If the new similarity score is above</p>
    <p>merge-threshold ,node is marked as merged</p>
    <p>Otherwise it is marked as inactive  In addition, all its neighbours with</p>
    <p>similarity scores below 1 is marked as active.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exploiting the Dependency Exploiting the Dependency GraphGraph</p>
    <p>This algorithm maintains a queue of active nodes containing all referencesimilarity nodes</p>
    <p>At every iteration, we compute the similarity score for the top node</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Enriching the ReferencesEnriching the References  After merging references r1 and r2, all the</p>
    <p>attributes of r2 can be considered as those of r1.</p>
    <p>When there is another reference r3, we choose the one with higher similarity.</p>
    <p>Example : connecting all neighbours of n we can remove node n.  if m gets new incoming neighbours and is not</p>
    <p>active, then m is inserted at the end of the queue</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Enforcing ConstraintsEnforcing Constraints  In many cases, negative evidences can</p>
    <p>contribute to the reconciliation process. (e.g. p2 &amp; p9)</p>
    <p>Constraint : is a rule enforcing that two references are quarenteed to be distinct.  e.g..the authors of one paper are distinct  Typically domain-dependent  Non-merge node : The two elements are</p>
    <p>quarenteed to be different and should never be reconciled</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Definitions Definitions (for constraints)(for constraints)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Computing Computing Similarity ScoresSimilarity Scores</p>
    <p>Given a node m=(r1,r2), the similarity function for m takes the similarity scores of ms neighbors as input and computes a score between 0 and 1</p>
    <p>The similarity score is sum of 3 components  Srvcontributed by real-valued incoming neigh.  Ssbcontributed by strong-boolean-valued neigh.  Swbcontributed by weak-boolean-valued neigh.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Real-Valued NeighborsReal-Valued Neighbors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Strong-boolean NeighborsStrong-boolean Neighbors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Weak-boolean NeighborsWeak-boolean Neighbors</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimantal ResultsExperimantal Results  Tests on two domains :</p>
    <p>Personal Information Management  Publication Portal</p>
    <p>Different 4 personal datasets is used Conference and Journals are merged(Venue class)</p>
    <p>Performance is measured by recall, precision and F-measure</p>
    <p>F-measure = 2*prec*recall / prec+recall</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DatasetsDatasets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ExperimentsExperiments  Proposed Algorithm is DEPGRAPH  General Reconciliation Approach :</p>
    <p>INDEPDEC  INDEPDEC compares person names</p>
    <p>and emails independently and combines the results for reference similarity without exploiting the dependencies between individual reconciliation decisions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ExperimentsExperiments  DEPGRAPH ,in addition, compares the</p>
    <p>names with the email accounts,considers the articles authored by the persons, counts the common people appearing in the coauthor or email-contact lists,applies reconciliation propogation and reference enrichment and enforces constraints.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ResultsResults</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment Results Experiment Results  DEPGRAPH obtains higher precision and recall for</p>
    <p>both person and venue references.  It improved recall for venue ref. by %18.6</p>
    <p>for person ref. by %5.4 =======</p>
    <p>Secondly, examine person references  Dividing dataset into two  One contains person ref.extracted only from</p>
    <p>emails(PEmail)  One contains person ref. extracted from articles</p>
    <p>(PArticle)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ResultsResults</p>
    <p>DEPGRAPH improves recall by %30.7 on the article datasets by %7.6 on the email datasets by %5.4 on the full datasets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions &amp; Future WorkConclusions &amp; Future Work  Many applications are based on</p>
    <p>information spaces that involve multiple classes and rich relationships between instances</p>
    <p>Thus far studies are in the context of reconciling ref. of a single class.</p>
    <p>This paper fills in this gap by proposing a generic framework</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions &amp; Future WorkConclusions &amp; Future Work  This framework influences later similarity</p>
    <p>computation with early reconciliation decisions, and enriches references by instant merging.</p>
    <p>Proposed algorithm obtains high precision and recall on test datasets.</p>
    <p>In the future,  An efficient incremental reconciliation approach  Learning techniques based on the framework</p>
    <p>could be considered.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>QuestionsQuestions</p>
    <p>???</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
