<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy-Sensitive VM Retrospection</p>
    <p>Wolfgang Richter1, Glenn Ammons3, Jan Harkes1, Adam Goode4, Nilton Bila2, Eyal de Lara2, Vasanth Bala3, Mahadev Satyanarayanan1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introspection vs Retrospection</p>
    <p>Examine active state of VM during execution</p>
    <p>Examine historical state of VMs and their snapshots</p>
    <p>VM Instance A</p>
    <p>Examine live logs</p>
    <p>A' A1 A2</p>
    <p>B' B1 B2</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>Examine all historic logs A*</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Change: Shift in Thinking</p>
    <p>Traditionally a VM == executable content  VM Image Libraries break this paradigm  Think of VMs as big data  What can we do with them?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Change: Shift in Thinking</p>
    <p>Traditionally a VM == executable content  VM Image Libraries break this paradigm  Think of VMs as big data  What can we do with them? Apple's Time Machine over all VM instances including their</p>
    <p>complete snapshotted history</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Retrospection</p>
    <p>Deep search over historical VM data  Snapshots, Virtual Disks,</p>
    <p>Help with:  Debugging and troubleshooting  Legal establishment of data/code provenance  Malware tracking  License violations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deep Search?</p>
    <p>Search content of files  Pictures, Documents, Binary files</p>
    <p>Enable proprietary plugins  Adobe, MS Office, Norton, SW Discovery Tools</p>
    <p>While respecting privacy...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Forensics - Before</p>
    <p>Compromised VM Quarantined VM</p>
    <p>Quarantined VM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Forensics - After</p>
    <p>Compromised VM Quarantined VM</p>
    <p>Quarantined VM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Forensics - After</p>
    <p>Compromised VM Quarantined VM</p>
    <p>Quarantined VM</p>
    <p>Unified interface for searching historic state: uncover suspicious log entries, infected binaries, etc. at once</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Copyright</p>
    <p>Examine a set of instances  Retrospect to find history of transforms  Provide evidence in court  Multiple companies with similar cloud</p>
    <p>infrastructures supporting retrospection could perform the same queries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy via Cryptography</p>
    <p>Complete trust, if encrypted keys shared  Some trust, key escrow service  No trust, no external search infrastructure  Per-file, per-directory, per-partition</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Principles</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Retrospection</p>
    <p>VMs become big data  New opportunities with deep search over</p>
    <p>historical VM data  Retrospection is the unifying mechanism</p>
    <p>for examining historical VM data  Nanuk  Our implementation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Nanuk</p>
    <p>DataretrieverDataretriever ClientClient</p>
    <p>ServerServer</p>
    <p>ServerServer</p>
    <p>ServerServer</p>
    <p>ScopeScope</p>
    <p>MirageMirage</p>
    <p>MySQLMySQL</p>
    <p>DataretrieverDataretriever</p>
    <p>Scope Definition</p>
    <p>Query+Cookie Metadata Query</p>
    <p>Raw Data</p>
    <p>Request Objects</p>
    <p>DataretrieverDataretriever</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IBM Research Mirage</p>
    <p>Virtual Image Library</p>
    <p>File-level deduplication  Files are referenced by SHA-1</p>
    <p>Reads VM Image partitions and file systems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>OpenDiamond Platform</p>
    <p>Distributed, interactive, unindexed search</p>
    <p>Focuses on the principle of early discard</p>
    <p>Enables arbitrary search queries  Arbitrary x86 binary code as query primitives</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Achievable Efficient Retrospection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Effect of Deduplication - Bytes</p>
    <p>Reduce Storage Space</p>
    <p>Data from 78 NCSU VCL VM Images based on Windows XP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reduce Search Time</p>
    <p>Data from 78 NCSU VCL VM Images based on Windows XP</p>
    <p>Effect of Deduplication - Files</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
