<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prt  Voter with Confirmation Codes</p>
    <p>EVT/WOTE San Francisco 2011</p>
    <p>P Y A Ryan 1</p>
    <p>Peter Y A Ryan  Universit du Luxembourg</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>End-to-end verifiable voting.</p>
    <p>Outline of Prt  Voter (polling station).</p>
    <p>Outline of Pretty Good Democracy (internet).</p>
    <p>Prt  Voter with confirmation codes (polling station).</p>
    <p>Discussion.</p>
    <p>Conclusions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Design Philosophy</p>
    <p>Verify the election, not the system!</p>
    <p>Assurance should be based on transparency and auditability, not on claims of correctness of code.</p>
    <p>We transform the problem to one of verifying the correctness of a mathematical computation.</p>
    <p>As simple and understandable as possible.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Requirements</p>
    <p>Integrity/accuracy: the count accurately reflects votes cast.</p>
    <p>Ballot secrecy: the way a voter cast their vote should only be known to the voter.</p>
    <p>Coercion resistance: voters cannot prove to a third party how they voted, even if they cooperate with the coercer.</p>
    <p>Availability, accessibility etc. etc....</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>E2E verifiability</p>
    <p>Voters can confirm that their vote is accurately counted, without violating ballot secrecy.</p>
    <p>Voters are provided with an encrypted ballot.</p>
    <p>These ballots are posted to a secure web bulletin board. Voters can verify that their receipt is correctly posted.</p>
    <p>A (universally) verifiable, anonymising tabulation is performed on the receipts.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prt  Voter</p>
    <p>Uses familiar, paper ballot forms.  The candidate list is independently</p>
    <p>randomised on each ballot form.  Information defining the candidate order</p>
    <p>is encrypted on the ballot (or committed to the WBB).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prt  Voter Ballot</p>
    <p>Obelix</p>
    <p>Idefix</p>
    <p>Abraracourix</p>
    <p>Asterix</p>
    <p>Panaromix</p>
    <p>Falbala</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The voting ceremony</p>
    <p>Voter enters the polling station, pre-registers and takes a ballot form at random, sealed in an envelope.</p>
    <p>Enters a booth, extracts the ballot, marks her choice and destroys the Left Hand portion.</p>
    <p>She leaves the booth with the receipt (the RH portion), and re-registers with an official.</p>
    <p>The receipt is scanned, digitally signed and franked and posted to the bulletin board.</p>
    <p>The voter heads off clutching her receipt.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tabulation</p>
    <p>Voters can visit the WBB and confirm that their receipt appears correctly.</p>
    <p>A verifiable, anonymising mix or homomorphic tabulation is performed on the posted receipts.</p>
    <p>All steps are subject to (random) audits.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Remarks</p>
    <p>The receipt reveals nothing about the vote</p>
    <p>Voter experience simple and familiar.</p>
    <p>Votes are not directly encrypted, hence voters do not communicate their choice to a device. This neatly sidesteps many side-channel threats.</p>
    <p>Ballot auditing rather clean.</p>
    <p>Can be adapted to deal with ranked voting, AV etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Code Voting</p>
    <p>&quot; Due to Chaum (2001?).</p>
    <p>&quot; Voters get a code sheet with random voting and acknowledgement codes against each candidate.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Code sheet</p>
    <p>Odin  74522  89043  Thor 22916  60344  Hel 89321  6754</p>
    <p>Forseti  29945  59684  39772510</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voting</p>
    <p>&quot; Voter logs onto a server and provides the serial number of their code sheet along with the voting code for their candidate of choice.</p>
    <p>&quot; The server returns the corresponding ack code.</p>
    <p>&quot; The ack code serves to authenticate the server and confirm receipt of the correct code, but non end-to-end verifiability.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pretty Good Democracy</p>
    <p>Code voting side-steps many insecurities of the internet but does not provide E2E verifiability.</p>
    <p>Knowledge of the codes is secret shared amongst a set of Trustees.</p>
    <p>For receipt-freeness we use a single ack code per code sheet.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PGD Code sheet  Candidate Voting code Asterix 4098 Idefix 3990 Obelix 6994 Panoramix 2569 Serial number 49950284926 Acknowledgement code 4482094</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pretty Good Democracy</p>
    <p>Voter logs on and provides the serial number and vote code for the candidate of choice.</p>
    <p>A threshold set of the trustees cooperate to validate the code, register it and reveal the ack code.</p>
    <p>Receipt of the correct ack code confirms that the correct vote code has been registered by a threshold set of the Trustees.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security properties</p>
    <p>Tabulation much as in Prt  Voter.</p>
    <p>Violation of secrecy of codes can violate accuracy (undetectably).</p>
    <p>Need to assume absence of colluding threshold set of trustees.</p>
    <p>Receipt free due to single ack code per code sheet.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prt  Voter with Confirmation Codes</p>
    <p>&quot; Combines ideas from Prt  Voter and PGD: introduce a PGD style confirmation code into Prt  Voter.</p>
    <p>&quot; The vote is registered by a threshold set of trustees at the time of casting and a code returned immediately.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Set-up</p>
    <p>&quot; Initially we need to set up a table each row of which corresponds to a ballot:</p>
    <p>&quot; i, ({CCi1}, {i(1)}), ({CCi2, {i(2)}),.....({CCin},{i(n)})</p>
    <p>&quot; Each cell is a pair: an encryption of the code and of a candidate index.</p>
    <p>&quot; The candidate indices are permuted in each row.</p>
    <p>&quot; Audit for consistency.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example &quot; 488213, ({4723}, {2}), ({9022},{1}), ({3726},{4}), ({2551},{3})</p>
    <p>Candidate Vote Confirmation  Idefix 4723 Asterix  9022</p>
    <p>Pamoramix 3726  Obelix 2551</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ballot forms</p>
    <p>Thor</p>
    <p>Odin</p>
    <p>Forseti</p>
    <p>Hermod</p>
    <p>x 384922</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The ceremony</p>
    <p>&quot; In the booth, the voter marks her x and destroys the LH portion as usual, leaving the scratch strips intact.</p>
    <p>&quot; She then casts her vote, which is registered by the trustees and the confirmation code returned.</p>
    <p>&quot; She reveals the appropriate code on the ballot and checks that it matches.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tabulation</p>
    <p>&quot; Once the election is over, the flagged, encrypted candidate indices are extracted and tabulated in the usual, verifiable fashion.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>&quot; Voters dont now have to visit the WBB, but still have the option.</p>
    <p>&quot; Note: distinct codes for each candidate.</p>
    <p>&quot; Could we drop the receipt altogether?</p>
    <p>&quot; More convenient.</p>
    <p>&quot; More conducive of trust?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distributed construction</p>
    <p>&quot; We have a nice distributed construction for the information posted to the WBB such that no single entities knows any codes.</p>
    <p>&quot; But the need to decrypt, print and distribute this information via the code sheets undermines this.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distributed printing</p>
    <p>&quot; Is there an effective way of distributing the printing of the codes and candidates?</p>
    <p>&quot; Could use Alex et als How to print a secret techniques.</p>
    <p>&quot; In the paper I suggest having a different Clerk for each digit of the codes, using scratch strips or invisible ink techniques.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>&quot; Potentially a interesting extension of Prt  Voter.</p>
    <p>&quot; Arguably more secure, more convenient, most conducive of trust.</p>
    <p>&quot; Could we dispense with receipts, perhaps with a VEPAT (hash chained?) and/or use a Scantegrity approach?</p>
    <p>&quot; Link to VoteBox?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks to</p>
    <p>&quot; Steve Schneider, David Chaum, Ron Rivest, James Heather, Vanessa Teague, Chris Culnane, Joson Zia,.....</p>
    <p>&quot; Fonds Nationale de Research (FNR) Luxembourg</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
