<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>COPE: Traffic Engineering COPE: Traffic Engineering in Dynamic Networksin Dynamic Networks Hao Wang, Hao Wang, HaiyongHaiyong Xie, Xie, LiliLili QiuQiu,,</p>
    <p>Yang Richard Yang, Yang Richard Yang, Yin ZhangYin Zhang, Albert Greenberg, Albert Greenberg Yale UniversityYale University UT AustinUT Austin</p>
    <p>AT&amp;T Labs AT&amp;T Labs -- ResearchResearch ACM SIGCOMM 2006ACM SIGCOMM 2006</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation  High cost of network assets &amp; highly competitive nature of ISP market  Routing influences efficiency of network resource utilization</p>
    <p>Latency, loss rate, congestion,   Two components  Understand traffic demands  Configure routing protocols</p>
    <p>This paper focuses on intra-domain TE  But the basic approach may also apply in inter-domain TE and network optimization in general</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Internet traffic is highly unpredictable!  Can be relatively stable most of the time   However, usually contains spikes that ramp up extremely quickly</p>
    <p>We identified sudden traffic spikes in the traces of several networks  Unpredictable traffic variations have been observed and studied by other researchers</p>
    <p>[ Teixeira et al. 04, Uhlig &amp; Bonaventure 02, Xu et al. 05 ]  Confirmed by operators of several large networks via email survey  Abrupt traffic changes often occur when service is most valuable!</p>
    <p>Many possible causes for traffic unpredictability  Worms/viruses, DoS attacks, flash crowds, BGP routing changes</p>
    <p>[ Teixeira et al. 05, Agarwal et al. 05 ], failures in other networks, load balancing by multihomed customers, TE by peers   TE needs to handle unpredictable traffic</p>
    <p>Otherwise, links and/or routers may get unnecessarily overloaded  Long delay, high loss, reduced throughput, violation of SLA</p>
    <p>Customers can remember bad experiences really well</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Off-line:  Single predicted TM [ Sharad et al. 05 ]  Multiple predicted TMs [ Zhang et al. 05 ]</p>
    <p>On-line: MATE [ Elwalid et al. 01 ] &amp; TeXCP [ Kandula et al. 05 ]  Pro: Works great when traffic is predictable  Con: May pay a high penalty when real traffic deviates substantially from the prediction</p>
    <p>Oblivious routing  Examples:</p>
    <p>Oblivious routing [ Racke 02, Azar et al. 03, Applegate et al. 03 ]  Valiant load-balancing [ Kodialam et al. 05, Zhang &amp; McKeown 04 ]</p>
    <p>Pro: Provides worst-case performance bounds  Con: May be sub-optimal for normal traffic</p>
    <p>The optimal oblivious ratio of several real network topologies studied in [Applegate et al 03] is ~2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>Bound for set X</p>
    <p>Optimize for set C</p>
    <p>minf maxdC PC(f, d)s.t. (1) f is a routing (2) xX: PX(f, x)  PE</p>
    <p>C: common-case (predicted) TMs X: all TMs of interest PC(f,d): common-case penalty function PX(f,x): worst-case penalty function PE: penalty envelope</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>V: set of routers  E: set of network links</p>
    <p>Traffic matrices (TMs)  A TM is a set of demands: d = { dab | a,b  V }  dab: traffic demand from a to b  Can extend to point-to-multipoint demands</p>
    <p>MPLS-style, link-based routing  f = { fab(i,j) | a,b  V, (i,j)  E }  fab(i,j) : the fraction of demand from a to b (i.e., dab) that is routed through link (i,j)  Paper includes ideas on how to approximate OSPFstyle (i.e., shortest path implementable) routing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimal Utilization</p>
    <p>Performance Ratio ),(min)(</p>
    <p>routing a is dfUdOU</p>
    <p>f =</p>
    <p>)(</p>
    <p>),( ),(</p>
    <p>dOU</p>
    <p>dfU dfPR =</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>Vba ijabab</p>
    <p>Eji cjifddfU</p>
    <p>, ),(</p>
    <p>/),(max),(</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C: convex hull of multiple past TMs  A linear predictor predicts the next TM as a convex combination of past TMs (e.g., EWMA)  Aggregation of all possible linear predictors  the convex hull</p>
    <p>X: all possible non-negative TMs  Can add access capacity constraints or use a bigger convex hull</p>
    <p>PC(f,d): penalty function for common cases maximum link utilization: U(f,d)  performance ratio: PR(f,d)</p>
    <p>PX(f,x): penalty function for worst cases performance ratio: PR(f,x) PE: penalty envelope</p>
    <p>PE =  minf maxxX PX(f,x)  1 controls the size of PE w.r.t. the optimal worst-case penalty</p>
    <p>=1  oblivious routing  =  prediction-based TE</p>
    <p>minf maxdC PC(f, d) s.t. (1) f is a routing; and (2) xX: PC(f, x)  PE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>solving a linear program (LP)  Common-case optimization</p>
    <p>Common case: convex hull of multiple past TMs  All TMs in previous day + same/previous days in last week</p>
    <p>Minimize either MLU or PR over the convex hull  Penalty envelope</p>
    <p>Bounded PR over all possible nonnegative TMs  See paper for details of our LP formulation</p>
    <p>detection of significant changes in TM)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prediction-based TE</p>
    <p>Best common-case +</p>
    <p>Poor worst-case Oblivious Routing</p>
    <p>Poor common-case +</p>
    <p>Best worst-case COPE</p>
    <p>Good common-case +</p>
    <p>Bounded worst-case</p>
    <p>Spectrum of TE with unpredictable traffic</p>
    <p>Position controllable by penalty envelope</p>
    <p>There are enough unexpected cases  Penalty envelope is required The worst unexpected case too unlikely to occur Too wasteful to optimize for the worst-case (at the cost of poor common-case performance)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>COPE: COPE with PC(f,d) = PR(f,d) (i.e. performance ratio)  COPE-MLU: COPE with PC(f,d) = U(f,d) (i.e. max link utilization)  Oblivious routing: minf maxxPR(f,x) ( COPE with =1)  Dynamic: optimize routing for TM in previous interval  Peak: peak interval of previous day + prev/same days in last week  Multi: all intervals in previous day + prev/same days in last week  Optimal: requires an oracle</p>
    <p>Dataset  US-ISP</p>
    <p>hourly PoP-level TMs for a tier-1 ISP (1 month in 2005)  Optimal oblivious ratio: 2.045; default penalty envelope: 2.5</p>
    <p>Abilene  5-min router-level TMs on Abilene (6 months: Mar  Sep. 2004)  Optimal oblivious ratio: 1.853; default penalty envelope: 2.0</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>P e</p>
    <p>rf o</p>
    <p>rm a</p>
    <p>n ce</p>
    <p>r a</p>
    <p>tio</p>
    <p>Intervals sorted by performance ratio</p>
    <p>multi peak dynamic oblivious COPE-MLU COPE</p>
    <p>Common cases: COPE is close to optimal/dynamic and much better than others Unexpected cases: COPE beats even OR and is much better than others</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>M L</p>
    <p>U a</p>
    <p>ft e</p>
    <p>r n</p>
    <p>o rm</p>
    <p>a liz</p>
    <p>a tio</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>Interval</p>
    <p>multi peak dynamic oblivious COPE-MLU COPE</p>
    <p>Common cases: COPE is close to optimal/dynamic and much better than others Unexpected cases: COPE beats even OR and is much better than others</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>P e rf</p>
    <p>o rm</p>
    <p>a n ce</p>
    <p>r a tio</p>
    <p>Sorted interval</p>
    <p>multi peak</p>
    <p>dynamic oblivious</p>
    <p>COPE</p>
    <p>Common cases: COPE is close to optimal/dynamic and much better than others Unexpected cases: COPE is close to OR and much better than others</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>M L U</p>
    <p>Interval</p>
    <p>multi peak</p>
    <p>dynamic oblivious</p>
    <p>COPE optimal</p>
    <p>Common cases: COPE is close to optimal/dynamic and much better than others</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>M L U</p>
    <p>Interval</p>
    <p>multi peak</p>
    <p>dynamic oblivious</p>
    <p>COPE optimal</p>
    <p>Unexpected cases: COPE is close to OR and much better than others</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>P e</p>
    <p>rf o</p>
    <p>rm a</p>
    <p>n ce</p>
    <p>r a</p>
    <p>tio</p>
    <p>Intervals sorted by performance ratio</p>
    <p>oblivious PE = 2.2 PE = 2.4 PE = 2.6 PE = 2.8</p>
    <p>COPE is insensitive to PE; even a small margin in PE can significantly improve the common-case performance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Changes in availability of interdomain routes can cause significant shifts of traffic within the domain  E.g. when a peering link fails, all traffic through that link is rerouted</p>
    <p>Challenges  Point-to-multipoint demands</p>
    <p>need to find splitting ratios among exit points  The set of exit points may change</p>
    <p>topology itself is dynamic  Too many prefixes</p>
    <p>cannot enumerate all possible exit point changes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>intradomain topology peer</p>
    <p>peerpeer</p>
    <p>peer</p>
    <p>virtual</p>
    <p>virtual</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>COPE can significantly limit the impact of peering link failures</p>
    <p>M L U</p>
    <p>Interval</p>
    <p>link 11 and 15 fail</p>
    <p>COPE PE=2.2, with failures COPE PE=2.2, no failure optimal, with failures optimal, no failure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Common cases: close to optimal; much better than oblivious routing and prediction-based TE with comparable overhead  Unexpected cases: much better than prediction-based TE, and sometimes may beat oblivious routing  COPE is insensitive to the size of the penalty envelope; even a small margin in PE improves common-case performance a lot  COPE can be extended to cope with interdomain routes</p>
    <p>Lots of ongoing &amp; future work  Efficient implementation of COPE  COPE with MPLS and VPN  COPE with OSPF  COPE with online TE  COPE for other network optimization problems</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!Thank you!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
