<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2007 AT&amp;T Intellectual Property. All rights reserved. AT&amp;T and the AT&amp;T logo are trademarks of AT&amp;T Intellectual Property.</p>
    <p>Proactive Network Management of IPTV Networks</p>
    <p>Rakesh K. Sinha, K. K. Ramakrishnan, Bob Doverspike, Dahai Xu, Jorge Pastor, Aman Shaikh,</p>
    <p>Seungjoon Lee, Chris Chase AT&amp;T Labs - Research, New Jersey, USA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Page 3</p>
    <p>IPTV service</p>
    <p>High visibility: direct customer impact.</p>
    <p>Service is very sensitive to delay and packet loss</p>
    <p>Congestion on links -&gt; packet loss-&gt; video quality impairment</p>
    <p>Need to tackle multiple failures, which are not very rare.</p>
    <p>Higher layer mechanisms - FEC, retransmission based recovery</p>
    <p>of lost packets - can handle (with reasonable delays), burst</p>
    <p>losses of about 50 milliseconds</p>
    <p>Fast restoration is critical</p>
    <p>AT&amp;Ts IPTV service:</p>
    <p>2+ million customers;</p>
    <p>Triple play: video, internet, and voice</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Page 4</p>
    <p>Network backbone</p>
    <p>One Video hub office (VHO) per metro area</p>
    <p>National content is acquired at Super hub office (SHO)</p>
    <p>Content is distributed to VHOs using single source specific mode multicast tree</p>
    <p>(PIM-SSM)</p>
    <p>a separate multicast tree</p>
    <p>for each channel</p>
    <p>SHO</p>
    <p>VHO</p>
    <p>VHO</p>
    <p>VHO VHO</p>
    <p>VHO</p>
    <p>VHO</p>
    <p>VHO</p>
    <p>VHO</p>
    <p>VHO</p>
    <p>VHO</p>
    <p>S/VHO = Super/Video Hub Office</p>
    <p>Router</p>
    <p>Metro Intermediate Office</p>
    <p>Video Serving Office</p>
    <p>DSLAM = Digital Subscriber</p>
    <p>Loop Access Multiplexer</p>
    <p>RG = Residential Gateway Metro Area</p>
    <p>RG Set-top</p>
    <p>Box</p>
    <p>RG</p>
    <p>Long Distance</p>
    <p>Backbone</p>
    <p>Access</p>
    <p>Details in 2009</p>
    <p>IEEE Internet</p>
    <p>Computing Paper</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Local Link-Based Fast Re-Route (FRR)</p>
    <p>Backup Path</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>Virtual link between AB with virtual interfaces</p>
    <p>Virtual link consists of both a primary and backup</p>
    <p>Path: The OSPF topology (and multicast tree) built on top of the</p>
    <p>virtual link</p>
    <p>A</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>FRR example on virtual link (10,11)</p>
    <p>Back up path</p>
    <p>Normal traffic forwarded on primary link (10,11)</p>
    <p>When primary link fails, link layer mechanism using FRR</p>
    <p>switches to backup</p>
    <p>No OSPF/PIM-SSM convergence required</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Page 9</p>
    <p>Challenges in implementing IPTV services</p>
    <p>Due to high sensitivity of IPTV service, must plan for</p>
    <p>multiple, concurrent outages</p>
    <p>In a study of link outages over 4 months, we found that</p>
    <p>in 17% of cases, at least 2 links were down concurrently.</p>
    <p>IP Multicast results in a very efficient network -&gt; smaller</p>
    <p>overbuild capacity -&gt; requires more careful multi-layer</p>
    <p>restoration planning, design, and management.</p>
    <p>Because FRR is invisible to IGP/PIM, these protocols can</p>
    <p>potentially interact in a bad way creating congestion in</p>
    <p>the network.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our approach</p>
    <p>Be proactive in dealing with the effect of multiple failures</p>
    <p>Maintenance activity is often planned far in advance and is often</p>
    <p>agnostic to real-time network state</p>
    <p>We coordinate planned network maintenance activity with real</p>
    <p>time network state.</p>
    <p>Need a comprehensive view across many different network layers.</p>
    <p>Example (details later): an SNMP based tool can tell when a link is</p>
    <p>congested but by looking at a variety of data sources, we can</p>
    <p>pinpoint to one of 3 or 4 different reasons for link congestion.</p>
    <p>Page 10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dealing w/ Network component failures</p>
    <p>(Reactive) Use FRR whenever backup path is available; Use IGP otherwise. There is potential for congestion with multiple failures</p>
    <p>overlap of two FRR paths, OR</p>
    <p>overlap of FRR path with multicast tree.</p>
    <p>(Proactive) Avoid potential overlap by using a cross-layer approach to reconfigure the multicast tree after a successful FRR event. [COMSNETS 2010]</p>
    <p>Another issue: Alert the operator to any changes in network state. E.g,</p>
    <p>An FRR event may reroute traffic to a different set of links</p>
    <p>A PIM re-convergence may alter the multicast tree</p>
    <p>Page 11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dealing w/ Network maintenance</p>
    <p>Maintenance activity is often planned far in advance and is</p>
    <p>often agnostic to real-time network state</p>
    <p>Coordinate planned network maintenance activity with</p>
    <p>real-time network state. Examples</p>
    <p>any link carrying traffic should not have a maintenance</p>
    <p>activity</p>
    <p>IPTV networks are typically shared as an access network</p>
    <p>providing Internet connectivity to customers and a pair of</p>
    <p>routers within a metro office maintain BGP sessions with ISP</p>
    <p>edge routers. If one of these BGP sessions is down, its</p>
    <p>mate router should not be touched.</p>
    <p>Page 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Page 13</p>
    <p>Pinpoint the cause of link congestion</p>
    <p>An SNMP based tool can point out which links are</p>
    <p>congested. However knowing the underlying cause can for</p>
    <p>congestion gives an insight in how to fix it.</p>
    <p>Holistic view needed to disambiguate cause</p>
    <p>Different ways that a link can get congested</p>
    <p>Oversubscribed? Too many TV channels/VoD</p>
    <p>Overlap between different FRR paths and/or multicast tree</p>
    <p>Lots of parallel links between offices and sometimes we can get</p>
    <p>load imbalance: high bandwidth channels on one link and low</p>
    <p>bandwidth channels on the other link.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Page 14</p>
    <p>Multiple views of the network</p>
    <p>NetDB tool (developed at AT&amp;T Research): parses router configuration files to build failure-free topology</p>
    <p>OSPFMon tool (developed at AT&amp;T Research): establishes a partial adjacency with one or more routers to receive LSAs and create a real-time topology</p>
    <p>FRR is invisible to IGP and may appear self-healing but it alters the network state significantly</p>
    <p>Need logic to infer that successful FRR has happened</p>
    <p>Use NetDB to get links in the back-up path being used</p>
    <p>MRTG tool: collects link utilizations</p>
    <p>BGP reachability: compare number of routes to a threshold; also monitor various alarms</p>
    <p>Operations Support System: list of links scheduled to undergo maintenance during the next 24 hours.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Page 15</p>
    <p>Web based visualization tool: Birdseye</p>
    <p>Synthesizes and interprets data from a variety of data sources to obtain a comprehensive network view. Our overall philosophy is to</p>
    <p>Maintain an idealized, failure-free state</p>
    <p>List of links and routers, link capacities, multicast tree, FRR backup paths, etc.</p>
    <p>Maintain real-time state</p>
    <p>Real-time topology, link utilization, BGP reachability, database of links planned for scheduled maintenance</p>
    <p>Either directly from tools or by interpreting data from multiple tools.</p>
    <p>Parse the differences and show necessary alerts to the operator</p>
    <p>Has been in use in AT&amp;T Network Operations Center for 1+ yr.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Page 16</p>
    <p>Sample GUI snapshot: triple link failure</p>
    <p>TO PROTECT PROPRIETARY</p>
    <p>INFORMATION THIS DOES NOT</p>
    <p>DEPICT AN ACTUAL NETWORK</p>
    <p>OR OUTAGE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Page 17</p>
    <p>Sample snapshot: updated multicast tree</p>
    <p>TO PROTECT PROPRIETARY</p>
    <p>INFORMATION THIS DOES NOT</p>
    <p>DEPICT AN ACTUAL NETWORK</p>
    <p>OR OUTAGE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Page 18</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>IPTV services have high sensitivity to impairments and high</p>
    <p>visibility in terms of customer impact</p>
    <p>Need careful designing of network protocols to deal with</p>
    <p>multiple failures</p>
    <p>Operators need a comprehensive view of the network</p>
    <p>Our Birdseye tool distills network data from multiple AT&amp;T</p>
    <p>developed systems and public tools and domain knowledge of</p>
    <p>networking protocols to compile a holistic view to the operators</p>
    <p>Has been in use at Network Operation Center for over a year for</p>
    <p>a service with 2+ million customers</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
