<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DarkNOC</p>
    <p>Dashboard for Honeypot Management</p>
    <p>Bertrand Sobesto(1), Michel Cukier(1), Ma9 Hiltunen(2), David Kormann(2), Gregory Vesonder(2), Robin Berthier(3)</p>
    <p>(1) University of Maryland, (2) AT&amp;T Labs-Research, (3) UIUC.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Honeypots overview  DarkNOC  Case study</p>
    <p>Do you really want to manage your own honeypots? Join us instead.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Honeypots  Highly monitored systems meant to aAract aAackers and analyze their behavior.</p>
    <p>Traffic observed on the honeypot network is considered malicious</p>
    <p>Different characterisGcs  Scale (local vs. distributed)</p>
    <p>E.g., Leurre.com, Internet MoGon Sensor, SGNET  Purpose (research vs. producGon)  Level of interacGon (high vs. low)</p>
    <p>Real OS + apps vs. emulated (e.g., Nepenthes, Dionaea, Honeyd)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Problems</p>
    <p>Distributed Honeypots can generate large volume of data</p>
    <p>Running high interacGon Honeypots is risky as they can get compromised</p>
    <p>Network infrastructure can suffer from aAackers acGons and needs to be monitored</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DarkNOC</p>
    <p>DarkNOC (Darknet Network OperaGon Center) is a management and monitoring tool for complex honeynets  Support different types of honeypots (low and high interacGon)</p>
    <p>Support different data collecGon devices  Support both research and producGon</p>
    <p>Currently used to manage a honeypot network consisGng of several subnets with hundreds of IP addresses.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Architecture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data sources NeZlow Date flow start Duration Port SrcIP:Port -&gt; DstIP:Port Packets Bytes Flows 2010-02-09 06:43:... 4294966.937 TCP 218.8.251.187:20347 -&gt; x.x.x.x:80 2 94 1 2010-02-09 06:43:... 4294966.977 TCP 218.8.251.187:20347 -&gt; x.x.x.x:80 2 94 1</p>
    <p>Snort IDS events 04/15-06:49:15.474819 [**] [1:12799:3] SHELLCODE base64 x86 NOOP [**] [Classification: Executable Code was Detected]... {TCP} a.b.c.d:15017 -&gt; W.X.Y.Z.:80 04/15-06:49:15.474819 [**] [1:12802:3] SHELLCODE base64 x86 NOOP [**] [Classification: Executable Code was Detected]... {TCP} a.b.c.d:15017 -&gt; W.X.Y.Z.:80 04/15-06:49:15.619028 [**] [1:12800:3] SHELLCODE base64 x86 NOOP [**] [Classification: Executable Code was Detected]... {TCP} a.b.c.d:15017 -&gt; W.X.Y.Z.:80</p>
    <p>Malware CollecGon [2011-04-15T06:49:19] a.b.c.d-&gt; W.X.Y.Z. gp://1:1@a.b.c.d:21/Rewetsr.exe c511c4f9bdd3bb892e582kc9a00da9c</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sogware Architecture  Constraints</p>
    <p>Easy to use (any web browser), intuiGve.  Speed: User interface fast despite the volume of data  Data validity: Data displayed up to date even under high data volume.</p>
    <p>Backend</p>
    <p>Process flow data and populate cache tables</p>
    <p>for the GUI</p>
    <p>Graphical User</p>
    <p>Interface Web interface to</p>
    <p>display the informaGon</p>
    <p>Alert Module</p>
    <p>Execute users flow queries and send the</p>
    <p>result via email</p>
    <p>DarkNOC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Graphical User Interface Flows / subnet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GUI: NetFlow Data</p>
    <p>RRD Graphs  Number of aAackers</p>
    <p>Number of unique external source IP addresses  Number of flows  Different scales: Day, week and month  Updated every 5 minutes by the backend program</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GUI: More on NetFlow Data  Top and boAom targeted ports  Top aAackers, top targets  Top origin countries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GUI: Snort Events</p>
    <p>Number of Snort events  Last 50 snort events (source and desGnaGon IPs hidden here).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GUI: More on Snort events</p>
    <p>Top 10 and boAom 10 snort signatures within the last 24 hours</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case study: UMD Honeynet  An infrastructure to support honeypot-based experiments</p>
    <p>Provide data collecGon infrastructure (Flow, Snort and PCAP)  Controlled environment</p>
    <p>Currently about 2,000 IP addresses from 5 different insGtuGons:  University of Maryland  AT&amp;T  University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign  Laboratoire dAnalyse et dArchitecture des Systmes (LAAS) in Toulouse,</p>
    <p>France  Ecole NaGonale des Sciences Appliques in Marrakech</p>
    <p>The UMD Honeynet is hosted at the University of Maryland, traffic from other insGtuGons is forwarded through a secured tunnel (Honeymole).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UMD Honeynet Architecture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study: Honeynet management</p>
    <p>Monitoring of the core components of the architecture (tunnels, honeypots)</p>
    <p>IdenGficaGon of data collecGon failures  IdenGficaGon of network failures</p>
    <p>UMD Internet network is not tunneled Network issue?</p>
    <p>Significant variaGons in the number of flows for the UMD Internal subnet</p>
    <p>Network issue?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study: Security tool</p>
    <p>Alert module  Alert on compromised campus hosts targeGng the Honeynet</p>
    <p>AAack profiling  Origin countries and services targeted most</p>
    <p>IdenGfy misconfiguraGons  Traffic that is not normally allowed</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alert module  Report to U. Maryland security folks twice a day:</p>
    <p>--------------- Analysis Report --------------- Flow Time Window: 2011/06/06.06:00:00-2011/06/06.18:00:01 Number of hosts detected: 3 To access the online version of the report: https://xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx/darknoc/alert_hosts.php?report=263</p>
    <p>xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx (X.umd.edu) - Number of flows: 1 - Number of packets: 1 - Number of bytes: 51 To visualize the flows: https://xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx/darknoc/alert_hosts.php?id=1124</p>
    <p>yyy.yyy.yyy.yyy (Y.umd.edu) - Number of flows: 10 - Number of packets: 10 - Number of bytes: 1915 To visualize the flows: https://xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx/darknoc/alert_hosts.php?id=1125</p>
    <p>zzz.zzz.zzz.zzz (Z.umd.edu) - Number of flows: 10 - Number of packets: 10 - Number of bytes: 1915 To visualize the flows: https://xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx/darknoc/alert_hosts.php?id=1126</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AAack profiling</p>
    <p>A typical day of traffic on the honeynet Significant increase of traffic on the UMD internal subnet</p>
    <p>No parGcular increase of the number of aAackers</p>
    <p>But port TCP/22 moves to the first place in the Top 10 ports</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>You can join the adventure!</p>
    <p>Interested joining the UMD Honeynet? All you need is:  A Linux machine</p>
    <p>An old box (Honeymole works great on a PII), can even be a VM  2 network interfaces  Internet connecGvity (Honeymole works with NAT)</p>
    <p>Unused IP addresses (from 3 to a lot)  We take care of the honeypot deployment at Maryland.</p>
    <p>What you will get:  Access to DarkNOC and our data repository (subject to partners approval)</p>
    <p>Possibility to deploy your experiments using IP addresses of other insGtuGons (within reason and subject to other insGtuGons approval :-)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The authors would like to thank the Office of InformaGon Technology at the University of</p>
    <p>Maryland for permi|ng this work</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
