<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adaptive Stream Filters for Entity-based Adaptive Stream Filters for Entity-based Queries with Non-value ToleranceQueries with Non-value Tolerance</p>
    <p>VLDB 2005VLDB 2005</p>
    <p>Reynold Cheng Reynold Cheng (Speaker)(Speaker)</p>
    <p>Ben Kao, Ben Kao, Alan KwanAlan Kwan</p>
    <p>Sunil Prabhakar, Sunil Prabhakar, Yicheng TuYicheng Tu</p>
    <p>The Hong Kong The Hong Kong Polytechnic UniversityPolytechnic University</p>
    <p>The University of The University of Hong KongHong Kong</p>
    <p>Purdue UniversityPurdue University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Streams and ApplicationsData Streams and Applications</p>
    <p>Data Stream Management Systems (DSMS)Data Stream Management Systems (DSMS)  Sensor networks, location-based applicationsSensor networks, location-based applications  STREAMSTREAM [ABB03], [ABB03], STEAMSTEAM [HAFME03], [HAFME03], AURORAAURORA</p>
    <p>[ACC03], [ACC03], CACQCACQ [MSH02] [MSH02]  Stream applicationsStream applications</p>
    <p>Telecom call recordsTelecom call records  Network security [BO03]Network security [BO03]  Habitat monitoring [MPS02]Habitat monitoring [MPS02]  Structural health monitoringStructural health monitoring</p>
    <p>ContinuousContinuous QueriesQueries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DSMS ModelDSMS Model</p>
    <p>User Query</p>
    <p>Processing Unit</p>
    <p>Central Processor</p>
    <p>Continuous Query</p>
    <p>Result (Refreshed if needed)</p>
    <p>stream</p>
    <p>stream</p>
    <p>stream</p>
    <p>streamNetworkReal-time, Response Time</p>
    <p>requirement</p>
    <p>Massive, Fast Limited</p>
    <p>memory, CPU, network</p>
    <p>bandwidth</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trading Accuracy for Query TimelinessTrading Accuracy for Query Timeliness</p>
    <p>A user may accept an answer with a A user may accept an answer with a carefully controlled carefully controlled error toleranceerror tolerance  wide-area resource accountingwide-area resource accounting  load-balancing in replicated serversload-balancing in replicated servers</p>
    <p>The system exploits The system exploits error toleranceerror tolerance to to reduce communication and computation reduce communication and computation costscosts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Value-based ToleranceValue-based Tolerance</p>
    <p>Often assumed in literature [Often assumed in literature [OJW03, JCW04OJW03, JCW04]]  Maximum error is a numerical value Maximum error is a numerical value</p>
    <p>specified by userspecified by user  MAX Query: MAX Query: Return sensor id with the Return sensor id with the</p>
    <p>highest temperaturehighest temperature  Guarantee the sensor id returned has Guarantee the sensor id returned has</p>
    <p>temperature value not lower than temperature value not lower than  from that from that of the true answerof the true answer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Is Selecting Is Selecting  Easy? Easy?</p>
    <p>Location-based application: a user inquires about Location-based application: a user inquires about his closest neighborhis closest neighbor  Should the tolerance be 0.1, 1, or 100 meters?Should the tolerance be 0.1, 1, or 100 meters?</p>
    <p>Sensor network collects humidity, temperature, UV-Sensor network collects humidity, temperature, UVindex, wind speedindex, wind speed  Does user know the range of error for each type?Does user know the range of error for each type?</p>
    <p>Multi-dimensionalMulti-dimensional data streams (e.g., location) data streams (e.g., location)  Multimedia Multimedia data streams (e.g., CCTV images)data streams (e.g., CCTV images)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Is Selecting Is Selecting  for MAX Query easy?for MAX Query easy?</p>
    <p>Suppose a user accepts an object that ranks 2nd or above.</p>
    <p>small</p>
    <p>If  is too small</p>
    <p>large</p>
    <p>If  is too large</p>
    <p>ideal</p>
    <p>The ideal</p>
    <p>Tolerance wasted</p>
    <p>Error unacceptable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rank-based ToleranceRank-based Tolerance</p>
    <p>Express error tolerance Express error tolerance as a as a rankrank</p>
    <p>Error tolerance = no. Error tolerance = no. of positions the of positions the returned sensor could returned sensor could rank below the highest rank below the highest oneone</p>
    <p>More intuitive and More intuitive and easier to specifyeasier to specify</p>
    <p>Rank-based tolerance = 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Non-Value ToleranceNon-Value Tolerance</p>
    <p>Rank-based tolerance is Rank-based tolerance is non-value- tolerancenon-value- tolerance  numerical value numerical value  not usednot used</p>
    <p>Fraction-based ToleranceFraction-based Tolerance  False Positive False Positive FF++(t): % of returned answers (t): % of returned answers</p>
    <p>that are incorrect at time that are incorrect at time tt  False Negative False Negative FF--(t): % of correct answers not (t): % of correct answers not</p>
    <p>returned at time returned at time tt  FF++(t) (t)   ++; ; FF--(t) (t)   -</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Entity-based QueriesEntity-based Queries</p>
    <p>Return sets of object ids, not numerical values [CKP03]Return sets of object ids, not numerical values [CKP03]  Rank-based queries: Rank-based queries: order of stream values decides the order of stream values decides the</p>
    <p>final answerfinal answer  e.g., top-e.g., top-kk query, query, kk-nearest-neighbor query-nearest-neighbor query</p>
    <p>Non-rank-based queries: Non-rank-based queries: order of stream values is not order of stream values is not importantimportant  e.g., range querye.g., range query</p>
    <p>Non-value tolerance Non-value tolerance matchesmatches entity-based queries! entity-based queries!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N o n - r a n k - b a s e d q u e r i e s R a n k - b a s e d q u e r y</p>
    <p>V a l u e - b a s e d t o l e r a n c e</p>
    <p>R a n k - b a s e d q u e r y k N N Q u e r y</p>
    <p>R a n k - b a s e d t o l e r a n c e</p>
    <p>R a n k - b a s e d q u e r y k N N Q u e r y</p>
    <p>N o n - r a n k - b a s e d q u e r y R a n g e Q u e r y</p>
    <p>F r a c t i o n - b a s e d t o l e r a n c e</p>
    <p>N o n - v a l u e t o l e r a n c e</p>
    <p>A p p r o x i m a t e C o n t i n u o u s Q u e r i e s</p>
    <p>Continuous Query ClassificationContinuous Query Classification</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adaptive Filter [OJW03]: Adaptive Filter [OJW03]: Initialization PhaseInitialization Phase Adaptive Filter [OJW03]: Adaptive Filter [OJW03]: Initialization PhaseInitialization Phase</p>
    <p>Constraint Assignment</p>
    <p>Unit</p>
    <p>Data Stream 1</p>
    <p>Filter Bounds</p>
    <p>User-defined Tolerance</p>
    <p>Data Stream 2</p>
    <p>Data Stream 3</p>
    <p>[l3,u3]</p>
    <p>[l2,u2]</p>
    <p>[l1,u1]</p>
    <p>Answer tolerance is met as long as</p>
    <p>no update is generated</p>
    <p>Answer tolerance is met as long as</p>
    <p>no update is generated</p>
    <p>Query Processing</p>
    <p>Unit</p>
    <p>Approximate Answer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adaptive Filter: Maintenance PhaseAdaptive Filter: Maintenance PhaseAdaptive Filter: Maintenance PhaseAdaptive Filter: Maintenance Phase</p>
    <p>Constraint Assignment</p>
    <p>Unit</p>
    <p>New Filter Bound</p>
    <p>User-defined Tolerance</p>
    <p>Update (v2&gt;u2 or v2 &lt; l2)</p>
    <p>Data Stream 1 (v1)</p>
    <p>Data Stream 2 (v2)</p>
    <p>Data Stream 3 (v3)</p>
    <p>[l3,u3]</p>
    <p>[l2,u2]</p>
    <p>[l1,u1]</p>
    <p>[l2,u2]</p>
    <p>Request Value v3Tolerance</p>
    <p>violated! trigger</p>
    <p>Maintenance Phase</p>
    <p>Query Processing</p>
    <p>Unit</p>
    <p>Approximate Answer</p>
    <p>Corrected Approximate Answer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ContributionsContributions</p>
    <p>Apply Apply filter boundsfilter bounds to to rank-based / non-rank-based queriesrank-based / non-rank-based queries</p>
    <p>subject to subject to rank-based / fraction-based tolerancerank-based / fraction-based tolerance</p>
    <p>to reduce to reduce message costsmessage costs</p>
    <p>Correctness proofs, cost analysis and Correctness proofs, cost analysis and experimental evaluation of each protocolexperimental evaluation of each protocol</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>N o n - r a n k - b a s e d q u e r i e s R a n k - b a s e d q u e r y</p>
    <p>V a l u e - b a s e d t o l e r a n c e</p>
    <p>R a n k - b a s e d q u e r y k N N Q u e r y</p>
    <p>R a n k - b a s e d t o l e r a n c e</p>
    <p>R a n k - b a s e d q u e r y k N N Q u e r y</p>
    <p>N o n - r a n k - b a s e d q u e r y R a n g e Q u e r y</p>
    <p>F r a c t i o n - b a s e d t o l e r a n c e</p>
    <p>N o n - v a l u e t o l e r a n c e</p>
    <p>A p p r o x i m a t e C o n t i n u o u s Q u e r i e s</p>
    <p>Filter Bound ProtocolsFilter Bound Protocols</p>
    <p>RTP FT-RP FT-NRPZT-RP ZT-NRP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Non-Rank-based QueriesNon-Rank-based Queries</p>
    <p>S6 S5 S2 S7S4 S8S1S3</p>
    <p>Ordered Values</p>
    <p>Answer Set Example: 1D Range Query</p>
    <p>Range = [10, 30]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fraction-based ToleranceFraction-based Tolerance</p>
    <p>S6 S5 S2 S7S4 S8S1S3</p>
    <p>Range of Q = [l, u]</p>
    <p>Ordered Values</p>
    <p>Update Update</p>
    <p>False PositiveFalse Negative</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fraction-based ToleranceFraction-based Tolerance</p>
    <p>Answer actually returned</p>
    <p>A(t)</p>
    <p>E+(t)</p>
    <p>True answer at time t</p>
    <p>F(t)  E(t)</p>
    <p>A(t)</p>
    <p>|A(t)|-E+(t) E-(t)</p>
    <p>F(t)  E(t)</p>
    <p>A(t)  E(t) E(t)</p>
    <p>= |A(t)| - E+(t) + E-(t)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Initialization PhaseInitialization Phase</p>
    <p>Given Given ++ and and</p>
    <p>Calculate no. of streams (Calculate no. of streams (EEmaxmax+ +) that can be false positives) that can be false positives</p>
    <p>Assign Assign false +ve filtersfalse +ve filters [- [-, + ] to , + ] to EEmax max streamsstreams  Assign [l,u] to remaining onesAssign [l,u] to remaining ones</p>
    <p>-) that can be false negatives) that can be false negatives  Assign Assign false -ve filters false -ve filters [+, +] to [+, +] to EEmaxmax</p>
    <p>- streamsstreams  Assign [l,u] to remaining onesAssign [l,u] to remaining ones</p>
    <p>Tolerance is satisfied if no new updates are receivedTolerance is satisfied if no new updates are received</p>
    <p>At any time t without update, F+(t)  +</p>
    <p>F-(t)</p>
    <p>At any time t without update, F+(t)  +</p>
    <p>F-(t)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Maintenance Phase: Good UpdateMaintenance Phase: Good Update</p>
    <p>S6 S5 S2 S7S4 S8S1S3</p>
    <p>Insert SInsert S7 7 into A(into A(ttcc))  FF++ and Fand F</p>
    <p>-dropdrop</p>
    <p>FF++((ttcc) &lt; F) &lt; F+ +((tt00) )   +</p>
    <p>+  FF--((ttcc) &lt; F) &lt; F</p>
    <p>-((tt00) )</p>
    <p>Tolerance is metTolerance is met</p>
    <p>time time ttcc time time tt00</p>
    <p>Filter [l,u] Range of Q = [l, u]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Maintenance Phase: Bad UpdateMaintenance Phase: Bad Update</p>
    <p>+ andand F F - - ((ttcc))   - may not be true may not be true</p>
    <p>S6 S5 S2 S4 S8S1S3</p>
    <p>time time ttcctime time tt00Filter [l,u]</p>
    <p>Range of Q = [l, u]</p>
    <p>S7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fix: Consulting False Positive FilterFix: Consulting False Positive Filter</p>
    <p>S6 S5 S2 S7S4 S8 S1S3</p>
    <p>Select stream Select stream SS44 A(tA(tcc)) with [- with [-, +] filter , +] filter  Request SRequest S44 for its updated value for its updated value  If If VV44  [[l, ul, u]]</p>
    <p>install [install [l, ul, u] filter to S] filter to S44  prove thatprove that F F ++(t(tcc))   +</p>
    <p>+ and and F F - - ((ttcc))   - are satisfiedare satisfied</p>
    <p>If If VV4 4  [[ll, , uu]], consult a false ve filter, consult a false ve filter  Worst case: 5 messages Worst case: 5 messages</p>
    <p>Filter [-, +][-, +]</p>
    <p>Range of Q = [l, u]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Filter Bound Protocols for Rank-Filter Bound Protocols for Rankbased Queriesbased Queries</p>
    <p>k-NN query is a representative of NN, Min, Maxk-NN query is a representative of NN, Min, Max  Fraction-based tolerance / k-NN queryFraction-based tolerance / k-NN query</p>
    <p>View a k-NN query as a range query, by using the View a k-NN query as a range query, by using the kth nearest neighbor as the rangekth nearest neighbor as the range</p>
    <p>Adapt fraction-based tolerance/range queryAdapt fraction-based tolerance/range query  Rank-based tolerance / k-NN queryRank-based tolerance / k-NN query</p>
    <p>Maintain knowledge about (k+r)Maintain knowledge about (k+r)thth and (k+r+1) and (k+r+1)stst item item  Filter bound is defined by the average of the (k+r)Filter bound is defined by the average of the (k+r)thth</p>
    <p>and (k+r+1)and (k+r+1)stst item item</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ExperimentsExperiments</p>
    <p>CompareCompare  No filter is used at allNo filter is used at all  Filter protocols with zero toleranceFilter protocols with zero tolerance  Our tolerance-based protocolsOur tolerance-based protocols</p>
    <p>Measure total no. of messages required Measure total no. of messages required for executing a continuous queryfor executing a continuous query</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental SetupExperimental Setup</p>
    <p>Real DataReal Data  30 days of wide-area traces of TCP connections 30 days of wide-area traces of TCP connections</p>
    <p>based on TCP trace [ITA20]based on TCP trace [ITA20]  Synthetic DataSynthetic Data</p>
    <p>Generated by CSIM 18Generated by CSIM 18  Data value: Data value: Uniform distributionUniform distribution  Fluctuation of updates: Fluctuation of updates: Normal distributionNormal distribution  Interarrival time of updates: Interarrival time of updates: Exponential Exponential</p>
    <p>distributiondistribution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fraction-based Tolerance for Range Query Fraction-based Tolerance for Range Query with Real Datawith Real Data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fraction-based Tolerance for Range Query Fraction-based Tolerance for Range Query with Synthetic Datawith Synthetic Data</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ConclusionsConclusions</p>
    <p>Value-based tolerance can be difficult to specify Value-based tolerance can be difficult to specify for continuous queries in stream systemsfor continuous queries in stream systems</p>
    <p>Rank-based and fraction-based toleranceRank-based and fraction-based tolerance  Applied to rank- queries and non-rank- queriesApplied to rank- queries and non-rank- queries  Filter bound protocols translate non-value- Filter bound protocols translate non-value</p>
    <p>tolerance to filter boundstolerance to filter bounds  Experiments illustrate protocol effectivenessExperiments illustrate protocol effectiveness</p>
    <p>Please contact Reynold Cheng (csckcheng@comp.polyu.edu.hk) for detailsPlease contact Reynold Cheng (csckcheng@comp.polyu.edu.hk) for details</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Issues of Running Out of Issues of Running Out of FiltersFilters  If all false positive and false negative If all false positive and false negative</p>
    <p>filters run out, the system degrades to filters run out, the system degrades to one in which no tolerance is exploitedone in which no tolerance is exploited</p>
    <p>To improve performance, initialization To improve performance, initialization phase may be executed againphase may be executed again</p>
    <p>Experiments over long-running queriesExperiments over long-running queries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Long-Running QueriesLong-Running Queries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>False +ve / -ve Filters Selection HeuristicFalse +ve / -ve Filters Selection Heuristic</p>
    <p>N u</p>
    <p>m b</p>
    <p>e r</p>
    <p>o f</p>
    <p>M e</p>
    <p>ss a</p>
    <p>g e</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Random Boundary</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
