<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BotMagnifier: Locating Spambots on the Internet</p>
    <p>Gianluca Stringhini Thorsten Holz</p>
    <p>Brett Stone-Gross Christopher Kruegel</p>
    <p>Giovanni Vigna</p>
    <p>USENIX Security Symposium</p>
    <p>August 12, 2011</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spam is a big problem</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spam is sneaky</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spam is sneaky</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tracking Spambots is important</p>
    <p>Botnets are responsible for 85% of worldwide spam</p>
    <p>ISPs and organizations can clean up their networks</p>
    <p>Existing blacklists (DNSBL) can be improved</p>
    <p>Mitigation efforts can be directed to the most aggressive botnets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tracking Spambots is challenging</p>
    <p>The IP addresses of infected machines change frequently</p>
    <p>It is easy to recruit new members into a botnet</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>An approach is to set up spam traps. However, a few problems arise:</p>
    <p>Only a subset of the bots will send emails to the spam trap addresses</p>
    <p>Some botnets target only users located in certain countries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Insight</p>
    <p>Bots that belong to the same botnet share similarities</p>
    <p>As a result, they will follow a similar behavior when sending spam</p>
    <p>Commoditized botnets could appear as multiple botnets</p>
    <p>By observing a portion of a botnet, it is possible to identify more bots that belong to it</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Input Datasets</p>
    <p>How can we achieve this?</p>
    <p>Our approach takes two datasets as input:</p>
    <p>The IP addresses of known spamming bots, grouped by spam campaign (seed pools)</p>
    <p>A log of email transactions carried out on the Internet, both legitimate and malicious (transaction log)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our System</p>
    <p>We implemented our approach in a tool, called BotMagnifier</p>
    <p>We used a large spam trap to populate seed pools</p>
    <p>We used the logs of a Spamhaus mirror as transaction log</p>
    <p>Each query to the Spamhaus mirror corresponds to an email</p>
    <p>We show how BotMagnifier also works when using other datasets as transaction logs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our System</p>
    <p>BotMagnifier is executed periodically</p>
    <p>It takes as input a set of seed pools</p>
    <p>At the end of each observation period, it outputs:</p>
    <p>The IP addresses of the bots in the magnified pools</p>
    <p>The name of the botnet that carried out each campaign</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phase I: Building Seed Pools</p>
    <p>Set of IP addresses that participated in a specific spam campaign</p>
    <p>Built using the data of a spam trap set up by a large US ISP</p>
    <p>1M messages / day</p>
    <p>We consider messages with similar subject lines as part of the same campaign</p>
    <p>Design decisions:</p>
    <p>Minimum seed pool size: 1,000 IP addresses</p>
    <p>Observation period: 1 day</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phase II: Characterizing Bot Behavior</p>
    <p>For each seed pool:</p>
    <p>We query the transaction log to find all the events that are associated with the IP addresses in it</p>
    <p>We analyze the set of destinations targeted and build a target set</p>
    <p>Problem The target sets of two botnets might have substantial overlaps</p>
    <p>We extract the set of destinations that are unique to each seed pool (characterizing set)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phase III: Bot Magnification</p>
    <p>Goal: find the IP addresses of previously-unknown bots</p>
    <p>BotMagnifier considers an IP address x as behaving similarly to the bots in a seed pool if:</p>
    <p>x sent emails to at least N destinations in the target set</p>
    <p>x never sent an email to a destination outside the target set</p>
    <p>x has contacted at least one destination in the characterizing set</p>
    <p>How large should N be?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Threshold Computation</p>
    <p>N should be greater for campaigns targeting a larger number of destinations</p>
    <p>N = k  |T (pi )|, 0 &lt; k  1</p>
    <p>where |T (pi )| is the size of the target set, and k is a parameter</p>
    <p>Precision vs. Recall analysis on ten campaigns for which we had ground truth (coming from Cutwail C&amp;C servers)</p>
    <p>k = kb +</p>
    <p>|T(pi )|  kb = 8  104, = 10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phase IV: Spam Attribution</p>
    <p>We want to label spam campaigns based on the botnet that carried them out</p>
    <p>Running Malware Samples</p>
    <p>We match the subject lines observed in the wild with the ones of the bots we ran</p>
    <p>Botnet Clustering</p>
    <p>IP overlap</p>
    <p>Destination distance</p>
    <p>Bot distance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Validation of the Approach To validate our approach, we studied Cutwail, for which we had direct data about the IP addresses of the infected machines</p>
    <p>The C&amp;C servers we analyzed accounted for approximately 30% of the botnet</p>
    <p>We ran the validation experiment for the period between July 28 and August 16, 2010</p>
    <p>For each of the 18 days:</p>
    <p>We selected a subset of the IP addresses referenced by the C&amp;C servers</p>
    <p>With the help of the spam trap, we identified the campaigns carried out</p>
    <p>We generated the seed and magnified pools</p>
    <p>BotMagnifier identified 144,317 IP addresses as bots. Of these, 33,550 were actually listed in the C&amp;C databases ( 23%).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of Tracking Results</p>
    <p>We ran our system between September 28, 2010 and February 5, 2011</p>
    <p>BotMagnifier tracked 2,031,110 bot IP addresses</p>
    <p>Of these, 925,978 belonged to magnified pools, while the others belonged to seed pools</p>
    <p>Botnet Total # of IP addresses # of static IP addresses Lethic 887,852 117,335</p>
    <p>Rustock 676,905 104,460</p>
    <p>Cutwail 319,355 34,132</p>
    <p>MegaD 68,117 3,055</p>
    <p>Waledac 36,058 3,450</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of Tracking Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of Tracking Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of Tracking Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of Tracking Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Application of Results</p>
    <p>Can BotMagnifier improve existing blacklists?</p>
    <p>We analyzed the email logs from the UCSB CS mail server from November 30, 2010 to February 8, 2011</p>
    <p>If a mail got delivered, the IP address was not blacklisted at the time</p>
    <p>The spam ratios computed by SpamAssassin provide us with ground truth</p>
    <p>We then looked for false positives. BotMagnifier wrongly identified 12 out of 209,013 IP addresses as bots.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Stream Independence</p>
    <p>We show how BotMagnifier can be used on alternative datasets, too</p>
    <p>We used the netflow logs from an ISP backbone routers 1.9M emails logged per day</p>
    <p>We had to use new values for kb and</p>
    <p>The experiment lasted from January 20, 2011 to January 28, 2011.</p>
    <p>BotMagnifier identified 36,739 in magnified pools. This grew the seed pools by 38%.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>We presented BotMagnifier, a tool for tracking and analyzing spamming botnets</p>
    <p>We showed that our approach is able to accurately identify and track botnets</p>
    <p>By using more comprehensive datasets, the magnification results would get better</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks!</p>
    <p>email: gianluca@cs.ucsb.edu twitter: @gianlucaSB</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
