<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>I rate you. You rate me. Should we do so publicly?</p>
    <p>Chun-Yuen Teng, Debra Lauterbach, Lada A. Adamic School of InformaBon,</p>
    <p>University of Michigan, Ann Arbor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RaBngs are an integral part of Web 2.0, but are they honest?</p>
    <p>Many sites use recommender/reputaBon systems to help users idenBfy reliable content and services</p>
    <p>How can one elicit honest raBngs?  when users review items  when users rate other users reviews  when users rate other users</p>
    <p>We study a variety of sites that cover this space of raBng types and various design choices</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Amazon  Amazon.com provides a plaMorm which allows users to review products</p>
    <p>Users can decide to use a pen name or real name to review products</p>
    <p>15 thousand arBcle recent reviews from top 1500 reviewers (about one half using pen names)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Epinions  Epinions.com allows users to share product reviews.  Users can write reviews, rate other users reviews, and specify which users they trust or distrust</p>
    <p>~800K user-to-user raBngs (trust or not)  ~100K users and 3 million arBcles</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CouchSurfing</p>
    <p>Users can do the following for other users:  specify friendship level (e.g. acquaintance, friend, best friend)</p>
    <p>specify how much they trust them (e.g. somewhat, highly)</p>
    <p>vouch for them  leave posiBve, neutral, or negaBve references</p>
    <p>CouchSurfing is a service for travelers looking to meet new people while finding a couch to sleep on.</p>
    <p>data: 600K users, 3 million edges</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Structure of raBng systems</p>
    <p>Product review/raBng</p>
    <p>RaBng of product reviews RaBng of other users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research QuesBons  How do design choices in online social networking &amp; recommendaBon sites influence raBngs?</p>
    <p>Are there other factors affecBng raBngs?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design choices</p>
    <p>?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design choices: displaying raBngs  Show raBngs publicly or keep private  Amazon  Product reviews are public</p>
    <p>CouchSurfing  Public (friend, vouch, reference), private for trust</p>
    <p>Epinions  Public for raBng of reviews  Public for trust links to other users  Private for distrust links to other users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design choices: anonymity  Do users have to idenBfy themselves when giving raBngs?</p>
    <p>Amazon  Choice of pen name or real name</p>
    <p>Epinions  Choice of username or staying anonymous when raBng other users reviews</p>
    <p>CouchSurfing  All public raBngs are idenBfied: friendship, references, vouches</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design choices: reciprocity  Is there any potenBal for reciprocity?  Amazon  Not really: products dont rate you back</p>
    <p>Epinions  Yes</p>
    <p>CouchSurfing  Yes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy and ra+ngs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy and raBngs: scarcity of public, negaBve raBngs when idenBfied</p>
    <p>CouchSurfing  Users leave a posiBve reference for 87.7 % of those they host and for 90.1% of those who host them</p>
    <p>Neutral/missing references are confounded in data  The raBo of posiBve to negaBve references is 2500:1!</p>
    <p>extremely</p>
    <p>negative</p>
    <p>negative neutral/</p>
    <p>no reference</p>
    <p>positive extremely</p>
    <p>positive</p>
    <p># r</p>
    <p>e fe</p>
    <p>re n c e s</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Privacy and raBngs: negaBve raBngs do occur when they are private</p>
    <p>Epinions  Users express trust publicly and distrust privately  non-trivial fracBon (14.7%) are distrust raBngs.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity and ra+ngs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity and raBngs in absence of reciprocity</p>
    <p>a2ribute pen name REAL NAMETM sta+s+cally significant</p>
    <p>product raBng # stars</p>
    <p># reviews 498 551 yes length of review (words)</p>
    <p># of fan voters 28.6 37.1 yes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anonymity and raBngs when there is potenBal for reciprocity</p>
    <p>Anonymous raBngs are lower (3.84) on average than idenBfied raBngs (4.71)</p>
    <p>For the same user, anonymous raBngs sBll average lower (4.01) than idenBfied ones (4.76)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Is there evidence of reciprocity in ra+ngs?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reciprocity in Epinions  We aggregate the user-to-arBcle raBngs into user-to- user raBngs.</p>
    <p>e.g.: if user A rates two of user Bs arBcles with average raBng of 4, raBng(A-&gt;B) = 4</p>
    <p># of RaBngs and raBng scores show reciprocity  RaBng from A to B is correlated with raBng from B to A (rho = 0.475)</p>
    <p># of raBngs from A to B and B to A also displays reciprocity (rho = 0.49)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reciprocity in CouchSurfing  Public friendship raBngs are more highly correlated (rho = 0.73) than private trust raBngs (rho = 0.39)</p>
    <p>We omit trust rating of 2 (I dont know the person)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reciprocity in CouchSurfing  Vouching also demonstrates reciprocity  If A vouched for B, 70% of the Bme B also vouched for A  Mean private trust score for reciprocated vouches was higher (4.47) than unreciprocated ones (4.19)  lack of raBng could signal lower trust</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Are truthful raBngs reliable?  Even if one were able to elicit truthful raBngs, would there sBll be biases?</p>
    <p>To answer this we used demographic informaBon from CouchSurfing.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Gender effects for trust &amp; friendship  Men rate both men and women about equally on trust and friendship</p>
    <p>Women rate other women more highly on both</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Age  Trust is very slightly higher the smaller the age difference between rater and ratee (= -0.06)</p>
    <p>Trust depends on age of ratee  typical CouchSurfing demographic preferred?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Geography  Closer friends tend to be geographically proximate  Friendship for ones countrymen (4.19) is higher than foreigners (3.65)</p>
    <p>Trust for ones countrymen is higher than for foreigners (4.33 vs 4.16)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Geography</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Geography  Countries with similar cultural background tend to be trusBng of one another (e.g. Austria and Germany)</p>
    <p>Sharing a border does not always correspond to greater trust (e.g. Canadians did not rate US contacts more highly)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>RaBngs should not be taken at face value  Public, idenBfied raBngs tend to be posiBve when there is potenBal for reciprocity</p>
    <p>Demographics are Bed to how users give raBngs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future work  Survey users as to when and why they choose to rate anonymously</p>
    <p>IdenBfy the criteria users use in raBng others  Develop trust predicBon algorithms accounBng for biases</p>
    <p>htp://netsi.org more info</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
