<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>On the Constancy of Internet Path Properties</p>
    <p>ACM SIGCOMM Internet Measurement Workshop November, 2001</p>
    <p>ACIRI {vern,shenker}@aciri.org</p>
    <p>AT&amp;T Labs  Research {yzhang,duffield}@research.att.com</p>
    <p>Vern Paxson Scott Shenker</p>
    <p>Yin Zhang Nick Duffield</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Talk Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation  Three notions of constancy</p>
    <p>Mathematical</p>
    <p>Operational</p>
    <p>Predictive</p>
    <p>Constancy of three Internet path properties</p>
    <p>Packet loss</p>
    <p>Packet delays</p>
    <p>Throughput</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Recent surge of interest in network measurement</p>
    <p>Mathematical modeling</p>
    <p>Operational procedures</p>
    <p>Adaptive applications  Measurements are most valuable when the</p>
    <p>relevant network properties exhibit constancy</p>
    <p>Constancy: holds steady and does not change</p>
    <p>We will also use the term steady, when use of constancy would prove grammatically awkward</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mathematical Constancy</p>
    <p>Mathematical Constancy</p>
    <p>A dataset is mathematically steady if it can be described with a single time-invariant mathematical model.</p>
    <p>Simplest form: IID  independent and identically distributed</p>
    <p>Key: finding the appropriate model</p>
    <p>Examples</p>
    <p>Mathematical constancy</p>
    <p>Session arrivals are well described by a fix-rate Poisson process over time scales of 10s of minutes to an hour [PF95]</p>
    <p>Mathematical non-constancy</p>
    <p>Session arrivals over larger time scales</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Operational Constancy</p>
    <p>Operational constancy</p>
    <p>A dataset is operationally steady if the quantities of interest remain within bounds considered operationally equivalent</p>
    <p>Key: whether an application cares about the changes</p>
    <p>Examples</p>
    <p>Operationally but not mathematically steady</p>
    <p>Loss rate remained constant at 10% for 30 minutes and then abruptly changed to 10.1% for the next 30 minutes.</p>
    <p>Mathematically but not operationally steady</p>
    <p>Bimodal loss process with high degree of correlation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Predictive Constancy</p>
    <p>Predictive constancy</p>
    <p>A dataset is predictively steady if past measurements allow one to reasonably predict future characteristics</p>
    <p>Key: how well changes can be tracked</p>
    <p>Examples</p>
    <p>Mathematically but not predictively steady</p>
    <p>IID processes are generally impossible to predict well</p>
    <p>Neither mathematically nor operationally steady, but highly predictable</p>
    <p>E.g. RTT</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis Methodology</p>
    <p>Mathematical constancy</p>
    <p>Identify change-points and partition a timeseries into change-free regions (CFR)</p>
    <p>Test for IID within each CFR  Operational constancy</p>
    <p>Define operational categories based on requirements of real applications</p>
    <p>Predictive constancy</p>
    <p>Evaluate the performance of commonly used estimators</p>
    <p>Exponentially Weighted Moving Average (EWMA)</p>
    <p>Moving Average (MA)</p>
    <p>Moving Average with S-shaped Weights (SMA)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Testing for Change-Points</p>
    <p>Identify a candidate change-point using CUSUM</p>
    <p>Apply a statistical test to determine whether the change is significant</p>
    <p>CP/RankOrder:</p>
    <p>Based on Fligner-Policello Robust Rank-Order Test [SC88]</p>
    <p>CP/Bootstrap:</p>
    <p>Based on bootstrap analysis</p>
    <p>Binary segmentation for multiple change-points</p>
    <p>Need to re-compute the significance levels</p>
    <p>Ck = i=1..k (Ti  E(T))Ti E(T)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measurement Methodology</p>
    <p>Two basic types of measurements</p>
    <p>Poisson packet streams (for loss and delay)</p>
    <p>Payload: 64 or 256 bytes; rate: 10 or 20 Hz; duration: 1 Hour.</p>
    <p>Poisson intervals  unbiased time averages [Wo82]</p>
    <p>Bi-directional measurements  RTT</p>
    <p>TCP transfers (for throughput)</p>
    <p>1 MB transfer every minute for a 5-hour period</p>
    <p>Measurement infrastructure</p>
    <p>NIMI: National Internet Measurement Infrastructure</p>
    <p>35-50 hosts</p>
    <p>~75% in USA; the rest in 6 countries</p>
    <p>Well-connected: mainly academic and laboratory sites</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Datasets Description</p>
    <p>Two main sets of data</p>
    <p>Winter 1999-2000 (W1)</p>
    <p>Winter 2000-2001 (W2)</p>
    <p># NIMI sites</p>
    <p># transfers # thruput</p>
    <p>traces # packets</p>
    <p># packet traces</p>
    <p>Dataset</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Individual Loss vs. Loss Episodes</p>
    <p>Traditional approach  look at individual losses [Bo93,Mu94,Pa99,YMKT99].</p>
    <p>Correlation reported on time scales below 200-1000 ms</p>
    <p>Our approach  consider loss episodes</p>
    <p>Loss episode: a series of consecutive packets that are lost</p>
    <p>Loss episode process  the time series indicating when a loss episode occurs</p>
    <p>Can be constructed by collapsing loss episodes and the non-lost packet that follows them into a single point.</p>
    <p>ORVVSURFHVV</p>
    <p>HSLVRGHSURFHVV</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Source of Correlation in the Loss Process</p>
    <p>Many traces become consistent with IID when we consider the loss episode process</p>
    <p>Correlation in the loss process is often due to back-to-back losses, rather than intervals over which loss rates become elevated and nearby but not consecutive packets are lost.</p>
    <p>Traces consistent with IID</p>
    <p>EpisodeLoss Time scale</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Poisson Nature of Loss Episodes within CFRs</p>
    <p>Independence of loss episodes within change-free regions (CFRs)</p>
    <p>Exponential distribution of interarrivals within change-free regions</p>
    <p>85% CFRs have exponential interarrivals</p>
    <p>IID CFRs</p>
    <p>IID tracesTime scale</p>
    <p>Loss episodes are well modeled as homogeneous Poisson process within change-free regions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mathematical Constancy of Loss Episode Process C</p>
    <p>um ul</p>
    <p>at iv</p>
    <p>e P</p>
    <p>ro ba</p>
    <p>bi lit</p>
    <p>y</p>
    <p>Higher loss rate makes the loss episode process less steady</p>
    <p>Change-point test: CP/RankOrder</p>
    <p>Lossy traces are traces with overall loss rate over 1%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Operational Constancy of Loss Rate</p>
    <p>Loss rate categories</p>
    <p>0-0.5%, 0.5-2%, 2-5%, 5-10%, 10-20%, 20+%</p>
    <p>Probabilities of observing a steady interval of 50 or more minutes</p>
    <p>There is little difference in the size of steady intervals of 50 or less minutes.</p>
    <p>Prob.TypeInterval</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mathematical vs. Operational</p>
    <p>Categorize traces as steady or not steady</p>
    <p>whether a trace has a 20-minute steady region</p>
    <p>Operational constancy of packet loss coincides with mathematical constancy on large time scales (e.g. 1 min), but</p>
    <p>not so well on medium time scales (e.g. 10 sec).</p>
    <p>Interval</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Predictive Constancy of Loss Rate</p>
    <p>What to predict?</p>
    <p>The length of next loss free run</p>
    <p>Used in TFRC [FHPW00]</p>
    <p>Estimators  EWMA, MA, SMA</p>
    <p>Mean prediction error E [ | log (predicted / actual) | ]</p>
    <p>The parameters dont matter, nor does the averaging scheme.</p>
    <p>C um</p>
    <p>ul at</p>
    <p>iv e</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>ba bi</p>
    <p>lit y</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Effects of Mathematical and Operational Constancy on Prediction</p>
    <p>Prediction performance is the worst for traces that are both mathematically and operationally steady</p>
    <p>C um</p>
    <p>ul at</p>
    <p>iv e</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>ba bi</p>
    <p>lit y</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Delay Constancy</p>
    <p>Mathematical constancy</p>
    <p>Delay spikes</p>
    <p>A spike is identified when</p>
    <p>5t PD[^. 5PV` (K = 2 or 4) where</p>
    <p>5 is the new RTT measurement;</p>
    <p>5is the previous non-spike RTT measurement;</p>
    <p>The spike episode process is well described as Poisson within CFRs</p>
    <p>Body of RTT distribution (Median, IQR)</p>
    <p>Overall, less steady than loss</p>
    <p>Good agreement (90-92%) with IID within CFRs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Delay Constancy (contd)</p>
    <p>Operational constancy</p>
    <p>Operational categories</p>
    <p>0-0.1sec, 0.1-0.2sec, 0.2-0.3sec, 0.3-0.8sec, 0.8+sec</p>
    <p>Based on ITU Recommendation G.114</p>
    <p>Not operationally steady</p>
    <p>Over 50% traces have max steady regions under 10 min;</p>
    <p>80% are under 20 minutes</p>
    <p>Predictive constancy</p>
    <p>All estimators perform similar</p>
    <p>Highly predictable in general</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Throughput Constancy</p>
    <p>Mathematical constancy</p>
    <p>90% of time in CFRs longer than 20 min</p>
    <p>Good agreement (92%) with IID within CFRs</p>
    <p>Operational constancy</p>
    <p>There is a wide range</p>
    <p>Predictive constancy</p>
    <p>All estimators perform very similar</p>
    <p>Estimators with long memory perform poorly</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Our work sheds light on the current degree of constancy found in three key Internet path properties</p>
    <p>IID works surprisingly well</p>
    <p>Its important to find the appropriate model.</p>
    <p>Different classes of predictors frequently used in networking produced very similar error levels</p>
    <p>What really matters is whether you adapt, not how you adapt.</p>
    <p>One can generally count on constancy on at least the time scales of minutes</p>
    <p>This gives the time scales for caching path parameters</p>
    <p>We have developed a set of concepts and tools to understand different aspects of constancy</p>
    <p>Applicable even when the traffic condition changes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgments</p>
    <p>Andrew Adams  Matt Mathis  Jamshid Mahdavi  Lee Breslau  Mark Allman  NIMI volunteers</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
