<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Active Learning with the CyberCIEGE Video Game</p>
    <p>Michael F. Thompson and Dr. Cynthia E. Irvine Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>Naval Postgraduate School Monterey, CA USA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The CyberCIEGE Educational Video Game</p>
    <p>Educational tool for teaching cyber security - Developed by NPS via several government sponsors - Used by universities, community colleges, &amp; government</p>
    <p>Players construct and defend computer networks - 3D construction &amp; management simulation video game - Many scenarios illustrating a range of security topics</p>
    <p>Custom-built game engine manages attacks and economy - Enterprise assets and users who need to access assets - Attacks driven by motive: malware; flaws; insiders; etc.</p>
    <p>August 2011 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Educational Goals</p>
    <p>Broad audience - Cover a wide variety of computer security concepts - Relatively low barrier to entry beyond basic game mechanics</p>
    <p>Let students approach the game on their terms - Try wrong choices, experiment, fail, reflect - Stand alone game hosted on standard platform (windows) - Game available in computer labs and for use on own laptops</p>
    <p>Primarily a teaching (vice testing) tool</p>
    <p>August 2011 3</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CyberCIEGE Components</p>
    <p>Domain-specific simulation engine packaged as a game - Network topology and security assessment - Game economy and motive-driven attacks</p>
    <p>Scenario definition language - Express a range of scenarios - Simple training &amp; awareness through cyber-warfare</p>
    <p>Video-enhanced encyclopedia - Animated tutorial videos - Player help and lab manuals</p>
    <p>Student assessment tool - Detailed game logs reflecting student choices - Summary reports showing student progress</p>
    <p>August 2011 4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Network Simulation</p>
    <p>Illustrate fundamental computer security concepts - Configurable components; meaningful player choices - Experience consequences of choices</p>
    <p>Not a high fidelity vulnerability analysis tool - Abstract representation of security products and features - Avoids much of the configuration minutia; focus on function</p>
    <p>Attack engine - Network topology and configuration assessment - Insiders; trap doors; wiretaps; physical security; etc.</p>
    <p>August 2011 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Hands on Experimentation with Security Concepts</p>
    <p>Scenario-specific Policies: Users and Information (assets) - User (character) goals to access assets - Attacker motives to compromise assets</p>
    <p>Things the player can change: - Physical Security: guards; locks; biometrics; access lists - Component configuration (e.g., ACLs; filters; VPNs; etc.) - Procedures (user behavior depends on policy/training) - Patch management; configuration management; etc. - Network topology: air gaps; vulnerable network links - PKI used for VPNs, email and SSL/TLS - Personnel security: background checks; malicious insiders</p>
    <p>August 2011 6</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Game Engine Attacks: Motives Determine Strength</p>
    <p>Direct and indirect access by outside attackers - May require entering a physical zone - Trojan horses; trap doors; flaws; configuration errors - Procedures (external software, user training, CM, etc.) - Separate Internet attacks</p>
    <p>Insiders - Like outsiders, but based on trust (background checks) - May be bribed to disclose / modify assets directly</p>
    <p>Wiretaps (viewing &amp; modifying bits on the wire)  Other</p>
    <p>- Compromises of PKI elements (e.g., subverted CA) - Smart cards as a medium for data flow</p>
    <p>August 2011 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workstation and Server Components</p>
    <p>Operating Systems - Access control lists - Label based mandatory access controls - Authentication, password policies; auth servers, biometrics</p>
    <p>Configure application based security - SSL / TLS on servers (web servers; SSH servers) - Email encryption; browsers; SSH clients; VPN clients</p>
    <p>Varying assurance and patch requirements - High motive attacks require high assurance platforms</p>
    <p>August 2011 8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Networking Components</p>
    <p>Routers - Simple interconnection of networks. No network</p>
    <p>addressing - Configurable application service filters (firewall).</p>
    <p>VPN Gateways (clients are similar) - Symmetric key or public key (PKI) - Connection Profiles define traffic protection types - Illustrates risks, e.g., island hopping - Clients configurable for measured boot (like a TPM)</p>
    <p>Link Encryptors - Manual key management vs software-based - Wont work through routers</p>
    <p>August 2011 9</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sample Game Play</p>
    <p>CyberCIEGE Network Filters scenario</p>
    <p>August 2011 10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NPS Experience with CyberCIEGE</p>
    <p>Scenarios assigned as labs for Intro to Computer Security - Students receive full period of introduction and group play - Included in course for nineteen quarters</p>
    <p>No formal NPS research, pilot studies at two institutions</p>
    <p>Based on informal feedback and observations of logs: - Most students enjoy the game and have learned from it - Students approach games in a variety of different ways</p>
    <p>Key adaptations based on our experience - Feedback for a broader set of player choices: MORE HELP - In-game formative assessment (e.g., multiple choice)</p>
    <p>August 2011 11</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Time Spent on the Filters Scenario (149 students)</p>
    <p>August 2011 12</p>
    <p># of</p>
    <p>s tu</p>
    <p>de nt</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Total minutes per student</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Filters Scenario Sessions Started (149 students)</p>
    <p>August 2011 13</p>
    <p># S</p>
    <p>tu de</p>
    <p>nt s</p>
    <p># Times Played</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Current and Future Work</p>
    <p>NPS is working with NSF to adapt CyberCIEGE - Further align with standard computer security textbooks - Additional focus on network parameter, e.g., packet analysis - Ultimate objective: to use in formal education settings</p>
    <p>A need for formal education research - Are games an effective way to teach?</p>
    <p>In the class room; in the lab; as homework?  Is there a measurable difference from other techniques?</p>
    <p>- Seeking education research collaborators</p>
    <p>August 2011 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Hands-on exercises promote active learning  Computer security is a good target for serious games</p>
    <p>- Sometimes subtle concepts - Simulate complex environments and extreme consequences</p>
    <p>Effectiveness of serious games needs formal research - CyberCIEGE has good depth of material - Hundreds of universities and community colleges</p>
    <p>CyberCIEGE is available with a no-cost educational license - Email cyberciege@nps.edu - SDK available for customizing scenarios</p>
    <p>August 2011 15</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contact</p>
    <p>Center for Information Systems Security Studies and Research Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>Naval Postgraduate School, Monterey, CA 93943 U.S.A</p>
    <p>http://www.cisr.us</p>
    <p>March 2011 16</p>
    <p>Cynthia E. Irvine, Ph.D Professor and Director</p>
    <p>irvine@nps.edu</p>
    <p>Michael F. Thompson Research Associate</p>
    <p>mfthomps@nps.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
