<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jeffrey Pang1 Ben Greenstein2 Ramakrishna Gummadi3 Srinivasan Seshan1 David Wetherall2,4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>They leave digital fingerprints that reveal who we are  And thus where weve been</p>
    <p>Bob@Intel Bob@Intel</p>
    <p>Why is Bob over there?</p>
    <p>Motivation: The Mobile Wireless Landscape</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Location privacy is growing concern  Wireless Privacy Protection Act [U.S. House Bill 05]</p>
    <p>Geographic location/privacy working group [IETF]</p>
    <p>Motivation: The Mobile Wireless Landscape</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation: The Mobile Wireless Landscape</p>
    <p>A well known technical problem  Devices have unique and consistent addresses</p>
    <p>e.g., 802.11 devices have MAC addresses</p>
    <p>fingerprinting them is trivial!</p>
    <p>MAC address now: 00:0E:35:CE:1F:59</p>
    <p>MAC address later: 00:0E:35:CE:1F:59</p>
    <p>Adversary tcpdump tcpdump</p>
    <p>time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation: The Mobile Wireless Landscape</p>
    <p>The widely proposed techical solution  Pseudonyms: Change addresses over time</p>
    <p>802.11: Gruteser 05, Hu 06, Jiang 07  Bluetooth: Stajano 05  RFID: Juels 04  GSM: already employed</p>
    <p>MAC address now: 00:0E:35:CE:1F:59</p>
    <p>MAC address later: 00:AA:BB:CC:DD:EE</p>
    <p>tcpdump tcpdump</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation: The Mobile Wireless Landscape</p>
    <p>Our work shows: Pseudonyms are not enough  Implicit identifiers: identifying characteristics of traffic  E.G., most users identified with 90% accuracy in hotspots</p>
    <p>tcpdump tcpdump</p>
    <p>Search: Bobs Home Net Packets  Intel Email Server</p>
    <p>Search: Bobs Home Net Packets  Intel Email Server</p>
    <p>time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions</p>
    <p>Four Novel 802.11 Implicit Identifiers</p>
    <p>Automated Identification Procedure</p>
    <p>Evaluating Implicit Identifier Accuracy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions</p>
    <p>Four Novel 802.11 Implicit Identifiers</p>
    <p>Automated Identification Procedure</p>
    <p>Evaluating Implicit Identifier Accuracy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implicit Identifiers by Example</p>
    <p>Consider one user at SIGCOMM 2004  Transferred 512MB via BitTorrent</p>
    <p>Poor network etiquette?</p>
    <p>Seen in a anonymized wireless trace</p>
    <p>MAC addresses hashed, effectively a pseudonym</p>
    <p>Can we identify the culprit using implicit identifiers?</p>
    <p>tcpdump</p>
    <p>?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implicit Identifiers by Example</p>
    <p>Implicit identifier: SSIDs in probes  Set of SSIDs in 802.11 probe requests  Many 802.11 drivers search for preferred networks  Usually networks you have associated with before</p>
    <p>SSID Probe: roofnet</p>
    <p>User of roofnet</p>
    <p>tcpdump</p>
    <p>?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implicit Identifiers by Example</p>
    <p>Implicit identifier: SSIDs in probes  Set of SSIDs in 802.11 probe requests  Many 802.11 drivers search for preferred networks  Usually networks you have associated with before</p>
    <p>SSID Probe: roofnet</p>
    <p>tcpdump</p>
    <p>Bittorrent transfer</p>
    <p>? tcpdump</p>
    <p>time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implicit Identifiers by Example</p>
    <p>Implicit identifier: network destinations  IP &lt;address, port&gt; pairs in network traffic</p>
    <p>At SIGCOMM, each visited by 1.15 users on average</p>
    <p>Some nearly-unique destinations repeatedly visited (e.g., email server)</p>
    <p>SSH/IMAP server: 159.16.40.45</p>
    <p>tcpdump</p>
    <p>? tcpdump</p>
    <p>time</p>
    <p>SSH/IMAP server: 159.16.40.45</p>
    <p>?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implicit Identifiers by Example</p>
    <p>Implicit identifier: broadcast packet sizes  Set of 802.11 broadcast packet sizes in network traffic</p>
    <p>E.g., Windows machines NetBIOS naming advertisements; FileMaker and Microsoft Office advertise themselves</p>
    <p>Broadcast pkt sizes: 239, 245, 257</p>
    <p>tcpdump</p>
    <p>? tcpdump</p>
    <p>time</p>
    <p>Broadcast pkt sizes: 239, 245, 257</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implicit Identifiers by Example</p>
    <p>Implicit identifier: MAC protocol fields  Header bits (e.g., power management., order)</p>
    <p>Supported rates</p>
    <p>Offered authentication algorithms</p>
    <p>tcpdump</p>
    <p>? tcpdump</p>
    <p>time</p>
    <p>Protocol Fields: 11,4,2,1Mbps, WEP</p>
    <p>Protocol Fields: 11,4,2,1Mbps, WEP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implicit Identifier Summary</p>
    <p>Network destinations</p>
    <p>SSIDs in probes</p>
    <p>Broadcast pkt sizes</p>
    <p>MAC protocol fields</p>
    <p>Vi si bl</p>
    <p>e ev</p>
    <p>en w</p>
    <p>ith</p>
    <p>W EP</p>
    <p>/W PA</p>
    <p>T KI</p>
    <p>P</p>
    <p>en cr</p>
    <p>yp tio</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>More implicit identifiers exist  Results we present establish a lower bound</p>
    <p>Id en</p>
    <p>tif yi ng</p>
    <p>e ve</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>if de</p>
    <p>vi ce</p>
    <p>s ha</p>
    <p>ve</p>
    <p>id en</p>
    <p>tic al</p>
    <p>d riv</p>
    <p>er s</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fixing Implicit Identifiers is not Simple</p>
    <p>Encryption does not prevent traffic analysis  Cover traffic?  Challenge: Shared medium  large performance hit</p>
    <p>Service discovery is done in the clear  Dont probe?  Challenge: Beaconing is often undesirable also</p>
    <p>Implementation and configuration variation  Standardize?  Challenge: Ambiguity of specifications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions</p>
    <p>Four Novel 802.11 Implicit Identifiers</p>
    <p>Automated Identification Procedure</p>
    <p>Evaluating Implicit Identifier Accuracy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tracking 802.11 Users</p>
    <p>Many potential tracking applications:  Was user X here today?  Where was user X today?</p>
    <p>What traffic is from user X?</p>
    <p>When was user X here?</p>
    <p>Etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tracking 802.11 Users</p>
    <p>Tracking scenario:  Every users changes pseudonyms every hour</p>
    <p>Adversary monitors some locations  One hourly traffic sample from each user in each location</p>
    <p>? ?</p>
    <p>? tcpdump</p>
    <p>Build a profile from training samples: First collect some traffic known to be from user X and from random others</p>
    <p>tcpdump .....? ?</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>Then classify observation samples</p>
    <p>Traffic at 2-3PM Traffic at 3-4PM</p>
    <p>Traffic at 4-5PM</p>
    <p>Traffic at 2-3PM Traffic at 3-4PM</p>
    <p>Traffic at 4-5PM</p>
    <p>Traffic at 2-3PM Traffic at 3-4PM</p>
    <p>Traffic at 4-5PM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sample Classification Algorithm</p>
    <p>Core question:  Did traffic sample s come from user X?</p>
    <p>A simple approach: nave Bayes classifier  Derive probabilistic model from training samples</p>
    <p>Given s with features F, answer yes if:</p>
    <p>Pr[ s from user X | s has features F ] &gt; T</p>
    <p>for a selected threshold T.</p>
    <p>F = feature set derived from implicit identifiers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deriving features F from implicit identifiers</p>
    <p>Set similarity (Jaccard Index), weighted by frequency:</p>
    <p>IR_Guest</p>
    <p>SAMPLE FROM OBSERVATION</p>
    <p>Sample Classification Algorithm</p>
    <p>linksys djw</p>
    <p>SIGCOMM_1</p>
    <p>PROFILE FROM TRAINING</p>
    <p>Rare</p>
    <p>Common w(e) = low</p>
    <p>w(e) = high</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Contributions</p>
    <p>Four Novel 802.11 Implicit Identifiers</p>
    <p>Automated Identification Procedure</p>
    <p>Evaluating Implicit Identifier Accuracy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluating Classification Effectiveness</p>
    <p>Simulate tracking scenario with wireless traces:</p>
    <p>Split each trace into training and observation phases</p>
    <p>Simulate pseudonym changes for each user X</p>
    <p>Duration Profiled Users Total Users</p>
    <p>SIGCOMM conf. (2004)</p>
    <p>UCSD office building (2006)</p>
    <p>Apartment building (2006)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Question: Is observation sample s from user X?</p>
    <p>Evaluation metrics:  True positive rate (TPR)</p>
    <p>Fraction of user Xs samples classified correctly</p>
    <p>False positive rate (FPR) Fraction of other samples classified incorrectly</p>
    <p>Evaluating Classification Effectiveness</p>
    <p>Pr[ s from user X | s has features F ] &gt; T</p>
    <p>= 0.01</p>
    <p>= ???</p>
    <p>Fix T for FPR</p>
    <p>Measure TPR</p>
    <p>(See paper)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Individual Feature Accuracy</p>
    <p>TPR  60%</p>
    <p>TPR  30%</p>
    <p>Individual implicit identifiers give evidence of identity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Multiple Feature Accuracy Users with TPR &gt;50%:</p>
    <p>Public: 63% Home: 31% Enterprise: 27%</p>
    <p>We can identify many users in all environments</p>
    <p>Public Home Enterprise</p>
    <p>netdests</p>
    <p>ssids</p>
    <p>bcast</p>
    <p>fields</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Multiple Feature Accuracy</p>
    <p>Some users much more distinguishable than others</p>
    <p>Public networks: ~20% users identified &gt;90% of the time</p>
    <p>Public Home Enterprise</p>
    <p>netdests</p>
    <p>ssids</p>
    <p>bcast</p>
    <p>fields</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>One Application</p>
    <p>Question: Was user X here today?  More difficult to answer:</p>
    <p>Suppose N users present each hour  Over an 8 hour day, 8N opportunities to misclassify Decide user X is here only if multiple samples are</p>
    <p>classified as his</p>
    <p>Revised: Was user X here today for a few hours?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Tracking with 90% Accuracy</p>
    <p>Majority of users can be identified if active long enough</p>
    <p>Of 268 users (71%):</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Implicit identifiers can accurately identify users  Individual implicit identifiers give evidence of identity  We can identify many users in all environments  Some users much more distinguishable than others</p>
    <p>Understanding implicit identifiers is important  Pseudonyms are not enough  We establish a lower bound on their accuracy</p>
    <p>Eliminating them poses research challenges  Current work: Confidential service discovery  Current work: Traffic analysis resistant MAC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extra Slides</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Other Implicit Identifiers  Device driver fingerprints [Franklin 06]  Clock-skew fingerprints [Kohno 05]  Click-prints [Padmanabhan 06]  RF antenna fingerprints [Hall 04]</p>
    <p>Our work:  802.11 fingerprints for individual users  Tracking with only commodity hardware/software  Better coverage than some previous work  Procedure to combine implicit identifiers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluating Classification Effectiveness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Individual Feature Accuracy</p>
    <p>Individual implicit identifiers give evidence of identity</p>
    <p>TPR  50%</p>
    <p>Other implicit identifiers distinguish groups of users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Tracking with 90% Accuracy</p>
    <p>Many users can be identified in all environments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Old Slides</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Answers to Common Questions  Is tracking accuracy good enough to track an entire city/how does it vary with population size?</p>
    <p>Our accuracy results arent good enough to allow fine-grained tracking of most users in environments with more than 100s of users because the adversary will simply obtain too many samples and have too many opportunities for false positives. However, we note that by modifying the question a little, such as was this person here for x hours, where x is reasonably large, such as a couple days or was this person here in this specific area with smaller population in the sub-100s, we can answer it fairly accurately.</p>
    <p>Your traces were only over a couple days, why would one expect fingerprints to remain identifying over longer periods of time?</p>
    <p>You are correct and we cant say anything empirical for longer term tracking. However, we suspect that the implicit identifiers would remain identifying because they are mostly caused by automatic behavior of drivers and applications and thus wouldnt change due to human behavior or location. In the paper we show that ssids are stable over weeks at least for example.</p>
    <p>Do you think people really care about location privacy?  I think that people dont care until they realize that they have a problem and then they do (e.g., the article about a guy tracking his</p>
    <p>ex-girlfriend). One magnifying factor is that because of the low cost of 802.11 radios and the ubiquity of 802.11 in devices, almost anyone can easily monitor some locations and track users of interest.</p>
    <p>Dont you think people could modify their behavior in order not to be as identifying when they want to be private?  Sure; if they had the technical knowledge to do so, they could easily modify their behavior to look different and leave a different</p>
    <p>implicit fingerprint. However, I would argue that this is undesirable because it means that privacy concerns have a chilling effect on the types of act ivies we are willing to do thus limiting the wireless applications. I think the protocols themselves should protect us enough so that we dont have to worry about these things.</p>
    <p>What about wireless protocols other than 802.11?  I believe many of the implicit identifiers still exist, for the reason that the fundamental reasons behind their existence remain: you</p>
    <p>can still do traffic analysis even with encryption, all wireless protocols have some form of service discovery, and there is implementation variation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Problem  People are worried about tracking, 802.11 is especially worrisome  Pseudonyms proposed, not enough</p>
    <p>Bittorrent Example  Use to explain each identifier  Summarize implicit identifiers</p>
    <p>How to train as an example  Points to bring up and jx:</p>
    <p>1 hour sample size  How to select the classifier threshold  How adversary could obtain training samples</p>
    <p>Learning process  Q1 results  Q2 results</p>
    <p>An attacker can use multiple features and multiple samples, so ask question</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implicit Identifiers by Example</p>
    <p>Implicit identifier: network destinations  IP &lt;address, port&gt; pairs in network traffic</p>
    <p>At SIGCOMM, each visited by 1.15 users on average</p>
    <p>Some nearly-unique destinations repeatedly visited (e.g., email server)</p>
    <p>SSH/IMAP server: 159.16.40.45</p>
    <p>WPA TKIP encryption</p>
    <p>XXXXX</p>
    <p>tcpdump</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Individual Feature Accuracy</p>
    <p>Some users more distinguishable than others</p>
    <p>netdests: ~60% users identified &gt;50% of the time</p>
    <p>~20% users identified &gt;90% of the time</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
