<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>On the Use and Performance of Content Distribution Networks</p>
    <p>Yin Zhang Joint work with</p>
    <p>Balachander Krishnamurthy and Craig Wills</p>
    <p>AT&amp;T Labs Research, WPI {yzhang,bala}@research.att.com, cew@cs.wpi.edu</p>
    <p>ACM SIGCOMM Internet Measurement Workshop November, 2001</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>What is a CDN?</p>
    <p>A network of servers delivering content on behalf of an origin site</p>
    <p>State of CDNs</p>
    <p>A number of CDN companies</p>
    <p>E.g. Akamai, Digital Island, Speedera</p>
    <p>Used by many popular origin sites</p>
    <p>E.g., CNN, CNBC,</p>
    <p>Little has been published on the use and performance of existing CDNs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Questions to Answer</p>
    <p>What CDN techniques are being used?</p>
    <p>What is the extent to which CDNs are being used by popular origin sites?</p>
    <p>What is the nature of CDN-served content?</p>
    <p>What methodology can be used to measure the relative performance of CDNs?</p>
    <p>What are specific CDNs performing both relative to origin servers and among themselves?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What CDN redirection techniques are being used?</p>
    <p>Techniques examined</p>
    <p>DNS redirection (DR)</p>
    <p>Full-site delivery (DR-F)</p>
    <p>Partial-site delivery (DR-P)</p>
    <p>URL rewriting (UR)  Hybrid scheme (URDR)</p>
    <p>URL rewriting + DNS redirection</p>
    <p>Techniques NOT examined</p>
    <p>Manual hyperlink selection</p>
    <p>HTTP redirection</p>
    <p>Layer 4 switching</p>
    <p>Layer 7 switching</p>
    <p>Origin ServerClient</p>
    <p>CDN Name Server</p>
    <p>CDN Server</p>
    <p>&amp;'1VHUYHU</p>
    <p>QDPH</p>
    <p>&amp;'1</p>
    <p>VHUYHU,3</p>
    <p>T X</p>
    <p>H V</p>
    <p>W</p>
    <p>V S</p>
    <p>R Q</p>
    <p>V H</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How widely are CDNs being used?</p>
    <p>Sources of data</p>
    <p>CDN use by popular sites</p>
    <p>Date/Duration</p>
    <p>Proxy log</p>
    <p>Periodic crawl</p>
    <p>Type</p>
    <p>SitesDatasets</p>
    <p>HotMM127: 31% (Akamai: 98%) URL588-MM500: 17% (Akamai: 85%)</p>
    <p>Dec. 2000</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Nature of CDN-served Content</p>
    <p>Daily change characteristics of CDN-served objects</p>
    <p>Nature of HTTP-requested CDN content</p>
    <p>Images account for 96-98% CDN-served objects, or 40-60% CDN-served bytes</p>
    <p>Akamai serves 85-98% CDN-served objects (bytes)</p>
    <p>Cache hit rates of CDN-served images are generally 20-30% higher than non-CDN served images</p>
    <p>URL588-MM500HotMM127Dataset</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Study: Methodology</p>
    <p>Get CDN server IP address URL rewriting  first get CDN server name</p>
    <p>Warm up CDN cache Retrieve pages using httperf</p>
    <p>Parallel-1.0  4 HTTP/1.0 Serial-1.1 -- 2 persistent HTTP/1.1 Pipeline-1.1  1 pipelined HTTP/1.1</p>
    <p>General Methodology: From N client sites periodically download pages from different CDNs and origin sites.</p>
    <p>Client Origin Server</p>
    <p>CDN Name ServerCDN Server</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Content for Performance Study</p>
    <p>Challenge:</p>
    <p>Different CDNs have different customers. How to compare apples to apples?</p>
    <p>Solution: Canonical Pages</p>
    <p>Create template page based on distributions of the number and size of embedded images at popular sites</p>
    <p>In our study, we download 54 images and record download time for the first 6, 12, 18, 54 images.</p>
    <p>For each CDN, construct a canonical page with a list of image URLs currently served by the CDN from a single origin site, that closely match the sizes in the template page.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measurement Infrastructure</p>
    <p>CDNs</p>
    <p>*AT&amp;T ICDS NOT tested due to conflict of interest.</p>
    <p>Origin sites</p>
    <p>US: Amazon, Bloomberg, CNN, ESPN, MTV, NASA, Playboy, Sony, Yahoo</p>
    <p>International: 2 Europe, 2 Asia, 1 South America, 1 Australia</p>
    <p>Client sites</p>
    <p>24 NIMI client sites in 6 countries</p>
    <p>NIMI: National Internet Measurement Infrastructure</p>
    <p>Well-connected: mainly academic and laboratory sites</p>
    <p>Clearway</p>
    <p>UR</p>
    <p>Fasttide Akamai, Speedera,</p>
    <p>Digital Island AderoCDNs</p>
    <p>URDRDR-PDR-FTechnique</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Response Time Results (I) Excluding DNS Lookup Time</p>
    <p>CDNs generally provide much shorter download time.</p>
    <p>C um</p>
    <p>ul at</p>
    <p>iv e</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>ba bi</p>
    <p>lit y</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Response Time Results (II) Including DNS Lookup Time</p>
    <p>DNS overhead is a serious performance bottleneck for some CDNs.</p>
    <p>C um</p>
    <p>ul at</p>
    <p>iv e</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>ba bi</p>
    <p>lit y</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Impact of Protocol Options and the Number of Images</p>
    <p>Pipeline-1.1</p>
    <p>Serial-1.1</p>
    <p>Parallel-1.0</p>
    <p>Protocol Option</p>
    <p>Mean Download Time Range (sec.) Site</p>
    <p>Mean Download Performance Range for Different Numbers of Images and Protocol Options (Jan. 2001)</p>
    <p>CDNs perform significantly better than origin sites, although reducing the number of images (e.g. due to caching) and using HTTP/1.1</p>
    <p>options reduces the performance difference.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Effectiveness of DNS Load Balancing</p>
    <p>Small DNS TTLs generally do not improve download times.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Effectiveness of DNS Load Balancing (contd)</p>
    <p>Mean completion time (sec.)</p>
    <p>Fixed IP</p>
    <p>New IP</p>
    <p>CDN (technique)</p>
    <p>Fixed IPNew IP</p>
    <p>Parallel-1.0 Download Performance for CDN Server at New and Fixed IP Addresses (Jan. 01)</p>
    <p>Small DNS TTLs generally do not improve download times in either average or worst case situations.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CDN Server Use</p>
    <p>Number of Distinct IP Addresses Returned to a Client versus the Mean Download Time (MDT) of Parallel-1.0</p>
    <p>Having more CDN servers does not necessarily imply better download performance.</p>
    <p>MDT (sec)</p>
    <p>MDT (sec)</p>
    <p>Speedera (DR-P) Fasttide (URDR) Digisle (DR-P) Clearway (UR) Akamai (DR-P) Adero (DR-F)</p>
    <p>CDN (technique)</p>
    <p>TotalMaxMeanTotalMaxMean Jan. 2001Sept. 2001</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ongoing Research: CDN Performance for Streaming Media</p>
    <p>Emerging content  streaming media</p>
    <p>Streaming media account for less than 1% CDN-served objects, but 14-20% CDN-served bytes</p>
    <p>Methodology</p>
    <p>Similar to the one for static images</p>
    <p>Streaming content examined</p>
    <p>ASF (Advanced Streaming Format) streamed over HTTP</p>
    <p>Canonical streaming media object</p>
    <p>Encoding rates: 38/100/300 Kbps</p>
    <p>Duration: 10 sec. (specified via HTTP headers)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CDN Performance For Streaming Media: Preliminary Results</p>
    <p>(sec) DNS (sec)</p>
    <p>Last Byte (sec) CDN</p>
    <p>CDN Performance on Streaming Media: Mean DNS, First Byte, and Last Byte (relative to Target Delay of 10 sec) Delays</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>There is a clear increase in the number and percentage of popular origin sites using CDNs</p>
    <p>may have decreased subsequently</p>
    <p>CDNs performed significantly better than origin sites, although caching and HTTP/1.1 options both reduce the performance difference</p>
    <p>Small DNS TTLs generally do not improve client download times in either average or worst case situations</p>
    <p>Our methodology can be extended to test CDN performance for delivering streaming media</p>
    <p>More streaming media results available in the TM version: http://www.research.att.com/~bala/papers/abcd-tm.ps.gz</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgments</p>
    <p>Vern Paxson</p>
    <p>For being involved in earlier stages of the study and help with NIMI</p>
    <p>Reviewers</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
