<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A DecisionA Decision Analytic Approach for Analytic Approach for A DecisionA Decision--Analytic Approach for Analytic Approach for PP22P Cooperation Policy SettingP Cooperation Policy Settingp y gp y g</p>
    <p>G V k l 1 Th G P 2 S Kh d 1G. Vakili1, Th. G. Papaioannou2, S. Khorsandi1 1 Amirkabir University of Technology</p>
    <p>Tehran IranTehran  Iran 2 Ecole Polytechnique Fdrale de Lausanne (EPFL)</p>
    <p>Lausanne  Switzerland</p>
    <p>NetEcon10</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>O tliO tliOutlineOutline</p>
    <p>Our Motivation &amp; Goal Our ApproachOur Approach System Model Decision-Analytic Approach AnalysisAnalysis</p>
    <p>NE Analysis</p>
    <p>Evaluation ConclusionConclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>O M ti ti &amp; G lO M ti ti &amp; G lOur Motivation &amp; GoalOur Motivation &amp; Goal Overall performance of P2P systems depends on resource contributions of individual peers.</p>
    <p>Rational peers decide on their cooperation policies according to their individual utilitiesaccording to their individual utilities.</p>
    <p>Inherent conflict among individual utilities of the rational Inherent conflict among individual utilities of the rational peers results in</p>
    <p>free-riding unfair contribution low participation</p>
    <p>Our goal is dealing with the inherent individual utility conflicts to improve overall performance of the systemconflicts to improve overall performance of the system.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our ApproachOur ApproachOur ApproachOur Approach We employ decision-theory to model cooperation p y y p policy setting of participating peers:</p>
    <p>Each peer chooses its strategy according to observable strategies of the other peers. Through a swarm-based iterative learning process:</p>
    <p>R l h l Rational peers set their cooperation policies so as to maximize their own utility. Their decisions are coordinated in a distributed manner to Their decisions are coordinated in a distributed manner to improve the social welfare of the system.</p>
    <p>The game-theoretic analysis lacks an explicit and tractable handling of the individual strategy g gy dynamics present in the interactions among individual peersp</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SYSTEM MODELSYSTEM MODELSYSTEM MODELSYSTEM MODEL</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IndividualIndividual--based Lagrangian based Lagrangian Swarm Swarm ModelModel I t ti ti i t f P2P t hibit l Interacting participants of a P2P system exhibit general properties of an individual based Lagrangian swarm model:model:</p>
    <p>composed of many individual peers; the interactions are based on local information exchange; g ; emergence; self-organization.</p>
    <p>We made two modifications to adopt this model in h f P2P the context of a P2P system:</p>
    <p>Distributed local objectives (utility functions) are defined for individual peersindividual peers. The interaction of particles is represented as a noncooperative game.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DefinitionsDefinitionsDefinitionsDefinitions We assume that N peers p ; i:1 N participate in We assume that N peers pi ; i:1,,N participate in the system P li (d )Policy (di)</p>
    <p>a peers policy is its level of cooperation (a numerical t f th  t ib t d t th assessment of the peers contributed resources to the</p>
    <p>system) St t ( )Strategy (si)</p>
    <p>the strategy of a peer reflects its decision on the change i it ti l l ( li )in its cooperation level (policy)</p>
    <p>Utility (Ui) A peer's utility is determined by its strategy choices and depends on several parameters - discussed as follows.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Utility FunctionUtility Function Cost and Benefit</p>
    <p>Utility FunctionUtility Function</p>
    <p>the total cost for participating in the system with cooperation level of di will be cidi the benefit of cooperation of pj to pi is represented by bijdj ; where bij is measured (e.g.) as the inverse of latency ij j ij ( g ) y</p>
    <p>Incentives for high contributionIncentives for high contribution it is modeled by a monotonically increasing function of h i li f d d b bthe cooperation policy of a peer pi, denoted by bci</p>
    <p>Utility: 0;.. =  iiiijijii bdcdbbcU ;</p>
    <p>iiii</p>
    <p>Nj jijii</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DECISIONDECISION--ANALYTIC ANALYTIC DECISIONDECISION ANALYTIC ANALYTIC APPROACHAPPROACH</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>O llO llOverallOverall Observable strategies of other peers are monitored by each peer in a sequence of iterations. p q</p>
    <p>Based on this empirical evidence each peer can decide Based on this empirical evidence, each peer can decide rationally on a strategy in every iteration.</p>
    <p>This chain of decisions are made based on a method i i d b ti l ti i ti (PSO)inspired by particle swarm optimization (PSO).</p>
    <p>Through this chain of decisions each participating peer concludes its final cooperation policy with respect to the other peers' behavior.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>M F llM F llMore FormallyMore Formally To maximize its expected utility Ui , each peer pi sets its final cooperation policy through an iterative decision</p>
    <p>k making process: pi monitors the strategies of the other peers in its neighborhood N locally and evaluates their strategiesNi locally and evaluates their strategies. It chooses its strategy si</p>
    <p>next in the next iteration with respect to the evaluation result and to its own experience:</p>
    <p>d i h b i li f d d d h b li</p>
    <p>)()( 2211 current in</p>
    <p>current ip</p>
    <p>current i</p>
    <p>next i ddcrddcrss ++=</p>
    <p>dp is the best previous policy of pi and dn denotes the best policy of the other peers in Ni.</p>
    <p>Then the cooperation policy di of peer pi is revised as follows: nextcurrentnext sdd += iii sdd +=</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ANALYSIS ANALYSIS --ANALYSIS ANALYSIS EVALUATIONEVALUATION</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NE A l iNE A l iNE AnalysisNE Analysis We employ Nash equilibrium analysis to investigate the predicted strategies for the participating peers by th d i i l ti hthe decision-analytic approach.</p>
    <p>A di [B h i l P2PC i 03] f According to [Buragohain et al. P2PComputing03] for a similar quantitative model of the system in a homogeneous setting (for all pi bij = b ci= c) the NE is homogeneous setting (for all pi , bij b, ci c), the NE is given by:</p>
    <p>As we numerically show:</p>
    <p>y The expected NE of the game is not the Pareto-optimal one. The outcome derived from the proposed decision-analytic</p>
    <p>h ld k ll l b ffapproach would make all players better-off.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The comparison of the average The comparison of the average p gp g cooperation levelcooperation level</p>
    <p>e v e l</p>
    <p>o p e ra ti o n L</p>
    <p>Hetero</p>
    <p>Homo</p>
    <p>NE</p>
    <p>A NE</p>
    <p>Tendency toward Pareto efficiency</p>
    <p>Scaled Benefit</p>
    <p>Tendency toward Pareto efficiency</p>
    <p>Better outcome than NE Both homogeneous and heterogeneous settings evolve Both homogeneous and heterogeneous settings evolve similarly</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Convergence to a set of Pareto Convergence to a set of Pareto gg efficient strategyefficient strategy</p>
    <p>l 5</p>
    <p>a ti o n L e v e</p>
    <p>Scaled Benefit = 0.05</p>
    <p>A v e ra Scaled Benefit = 0.5</p>
    <p>Scaled Benefit = 1</p>
    <p>Number of Iterations</p>
    <p>Fast convergence regardless of the target cooperation level</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CONCLUSIONCONCLUSIONCONCLUSIONCONCLUSION</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C l i C l i F t W kF t W kConclusion Conclusion  Future WorkFuture Work We propose a decision-analytic approach based on the modified swarm model, to set and coordinate rational decisions of the individual peers on their cooperation policies in a distributed individual peers on their cooperation policies in a distributed manner.</p>
    <p>The resulting cooperation policies constitute the final set of decisions that maximize rational peers' utility in-line with the social welfare of the system.y</p>
    <p>Incentive-compatible for peers to follow</p>
    <p>Our approach quickly approximates a Pareto-optimal operating point of the system.</p>
    <p>In our future work, we will investigate information exchange mechanisms that involve incentives for neighbor truthfulness or own observation and verification.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>THANK YOU FOR YOUR THANK YOU FOR YOUR</p>
    <p>ATTENTION.ATTENTION.</p>
    <p>MORE QUESTIONS TO:MORE QUESTIONS TO:</p>
    <p>Golnaz Vakili g_vakili@aut.ac.ir</p>
    <p>Distributed Information Systems Lab, EPFL http://lsir.epfl.ch</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
