<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exertion-based billing for cloud storage access</p>
    <p>Matthew Wachs* Lianghong Xu*, Arkady Kanevsky, Greg Ganger*</p>
    <p>*PARALLEL DATA LABORATORY Carnegie Mellon University</p>
    <p>VMWARE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud accounting  Infrastructure-as-a-Service (IaaS)</p>
    <p>Provider makes resources available to clients  Clients pay for resources used</p>
    <p>Provider wants to recover costs  Client wants to pay fairly for use</p>
    <p>This talk: Focus on storage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Provider: Recovering costs  More bytes stored  more disks needed</p>
    <p>Bill for capacity</p>
    <p>Providers do this</p>
    <p>More time spent on requests  more disks needed  Bill for access  Not all providers do this  Those that do, use the wrong metric</p>
    <p>vCloud Express</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Billing for access  Providers currently bill for:</p>
    <p>IOs  Bytes transferred  Performance</p>
    <p>None matches time used  cost of resources</p>
    <p>Amazon EBS, S3, Windows Azure</p>
    <p>Amazon S3</p>
    <p>Amazon EC2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Unsustainable approach: Fixed cost per IO</p>
    <p>Request scenario Disk time Real cost Bill</p>
    <p>Cache miss, sequential 1 ms $0.01 $0.01</p>
    <p>Cache miss, long seek 20 ms $0.20 $0.01</p>
    <p>Cache hit 0 ms $0.00 $0.01</p>
    <p>Suppose provider charges $0.01 per IO but it takes $0.01/ms to operate a disk</p>
    <p>Provider loses money</p>
    <p>Client pays too much</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alternatives  Charge per byte or performance</p>
    <p>Both also vary as in previous example</p>
    <p>Charge for worst case ($0.20/IO instead of $0.01)  Clients with easy requests pay too much</p>
    <p>Charge for the average case  Some clients subsidize others  Will the average change over time?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Solution: Charge for disk time</p>
    <p>Request scenario Disk time Real cost Bill</p>
    <p>Cache miss, sequential 1 ms $0.01 $0.01</p>
    <p>Cache miss, long seek 20 ms $0.20 $0.20</p>
    <p>Cache hit 0 ms $0.00 $0.00</p>
    <p>Suppose it takes $0.01/ms to operate a disk and the provider charges $0.01/ms</p>
    <p>Costs recovered fairly</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>But, a technical problem remains  Resources may be shared across tenants  Workload A may be affected by Workload B</p>
    <p>Workload A sequential, Workload B disrupts locality  Workload A cacheable, Workload B evicts As pages  Workload B drives up Workload As bill</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interference example</p>
    <p>Workload Standalone exertion Exertion w/ interference</p>
    <p>Sequential 1 MB/s 1.6% 23%</p>
    <p>Random 1 MB/s 67% 74%</p>
    <p>Random workload increases Sequential workloads exertion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to solve?  Bill Workload B for its impact on Workload A?</p>
    <p>Not the fault of B that it coexists poorly with A</p>
    <p>Provider absorbs the cost?  Provider will either lose money or</p>
    <p>pass it along as a hidden cost to customers</p>
    <p>Avoid the interference in the first place</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance insulation is needed  Performance insulation: System property</p>
    <p>Another workload is not able to affect your  Efficiency  Exertion  Performance (in your share of time)</p>
    <p>beyond a small (e.g. 10%) factor</p>
    <p>Strictly limits transient influences</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to insulate storage  Preserve locality</p>
    <p>Disk-head timeslicing  Seek between workloads infrequently</p>
    <p>Cache partitioning  Partition sizes based on access patterns</p>
    <p>Argon storage system [FAST 2007]</p>
    <p>Provide predictable cache allocation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Insulation example</p>
    <p>Workload Standalone exertion Exertion w/ insulation</p>
    <p>Sequential 1 MB/s 1.6%  1.8%</p>
    <p>Random 1 MB/s 67%  75%</p>
    <p>Each workloads exertion is close to ideal because it receives dedicated disk time &amp; cache space</p>
    <p>Insulation limits impact of other workload to &lt; 10%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary  Clients should pay for resources used</p>
    <p>Storage: both capacity and access cost money</p>
    <p>Disk time is what costs, should be the metric</p>
    <p>Bills should be independent and predictable</p>
    <p>Performance insulation is needed to make it fair</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
