<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Distributed Systems Meet Economics: Pricing in the Cloud</p>
    <p>Presenter: Rishan Chen Peking University and Microsoft Research, Asia</p>
    <p>June 2010, Boston, MA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cloud is a distributed system</p>
    <p>System metrics  Throughput  Latency / response time  Failure rate  Power consumption, etc.</p>
    <p>As a pay-as-you-go service  Two parties connected by the pricing</p>
    <p>scheme  Its all about the money!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pricing in the Cloud</p>
    <p>It significantly changes the landscape of system design: Cost as an explicit and measurable system metric  How both parties optimize their logic  Is the pricing fair  How does the pricing interplay with the</p>
    <p>evolving system dynamics  How to measure the cost of failures, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methodology overview</p>
    <p>Approximate a typical workload in current cloud computing  Postmark (I/O-intensive)  PARSEC: Dedup, BlackScholes (CPU-intensive)  Hadoop (large-scale data processing)</p>
    <p>Complementary approaches for evaluations  A black-box approach with Amazon EC2  Built a cloud-computing test bed, Spring, to</p>
    <p>perform fully controlled experiments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Preliminary results</p>
    <p>Pricing may give different indices for users and providers for system optimizations (e.g., consolidation)</p>
    <p>System performance variations may lead to pricing fairness issues</p>
    <p>System evolution (e.g., adoption of new hardware like SSD) may affect pricing scheme</p>
    <p>Failures need to be better dealt with regarding to the cost</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Highlights of our study /1</p>
    <p>Pricing (profit) versus throughput</p>
    <p>Run Postmark continuously and report the number for four tasks; we compare the consolidation of x VMs on a single physical machine.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Highlights of our study /2</p>
    <p>Optimizing for cost versus optimizing traditional system metrics</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>v id</p>
    <p>e r</p>
    <p>In d</p>
    <p>e x</p>
    <p>U se</p>
    <p>r In</p>
    <p>d e</p>
    <p>x</p>
    <p>Postmark User Index (1/Cost)</p>
    <p>Provider Index (ROI)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Highlights of our study /3</p>
    <p>Pricing fairness: performance variation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Open questions</p>
    <p>What are good properties for a pricing scheme?</p>
    <p>How do users and providers adapt the system design to evolving and even hybrid pricing schemes?</p>
    <p>How is the pricing scheme adapted to the evolving system dynamics and (new) technologies?</p>
    <p>How to deal with failures cost regarding to the pricing?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related work</p>
    <p>Other pricing schemes  Bilateral  Amazon EC2 Spot Instances: Enable you to bid for</p>
    <p>unused Amazon EC2 capacity  Navraj Chohan, et al., See Spot Run: Using Spot Instances for</p>
    <p>MapReduce Workflows, June 2010</p>
    <p>Microsoft SQL Azure: Make pricing more scalable and more predictable</p>
    <p>Distributed computing w/ Economics  Jim Gray, Distributed Computing Economics, March 2003  Ang Li, et al., CloudCmp: Shopping for a Cloud Made Easy, June</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Pricing is an important bridge between users and providers</p>
    <p>It significantly changes the dynamics in system design</p>
    <p>The interplay between economics and system design can be a fruitful research direction</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
