<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Diffusion Dynamics of Games on Online Social Networks</p>
    <p>Xiao Wei, Jiang Yang, and Lada A. Adamic University of Michigan, Ann Arbor</p>
    <p>Ricardo Matsumura de Arajo Federal University of Pelotas, Brazil</p>
    <p>Manu Rekhi LOLapps -&gt; MySpace</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>MoGvaGon  How can games be designed to propagate efficiently along a social network?  What are the best invitaGon strategies at the individual level?</p>
    <p>Are there network effects?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related work  Online viral markeGng (Leskovec et al., EC06)  Social influence &amp; diffusion  Backstrom et al. 2006: joining LJ groups or CS conferences  Aral et al. 2009: disGnguishing homophily and influence  Liben-Nowell &amp; Kleinberg 2008: email chain le^ers  many studies of diffusion in blogs and microblogs (Twi^er)  Bakshy et al. 2009: social networks and content diffusion</p>
    <p>Facebook  Sun et al. (ICWSM 2009): diffusion of pages on FB  Gjoka WOSN 2008: more apps, decreased average usage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline  games we studied  invitaGon efficiency  inviter</p>
    <p>profile  invitaGon pa^erns</p>
    <p>invitee  how many and how different are the inviters?</p>
    <p>network effects for games that favor large within- game groups</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>50 million acGve users/month (June 2010)  founded in 2008  300,000 user generated applicaGons  11 games</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>a tale of 2 games  Grow your family (Yakuza Lords) or entourage (Diva Life) and win ba^les/gigs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Game acGviGes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Game demographics</p>
    <p>Yakuza Lords Diva Life</p>
    <p>most players 18-38 years old --</p>
    <p>Age of Gamers</p>
    <p>P o p u la</p>
    <p>ti o n P</p>
    <p>ro b a b il it y D</p>
    <p>e n s it y Yakuza Lords</p>
    <p>Diva Life</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>inviGng friends</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Your friends dont all want to play</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In defense of social invites</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Are social invites worth it?  only 37/25% (YL/DL) users received invites before</p>
    <p>installing game</p>
    <p>However  20% of non-invited players stayed past the first day  50% of invited players stuck around more than a day, and</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How broadly are users inviGng?  Invite a few friends who are close and/or might be interested? Or invite everybody?</p>
    <p>Percentage of Friends Invited</p>
    <p>C um</p>
    <p>ul at</p>
    <p>iv e</p>
    <p>P ro</p>
    <p>ba bi</p>
    <p>lit y Yakuza LordsDiva Life</p>
    <p>Ave. Number of FB Friends</p>
    <p>A ve</p>
    <p>. N um</p>
    <p>be r</p>
    <p>of In</p>
    <p>vi te</p>
    <p>es</p>
    <p>Yakuza Lords Diva Life</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inviter efficiency: strategy  Some users are more acGve inviters:  10% of users account for 50% of successful invites.</p>
    <p>But inviGng fewer friends gives higher yield per invite  (success rate, # invites sent) = -0.77</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>why is less more when it comes to invites? pacing, repeGGon, selecGvity</p>
    <p>to control for # of invites sent, consider separately users who have invited 6, 12, or 20 friends</p>
    <p>inviters who pace their invites are more likely to succeed:  (median interval between sending an invite, success rate) = 0.09~0.19***</p>
    <p>sending repeat invites pays off   (av. # invites per friend, success rate) = 0.23~0.27***</p>
    <p>inviGng fewer users at once gives higher yield   (av. # invites per click, success rate) = - 0.35~0.49***</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Inviter efficiency: profile  Can one idenGfy successful inviters based on their profile?</p>
    <p>no correlaGon with gender, educaGon, hometown, relaGonship status</p>
    <p>weak correlaGon ~0.1 with age</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>the inviters network &amp; sharing  almost no correlaGon (~-0.04) between the size of an inviters network and success rate</p>
    <p>almost no correlaGon with # of walls posts (game and other) ~0.04</p>
    <p>or privacy level of profile (~-0.06) (what gets shared publicly).</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>inviters engagement with the game and success</p>
    <p>higher engagement &lt;-&gt; higher invite success</p>
    <p>the top 10% of inviters by success rate have an average lifespan of 70 days</p>
    <p>correlaGon between Life Time an success rate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Puung it together: InvitaGon cascades</p>
    <p>successful invitaGon</p>
    <p>user who joined game</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cascades are wide and shallow  small-world: everyone runs into everyone else in the game in a small number of steps</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>invitaGons spread and</p>
    <p>collide</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>who is inviGng you?  more invites from different people -&gt; higher probability of joining</p>
    <p>but inviters dont have to be different form each other entropy of profiles does not ma^er</p>
    <p>helps if inviters belong to the same clique  (clustering coefficient) = 0.21 (YL),  = 0.14 (DL)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Are cliques being absorbed into the game?  families grow rapidly at first,</p>
    <p>then more and more slowly</p>
    <p>when friends join forces their success rate grows (they share credit for new recruits)</p>
    <p>Nth Family Member</p>
    <p>Jo in</p>
    <p>in g</p>
    <p>In te</p>
    <p>rv al</p>
    <p>in D</p>
    <p>ay</p>
    <p>Yakuza Lords Diva Life</p>
    <p>Number of inviters among friends</p>
    <p>C o</p>
    <p>rr e</p>
    <p>la ti o</p>
    <p>n C</p>
    <p>o e</p>
    <p>ff ic</p>
    <p>ie n</p>
    <p>t Yakuza Lords</p>
    <p>Number of inviters among friends</p>
    <p>C o</p>
    <p>rr e</p>
    <p>la ti o</p>
    <p>n C</p>
    <p>o e</p>
    <p>ff ic</p>
    <p>ie n</p>
    <p>t</p>
    <p>Diva Life</p>
    <p>correlaGon between ones own success rate and that of ones friends</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How far does influence carry?  correlaGon between ones success rate and descendants av. success rate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Using networks to propagate games or using games to grow networks?</p>
    <p>Users add each other as friends in order to grow families</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>conclusion  games are spreading successfully and virally over social networks, as users invite friends</p>
    <p>its not so much who the inviter is, but how selecGve and persistent they are</p>
    <p>engagement correlates with success  family-structured games experience boost from network effects</p>
    <p>persuasive users are proximate in the network  games can modify the social networks they are spreading on</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>future work  tracing user created games  what are the properGes of viral games?</p>
    <p>characterizing large-scale cascades</p>
    <p>more info  h^p://netsi.org</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
