<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anycast as a Load Balancing Feature</p>
    <p>Fernanda Weiden Peter Frost</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Service availability is critical to business function</p>
    <p>Large scale failures often require slow, manual restoration</p>
    <p>Maintenance of next-nearest fallback configuration is painful</p>
    <p>Traditional Anycast deployments scale poorly with capacity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Failover Techniques</p>
    <p>Backend failure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Failover Techniques</p>
    <p>Load Balancer failure, site failure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Anycast</p>
    <p>Anycast is a network routing technique where many hosts have the exact same IP address.</p>
    <p>Clients trying to reach that IP address are routed to the nearest host.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Architecture</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Combining Load Balancing and Anycast</p>
    <p>Reduced amount of route advertisers Reduced number of routing changes Tolerates LB failure No need for manual configuration to define failover location No need for manual intervention to deal with LB failure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>...and turning it into a service</p>
    <p>Many services per location One load balancing instance per location Centralized management for it all Simple to use to by other service owners/sysadmins</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Implementation Details - Load Balancer</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Software details</p>
    <p>Heartbeat Active-passive cluster resource management</p>
    <p>ldirectord Backend monitoring software Patched to add &quot;fallback command&quot;</p>
    <p>ip_vs Linux kernel module for load balancing</p>
    <p>Quagga Software implementation of routing protocol daemons Advertises availability of services using /32 routes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>If a new service owner wants to use it...</p>
    <p>Reserve IP on the Anycast subnet. Create the new Anycast VIP config:</p>
    <p>Same as a normal/local VIP Plus a &quot;fallback command&quot;</p>
    <p>Done.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Reference links</p>
    <p>Load Balancing, http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Load_balancing_(computing) The Linux Virtual Server Project, http://www.linuxvirtualserver.org High Availability, http://www.linux-ha.org Quagga, a software routing suite, http://www.quagga.net RFC1771 - A Border Gateway Protocol 4, http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc1771. html Ldirectord, http://www.vergenet.net/linux/ldirectord/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
