<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiences In Cyber Security Education: The MIT Lincoln Laboratory Capture-the-Flag Exercise*</p>
    <p>Joseph Werther, Michael Zhivich, Timothy Leek, Nickolai Zeldovich</p>
    <p>Cyber Security Experimentation And Test 2011</p>
    <p>This work is sponsored by DARPA CRASH under Air Force contract FA8721-05-C-0002. Opinions, interpretations, conclusions, and recommendations are those of the authors and are not necessarily endorsed by the United States Government.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction to the MIT/LL CTF</p>
    <p>Pedagogic Principles</p>
    <p>Similar Exercises &amp; Related Work</p>
    <p>MIT/LL CTF Exercise Design</p>
    <p>Survey Results</p>
    <p>Lessons Learned and Future work</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>10 boxes of Joe  20 boxes of donuts  15 Ethernet switches  180 of CAT6 cable  1 ESX server  5,193 lines of Python,  2,415 lines of PHP  1,432 lines of JavaScript  347 lines of HTML  Too many late nights to count  1 custom flag  $1,500 + 4 iPods  5 lectures + 1 lab  45 excellent contenders  1 unforgettable weekend</p>
    <p>MIT/LL CTF by Numbers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Capture the Flag Exercise for Boston Area Universities  53 Participants from 6 Universities  A two day exercise preceded by a week of lectures &amp; labs</p>
    <p>Focused on web application security  Covered security at multiple levels  Application, server, and client exploitation</p>
    <p>Built around the Wordpress Content Management System  Pervasive blogging tool  Easily extensible for CTF purposes</p>
    <p>Designed with education in mind  Make computer security accessible to a large community  Make traditional CS students passionate about security</p>
    <p>Introduction to the MIT/LL CTF</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>3 main ways to learn computer security  Reading, Building, and Experiencing  Tried to include all 3 elements into the MIT/LL CTF</p>
    <p>We consider offensive education to be very important  Required to fully understand defense  Motivated by previous work (Fanelli, Bratus, Locasto)</p>
    <p>Distributed the CTF Team VM a month before the event  Did not include challenge (exploitable) plug-ins  Emulated a more realistic IT/Security environment  Encouraged students to research and practice systems</p>
    <p>security ahead of time</p>
    <p>Pedagogic Principles</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Held 5 Lectures in the month before the CTF  Lectures were held in the evening  Slides and pointers to Internet resources provided</p>
    <p>Class 1 - Introduction to MITLL/CTF  What is a CTF, how is it played?  Rules and mechanics of the MIT/LL CTF</p>
    <p>Class 2  Web Applications &amp; Wordpress  Teach the Wordpress API  Give the basics of plug-in design</p>
    <p>Class 3  Web Server Security  Security principles and tools for locking down LAMP</p>
    <p>servers  Case study by MITs SIPB</p>
    <p>Classes 4 &amp; 5  Web Application Security  Explored multiple types of vulnerabilities  Covered bug identification, exploitation and mitigation  Held lab session using Googles Gruyere</p>
    <p>Educational Components</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DefCon CTF (Team vs. Team)  Requires qualification round (very high barrier to entry)  Qualification are open to all who wish to participate</p>
    <p>iCTF (previously Team vs. Team, now different)  Large intra-university CTF  No lecture/lab component</p>
    <p>CCDC (Team Vs. Red Team)  Concentrated on Computer Network &amp; System Defense  Aimed at giving practical experience in defending</p>
    <p>commercial networks</p>
    <p>NSAs CDX (Team Vs. Red Team)  Restricted to military educational institutions</p>
    <p>Other University CTFs  Many based around semester-long courses  Majority are limited to only one university</p>
    <p>Similar Exercises &amp; Related Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Each team was provisioned a Team VM on ESX server  Connected to the VM from laptops for defensive configuration  Could conduct offense from laptops or VM</p>
    <p>VM ran a standard LAMP stack  Came pre-configured with a set of custom Wordpress plug-ins</p>
    <p>The first 30 minutes were not scored  Apply patches, secure server VMs  Attacks permitted during this period</p>
    <p>Valuable/sensitive information was represented by flags  Flags consisted on long alpha-numeric strings  Resided on file system and in database</p>
    <p>Grading bots evaluated each teams VM for functionality  Evaluation and flag rotation took place at random points in a 15</p>
    <p>minute interval</p>
    <p>MIT/LL CTF Exercise Landscape</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Network</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scores calculated as a weighted average of four sub-scores</p>
    <p>Availability</p>
    <p>Fraction of functionality test cases passed by a teams website  Confidentiality</p>
    <p>Fraction of a teams flags not submitted by another team  Integrity</p>
    <p>Fraction of flags remaining unmodified on a teams VM  Offense</p>
    <p>Fraction of all available flags (belonging to other teams) submitted by a team</p>
    <p>MIT/LL CTF Scoring</p>
    <p>Score =Wd *Defense+(1!Wd)*Offense</p>
    <p>Defense = Wk*K k&quot;{C,I,A}</p>
    <p>#</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Scoreboard</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Received survey responses from 22 of the participants  Overall response very positive (91% said they would like to</p>
    <p>participate in another CTF)  Reported skill self-assessment</p>
    <p>Improved practical computer security skills  Increased interest in computer security as a career  Some concluded they were overconfident before the CTF</p>
    <p>Preparation time (outside of lecture)  1-2 hours (9 responders)  4-8 hours (8 responders)</p>
    <p>Defense vs Offense  50% spent more time on Defense  36% spent more time on Offense  86% of participants discovered and tried to patch at least 1</p>
    <p>vulnerability  Those who worked on offense developed an average of 1.5</p>
    <p>exploits</p>
    <p>Survey Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Expand the CTF to more New England Colleges  Improve marketing and getting new students involved</p>
    <p>Improve data collection &amp; environment instrumentation  Ensure the PCAP capture doesnt fail  Collect performance and traffic logs from VMs  Better visibility into offensive and defensive activities</p>
    <p>Provide teams with off-network console access to VMs  Offering snapshots and restores was useful, but</p>
    <p>automated exploitation made this difficult</p>
    <p>Devise better methods of measuring education  Incentivize survey participation  Survey/test both before and after the CTF &amp; classes</p>
    <p>Lessons Learned and Future Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What are the best ways to measure CTFs effect on participants knowledge of practical computer security?</p>
    <p>Quizzes seem unsatisfactory  Practical tests are difficult to arrange</p>
    <p>How can we better instrument the CTF without interfering with the game?</p>
    <p>Would like to have better visibility into defensive posture and offensive activities</p>
    <p>Compliance with CTF rules of the game</p>
    <p>What are the best ways to encourage learning about practical computer security after the CTF?</p>
    <p>Reading groups?  Hack-a-thons?</p>
    <p>Discussion Topics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
