<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Disaster Recovery as a Cloud Service: Economic Benefits and Deployment Challenges</p>
    <p>Tim Wood, Emmanuel Cecchet, KK Ramakrishnan*, Prashant Shenoy,</p>
    <p>Kobus van der Merwe*, and Arun Venkataramani</p>
    <p>UMass Amherst and AT&amp;T*</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Disasters happen</p>
    <p>Disasters are</p>
    <p>expensive</p>
    <p>Gulf Oil Spill</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Center Disasters  Disasters cause expensive application downtime</p>
    <p>Truck crash shuts down Amazon EC2 site (May 2010)  Lightning strikes EC2 data center (May 2009)  Comcast Down: Hunter shoots cable (2008)  Squirrels bring down NASDAQ exchange (1987 and 1994)</p>
    <p>Need plans and systems in place to recover from disasters</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Disaster Recovery  Use DR services to prevent lengthy service disruptions  Long distance data backups + failover mechanism</p>
    <p>Periodically replicate state  Switch to backup site after disaster</p>
    <p>send backups Enterprise DC</p>
    <p>Private Backup Site</p>
    <p>Public DR Cloud</p>
    <p>Can the cloud reduce the cost of DR and improve</p>
    <p>the level of service?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DR Metrics  DR Goal: minimize data loss, downtime, and cost</p>
    <p>Recovery Point Objective (RPO)  Amount of tolerable data loss</p>
    <p>Recovery Time Objective (RTO)  Acceptable system downtime</p>
    <p>Time</p>
    <p>RPO RTO</p>
    <p>Detect Provision</p>
    <p>Restore Connect</p>
    <p>We focus on RPO and RTO &gt; 0</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why DR Fits in the Cloud  Customer: pay-as-you-go and elasticity</p>
    <p>Normal case is cheap (need few resources to make backups)  Lower cost for a given RPO</p>
    <p>Can rapidly scale up resources after disaster is detected  Clouds virtualized infrastructure reduces RTO  Can allow for business continuity</p>
    <p>Provider: High degree of multiplexing  Customers will not all fail at once  Can offer extra services like disaster detection</p>
    <p>Is the cloud an economical platform for DR today?</p>
    <p>What additional features are needed?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DR on Demand  Warm Backup Site</p>
    <p>Cheaply synchronize state during normal operation  Obtain additional DR resources on demand after failure  Short delay to provision and initialize applications</p>
    <p>DR Cloud Enterprise DC</p>
    <p>App 1 App 2</p>
    <p>App 100</p>
    <p>Backup State</p>
    <p>Post-Disaster</p>
    <p>DR Server</p>
    <p>Normal Mode</p>
    <p>App 100</p>
    <p>App 1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cost Analysis Scenario  Compare the cost of DR in Colocation center to Cloud  Colo case pays for servers and space at all times  Cloud DR only pays for resources as they are used  Case 1: RUBiS ebay-like multi-tier web application</p>
    <p>3 web front ends  1 database server</p>
    <p>Only database state is replicated</p>
    <p>DR Cloud</p>
    <p>DR Server</p>
    <p>Enterprise DC</p>
    <p>Web servers</p>
    <p>Database Colocation Center</p>
    <p>Web servers</p>
    <p>Database</p>
    <p>Database</p>
    <p>Web servers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cost Analysis: Colocation vs Cloud  Normal Case</p>
    <p>Resources needed to replicate DB state</p>
    <p>Post-Disaster  Resources needed</p>
    <p>to run all application components</p>
    <p>99% Uptime cost (3 days of disaster per year)  Colo: $10,373 per year  Cloud: $1,562 per year</p>
    <p>Normal Case Post-Disaster</p>
    <p>Servers colo = 4 servers cloud = 1 VMs</p>
    <p>colo = 4 servers cloud = 5 VMs</p>
    <p>Network 5 GB/day 180 GB/day</p>
    <p>Colocation: $28.04/day $66.01/day</p>
    <p>Cloud: $3.80/day $52.03/day</p>
    <p>RUBiS</p>
    <p>Web servers</p>
    <p>Database</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RPO vs Cost Tradeoff  Case 2: Data Warehouse</p>
    <p>Post-disaster twice as expensive with Cloud  Cloud charges premium for high powered VM instance</p>
    <p>Cloud still cheaper overall due to lower normal case costs</p>
    <p>Cloud allows tradeoff between RPO and cost  Only pay for DR server during periodic backups in cloud</p>
    <p>Colo center pays server and space costs regardless</p>
    <p>of RPO!</p>
    <p>RPO ~0</p>
    <p>Continuous Replication</p>
    <p>Y e a rl y 9</p>
    <p>U p ti m</p>
    <p>e C</p>
    <p>o st</p>
    <p>Cloud Colo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cost Analysis Summary  Benefits of cloud computing depend on:</p>
    <p>Type of resources required to run application  Variation between normal mode and post-disaster costs  RPO and RTO requirements  Likelihood of disaster</p>
    <p>Cloud has greatest benefit when post disaster cost much higher than normal mode</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Provider Challenges  Revenue Maximization</p>
    <p>Mainly makes income from storage in normal case  But must pay for servers and keep them available</p>
    <p>Can use pricing mechanism such as spot instances  Rent resources but be able to quickly reclaim for DR</p>
    <p>Rent priority resources at higher cost that are guaranteed to be available</p>
    <p>Correlated Failures  Large disasters could affect many customers simultaneously  Cloud provider must</p>
    <p>Use a risk model to decide how many resources to own for DR  Spread out customers to minimize impact of correlated failures</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More DR Challenges  Planning</p>
    <p>Use models to help understand tradeoff between cost and RPO/RTO for a given application and workload</p>
    <p>Efficient state replication  Minimize the bandwidth and cloud server costs in the</p>
    <p>normal case</p>
    <p>Post Disaster Failover  Enable business continuity by minimizing recovery time  Automated/virtualized cloud infrastructure can lower RTO</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary  Cloud based Disaster Recovery</p>
    <p>Can substantially reduce cost for customer  Particularly when server cost varies before/after disaster</p>
    <p>Provides flexible tradeoff between cost and RPO  Can lower recovery time, enable business continuity  Provider must handle correlated failures</p>
    <p>Open challenges  How many resources must provider reserve for DR?  How to seamlessly transfer network connections?  How to fail back to primary site after disaster passes?</p>
    <p>twood@cs.umass.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cost Details</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Enabling Business Continuity  Business continuity allows applications to keep</p>
    <p>working after a disaster  Crucial for critical business/government services</p>
    <p>Virtualized cloud infrastructure can lower RTO  Automates VM creation and cloning  Cloud can also help with disaster detection</p>
    <p>Many remaining challenges  How to ensure application is revived in a consistent/correct</p>
    <p>state?</p>
    <p>How to redirect traffic to failover site?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>DR Requirements  Recovery Point Objective (RPO)</p>
    <p>Amount of tolerable data loss</p>
    <p>Recovery Time Objective (RTO)  Acceptable system downtime</p>
    <p>Performance  Impact on normal operation and after recovery</p>
    <p>Consistency  Correctness of application data and outputs</p>
    <p>Geographic Separation  DR site should not be affected by same disaster</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is the cloud good for?  Cloud platforms are best for users who have</p>
    <p>variable needs over time  Customers only pay for what they use  Providers get economy of scale and can multiplex resources</p>
    <p>for many customers</p>
    <p>Applications well matched for the cloud:  Web sites with growing or variable demand  Infrequent compute intensive jobs (monthly payroll)</p>
    <p>and...  Disaster recovery!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
