<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Zhenyu Wu, Mengjun Xie and Haining Wang Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>College of William and Mary</p>
    <p>Presenter: Zhenyu Wu</p>
    <p>Currently affiliated with University of Arkansas at Little Rock</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Energy and Green Computing  Energy cost has become a major factor in the total cost</p>
    <p>of ownership (TCO) of large-scale server clusters</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Energy and Green Computing  Millions of tons of carbon-dioxide are generated in</p>
    <p>order of power data centers</p>
    <p>Two Google searches = boiling a cup of coffee</p>
    <p>Global data center carbon emission (2007)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Energy Proportional Computing  Aims to make servers consume energy proportional to</p>
    <p>its workload.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Power usage break down:</p>
    <p>Energy Proportional Computing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Potential Vulnerabilities  Energy efficient computing assumes a cooperative</p>
    <p>working environment</p>
    <p>Power saving is passive, dependent on workload</p>
    <p>Not all workload consumes identical amount of energy</p>
    <p>=</p>
    <p>Alex Wissner-Gross, How you can help reduce the footprint of the Web</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Formulating Attack Vectors  Attack Vector:</p>
    <p>Isolate high energy cost requests  Analyze the triggering conditions</p>
    <p>Reproduce in high concentration  High percentages, but no necessarily large amounts</p>
    <p>Vulnerable systems: open services, such as search engine, knowledge base, public forum, etc.</p>
    <p>Have little or no control over the incoming request</p>
    <p>Energy consumption is largely dependent on the type and amount of service requests</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Designing an Energy Attack  We use a Wikipedia mirror server as the victim</p>
    <p>Publicly available large scale database</p>
    <p>Representative of standard open Internet services</p>
    <p>We discover the attack vector by profiling the server</p>
    <p>Powered by MediaWiki, a large scale content management system.</p>
    <p>Two levels of caching for efficient operation  Object Cache  for dynamically generated pages</p>
    <p>Memory Cache  for recently executed database queries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Designing an Energy Attack</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Designing an Energy Attack  Keys to launching the energy attack:</p>
    <p>Generate Cache Misses  Much higher energy/request than normal workload</p>
    <p>Avoid Generating Anomalies  Be low profile, non-obtrusive</p>
    <p>Must not generate traffic anomaly</p>
    <p>Must not cause obvious performance degradation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Designing an Energy Attack  Website access profiling</p>
    <p>Cache Misses:  The frequency of a web page being accessed is inversely</p>
    <p>proportional to its rank (Zipf s law)</p>
    <p>A small number of web pages are accessed very frequently A large number of web pages are accessed very infrequently</p>
    <p>Different access patterns = Cold pages = Cache misses</p>
    <p>Stealthiness:  The request inter-arrival time of human users follow Pareto</p>
    <p>distribution</p>
    <p>The attackers can mimic normal users by sending requests at average rates, and following Pareto distribution</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Measurements and Evaluations  Server Configurations:</p>
    <p>Dual Intel Xeon 5540 quad-core processor  6GB DDR3 SDRAM  2TB SATA HDD in RAID 5  Power usage monitored by Watts Up PRO power meter</p>
    <p>Experiment Methodology  The server is able to stably support accesses from up to</p>
    <p>attack with varying intensity  Measure the increase in power consumption and latency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Measurements and Evaluations  Workload  Response Time Profile (Normal)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Measurements and Evaluations  Workload  Power Consumption Profile (Normal)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Power vs. Latency Increase at high workloads (100 clients)</p>
    <p>Measurements and Evaluations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Power vs. Latency Increase at medium workloads (50 clients)</p>
    <p>Measurements and Evaluations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Power vs. Latency Increase at low workloads (10 clients)</p>
    <p>Measurements and Evaluations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Measurements and Evaluations  Damage achieved:</p>
    <p>6.2% ~ 42.3% additional power usage, depending on workload.</p>
    <p>For typical server workloads: 21.7% ~ 42.3% power wastage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Measurements and Evaluations  Damage achieved:</p>
    <p>6.2% ~ 42.3% additional power usage, depending on workload.</p>
    <p>For typical server workloads: 21.7% ~ 42.3% power wastage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Alternative Energy Attack Vectors  Algorithmic Complexity Attacks</p>
    <p>Algorithms that have high worst-case run time  Plain quick sort, nave hash-table, etc.</p>
    <p>Originally proposed as DoS attacks, can be adapted to use as energy attacks  Processors are the most power consuming devices</p>
    <p>Be stealthy: lower intensity, target non-computation intensive servers (such as file depositing services)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Alternative Energy Attack Vectors  Example:</p>
    <p>Linux directory cache vulnerability  Simple hash for quick file name lookup</p>
    <p>Vulnerable to collision attack</p>
    <p>FTP server  Setup: upload thousands of files with colliding names</p>
    <p>Attack: download, rename, read/write metadata, etc.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Alternative Energy Attack Vectors  Sleep Deprivation Attacks</p>
    <p>Originally proposed as DoS attacks in sensor network, can be adapted to use as energy attacks  Target components that have large dynamic power range</p>
    <p>Doesnt require high per-unit power consumption</p>
    <p>Example:</p>
    <p>A hard drive consumes 12~16 watts of power in operational states, but only ~1 watt in spin-down  File servers usually have tens of hard drives!</p>
    <p>Malicious access patterns can interfere with power management and prevent expected spin-down</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Challenge of Defense  The key is still missing:</p>
    <p>What we want to do  Differentiate high energy cost workload</p>
    <p>What we have at hand  Coarse grained power measurement instrument</p>
    <p>We are under attack!   And we have to suck it.</p>
    <p>Fine grained performance counters (approximation)  Good for single task systems (mobile phone / PDA / etc.)  Incompetent for highly parallel environment</p>
    <p>What we really need:  Fine grained power measurement support</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>WILLIAM  MARY</p>
    <p>Future Work  Extend beyond single server</p>
    <p>Server-clusters, server farms</p>
    <p>Data center, massively virtualized environment</p>
    <p>Etc.</p>
    <p>Explore software-based countermeasures</p>
    <p>Temporary workarounds to the lack of hardware support</p>
    <p>Explore possibility of inferring workload natures from application behavior profiling</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
