<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rongxing Lu, Xiaodong Lin, Xiaohui Liang, Xuemin (Sherman) Shen University of Waterloo, University of Ontario Institute of Technology</p>
    <p>FLIP: An Efficient Privacy-preserving Protocol for Finding Like-minded Vehicles on the Road</p>
    <p>Presenter: Rongxing Lu Email: rxlu@bbcr.uwaterloo.ca</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction  VANET, Vehicle Chatting Application</p>
    <p>System &amp; Security Model  Proposed FLIP Protocol  Security Proof  Performance Evaluation  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction: VANET</p>
    <p>VANETVANET</p>
    <p>Road Side Unit (RSU)</p>
    <p>Vehicle equipped with OnBoard Unit (OBU)</p>
    <p>V-2-I</p>
    <p>V-2-V</p>
    <p>Server (traffic monitoring, location based service)</p>
    <p>Vehicular Ad hoc Networks (VANETs), as a special instantiate of mobile ad hoc network, have been subject to extensive research efforts not only from the government, but also from the academia and automobile industry in recent years.</p>
    <p>Vehicular Ad hoc Networks (VANETs), as a special instantiate of mobile ad hoc network, have been subject to extensive research efforts not only from the government, but also from the academia and automobile industry in recent years.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction: VANET Application</p>
    <p>Accident</p>
    <p>Warning V-2-V</p>
    <p>V-2-I Server (traffic monitoring)</p>
    <p>Sharing MP3</p>
    <p>V-2-V</p>
    <p>V-2-I Server</p>
    <p>road info.</p>
    <p>Chatting</p>
    <p>Downloadi ng</p>
    <p>MP3, Map,</p>
    <p>Software</p>
    <p>Booking hotel</p>
    <p>Safety-Related ApplicationSafety-Related Application Nonsafety-Related</p>
    <p>Application Nonsafety-Related</p>
    <p>Application</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction: Vehicle Chatting</p>
    <p>Chatting</p>
    <p>Vehicle chatting is one of the most promising applications in VANETs, which allows vehicles moving along the same road to chat with each other on some topics of common interest, for the purpose of passing the time during the commute or asking for a help on the road.</p>
    <p>Vehicle chatting is one of the most promising applications in VANETs, which allows vehicles moving along the same road to chat with each other on some topics of common interest, for the purpose of passing the time during the commute or asking for a help on the road.</p>
    <p>Future Carpool Future</p>
    <p>Carpool New Movie</p>
    <p>Music New Movie</p>
    <p>Music</p>
    <p>However, the success of vehicle chatting application in VANET still hinges up the fully understanding and managing the security and privacy challenges that the public concerns, for example, the identity privacy, location privacy, and interest privacy.</p>
    <p>However, the success of vehicle chatting application in VANET still hinges up the fully understanding and managing the security and privacy challenges that the public concerns, for example, the identity privacy, location privacy, and interest privacy.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction: Contribution</p>
    <p>How to identify a vehicle who is like-minded and establish a shared session key for secure chatting, and how to prevent other vehicles who are not like-minded from knowing one vehicles interest have become two newly emerging privacy challenges in vehicle chatting application.</p>
    <p>How to identify a vehicle who is like-minded and establish a shared session key for secure chatting, and how to prevent other vehicles who are not like-minded from knowing one vehicles interest have become two newly emerging privacy challenges in vehicle chatting application.</p>
    <p>Contribution: we propose an efficient privacy-preserving finding like-minded vehicle protocol, called FLIP, which allows two vehicles with the common interest to identify each other and establish a shared session key, and at the same time, protects their Interest-Privacy (IP) from other vehicles who dont have the same interest on the road.</p>
    <p>Contribution: we propose an efficient privacy-preserving finding like-minded vehicle protocol, called FLIP, which allows two vehicles with the common interest to identify each other and establish a shared session key, and at the same time, protects their Interest-Privacy (IP) from other vehicles who dont have the same interest on the road.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Model</p>
    <p>Trusted Authority:</p>
    <p>Assign a family of pseudo-IDs to vehicle</p>
    <p>Each Vehicle: Periodically change pseudo-IDs</p>
    <p>FLIP: try to find a physically nearby like-minded vehicle without directly disclosing own interest; and establish a secure key to protect the future chatting content FLIP: try to find a physically nearby like-minded vehicle without directly disclosing own interest; and establish a secure key to protect the future chatting content</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Model</p>
    <p>Preconditions: 1)The size of the Interest Set I should be large. 2) In each execution of FLIP, the Interest Ia varies (pseudo-id fixed) Preconditions: 1)The size of the Interest Set I should be large. 2) In each execution of FLIP, the Interest Ia varies (pseudo-id fixed)</p>
    <p>FLIP</p>
    <p>Rationale: For a given interest set of k items, if Vb really has the same interest with Va, with high probability, both Va and Vb can choose the same interest. Otherwise, Vb can choose the same interest of Va only with probability 1/k.</p>
    <p>Rationale: For a given interest set of k items, if Vb really has the same interest with Va, with high probability, both Va and Vb can choose the same interest. Otherwise, Vb can choose the same interest of Va only with probability 1/k.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Model (2)</p>
    <p>Adversarial ModelAdversarial Model</p>
    <p>We allow the adversary A to access to all transcripts in the FLIP. All oracles only communicate with each other via A. The adversary A can replay, modify, delay, interleave or delete transcripts.</p>
    <p>We allow the adversary A to access to all transcripts in the FLIP. All oracles only communicate with each other via A. The adversary A can replay, modify, delay, interleave or delete transcripts.</p>
    <p>FLIP</p>
    <p>Passive Eavesdropping</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Model (3)</p>
    <p>Adversarial ModelAdversarial Model</p>
    <p>FLIP</p>
    <p>Use the query to perform active attacks by modifying and inserting the transcript of the protocol to identify the IP of the requestor and responsor Use the query to perform active attacks by modifying and inserting the transcript of the protocol to identify the IP of the requestor and responsor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Model (4)</p>
    <p>Adversarial ModelAdversarial Model FLIP</p>
    <p>This query models the known session key attack. The adversary A can get access to an old session key that has been previously established. This query models the known session key attack. The adversary A can get access to an old session key that has been previously established.</p>
    <p>This query models exposure of the private key corresponding to PIDi to the adversaryThis query models exposure of the private key corresponding to PIDi to the adversary</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Proposed FLIP Protocol</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security Proof</p>
    <p>Full version: http://bbcr.uwaterloo.ca/~rxlu/paper/GLOBECOM10FLIP.pdf</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Performance Evaluation</p>
    <p>The larger the Interest Set, the longer the average FD; but at the same time, the average FD can be reduced with the increase of . Therefore, by setting a proper size of |I| on considering of , a vehicle V can find a like-minded vehicle within an expected time on the road while keeping his IP from non-like-minded vehicles.</p>
    <p>The larger the Interest Set, the longer the average FD; but at the same time, the average FD can be reduced with the increase of . Therefore, by setting a proper size of |I| on considering of , a vehicle V can find a like-minded vehicle within an expected time on the road while keeping his IP from non-like-minded vehicles.</p>
    <p>Fi nd</p>
    <p>in g</p>
    <p>D el</p>
    <p>ay</p>
    <p>Mean passing-by rate =[20 /h; 40 /h; 60 /h; 80 /h; 100 /h; 120 /h]</p>
    <p>Interest set size [1; 2; . . . ; 10]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>How to find a group of like-minded vehicles on the road is one of future work. How to find a group of like-minded vehicles on the road is one of future work.</p>
    <p>In this work, we propose a secure finding like-minded vehicles protocol (FLIP), which can protect vehicles IP and is of vital importance to the success of vehicle chatting application on the road</p>
    <p>In this work, we propose a secure finding like-minded vehicles protocol (FLIP), which can protect vehicles IP and is of vital importance to the success of vehicle chatting application on the road</p>
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
