<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Andbot: Towards Advanced Mobile Botnets</p>
    <p>Cui Xiang Fang Binxing Yin Lihua Liu Xiaoyi Zang Tianning</p>
    <p>Research Center of Information Security Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AgendaAgenda</p>
    <p>Introduction Andbot OverviewAndbot Overview C&amp;C Design Evaluation Countermeasures Conclusions and Future Works</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IntroductionIntroduction</p>
    <p>PC botnet A group of compromised computers that</p>
    <p>l ll d b b i</p>
    <p>Mobile botnet A group of compromised Smartphones h l ll d bare remotely controlled by botmasters via</p>
    <p>C&amp;C channels. that are remotely controlled by botmasters via C&amp;C channels.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IntroductionIntroduction</p>
    <p>i h ildMobile botnets in the wild</p>
    <p>Name: SymbOS.Yxesy Target: Symbian Discovered: 2009</p>
    <p>Name: Ikee.B Target: iPhone</p>
    <p>Simple HTTP-based C&amp;C Suffers a single-point-failure</p>
    <p>Discovered: 2009</p>
    <p>Name: Geinimi Target: Android Discovered: 2010</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>IntroductionIntroduction Mobile Botnets ChallengesMobile Botnets Challenges</p>
    <p>Limited battery power Cost-sensitive Traffic abnormity Absence of public/static IP addresses</p>
    <p>Mobile Botnets: an underlying trend Widely used by billions of end usersWidely used by billions of end users More powerful computing capabilities More easily to access Internet (i.e., using WiFi, GPRS and 3G) More profitable than PC botnets Absence of efficient host-level security softwares(i.e., AV and FW)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Andbot OverviewAndbot Overview</p>
    <p>Attack targetsAttack targets Android platform</p>
    <p>Commands CallHome SMSD S</p>
    <p>Commands Format .CallHome#Channel#Address .SMSDoS#MobileNumber#Num#Random#Content#LenSMSDoS</p>
    <p>SMSSpread MonitorSMS</p>
    <p>.SMSDoS#MobileNumber#Num#Random#Content#Len</p>
    <p>.SMSSpread#Content#Dest</p>
    <p>.MonitorSMS#MobileNumber# Num#Channel#Address</p>
    <p>GenSMS DenySMS RelayCmd</p>
    <p>Num#Channel#Address .GenSMS#FakeFromNumber#DateTime</p>
    <p>.DenySMS#FromNumber RelayCmd Sleep</p>
    <p>.RelayCmd#CipherCmd#Num#MobileNumberList</p>
    <p>.Sleep#Seconds</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Andbot OverviewAndbot Overview C&amp;C OverviewC&amp;C Overview</p>
    <p>Topology : Centralized Protocol : URL Flux (PULL style)Protocol : URL Flux (PULL style) Addressing: Domain Name, Username Generation Algorithm</p>
    <p>IRC/HTTP-based C&amp;C URL Flux-based C&amp;C</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C&amp;C DesignC&amp;C Design Desirable C&amp;C of Mobile BotnetsDesirable C&amp;C of Mobile Botnets</p>
    <p>Stealthy: The capability to bypass botnet detection system;</p>
    <p>Resilient: Resistant to most of public known defense strategies Recover C&amp;C in an accepted time delayRecover C&amp;C in an accepted time delay</p>
    <p>Low-Cost: Low money costs low traffic and battery power consumption</p>
    <p>Andbot C&amp;C = Stealthy + Resilient + Low-Cost</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C&amp;C Design - URL FluxC&amp;C Design URL Flux</p>
    <p>Domain Flux vs. URL Flux</p>
    <p>Which domain name points to authorized computer?</p>
    <p>Which USER published authorized tweets?</p>
    <p>Public Key Domain Template DGA (Domain Generation Algorithm)</p>
    <p>Public Key Web 2.0 URL Template UGA (UsernameGeneration Algorithm) UGA (Username Generation algorithm)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C&amp;C Design - URL Flux</p>
    <p>Making and Publishing Secure &amp; Secret Tweets</p>
    <p>g</p>
    <p>Making and Publishing Secure &amp; Secret Tweets</p>
    <p>StartDate ExpireDate JPG URLStartDate ExpireDate JPG URL</p>
    <p>Input</p>
    <p>PPIrq5XSP3AOLAP4O5jf2WGY5IVGbiF4/O8yjTfz5znXe6q4RA/j5dl4FxRi Ro78/DgaOUlXqy8Z7GDSSuM2Yn9PJHCs4DY+wnANmD/lWvXFZHmlsnTweet 1</p>
    <p>Base64 (Sign (Hash (Input))#Encrypt(Input))</p>
    <p>g qy Vh/neR lK+schLxFQSeea20Va2NDPcfHox2JsEKa/KLX+bJFsUAVs36YCPj XQv+WVL9 0UOTs6ESePgUYq/pI7EY2vKfeTDqr0BTX66+zAA=Tweet 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C&amp;C Design - URL Flux</p>
    <p>Making and Publishing Secure &amp; Secret Tweets</p>
    <p>g</p>
    <p>Making and Publishing Secure &amp; Secret Tweets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Making and Publishing Secure &amp; Secret TweetsMaking and Publishing Secure &amp; Secret Tweets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C&amp;C Design - URL FluxC&amp;C Design URL Flux</p>
    <p>The complete URL Flux proceduresThe complete URL Flux procedures</p>
    <p>SMSDoS  Publish Tweets</p>
    <p>.SMSDoS .SMSSpread .MoniterSMS .GenSMS DenySMS</p>
    <p>URL</p>
    <p>Create JPG</p>
    <p>.DenySMS</p>
    <p>.Sleep</p>
    <p>Upload JPG</p>
    <p>Make Tweets p</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C&amp;C Design Low CostC&amp;C Design  Low Cost Low CostLow Cost</p>
    <p>IP-only Cheaper than SMS significantly GPRS is usually accessible Wi-Fi may be free of charge</p>
    <p>RSS d GZIP iRSS and GZIP compression Decrease traffic</p>
    <p>URL CachingURL Caching Cache authorized URL in its period of validity</p>
    <p>Sleep Sleep for some time based on the command of botmasters When sleeping, no resource consumption</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EvaluationEvaluation Traffic ConsumptionTraffic Consumption</p>
    <p>The most important evaluation factor I fl d b C&amp;C tInfluenced by many C&amp;C parameters</p>
    <p>the interval between two commands requesting the half-yearly and monthly username county y y if RSS and GZIP should be used if the bot should keep active only when smartphones in sleeping state the total num of different Microblogsthe total num of different Microblogs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EvaluationEvaluation</p>
    <p>Register Users in MicroblogPart of the a URL( The round trip delay Send bytes/Recv bytes/Register Users in Microblog i.e., tk1074939514</p>
    <p>Part of the a URL( http://digu.com/statuses /rss/tk1074939514.rss)</p>
    <p>The round trip delay between first packet and last packet</p>
    <p>Send bytes/Recv bytes/ Total bytes( including connection, and all packets headers etc)</p>
    <p>SubURL User Name Gzip Avg. Time Delay(s) Request/Response/Total Traffic(Byte)</p>
    <p>/statuses/rss/pbipnv132545.rss Not Exist No 7.618 164/348/1188</p>
    <p>/statuses/rss/tk1074939514.rss Exist No 13.745 141/1972/2995</p>
    <p>/statuses/rss/tk1074939514.rss Exist Yes 2.706 164/1062/1902</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EvaluationEvaluation</p>
    <p>Available Username Num Time Delay(S) Total Traffic(KB)</p>
    <p>Half- Year 10% 14.85s 7.07</p>
    <p>Authorized user</p>
    <p>JPG File Size(Byte)</p>
    <p>Cipher Cmd Len(Byte)</p>
    <p>Time Delay(S) Traffic Cost(Byte)Download the JPG</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CountermeasuresCountermeasures Building International Coordinated MechanismBuilding International Coordinated Mechanism</p>
    <p>Web 2.0 Abuse Response Using Microblog to publish malicious messages Using Blog, Google Sites and YouTube to host malicious image files</p>
    <p>Cloud Computing Platform Abuse Response Using Google App Engine to receive messages (i e CallHome Identity)Using Google App Engine to receive messages (i.e., CallHome, Identity) Using Amazon EC2 to host malicious C&amp;C servers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CountermeasuresCountermeasures Monitoring at SMSC side and Verify in Cloud Sandboxes/VMsMonitoring at SMSC side and Verify in Cloud Sandboxes/VMs</p>
    <p>Mobile Worm Detection at SMSC side Multi-SMS as input Similar to PC worm detection system such as Autograph, Early-birds Generating signatures automatically</p>
    <p>Verification via Cloud Sandboxes/VMsVerification via Cloud Sandboxes/VMs Verify the found worms Verify the softwares to be published</p>
    <p>Infiltration First analysis C&amp;C protocol Th i filt tThen program an infiltrator</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions and Future WorksConclusions and Future Works</p>
    <p>Smartphones are attractive targets to hackers Constructing a practical mobile botnet is feasible URL Flux is very suitable for mobile botnet C&amp;C Andbot is stealthy, resilient, and low cost, posing potential threat Defenders should pay more attention to advanced mobile botnets</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions and Future WorksConclusions and Future Works Dynamic Username Generation Algorithm (DUGA)Dynamic Username Generation Algorithm (DUGA)</p>
    <p>Querying the most active topic as seed for UGA Making blocking username registration in advance difficult</p>
    <p>Eliminating Time-Space Similarities via Randomization Injecting packet and flow-level noise Addi d d l h i tAdding a random delay when communicate</p>
    <p>Emergency C&amp;C Exploiting SMS as C&amp;C when distributing urgent tasksExploiting SMS as C&amp;C when distributing urgent tasks Recovering C&amp;C in case all Web 2.0 resources unavailable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!Thank You!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
