<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Incentive-Compatible Opportunistic Incentive-Compatible Opportunistic Routing for Wireless NetworksRouting for Wireless Networks</p>
    <p>Fan Wu, Tingting Chen, Sheng ZhongFan Wu, Tingting Chen, Sheng Zhong (SUNY Buffalo)</p>
    <p>Li Erran LiLi Erran Li (Bell Labs) Yang Richard YangYang Richard Yang (Yale University)</p>
    <p>Speaker: Fan WuFan Wu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>User-contributed wireless mesh networks  Low cost</p>
    <p>Unpredictable and lossy wireless links</p>
    <p>From http://an.kaist.ac.kr/~tdinhtoan/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation (cont)</p>
    <p>Opportunistic routing emerged to improve throughput, e.g.,  ExOR (Biswas and Morris [2005])</p>
    <p>MORE (Chachulski et. al. [2007])</p>
    <p>S R D LLP = 0.4</p>
    <p>LLP: Link Loss Probability</p>
    <p>LLP = 0.8</p>
    <p>ENT: Expected Number of Transmissions</p>
    <p>ENT = 1.18 LLP = 0.4</p>
    <p>ENT = 1.47</p>
    <p>p1 p2p1 p2</p>
    <p>p1+p2</p>
    <p>p1 p2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation (cont)</p>
    <p>Selfish behavior may reduce performance  Free-rider problem</p>
    <p>Adverse selection problem</p>
    <p>S R D LLP = 0.1</p>
    <p>LLP: Link Loss Probability</p>
    <p>LLP = 0.8</p>
    <p>ENT: Expected Number of Transmissions</p>
    <p>ENT = 0.78  LLP = 0.4</p>
    <p>ENT = 1.47</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation (cont)</p>
    <p>Existing incentive mechanisms are mainly based on shortest path routing</p>
    <p>Need to design incentive-compatible routing protocols so that each user node participates in opportunistic routing honestly</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Objective</p>
    <p>Develop incentive compatible techniques that can be integrated with a wide class of opportunistic routing protocols</p>
    <p>A basic opportunistic routing protocol:  collects link states and then</p>
    <p>computes a forwarding behavior profile for user nodes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Opportunistic Routing Protocol</p>
    <p>Source Node, S  Divides traffic into batches of packets  Keeps sending coded packets in current batch  Moves to next batch if acknowledged</p>
    <p>Intermediate Node, i  Broadcasts a coded packet if needed  Targets expected number of transmissions zi:</p>
    <p>i,j: loss probability on link (i, j)</p>
    <p>Destination Node, D  Decodes received packets  Sends acknowledgments</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Issues</p>
    <p>Issue 1: Motivating Honest Reporting</p>
    <p>Issue 2: Motivating Honest Measuring</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Issue: Motivating Honest Reporting</p>
    <p>Ideal scenario: Each node i reports the loss probabilities of its outgoing links</p>
    <p>Reality: Without proper incentive, node i may not report its link loss probabilities honestly</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Techniques to Motivate Honest Reporting</p>
    <p>We design a routing protocol, such that reporting loss probabilities truthfully is the best strategy of each node</p>
    <p>Techniques: We influence the strategies of the players by introducing  an auxiliary transmission and</p>
    <p>a carefully designed payment formula</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivating Honest Reporting: Auxiliary Transmission</p>
    <p>For each packet that a node i should forward, it is required to send an auxiliary traffic of size z*i,j to each node j Vp</p>
    <p>is a very small constant</p>
    <p>i,j is the reported loss probability on link (i,j)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivating Honest Reporting: Payment Formula</p>
    <p>L is the packet length</p>
    <p>covers the cost of packet transmissions</p>
    <p>covers the cost of auxiliary transmissions</p>
    <p>(We assume that transmitting a packet of size 1 has one unit of cost.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Auxiliary Transmission and the Payment Formula?</p>
    <p>Utility:</p>
    <p>Get maximized when</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AC K</p>
    <p>How does the protocol work?</p>
    <p>S</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>A,D ,  A</p>
    <p>,B</p>
    <p>B,D ,</p>
    <p>B,A</p>
    <p>z A , z</p>
    <p>* A,D , z</p>
    <p>* A,B z</p>
    <p>B , z* B,D , z*</p>
    <p>B,A</p>
    <p>ACK p A</p>
    <p>p B</p>
    <p>AUX</p>
    <p>AU X</p>
    <p>A U</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>A U</p>
    <p>X</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivating Honest Reporting: Analysis</p>
    <p>Theorem: It is a strictly dominant strategy equilibrium for all player nodes to truthfully report loss probabilities.</p>
    <p>Strictly Dominant Strategy Equilibrium: The equilibrium strategy is strictly better than any other strategy for each node regardless of other nodes behaviors.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Two Steps</p>
    <p>Step 1: Motivating Honest Reporting</p>
    <p>Step 2: Motivating Honest Measuring</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Issue: Cheating in Measurements</p>
    <p>Practical scenario: A node needs the cooperation (feedback) of its neighbors to measure link loss probabilities</p>
    <p>Dishonest feedback may allow one node to cheat its neighbors in order to raise its own utility</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Techniques to Achieve Truthful Measurements</p>
    <p>We design an enhanced routing protocol, such that truthfully measuring the loss probabilities is to the best interest of each node</p>
    <p>Techniques: We influence the strategies of the players by carefully designing  measurement (test) signals and  a payment formula (Auxiliary transmission is the same as before.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measurement Signaling</p>
    <p>Each node i sends nt measurement signals  Format of measurement signal:</p>
    <p>kS,i is a secret key shared by S and i  MAC is a cryptographic Message Authentication</p>
    <p>Code function</p>
    <p>Each node forwards measurement signals using traditional routing protocol</p>
    <p>If ni,j measurement signals are received, then</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Payment Covering Measurements</p>
    <p>Payment Formula:</p>
    <p>covers the cost of packet transmissions</p>
    <p>covers the cost of auxiliary transmissions</p>
    <p>prevents dropping measurement signals</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>TEST_1</p>
    <p>TEST_2</p>
    <p>TEST_nBA</p>
    <p>How does the enhanced protocol work?</p>
    <p>S</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>z A , z</p>
    <p>* A,D , z</p>
    <p>* A,B</p>
    <p>z B , z*</p>
    <p>B,D , z* B,A</p>
    <p>ACK</p>
    <p>AC K</p>
    <p>p A</p>
    <p>p B</p>
    <p>AUX</p>
    <p>AU X</p>
    <p>TEST_1</p>
    <p>TEST_2</p>
    <p>TEST_nDA</p>
    <p>TEST_1</p>
    <p>TEST_2</p>
    <p>TEST_nDB</p>
    <p>A U</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>A U</p>
    <p>X</p>
    <p>TEST_1</p>
    <p>TEST_2</p>
    <p>TEST_nAB</p>
    <p>TEST_1</p>
    <p>TEST_2</p>
    <p>TEST_nAD</p>
    <p>TEST_1</p>
    <p>TEST_2</p>
    <p>TEST_nBD</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivating Truthful Measurements: Analysis</p>
    <p>Theorem: There is a strict Nash equilibrium for all player nodes to behave honestly in sending test signals and forwarding the received test signals.</p>
    <p>Theorem: The above equilibrium is the only strict Nash equilibrium in the system.</p>
    <p>Strict Nash Equilibrium: Unilaterally deviating from the equilibrium strategy will hurt a players utility.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation Setup</p>
    <p>Real implementation and tests on the ORBIT testbed</p>
    <p>25 nodes  802.11b ad hoc mode  Trans. power 20 dBm  Bit-rate 11Mbps  MORE batch size 32  Packet size 1500 bytes  Loss prob. 24%~100%  Session length 30 s  =0.1  =0.05</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation Setup</p>
    <p>Node Behavior:  Honest behavior:</p>
    <p>Each node follows our protocol faithfully</p>
    <p>Cheating behavior:  Misreporting link loss probabilities in the simple</p>
    <p>extension;</p>
    <p>Sending incorrect number of measurement signals and</p>
    <p>Dropping others measurement signals in the enhanced extension</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cheating Behavior and Node Utility</p>
    <p>Simple extension Utilities obtained by node 18</p>
    <p>Enhanced extension Utilities obtained by node 11</p>
    <p>Utilities obtained by honest reporting and cheating randomly</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cheating Behavior and Node Utility</p>
    <p>Utilities obtained by applying various strategies</p>
    <p>Simple extension Enhanced extension</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Impacts on End-to-End Throughput</p>
    <p>Average throughput as a function of the number of hops on the path</p>
    <p>Simple extension Up to 33.2% (58.0%) gain when 20% (40%) cheating</p>
    <p>Enhanced extension Up to 13.7% (23.4%) gain when 20% (40%) cheating</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Miscellaneous</p>
    <p>Overhead:  Average auxiliary transmissions: 26.73 KB  Average data transmitted: 3.93 MB  Ratio: 0.66%</p>
    <p>Auxiliary payment:  Ratio between auxiliary payment and total</p>
    <p>payment  Simple extension: 0.23%  Enhanced extension: 1.20%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>We study incentives in opportunistic routing and provide first solutions.</p>
    <p>We present a simple and practical protocol to guarantees that it is a strict dominant strategy for each user node to behave honestly.</p>
    <p>We also design an enhanced protocol to prevent cheating in measuring loss probabilities.</p>
    <p>We implement and evaluate our protocols on the ORBIT lab. The experimental results show that our protocols can bring the system throughput achieved by opportunistic routing protocols back to the high level.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!Thank you!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
