<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Orion: Shortest Path Estimation for</p>
    <p>Large Social Graphs</p>
    <p>Xiaohan Zhao, Alessandra Sala, Christo Wilson, Haitao Zheng and Ben Y. Zhao</p>
    <p>Department of Computer Science, UC Santa Barbara, USA</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Super Large Social Graphs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Maximizing Social Influence  Product advertisement in OSN</p>
    <p>Bill Gates likes Windows Mobile 7</p>
    <p>Propagate information starting at specific nodes</p>
    <p>Goal: find the most influential nodes in graph  Nodes with shorter average distances to rest of graph</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ranked Social Search</p>
    <p>Search for specific friends in social network  Rank search results based on the social distances</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Algorithm Time complexity for all nodes pairs</p>
    <p>Breadth-First Search (BFS) O(mn)</p>
    <p>Dijkstra O(n2log(n)+mn)</p>
    <p>Floyd-Warshall (n3)</p>
    <p>Node Distance Algorithms</p>
    <p>For a graph with n nodes and m edges</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problem of Node Distance Algorithms</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A More Scalable Solution?</p>
    <p>Design a scalable system for large graphs  Real-time queries are important  Desired query time: O(1)  Do preprocessing</p>
    <p>How to achieve O(1) query time?  Represent node distance in a graph as distance</p>
    <p>between two nodes in Euclidean Space</p>
    <p>Map all graph nodes into Euclidean Space  A Graph Coordinate System</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Orion</p>
    <p>A Graph Coordinate System  Embedding: Capture node distances using Euclidean</p>
    <p>positions  Estimate node distances using coordinates in constant</p>
    <p>time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Designing Orion</p>
    <p>Experimental Results</p>
    <p>Using Orion in Graph Applications</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Design Goals of Orion</p>
    <p>Scalability (preprocessing time)  Preprocessing time scales linearly w/ graph size  Minimize number of BFS operations</p>
    <p>Accuracy  Distance estimates approximate ground truth</p>
    <p>Fast convergence  Individual node calibration should not oscillate</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Physical spring system  Each node needs to do BFS</p>
    <p>computation</p>
    <p>Multiple iteration</p>
    <p>Approaches for Embedding  Landmark-based approach</p>
    <p>Distances to fixed number of nodes</p>
    <p>Compute once each node</p>
    <p>Our Choice</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to Select Landmarks?  Intuition: highest degree nodes as landmarks</p>
    <p>Backbone of social graph</p>
    <p>Landmark separation  Highest degree nodes often</p>
    <p>connected to each other  Need to avoid clusters of</p>
    <p>landmarks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to Position Landmarks?  Nave solution: Global Simplex</p>
    <p>Downhill  O(k2D) for k landmarks in D-dimension</p>
    <p>space  However, k can be large for large</p>
    <p>graphs</p>
    <p>Incremental approach  Divide k landmarks into two groups</p>
    <p>Small initial group Lk (16)  Two step computation</p>
    <p>Initial group: global simplex downhill  Remaining landmarks added one by one</p>
    <p>Use initial landmarks to calibrate distance 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experimental Setup  Datasets</p>
    <p>Four datasets from Facebook regional networks</p>
    <p>Evaluation Metrics  Relative Error:</p>
    <p>dm: actual distance dp: estimated distance computed by Orion</p>
    <p>Computational Time</p>
    <p>Network Nodes Edges Avg. Path Len.</p>
    <p>Norway 293K 5,589K 4.2</p>
    <p>Egypt 246K 1,618K 5.0</p>
    <p>Los Angeles 275K 2,115K 5.1</p>
    <p>India 363K 1,556K 6.1</p>
    <p>E = |dmdp|</p>
    <p>dm</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A v</p>
    <p>e ra</p>
    <p>g e</p>
    <p>R e</p>
    <p>la tiv</p>
    <p>e E</p>
    <p>rr o</p>
    <p>r</p>
    <p># of Dimensions</p>
    <p>India Egypt LA Norway</p>
    <p>Dimensionality of Coordinates</p>
    <p>Error &lt; 0.2 when dimension &gt; 6  Higher dimensions  improved accuracy  But also increases computational time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Computational Time</p>
    <p>Time India Egypt L.A. Norway</p>
    <p>Orion Preprocessing 9493s 6156s 6967s 7506s Orion Response 0.0000002s 0.00000002s 0.00000018s 0.00000019s BFS Response 1.028s 0.75s 1.027s 1.44s</p>
    <p>Orion Preprocessing: to compute coordinates for all nodes  One-time cost  2 hours for 300K node graph on 1 cheap commodity server  Time scales linearly with graph size</p>
    <p>Easily parallelized across clusters</p>
    <p>Average time per node-distance query  Orion is 7 orders of magnitude faster than BFS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Application: Node Separation Metrics</p>
    <p>Node separation metrics  Common tool to analyze graphs  Include radius, diameter and average path length</p>
    <p>India Egypt L.A. Norway</p>
    <p>A v e</p>
    <p>ra g</p>
    <p>e p</p>
    <p>a th</p>
    <p>le n</p>
    <p>g th</p>
    <p>( h</p>
    <p>o p</p>
    <p>) Actual Orion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  We propose Orion, a scalable graph coordinate</p>
    <p>system for node distance computation</p>
    <p>Time complexity is low  Preprocessing: 2 hours for a 300K node graph</p>
    <p>Can be parallelized across machine clusters  Query Response: 0.2s to estimate node distances for</p>
    <p>per query</p>
    <p>Orion can accurately support node-distance based applications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future / Ongoing Work  Dynamics in social graphs</p>
    <p>Investigate the impact of graph dynamics on node distances</p>
    <p>Use heuristics to incrementally update graph embeddings at run time</p>
    <p>Weighted graphs</p>
    <p>Examine the use of graph coordinate systems on applications on weighted graphs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You. Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
