<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Collective Views of the NSA/CSS Cyber Defense Exercise on Curricula and Learning</p>
    <p>Objectives</p>
    <p>William J. Adams Efstratios L. Gavas</p>
    <p>Tim Lacey Sylvain P. Leblanc</p>
    <p>United States Military Academy United States Merchant Marine Academy</p>
    <p>Air Force Institute of Technology Royal Military College of Canada</p>
    <p>USENIX CSET 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Overview What is the CDX?</p>
    <p>Academies Experiences United States Merchant Marine Academy United States Military Academy Air Force Institute of Technology Royal Military College of Canada</p>
    <p>Attacks What happened?</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction</p>
    <p>Objective of Paper</p>
    <p>I Discuss the Cyber Defense Exercise (CDX) I Review curriculum I Promote hands-on IA activities I Show flexibility of cyber security exercises</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>What is the CDX?</p>
    <p>Overview of CDX</p>
    <p>I Four-day exercise, but months of preparation I Ninth year of competition I Red vs. Blue, with White moderating</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>What is the CDX?</p>
    <p>Overview of CDX</p>
    <p>I Eight teams participated: I Air Force Institute of Technology (AFIT) I Naval Postgraduate School (NPS) I Royal Military College of Canada (RMC) I United States Air Force Academy (USAFA) I United States Coast Guard Academy (USCGA) I United States Merchant Marine Academy (USMMA) I United States Military Academy (USMA) I United States Naval Academy (USNA)</p>
    <p>I Participation at both graduate and undergraduate levels</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>What is the CDX?</p>
    <p>Overview of CDX</p>
    <p>I Each team is given a mock budget to secure a poorly-configured/compromised network</p>
    <p>I Email, instant messaging, database and web servers, workstations, and a domain controller</p>
    <p>I Administer network while under attacks by NSA Red Team I Deal with exercise injects</p>
    <p>I Forensics, helpdesk requests, DNS and network reconfiguration</p>
    <p>I Reporting requirements</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Academies Experiences</p>
    <p>The Differences</p>
    <p>I Different curricula I Different learning objectives I Different resources</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Academies Experiences</p>
    <p>United States Merchant Marine Academy</p>
    <p>USMMA Overview</p>
    <p>I Established to train Merchant Marine officers I Part of the Department of Transportation</p>
    <p>I Smallest of the five US undergraduate service academies I In the Heroic1 phase of security team building</p>
    <p>I . . . Possibly the Incompetence phase!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Academies Experiences</p>
    <p>United States Merchant Marine Academy</p>
    <p>How They Came to Their Design</p>
    <p>I Cost Trade-Offs I Administrative Trade-Offs I Monitoring Trade-Offs</p>
    <p>I Mistakes Made I Last-Minute Course Corrections</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Academies Experiences</p>
    <p>United States Merchant Marine Academy</p>
    <p>Review of USMMA Network Design Keep It Simple, Sailor</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Academies Experiences</p>
    <p>United States Merchant Marine Academy</p>
    <p>USMMA Summary</p>
    <p>I We do OK I Simplicity was our weapon of choice I If you dont understand it  it is not secure! I Dont be afraid of your system</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Academies Experiences</p>
    <p>United States Military Academy</p>
    <p>USMA Overview</p>
    <p>I Serves as a senior-level capstone I Active ACM and CS programs I Large team size (30-60 people) I Supported through the Information Technology and</p>
    <p>Operations Center (ITOC)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Academies Experiences</p>
    <p>United States Military Academy</p>
    <p>USMA Observations</p>
    <p>I Cleaned workstations with homemade Tripwire-like script I Rebuilt database and web servers I No significant compromises I Communication was a special focus</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Academies Experiences</p>
    <p>Air Force Institute of Technology</p>
    <p>AFIT Overview</p>
    <p>I Graduate program I Focus on lab activities I Range of skills (novice to network administrator) I Two teams of fifteen I Supported through the Center for Cyberspace Research</p>
    <p>(CCR)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Academies Experiences</p>
    <p>Air Force Institute of Technology</p>
    <p>AFIT Observations</p>
    <p>I Effective use of IPsec I Utilized proxy server I Mitigated compromises with user privileges</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Academies Experiences</p>
    <p>Royal Military College of Canada</p>
    <p>RMC Overview</p>
    <p>I First year competing I Mixed graduates and undergraduates I Only graduate participation this year</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Academies Experiences</p>
    <p>Royal Military College of Canada</p>
    <p>RMC Observations</p>
    <p>I First time working in a Network Operations Center (NOC) I Reinforced communication needs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Attacks</p>
    <p>What happened?</p>
    <p>Attacks What happened?</p>
    <p>I Twenty-one significant, distinct compromises I Most effective: Malware callbacks (7) I Most interesting: OpenFire remote access (4)</p>
    <p>A lot to keep track of . . .</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>I Budget and operational issues are important I Fewer successful attacks I Wider range of attacks</p>
    <p>I Hands-on activities can better direct student I Live exercises build critical skills</p>
    <p>I Communication I Operations I Leadership</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>More information I http://www.afit.edu/en/ccr/ I http://www.itoc.usma.edu</p>
    <p>Final Words. . . I If you hack boats or students, contact me</p>
    <p>(gavase{at}usmma[.]edu) I Suggestions welcome</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
