<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ian F. Adams, Darrell D.E. Long, Ethan L. Miller University of California, Santa Cruz</p>
    <p>Maximizing Efficiency By Trading Storage for Computation</p>
    <p>Shankar Pasupathy Mark W. Storer NetApp Pergamum Systems</p>
    <p>Monday, June 15, 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trade Storage for Computation</p>
    <p>Storing rarely used intermediate or final results is wasteful  If results are still used, even infrequently, they may not be discarded</p>
    <p>In the cloud, computing a result is often cheaper than storing it  store the inputs and process, recompute on demand</p>
    <p>Challenges:  Decide when re-computation is cheaper than storage  Provenance: what must be known in order to reproduce a result?  Result integrity: must a result be identical to the original?</p>
    <p>Inputs ResultProcess</p>
    <p>Monday, June 15, 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Old Idea, New Potential</p>
    <p>Balancing storage and computation is common  Data de-duplication, file compression, dynamic programming...</p>
    <p>The cloud allows opportunities for large scale tradeoffs  Quickly allocate resources to compute on demand  No need for over provisioning to prepare for rare events</p>
    <p>purchase on demand computation when needed</p>
    <p>Storage Recomputation</p>
    <p>Monday, June 15, 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example  Archive of 100,000 photos</p>
    <p>Provide bmp, jpeg, tiff, Adobe, png  Use Amazon Web Services</p>
    <p>Store Everything  1600x1200 resolution images in 5 formats= 2.2TB  100 GB of requests  Cs =$347.00 per month</p>
    <p>Recompute Formats on Demand  Raw BMP=550 GB  720 on demand small linux instance hours  100 GB out from S3 to EC2+100 GB EC2 Out  Cr =$224.00 per month</p>
    <p>AWS Prices- June 12 2009AWS Prices- June 12 2009</p>
    <p>S3 Storage Cost $0.18 per GB/Month</p>
    <p>S3 Data In $0.03 per GB</p>
    <p>S3 Data Out $0.17 per GB</p>
    <p>EC2 Sm. Machine Instance $0.10 per hour</p>
    <p>EC2 Data In $0.10 per GB</p>
    <p>EC2 Data Out $0.17 per hour</p>
    <p>Cr = Cost of Re-computation Cs = Cost of Storage</p>
    <p>Monday, June 15, 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Calculating Cr and Cs can be difficult  Issues include: Likelihood of reuse, lead time, penalties for unavailable</p>
    <p>data, adaptation to cloud providers, pricing forecasts....  Requires knowledge from both cloud providers and users</p>
    <p>e.g. user has miss penalty data, provider has infrastructure understanding</p>
    <p>Provenance: What is necessary to recompute a result?  Provenance aware systems (e.g. PASS) can aid analysis</p>
    <p>Result Integrity: Can the original result be recomputed?  Can a similar result suffice? Or must it be identical?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thanks to our sponsors:  SSRC industrial sponsors  Petascale Data Storage Institute</p>
    <p>Thanks to:  Mark W. Storer (Pergamum Systems)  Darrell D.E. Long (UC Santa Cruz)  Ethan L. Miller (UC Santa Cruz)  Shankar Pasupathy (NetApp)  Ahmed Ahmer (University of Pittsburgh)</p>
    <p>Questions? Comments?</p>
    <p>Monday, June 15, 2009</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
