<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>P4P : Provider Portal for (P2P) Applications</p>
    <p>Laboratory of Networked Systems Yale University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgements  Joint work with</p>
    <p>Haiyong Xie (Yale)  Arvind Krishnamurthy (University of Washington)  Members of Yale Laboratory of Networked Systems (LANS). In particular,</p>
    <p>Richard Alimi, Hao Wang, Ye Wang, Glenn Thrope  Avi Silberschatz (Yale)</p>
    <p>Extremely grateful to  Charles Kalmanek (AT&amp;T Labs)  Marty Lafferty (DCIA)  Doug Pasko (Verizon)  Laird Popkin (Pando)  Rich Woundy (Comcast)  Members of the P4P working group</p>
    <p>Some slides are from the NANOG presentation by Pasko and Popkin</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>P2P: Benefits and Challenges</p>
    <p>P2P is a key to content delivery  Low costs to content owners/distributors  Scalability</p>
    <p>Challenge  Network-obliviousness usually leads to network inefficiency</p>
    <p>Intradomain: for Verizon network, P2P traffic traverses 1000 miles and 5.5 metro-hops on average</p>
    <p>Interdomain: 50%-90% of existing local pieces in active users are downloaded externally*</p>
    <p>*Karagiannis et al. Should Internet service providers fear peer-assisted content distribution? In Proceeding of IMC 2005</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ISP Attempts to Address P2P Issues</p>
    <p>Upgrade infrastructure  Customer pricing  Rate limiting, or termination of services</p>
    <p>P2P caching</p>
    <p>ISPs cannot effectively address network efficiency alone</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Locality-aware P2P: P2Ps Attempt to Improve Network Efficiency</p>
    <p>P2P has flexibility in shaping communication patterns</p>
    <p>Locality-aware P2P tries to use this flexibility to improve network efficiency  E.g., Karagiannis et al. 2005, Bindal et al. 2006,</p>
    <p>Choffnes et al. 2008 (Ono)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Problems of Locality-aware P2P</p>
    <p>Locality-aware P2P needs to reverse engineer network topology, traffic load and network policy</p>
    <p>Locality-aware P2P may not achieve network efficiency Choose congested links Traverse costly interdomain links</p>
    <p>ISP 0</p>
    <p>ISP K</p>
    <p>ISP 1</p>
    <p>ISP 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Fundamental Problem</p>
    <p>Feedback from networks is limited  E.g., end-to-end flow measurements or limited</p>
    <p>ICMP feedback</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Goal</p>
    <p>Design a framework to enable better cooperation between networks and P2P</p>
    <p>P4P: Provider Portal for (P2P) Applications</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ISP A</p>
    <p>iTracker</p>
    <p>P4P Architecture  Providers</p>
    <p>publish information via iTracker</p>
    <p>Applications  query providers</p>
    <p>information  adjust traffic patterns</p>
    <p>accordingly</p>
    <p>P2P</p>
    <p>ISP B</p>
    <p>iTracker</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example:Tracker-based P2P  Information flow</p>
    <p>1. peer queries appTracker</p>
    <p>2/3. appTracker queries iTracker</p>
    <p>4. appTracker selects a set of active peers ISP A</p>
    <p>peer</p>
    <p>appTracker</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>ISPs and applications have their own objectives/constraints  ISPs have diverse objectives  Applications also have diverse objectives</p>
    <p>Desirable to have  Providers: application-agnostic  Applications: network-agnostic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Motivating Example</p>
    <p>ISP objective:  Focus on intradomain  Minimize maximum link</p>
    <p>utilization (MLU)</p>
    <p>P2P objective:  Optimize completion</p>
    <p>time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Specifying ISP Objective  ISP Objective</p>
    <p>Minimize MLU</p>
    <p>Notations:  Assume K P2P applications in the ISPs network  be: background traffic volume on link e  ce: capacity of link e  Ie(i,j) = 1 if link e is on the route from i to j  tk : a traffic demand matrix {tkij} for each pair of nodes (i,j)</p>
    <p>e k ji</p>
    <p>e k ije</p>
    <p>Ee cjiItb /)),((maxmin</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Specifying P2P Objective  P2P Objective</p>
    <p>Optimize completion time</p>
    <p>Using a fluid model, we can derive that: optimizing P2P completion time</p>
    <p>maximizing up/down link</p>
    <p>capacity usage 0,</p>
    <p>,,</p>
    <p>,,..</p>
    <p>max</p>
    <p>ij</p>
    <p>ij iji</p>
    <p>ij iij</p>
    <p>i ij ij</p>
    <p>tji</p>
    <p>dti</p>
    <p>utits</p>
    <p>t</p>
    <p>*Modeling and performance analysis of bittorrent-like peer-to-peer networks. Qiu et al. Sigcomm 04</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>System Formulation  Combine the objectives of provider and</p>
    <p>application</p>
    <p>e k ji</p>
    <p>e k ije</p>
    <p>Ee cjiItb /)),((maxmin</p>
    <p>,,</p>
    <p>,,..</p>
    <p>max</p>
    <p>k ij</p>
    <p>ij</p>
    <p>k i</p>
    <p>k ji</p>
    <p>ij</p>
    <p>k i</p>
    <p>k ij</p>
    <p>i ij</p>
    <p>k ij</p>
    <p>tji</p>
    <p>dti</p>
    <p>utits</p>
    <p>ts.t., for any k,</p>
    <p>Tkt k</p>
    <p>T1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Difficulties</p>
    <p>A straightforward approach: centralized solution  Applications: ship their information</p>
    <p>to ISPs  ISPs: solve the optimization problem</p>
    <p>Issues  Not scalable  Not application-agnostic  Violation of P2P privacy</p>
    <p>e k ji</p>
    <p>e k ije</p>
    <p>Ee cjiItb /)),((maxmin</p>
    <p>,,</p>
    <p>,,..</p>
    <p>max</p>
    <p>k ij</p>
    <p>ij</p>
    <p>k i</p>
    <p>k ji</p>
    <p>ij</p>
    <p>k i</p>
    <p>k ij</p>
    <p>i ij</p>
    <p>k ij</p>
    <p>tji</p>
    <p>dti</p>
    <p>utits</p>
    <p>ts.t., for any k,</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Contribution: Decoupling ISP/P2Ps</p>
    <p>e k ji</p>
    <p>e k ije</p>
    <p>EeTt cjiItb</p>
    <p>k /)),((maxmin</p>
    <p>k :k</p>
    <p>e k ji</p>
    <p>e k ije</p>
    <p>Ttk</p>
    <p>cjiItbets kk</p>
    <p>),(:..</p>
    <p>min :</p>
    <p>Constraints couple ISP/P2Ps together!</p>
    <p>Tk tk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Key Contribution: Decoupling ISP/P2Ps</p>
    <p>e k ji</p>
    <p>e k ije</p>
    <p>EeTt cjiItb</p>
    <p>k /)),((maxmin</p>
    <p>k :k</p>
    <p>e k ji</p>
    <p>e k ije</p>
    <p>Ttk</p>
    <p>cjiItbets kk</p>
    <p>),(:..</p>
    <p>min :</p>
    <p>pe</p>
    <p>Introduce pe to decouple the constraints</p>
    <p>Tk tk</p>
    <p>)min(max 1</p>
    <p>ji</p>
    <p>k ijij</p>
    <p>e k Tt</p>
    <p>ee cp</p>
    <p>tpbp kk</p>
    <p>ee</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ISP/P2P Interactions  The interface between applications and</p>
    <p>providers is {pe}  Providers: compute {pe}, which reflects network</p>
    <p>status and policy  Applications: react and adjust {tkij} to optimize</p>
    <p>application objective</p>
    <p>tk(t)</p>
    <p>pe1(t) pe2(t)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Generaliztion  Generalize to other ISP objectives and P2P</p>
    <p>objectives</p>
    <p>Customized objective</p>
    <p>ISPs</p>
    <p>Minimize interdomain cost</p>
    <p>Minimize Bit-Distance Product</p>
    <p>Applications</p>
    <p>Maximize throughput</p>
    <p>Robustness</p>
    <p>Minimize MLU</p>
    <p>Rank peers using pe</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From Optimization Decomposition to Interface Design</p>
    <p>Issue: scalability</p>
    <p>Technique  PIDs: opaque IDs of a group of nodes</p>
    <p>Clients with the same PID have similar network costs with respect to other clients</p>
    <p>PID links: network links connecting PIDs (can be logical links)</p>
    <p>pe: P4P distance for each PID link e</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>From Optimization Decomposition to Interface Design Issue: privacy</p>
    <p>Technique: two views  Provider (internal) view</p>
    <p>Application (external) view  pij may be perturbed to</p>
    <p>preserve privacy</p>
    <p>ji route on e</p>
    <p>eij pp</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation Methodology</p>
    <p>BitTorrent simulations  Build a simulation package for BitTorrent  Use topologies of Abilene and Tier-1 ISPs in simulations</p>
    <p>Abilene experiment using BitTorrent  Run BitTorrent clients on PlanetLab nodes in Abilene  Interdomain emulation</p>
    <p>Field tests using Pando clients  Applications: Pando pushed 20 MB video to 1.25 million clients  Providers: Verizon and Telefonica provided network topologies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BitTorrent Simulation: Bottleneck Link Utilization</p>
    <p>P4P results in less than half utilization on bottleneck links</p>
    <p>native</p>
    <p>Localized</p>
    <p>P4P</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Abilene Experiment: Completion Time</p>
    <p>- P4P achieves similar performance with localized at percentile higher from 50%. - P4P has a shorter tail.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Abilene Experiment: Charging Volume</p>
    <p>Charging volume of the second link: native BT is 4x of P4P; localized BT is 2x of P4P</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Field Tests: ISP Perspectives  Interdomain Traffic Statistics</p>
    <p>Ingress: Native is 53% higher  Egress: Native is 70% higher</p>
    <p>Intradomain Traffic Statistics</p>
    <p>B D</p>
    <p>P</p>
    <p>Native P4P</p>
    <p>N o rm</p>
    <p>a li z e d V</p>
    <p>o lu</p>
    <p>m e</p>
    <p>ingress egress</p>
    <p>% o</p>
    <p>f L o c a l Tr</p>
    <p>a ffi</p>
    <p>c</p>
    <p>Native P4P</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Field Tests: P2P Completion Time</p>
    <p>Native P4P Improveme nt</p>
    <p>All P2P clients: P4P improves avg completion time by 23% FTTH clients: P4P improves avg completion time by 68%</p>
    <p>Im p ro</p>
    <p>v e m</p>
    <p>e n t</p>
    <p>%</p>
    <p>percentile</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary &amp; Future Work</p>
    <p>Summary  We propose P4P for cooperative Internet traffic</p>
    <p>control  We apply optimization decomposition to design an</p>
    <p>extensible and scalable framework  Concurrent efforts: e.g, Feldmann et al,</p>
    <p>Telefonica/Thompson</p>
    <p>Future work  P4P capability interface (caching, CoS)  Further ISP and application integration  Incentives, privacy, and security analysis of P4P</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Compute pDistance</p>
    <p>Introducing dual variable pe ( 0) for the inequality of each link e, the dual is</p>
    <p>To make the dual finite, we need</p>
    <p>The dual becomes</p>
    <p>pij is the sum of pe along the path from PID i to PID j</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>eecp 1</p>
    <p>)(min)( :;</p>
    <p>e e k</p>
    <p>k eee</p>
    <p>Ttk e ctbppD kk</p>
    <p>ji</p>
    <p>k ijij</p>
    <p>e k Tt</p>
    <p>eee tpbppD kkmin)(</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Update pDistance</p>
    <p>At update m+1,  calculate new</p>
    <p>shadow prices for all links,</p>
    <p>then compute pDistance for all PID pairs</p>
    <p>e eee</p>
    <p>S</p>
    <p>See</p>
    <p>pcp</p>
    <p>mmmpmp</p>
    <p>}0;1:{p :S</p>
    <p>Sset toprojection:[]</p>
    <p>})D({p ofent supergradi :</p>
    <p>size step :</p>
    <p>)]()()1([)1(</p>
    <p>e</p>
    <p>e</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
