<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 1</p>
    <p>Managing Energy and Managing Energy and Server Resources in Hosting Server Resources in Hosting</p>
    <p>CentersCenters</p>
    <p>Jeff Chase, Darrell Anderson, Ron Doyle, Jeff Chase, Darrell Anderson, Ron Doyle, Prachi Thakar, Amin VahdatPrachi Thakar, Amin Vahdat</p>
    <p>Duke UniversityDuke University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 2</p>
    <p>Back to the FutureBack to the Future  Return toReturn to server-centered computing server-centered computing: applications run as : applications run as</p>
    <p>servicesservices accessed through the Internet. accessed through the Internet.</p>
    <p>Web-based services, ASPs, netsourcingWeb-based services, ASPs, netsourcing</p>
    <p>Internet services are hosted on server clusters.Internet services are hosted on server clusters.</p>
    <p>Incrementally scalable, etc.Incrementally scalable, etc.</p>
    <p>Server clusters may be managed by a third party.Server clusters may be managed by a third party.</p>
    <p>Shared data center or Shared data center or hosting centerhosting center</p>
    <p>Hosting utility offers economies of scale:Hosting utility offers economies of scale:  Network accessNetwork access  Power and coolingPower and cooling  Administration and securityAdministration and security  Surge capacitySurge capacity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 3</p>
    <p>Managing Energy and Server ResourcesManaging Energy and Server Resources</p>
    <p>Key ideaKey idea: a : a hosting center OShosting center OS maintains the maintains the balance of requests and responses, energy inputs, balance of requests and responses, energy inputs, and thermal outputs.and thermal outputs.</p>
    <p>responses</p>
    <p>energy</p>
    <p>waste heat</p>
    <p>requests</p>
    <p>Power/cooling browndown Dynamic thermal management [Brooks]</p>
    <p>US in 2003US in 2003: : 22 TWh ($1B 22 TWh ($1B</p>
    <p>- $2B+)- $2B+)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 4</p>
    <p>ContributionsContributions</p>
    <p>Architecture/prototype for Architecture/prototype for adaptive provisioningadaptive provisioning of server of server resources in Internet server clusters (resources in Internet server clusters (MuseMuse))</p>
    <p>Software feedbackSoftware feedback</p>
    <p>Reconfigurable request redirectionReconfigurable request redirection</p>
    <p>Addresses a key challenge for hosting automationAddresses a key challenge for hosting automation</p>
    <p>Foundation for energy management in hosting centersFoundation for energy management in hosting centers  25% - 75% energy savings 25% - 75% energy savings</p>
    <p>Degrade rationally (gracefully) under constraint (e.g., browndown)Degrade rationally (gracefully) under constraint (e.g., browndown)</p>
    <p>Simple economic resource allocationSimple economic resource allocation  Continuous Continuous utility functionsutility functions: customers pay for performance.: customers pay for performance.</p>
    <p>Balance service quality and resource usage.Balance service quality and resource usage.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 5</p>
    <p>Static ProvisioningStatic Provisioning</p>
    <p>Dedicate fixed resources per customerDedicate fixed resources per customer</p>
    <p>Typical of co-lo or dedicated hostingTypical of co-lo or dedicated hosting</p>
    <p>Reprovision Reprovision manuallymanually as needed as needed</p>
    <p>Overprovision for surgesOverprovision for surges</p>
    <p>High variable cost of capacityHigh variable cost of capacity</p>
    <p>How to automate resource provisioning for managed hosting?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 6</p>
    <p>Load Is DynamicLoad Is Dynamic ibm.com external site  February 2001  Daily fluctuations (3x)  Workday cycle  Weekends off</p>
    <p>World Cup soccer site  May-June 1998  Seasonal fluctuations  Event surges (11x)  ita.ee.lbl.gov</p>
    <p>T h ro</p>
    <p>u g h p u t (r</p>
    <p>e q u e s ts</p>
    <p>/s )</p>
    <p>T h</p>
    <p>ro u</p>
    <p>g h</p>
    <p>p u</p>
    <p>t (r</p>
    <p>e q</p>
    <p>u e</p>
    <p>s ts</p>
    <p>/s )</p>
    <p>M T W Th F S SM T W Th F S S</p>
    <p>Week 6 7 8Week 6 7 8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 7</p>
    <p>Adaptive ProvisioningAdaptive Provisioning</p>
    <p>- Efficient resource usage - Load multiplexing - Surge protection - Online capacity planning - Dynamic resource recruitment</p>
    <p>- Balance service quality with cost - Service Level Agreements (SLAs)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 8</p>
    <p>Utilization TargetsUtilization Targets</p>
    <p>i &gt;target : service i is underprovisioned</p>
    <p>i = allocated server resource for service i</p>
    <p>i = utilization of i at is current load i</p>
    <p>target = configurable target level for i Leave headroom for load spikes.</p>
    <p>i &lt;target : service i is overprovisioned</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 9</p>
    <p>Muse ArchitectureMuse Architecture</p>
    <p>Control performance</p>
    <p>measures</p>
    <p>reconfigurable switches</p>
    <p>configuration commands</p>
    <p>offered request load</p>
    <p>storage tier</p>
    <p>Executive controls mapping of service traffic to server resources by means of:</p>
    <p>reconfigurable switches  scheduler controls (shares)</p>
    <p>server pool stateless</p>
    <p>interchangeable</p>
    <p>Executive</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 10</p>
    <p>Server Power DrawServer Power Draw</p>
    <p>CPU idle 93w</p>
    <p>CPU max 120w</p>
    <p>boot 136w</p>
    <p>disk spin 6-10woff/hiber</p>
    <p>work</p>
    <p>watts Idling consumes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 11</p>
    <p>Energy vs. Service QualityEnergy vs. Service Quality</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>C</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>Active set = {A,B,C,D} Active set = {A,B}</p>
    <p>A</p>
    <p>B</p>
    <p>i &lt;target  Low latency</p>
    <p>i =target  Meets quality goals  Saves energy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 12</p>
    <p>Energy-Conscious ProvisioningEnergy-Conscious Provisioning</p>
    <p>Light loadLight load: concentrate traffic on a minimal set of servers.: concentrate traffic on a minimal set of servers.  Step down surplus servers to a low-power state.Step down surplus servers to a low-power state.</p>
    <p>APMAPM and and ACPIACPI  Activate surplus servers on demand.Activate surplus servers on demand.</p>
    <p>Wake-On-LANWake-On-LAN  BrowndownBrowndown: can provision for a specified energy target.: can provision for a specified energy target.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 13</p>
    <p>Resource EconomyResource Economy  InputInput: the value of : the value of performanceperformance for each customer for each customer ii..</p>
    <p>Common unit of value: money.Common unit of value: money.</p>
    <p>Derives from the economic value of the service.Derives from the economic value of the service.</p>
    <p>Enables SLAs to represent flexible quality vs. cost tradeoffs.Enables SLAs to represent flexible quality vs. cost tradeoffs.</p>
    <p>Per-customer Per-customer utility functionutility function UUii = = bid  penalty.bid  penalty.</p>
    <p>Bid for traffic volume (throughput Bid for traffic volume (throughput ii).).</p>
    <p>Bid for better service quality, or subtract Bid for better service quality, or subtract penaltypenalty for poor quality. for poor quality.</p>
    <p>Allocate resources to maximize expected global utility (revenue or Allocate resources to maximize expected global utility (revenue or reward).reward).</p>
    <p>Predict performance effects.Predict performance effects.</p>
    <p>Sell Sell  to the highest bidder.to the highest bidder.  Never sell resources below cost.Never sell resources below cost. Maximize Maximize  bidbidii((ii(t, (t, ii))))</p>
    <p>Subject to Subject to i i  maxmax</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 14</p>
    <p>Maximizing RevenueMaximizing Revenue</p>
    <p>Consider any customer Consider any customer ii with allotment with allotment ii at at fixedfixed time time t.t.</p>
    <p>The marginal utility (The marginal utility (pricepriceii) for a resource unit allotted or ) for a resource unit allotted or reclaimed from reclaimed from ii is the gradient of is the gradient of UUii at at ii..</p>
    <p>Expected Expected</p>
    <p>UtilityUtility UUii(t, (t, ii))</p>
    <p>Resource allotmentResource allotment ii</p>
    <p>Adjust allotments until Adjust allotments until price price equilibriumequilibrium is reached. is reached.</p>
    <p>The algorithm assumes that The algorithm assumes that UUii is is</p>
    <p>concave:concave: the price gradients the price gradients are non-negative and are non-negative and monotonically non-increasingmonotonically non-increasing..</p>
    <p>pricepriceii</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 15</p>
    <p>Feedback and StabilityFeedback and Stability</p>
    <p>Allocation planning is Allocation planning is incrementalincremental..  Adjust the solution from the previous interval to react to new Adjust the solution from the previous interval to react to new</p>
    <p>observations.observations.  Allow system to stabilize before next re-evaluation. Allow system to stabilize before next re-evaluation.</p>
    <p>Set adjustment interval and magnitude to avoid oscillation.Set adjustment interval and magnitude to avoid oscillation.</p>
    <p>Control theory applies. Control theory applies. [Abdelzaher, Shin et al, 2001][Abdelzaher, Shin et al, 2001]</p>
    <p>Filter the load observations to distinguish transient and Filter the load observations to distinguish transient and persistent load changes.persistent load changes.</p>
    <p>Internet service workloads are extremely bursty.Internet service workloads are extremely bursty.</p>
    <p>Filter must balance stability and agility Filter must balance stability and agility [Kim and Noble 2001].[Kim and Noble 2001].</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 16</p>
    <p>Flop-Flip FilterFlop-Flip Filter  EWMA-based filter alone is not sufficient.EWMA-based filter alone is not sufficient.</p>
    <p>Average Average AAtt for each interval for each interval tt: : AAtt = = AAt-1t-1 + (1- + (1-)O)Ott</p>
    <p>The gain The gain  may be variable or may be variable or flip-flop.flip-flop.</p>
    <p>Load estimate Load estimate EEtt = E = Et-1t-1 if EEt-1t-1 - A - Att &lt; tolerance &lt; tolerance</p>
    <p>elseelse EEtt = A = Att  StableStable  ResponsiveResponsive</p>
    <p>Time (s)</p>
    <p>U ti</p>
    <p>li z a ti</p>
    <p>o n</p>
    <p>( %</p>
    <p>)</p>
    <p>Raw Data</p>
    <p>EW MA (a=7/8)</p>
    <p>Flop-Flip</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 17</p>
    <p>IBM Trace Run (IBM Trace Run (BeforeBefore))</p>
    <p>Time (minutes)</p>
    <p>T h</p>
    <p>ro u</p>
    <p>g h</p>
    <p>p u</p>
    <p>t (r</p>
    <p>eq u</p>
    <p>es ts</p>
    <p>/s )</p>
    <p>P o</p>
    <p>w e r D</p>
    <p>ra w</p>
    <p>(w a tts</p>
    <p>), L</p>
    <p>a ten</p>
    <p>cy (m</p>
    <p>s x50 )</p>
    <p>Throughput Power Latency</p>
    <p>T h ro</p>
    <p>u g</p>
    <p>h p u</p>
    <p>t (re q u</p>
    <p>ests /s)</p>
    <p>P o</p>
    <p>w er d</p>
    <p>raw (w</p>
    <p>atts) L</p>
    <p>aten cy (m</p>
    <p>s* 5</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 18</p>
    <p>IBM Trace Run (IBM Trace Run (AfterAfter))</p>
    <p>Tim e (m inute s)</p>
    <p>T h</p>
    <p>ro u</p>
    <p>g h</p>
    <p>p u</p>
    <p>t (r</p>
    <p>e q</p>
    <p>u e s ts</p>
    <p>/s )</p>
    <p>P o</p>
    <p>w e r D</p>
    <p>ra w</p>
    <p>(w a tts</p>
    <p>), L</p>
    <p>a te</p>
    <p>n c y (m</p>
    <p>s x</p>
    <p>Throughput</p>
    <p>Power</p>
    <p>Latency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 19</p>
    <p>Evaluating Energy SavingsEvaluating Energy Savings</p>
    <p>Trace replay shows adaptive provisioning in action.Trace replay shows adaptive provisioning in action.</p>
    <p>Server energy savings in this experiment was 29%.Server energy savings in this experiment was 29%.</p>
    <p>5-node cluster, 3x load swings, 5-node cluster, 3x load swings, targettarget = 0.5 = 0.5</p>
    <p>Expect roughly comparable savings in cooling costs. Expect roughly comparable savings in cooling costs.  Ventilation costs are fixed; chiller costs are proportional to Ventilation costs are fixed; chiller costs are proportional to</p>
    <p>thermal loading.thermal loading.</p>
    <p>For a given shape load curve, achievable energy savings For a given shape load curve, achievable energy savings increases with cluster size.increases with cluster size.</p>
    <p>E.g., higher request volumes,E.g., higher request volumes,  or lower or lower targettarget for better service quality.for better service quality.</p>
    <p>Larger clusters give finer granularity to closely match load.Larger clusters give finer granularity to closely match load.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 20</p>
    <p>Expected Resource SavingsExpected Resource Savings</p>
    <p>Ma x Se rve rs</p>
    <p>S a v in</p>
    <p>g s (</p>
    <p>% )</p>
    <p>W orld Cup (two month)</p>
    <p>W orld Cup (month 2)</p>
    <p>W orld Cup (week 8)</p>
    <p>IBM (week)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 21</p>
    <p>ConclusionsConclusions</p>
    <p>Dynamic request redirection enables fine-grained, continuous Dynamic request redirection enables fine-grained, continuous control over mapping of workload to physical server resources in control over mapping of workload to physical server resources in hosting centers.hosting centers.</p>
    <p>Continuous monitoring and control allows a hosting center OS to Continuous monitoring and control allows a hosting center OS to provision resources adaptively.provision resources adaptively.</p>
    <p>Adaptive resource provisioning is central to energy and thermal Adaptive resource provisioning is central to energy and thermal management in data centers.management in data centers.</p>
    <p>Adapt to energy browndown by degrading service quality.Adapt to energy browndown by degrading service quality.</p>
    <p>Adapt to load swings for 25% - 75% energy savings.Adapt to load swings for 25% - 75% energy savings.</p>
    <p>Economic policy framework guides provisioning choices based Economic policy framework guides provisioning choices based on SLAs and cost/benefit tradeoffs.on SLAs and cost/benefit tradeoffs.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 22</p>
    <p>Future WorkFuture Work</p>
    <p>multiple resources (e.g., memory and storage)multiple resources (e.g., memory and storage)</p>
    <p>multi-tier services and multiple server poolsmulti-tier services and multiple server pools</p>
    <p>reservations and latency QoS penaltiesreservations and latency QoS penalties</p>
    <p>rational server allocation and request distributionrational server allocation and request distribution</p>
    <p>integration with thermal system in data centerintegration with thermal system in data center</p>
    <p>flexibility and power of utility functionsflexibility and power of utility functions</p>
    <p>server networks and overlaysserver networks and overlays</p>
    <p>performability and availability SLAsperformability and availability SLAs</p>
    <p>application feedbackapplication feedback</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 23</p>
    <p>Executive</p>
    <p>client cluster server pool</p>
    <p>Extreme GigE switch</p>
    <p>LinkSys 100 Mb/s</p>
    <p>switch</p>
    <p>redirectors (PowerEdge 1550)</p>
    <p>SURGE or trace load generators</p>
    <p>Muse Prototype and TestbedMuse Prototype and Testbed</p>
    <p>FreeBSD-based redirectors resource containers APM and Wake-on-LAN</p>
    <p>faithful trace replay + synthetic Web loads server CPU-bound</p>
    <p>power meter</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 24</p>
    <p>Throughput and LatencyThroughput and Latency saturated: i &gt; target i increases linearly with i</p>
    <p>Average per-request service demand: i i / i</p>
    <p>overprovisioned: i &gt; target may reclaim: i(target - i)0</p>
    <p>Tim e (s)</p>
    <p>C P</p>
    <p>U (</p>
    <p>% )</p>
    <p>Allocation</p>
    <p>Usage</p>
    <p>Time (s)</p>
    <p>T h ro</p>
    <p>u g h p u t</p>
    <p>(r e q u e s ts</p>
    <p>/s )</p>
    <p>L a te</p>
    <p>n c y (m</p>
    <p>s )</p>
    <p>Throughput</p>
    <p>Latency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 25</p>
    <p>An OS for a Hosting CenterAn OS for a Hosting Center</p>
    <p>Hosting centers are made up of heterogeneous Hosting centers are made up of heterogeneous components linked by a network fabric.components linked by a network fabric.</p>
    <p>Components are specialized.Components are specialized.</p>
    <p>Each component has its own OS.Each component has its own OS.</p>
    <p>The role of a The role of a hosting center OShosting center OS is to: is to:</p>
    <p>Manage shared resources (e.g., servers, energy) Manage shared resources (e.g., servers, energy)</p>
    <p>Configure and monitor component interactionsConfigure and monitor component interactions</p>
    <p>Direct flow of request/response trafficDirect flow of request/response traffic</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 26</p>
    <p>Allocation Under Constraint (0)Allocation Under Constraint (0)</p>
    <p>Tim e (s)</p>
    <p>T h</p>
    <p>ro u</p>
    <p>g h</p>
    <p>p u</p>
    <p>t (r</p>
    <p>e q</p>
    <p>u e s ts</p>
    <p>/s )</p>
    <p>A llo</p>
    <p>tm e n</p>
    <p>t (s e rv</p>
    <p>e rs</p>
    <p>)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 27</p>
    <p>Allocation Under Constraint (1)Allocation Under Constraint (1)</p>
    <p>-100 100 300 500 700 900 1100 1300 1500</p>
    <p>Tim e (s)</p>
    <p>T h</p>
    <p>ro u</p>
    <p>g h</p>
    <p>p u</p>
    <p>t (r</p>
    <p>e q</p>
    <p>u e s ts</p>
    <p>/s )</p>
    <p>A llo</p>
    <p>tm e n</p>
    <p>t (s e rv</p>
    <p>e rs</p>
    <p>)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Slide 28</p>
    <p>OutlineOutline</p>
    <p>Adaptive server provisioningAdaptive server provisioning</p>
    <p>Energy-conscious provisioningEnergy-conscious provisioning</p>
    <p>Economic resource allocationEconomic resource allocation</p>
    <p>Stable load estimationStable load estimation</p>
    <p>Experimental resultsExperimental results</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
