<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>And when the radical priest Come to get me released</p>
    <p>We was all on the cover of Newsweek</p>
    <p>Mark Allman International Computer Science Institute</p>
    <p>USENIX WOWCS April 2008</p>
    <p>What Ought A Program Committee To Do?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview</p>
    <p>Old World: Internet is our sandbox  New World: Internet is crucial infrastructure</p>
    <p>This has many practical implications, which includes questions about the appropriateness of our experiments and measurements</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview (cont.)</p>
    <p>Issues of appropriateness have started being asked within program committees</p>
    <p>E.g., when does measurement traffic become an attack? (See [11])</p>
    <p>E.g., how should public measurement data be treated? (See [3,10,5])</p>
    <p>E.g., how should our research platforms like PlanetLab be treated? (See [7])</p>
    <p>E.g., how should users be treated and do we need their consent? (See [12])</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Decisions, Decisions</p>
    <p>Job of a PC is to accept or reject papers  How much should ethical considerations play</p>
    <p>into that process?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Decisions (cont.)</p>
    <p>Easy approach: just judge the technical contribution</p>
    <p>aligns well with our expertise  community can police itself  e.g., [3,10,5] trifecta</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Decisions (cont.)</p>
    <p>The flip side:  PCs are in a unique position to take concrete</p>
    <p>action</p>
    <p>Doing nothing could spiral into a culture that rewards only the ends without even considering the means</p>
    <p>Shady experimental techniques might hurt a venues reputation (or, sponsors)</p>
    <p>Could be viewed as protecting community resources (e.g., shared facilities and data)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Further Questions  If a PC does make a judgement that some</p>
    <p>methodology is inappropriate and rejects a papers, is that it?</p>
    <p>Should there be some further investigation or sanction?</p>
    <p>similar to suspected plagarism ?  perhaps databases of previous reviews would</p>
    <p>be enough?</p>
    <p>perhaps the next PC will figure things out? 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The IRB</p>
    <p>What is the role of the Institutional Review Board?</p>
    <p>seems like a potentially useful avenue for vetting</p>
    <p>If it is OK with an IRB should it be OK for our conferences?</p>
    <p>What about thorny methodologies that do not involve human subjects?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>So ... What Ought A Program Committee</p>
    <p>To Do?</p>
    <p>Mark Allman</p>
    <p>mallman@icir.org http://www.icir.org/mallman/</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Extra Slides</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Related Work</p>
    <p>Legal aspects of our work  E.g., [9,13]</p>
    <p>Professional code of conduct  E.g., ACM code [6]  Can cut both ways</p>
    <p>Compromise of algorithms  E.g., [8]  We focus on running systems</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
