<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interstate Voter Registration Database Matching: The OregonWashington 2008 Pilot Project</p>
    <p>R. Michael Alvarez California Institute of Technology Jeff Jonas IBM William E. Winkler Bureau of the Census Rebecca N. Wright Rutgers University</p>
    <p>EVT/WOTE 2009 Montreal, Canada August 1011, 2009</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Voter Registration</p>
    <p>Used in the United States (and many countries) to ensure that only eligible voters vote.</p>
    <p>Voter registration databases (VRDs) are a cornerstone of the electoral process.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Help America Vote Act (HAVA)</p>
    <p>Requires VRDs at the state level:</p>
    <p>Was previously done on the county level.  Initially passed in 2002, but deadline for compliance</p>
    <p>extended to 2006.</p>
    <p>Most states have now complied.</p>
    <p>each State  shall implement  a single, uniform, official, centralized, interactive computerized statewide voter registration list defined, maintained, and administered at the State level that contains the name and registration information of every legally registered voter in the State</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Role of VRD Matching</p>
    <p>Newly registered voters in a state must be added to the states VRD.  Later registrations in the same state (e.g., due to moves, change of</p>
    <p>party) should be matched to the existing record in that states VRD and that record updated.</p>
    <p>HAVA requires use of identifiers such as a state drivers license number or last four digits of the social security number.</p>
    <p>Difficulties when a voter moves states:  No HAVAmandated matching.  No access to other states drivers license numbers.  Voters rarely explicitly cancel their old registrations.</p>
    <p>A group of Midwest states have begun matching across states, since 2005. They use a complete match on full name and date of birth. Limited information is publicly available.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oregon/Washington Project</p>
    <p>Initial idea came from an informal conversation at a meeting of the National Academies Committee on State Voter Registration Databases:  Question: How hard is it to do interstate matching? Are complicated legal and technical arrangements necessary? Or could we just do it?</p>
    <p>Based on this, election officials in Oregon and Washington decided in August 2008 to move forward on a VRD matching project with help and oversight from us.</p>
    <p>It was deemed important from the start to be open and transparent about the process.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Oregon/ Washington Project</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Election Officials Involved</p>
    <p>Oregon: Dave Franks, Ericka Haas, John Lindback.</p>
    <p>Washington: Katie Blinn, Shane Hamlin, Nick Handy, Tim Likness, Paul Miller, David Motz, Randy Newton.</p>
    <p>County election officials also became involved.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Initial Matching</p>
    <p>Decided to use for matching only name and date ofbirth fields, information that is available in the publicly available voter registration files.</p>
    <p>In August 2008, the Oregon Secretary of States Office received Washingtons VRD records and carried out an initial matching.</p>
    <p>Only minor formatting of dateofbirth field was needed.</p>
    <p>On an iMac, the initial matching took 90 minutes of preprocessing (a file merge) and 50 minutes for the actual matching.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Matching Results</p>
    <p>Matching was carried out two ways: First, requiring an exact match of full name and birth date. Second with middle initial only.</p>
    <p>From these results, it was decided to use middle initial only.</p>
    <p>August 2008 Matching</p>
    <p>Oregon 2,053,444 records 280MB</p>
    <p>Washington 3,407,596 records 465MB</p>
    <p>Match on full name, DOB 3,482 matches found 0.064%</p>
    <p>Match on first, last, MI, DOB 8,292 matches found 0.152%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Top County Matches: Oregon County Matches Registrations Match %</p>
    <p>Multnomah 2,717 422,336 0.64</p>
    <p>Washington 1,058 266,523 0.40</p>
    <p>Clackamas 876 220,448 0.40</p>
    <p>Lane 537 204,976 0.26</p>
    <p>Marion 380 147,849 0.26</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Top County Matches: Oregon</p>
    <p>Umatilla 228 31,762 0.72</p>
    <p>Clatsop 133 21,503 0.62</p>
    <p>Some less populated border counties had a high percentage of matches:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Top County Matches: Washington</p>
    <p>County Matches Registrations Match %</p>
    <p>King 2,774 1,108,128 0.25</p>
    <p>Clark 1,765 216,508 0.82</p>
    <p>Pierce 534 411,103 0.13</p>
    <p>Snohomish 348 372,636 0.09</p>
    <p>Spokane 334 258,952 0.13</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Top County Matches: Washington</p>
    <p>Klickitat 155 121,171 1.27</p>
    <p>Pacific 88 13,052 0.67</p>
    <p>Again, some less populated counties near the border had a higher percentage of matches:</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Top Matching County Pairs</p>
    <p>Oregon County</p>
    <p>Washington County</p>
    <p>Matches</p>
    <p>Multnomah King 991</p>
    <p>Multnomah Clark 790</p>
    <p>Washington King 398</p>
    <p>Clackamas Clark 302</p>
    <p>Washington Clark 244</p>
    <p>Clackamas King 235</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Top Matching County Pairs</p>
    <p>Oregon County</p>
    <p>Washington County</p>
    <p>Matches</p>
    <p>Multnomah King 991</p>
    <p>Multnomah Clark 790</p>
    <p>Washington King 398</p>
    <p>Clackamas Clark 302</p>
    <p>Washington Clark 244</p>
    <p>Clackamas King 235</p>
    <p>Follow up for resolution of matches was done with matches between Clackamas, Multnomah, and Washington Counties in Oregon and Clark County in Washington.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pilot Project</p>
    <p>Reduced risk as compared to larger deployment.</p>
    <p>Finetuning of procedures before a larger deployment.</p>
    <p>Focus on counties with both geographic proximity and a large number of matches.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Resolution Process</p>
    <p>Attempt to confirm some of these potential matches as actual matches.</p>
    <p>No voter registrations were cancelled without a confirmation from the voter.</p>
    <p>Normal county/state cancellation procedures were followed.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Letters Sent</p>
    <p>For each potential match, a letter was sent to the less recent address, from that state.  For example:</p>
    <p>In this case, a letter would have been sent by Washington to the Washington address.</p>
    <p>Andrea R. Johnson 05/22/1975 Reg date: 8/15/2005</p>
    <p>Clark (WA)</p>
    <p>Andrea R. Johnson 05/22/1975 Reg date: 6/25/2007</p>
    <p>Multnomah (OR)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>96% of the letters were not returned as undeliverable.  59% of those delivered resulted in cancellations.  20 returned responses did not have enough information to process the cancellation.</p>
    <p>Two responses sent to Washington were for Oregon and were sent to Oregon for further processing.</p>
    <p>Oregon Washington</p>
    <p>Total Mailed 686 626</p>
    <p>Delivered 650 599</p>
    <p>Response received 391 362</p>
    <p>Response rate of delivered 60% 60%</p>
    <p>Cancellations 379 352</p>
    <p>Unresolved responses 12 8 (+2)</p>
    <p>Results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Possible Double Voting?</p>
    <p>The potential matches were examined by county officials to determine if possible double voting might have occurred.</p>
    <p>There were 12 matches that election official felt might have represented a double voter in both Washington and Oregon in prior elections, but it was too far in the past to determine.</p>
    <p>Of these 12:  Six returned a form requesting cancellation.  Another voted in Oregon but not in Washington in the 2008 election (even though the most recent registration date was in Washington).</p>
    <p>Additional cases are being investigated.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>False positives and negatives</p>
    <p>Study design does not provide good insight into false positive and false negative rates.</p>
    <p>Effectively assumes positives are false without action by voter.  Voters were not given an opportunity to identify and</p>
    <p>document false positives.</p>
    <p>Possibly other methods might be helpful:  manual follow up by a human (expensive, possibly intrusive).  Use of secondary data sources.</p>
    <p>Almost certainly false negatives resulted from the stringent matching criteria used.</p>
    <p>Particularly for people intentionally trying to register twice.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>False positives and negatives, contd.</p>
    <p>The literature is rich with more sophisticated matching algorithms that could be used.</p>
    <p>Inevitably, there will always be some false positives, so voter verification and notification is critical.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alternate Matching Procedures</p>
    <p>A number of alternatives can identify more potential matches, as well as disambiguate potential matches without requiring voter involvement:  Name roots, name transliteration, name order and</p>
    <p>transposition, typoaware name closeness testing (Soundex technique, JaroWinkler method).</p>
    <p>Date of birth closeness, transposition, and testing for use of current year.</p>
    <p>Use of additional fields if available (especially last four digits of social security number).</p>
    <p>Use of thirdparty data (public record or commercial).  Automated signature analysis.</p>
    <p>We did explore some fuzzy matching techniques, using partial name matches and different weights to different fields. (See paper for details.)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future Directions</p>
    <p>Oregon and Washington plan to expand the project to all counties in both states.</p>
    <p>Could be expanded to include other states.  Plans should be developed for:  follow up with undeliverable mailings.  procedures to mark records as explicit nonmatches with other records to avoid repeated contact to the same properly registered voters.</p>
    <p>more intensive followup of at least a sample of voters to better determine false positive and negative rates.</p>
    <p>Identifying and responding to any possible voter confusion or annoyance the project may cause.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>The OregonWashington project gave election officials in both states handson experience with VRD matching with a neighboring state.</p>
    <p>It resulted in some cleaning of the VRDs in the participating counties.</p>
    <p>Starting with a smallscale project and interacting with us on the project allowed the election officials to gain experience, build confidence, and evaluate risks and benefits before considering expansion to a larger scale matching project.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Interstate Voter Registration Database Matching: The OregonWashington 2008 Pilot Project</p>
    <p>R. Michael Alvarez California Institute of Technology Jeff Jonas IBM William E. Winkler Bureau of the Census Rebecca N. Wright Rutgers University</p>
    <p>EVT/WOTE 2009 Montreal, Canada August 1011, 2009</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
