<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Automating Voting Terminal Event Log Analysis</p>
    <p>Tigran Antonyan, Seda Davtyan, Sotirios Kentros, Aggelos Kiayias, Laurent Michel, Nicolas Nicolaou, Alexander Russell,</p>
    <p>Alexander A. Shvartsman</p>
    <p>Voting Technology Research (VoTeR) Center University of Connecticut</p>
    <p>http://voter.engr.uconn.edu</p>
    <p>Presented by Nicolas Nicolaou</p>
    <p>Work funded by the Connecticut Secretary of the State Office</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Auditing?</p>
    <p>[http://www.statehousereport.com]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation Electronic Voting Technologies</p>
    <p>Direct Recording Electronic (DRE) Optical Scan (OS) tabulator</p>
    <p>VVPAT  Voter Verifiable Paper Audit Trail Used in over 50% of counties in 2008</p>
    <p>Terminal Usage in Election Procedures Safe Storage</p>
    <p>No Interaction (?) Polling Place</p>
    <p>Officials (Before Election) Voters + Officials (During Elections) Officials (After Elections)</p>
    <p>Is the interaction with the terminal benign and does it follow the election procedures?</p>
    <p>Safe storage</p>
    <p>(No Interaction)</p>
    <p>Officials Interaction</p>
    <p>Voters+ Officials</p>
    <p>Interaction</p>
    <p>Officials Interaction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Question</p>
    <p>How can someone check the Actions and their Validity, performed on an E-Voting Terminal during an Election Process?</p>
    <p>Can we devise an Automated Procedure to perform this check?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Event Log</p>
    <p>What is an Event Log A list of Timestamped Entries</p>
    <p>Actions performed on the terminal, and Time/Date associated with any recorded action What actions are recorded?</p>
    <p>Where an Event Log is found In every E-voting Terminal with Logging Capabilities</p>
    <p>Usually Dedicated Memory Space</p>
    <p>Event Logs are useful for: Monitoring actions on e-voting terminals</p>
    <p>Before, During and After the elections Report environmental effects</p>
    <p>i.e. Power Failure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why Auditing the Event Log?</p>
    <p>Detect Expected Event Histories Compliant with electoral procedures</p>
    <p>Detect Irregular Event Histories Deviation form electoral procedures Malfunction of machines Reveal any malicious intent</p>
    <p>To Improve Electoral Procedures Minimize procedural uncertainties Increase the chance of detecting malicious actions</p>
    <p>Event Log Audit is Essential for any Election Process</p>
    <p>Every E-Voting System should provide an Event Log</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Need for Independent Log Audit E-Voting Systems with Logging Capabilities</p>
    <p>Print Event Log Provide Software to read and analyze the Event Log</p>
    <p>Usually Developed by the Vendor</p>
    <p>Issues Printing Module</p>
    <p>Module Defects Wrong Sequence of events</p>
    <p>Manual Parse of the printout Time Consuming and Inaccurate</p>
    <p>Vendor Software Reliability</p>
    <p>What are the analysis criteria? Conflict of Interest?</p>
    <p>Is it trustworthy? 8/11/2009 EVT/WOTE 09 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Approach Understand and Parse the Log</p>
    <p>Input: Event Log raw data and format Output: Exact Action sequence recorded in the Log</p>
    <p>Examine log sequences in light of predefined Action Rules Rules can be customized by</p>
    <p>Voting Terminal: Actions it can record Election Process: Sequence of Actions it contains</p>
    <p>Report whether Log Sequences satisfy the Rules</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study: AccuVote (AV-OS)</p>
    <p>Premiers Accu-Vote Optical Scan tabulator Provides inherent VVPB/VVPAT But is not perfect:</p>
    <p>Tampering with Memory cards [Hursti05], [EVT07] Firmware manipulations [SAC09] Reports by others and CA, CT, FL, AL,</p>
    <p>Provides Logging Capabilities Printing the Event Log for Auditing</p>
    <p>Print Module is Defective Suffers from other Deficiencies</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case Study: AccuVote OS (AV-OS) Physical Characteristics</p>
    <p>Firmware Version 1.96.6 Input Devices</p>
    <p>Yes/No Buttons Optical Scanner</p>
    <p>Output Devices Printer LCD</p>
    <p>Memory Card Contains Election Data Divided in 5 sections Contents of the MC obtained by build-in extraction module</p>
    <p>Header</p>
    <p>Event Log</p>
    <p>Election Data</p>
    <p>Bytecode (AccuBasic)</p>
    <p>Counters</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Applying Our Approach: AV-OS Logs</p>
    <p>Design and Implement a Procedure for AccuVote OS Event Log Audit</p>
    <p>Parse, analyze and evaluate event logs Automated Log Analyzer</p>
    <p>General for other E-Voting Systems</p>
    <p>Discover AV-OS event log Defects and Deficiencies</p>
    <p>Used in the Event Log Audit in the CT Presidential Elections of November 2008</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Log Audit Procedure at a Glance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AV-OS Event Log Entries</p>
    <p>Log entries: 512 Circular Buffer</p>
    <p>AV-OS Event Log has two types of entries:</p>
    <p>Action entries Date entries</p>
    <p>Action entries consist of Time of occurrence Action name</p>
    <p>Date entries only follow: INITIALIZED action SESSION START action</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Event Types Recorded by AV-OS</p>
    <p>Action Name Action Description AUDIT REPORT Appears when an Audit Report is printed. BAL COUNT END After the ender card is inserted in an election, this action appears. BAL COUNT START Appears when the first ballot is cast in an election. BAL TEST START Records the beginning of a test election. CLEAR COUNTERS Appears when the counters are set to zero. COUNT RESTARTED Appears if the machine is reset during an election, after at least one ballot is cast. DOWNLOAD END Recorded during the download of data is ended. DOWNLOAD START Recorded during the download of data is started. DUPLICATE CARD Appears when a card is duplicated. Present in the master card and the copy. ENDER CARD Records when an ender card is inserted, signifying the end of an election. INITIALIZED The 1st action in the Log. Date action appears when one programs the card. MEM CARD RESET A memory card reset returns a card in not set status, if it was set for election. OVERRIDE Records an override by a poll worker. Used for the insertion of overvoted ballots. POWER FAIL If the machine is unplugged or a power failure occurs, this action is recorded. PREP FOR ELECT Recorded when the card is set for election. SESSION START Date action. Appears every time you reset the machine. TOTALS REPORT Appears when a Totals Report is printed. UNVOTED BAL TST Appears when an unvoted ballot test is performed. UPLOAD END When an upload is completed, this action is recorded. UPLOAD ERROR Appears when an upload error is detected. UPLOAD STARTED Marks the beginning of an upload. VOTED BAL TEST Appears when an voted ballot test is performed. ZERO TOT REPORT Appears when a Zero Totals Report is printed.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Modeling AV-OS as a FSM</p>
    <p>States: Preserved after a restart</p>
    <p>Blank State Loaded Election State Set for Election with Zero Counters Set for Election with Non-Zero Counters Print Totals Report Election Closed</p>
    <p>Not preserved after restart Voted Ballot Test Unvoted Ballot Test Test Election with Zero Counters Test Election with Non-Zero Counters</p>
    <p>Transitions denoted by a triple &lt; U || A || L &gt; U: User action A: Ensuing Sequence of Machine Actions L: Sequence of Logged Events</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example  Set For Election State</p>
    <p>Set For Election / Zero Counters</p>
    <p>Restart Machine || Print Zero Totals Report || Session Start, Zero Totals Report</p>
    <p>Ender Card || End Election, Print Totals Report || Ender Card, Bal Count Start, Ballot Count End</p>
    <p>Cast Ballot || Cast Vote || Bal Count Start</p>
    <p>Set For Election / Non-Zero Counters</p>
    <p>Print Totals Report</p>
    <p>Override || Cast Vote || Override, Bal Count Start</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Specify the Election Process</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Time-Sensitivity of the Election Process</p>
    <p>Card Programming and Pre-Election testing by Provider 3-4 weeks before the elections</p>
    <p>Pre-Election Testing and Setting for Election in the Precincts 1-2 weeks before the elections</p>
    <p>Expected Sequence of timed events on Election Day: SESSION START-DATE, ZERO TOTALS REPORT</p>
    <p>Before the polls open BALLOT COUNT STARTS</p>
    <p>After the polls open Any number of OVERRIDE events</p>
    <p>While the polls are open ENDER CARD, BALLOT COUNT END, TOTALS REPORT</p>
    <p>When the polls close</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Automating the Event Log Analysis</p>
    <p>Define a set of Time Sensitive Rules Derived from FSM and Election Process Rules defined in an XML file</p>
    <p>Easily customizable</p>
    <p>Analysis Tool Input: Set of Rules and AV-OS Event Log Output: Return Expected or Irregular</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Examples of Flagged Events</p>
    <p>A. Expected Election Run B. Restart During the Election Process C. Power Failure and Restart During the Election Process</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AV-OS Event Log Defects/Deficiencies</p>
    <p>Printing an Overflowed Event Log</p>
    <p>Totals Report Recording Deficiency</p>
    <p>Date recording Deficiency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Printing Defect Demonstration Printing Enumerates Events</p>
    <p>Let an action event be denoted as &lt;s,n,t&gt;</p>
    <p>n: action name t: time it occurred</p>
    <p>Let assume #entries=522 Date Entries = 11 Action Entries = 511 10 first entries overwritten</p>
    <p>Print starts from 11th entry &lt;n11,t11&gt;</p>
    <p>Expected Behavior</p>
    <p>Erroneous Behavior</p>
    <p>Event Log Actions</p>
    <p>Seq Seq Buffer</p>
    <p>Expected Printout: &lt;11,n11,t11&gt;,&lt;12,n12,t12&gt;,,&lt;512,n512,t512&gt;,,&lt;522,n522,t522&gt; Erroneous Printout &lt;1,n11,t11&gt;,,&lt;502,n512,t512&gt;,,&lt;512,n522,t522&gt;,&lt;513,n11,t11&gt;,,&lt;522,n22,t22&gt;</p>
    <p>Duplicates</p>
    <p>Beginning of buffer</p>
    <p>First NotOverwritten Entry</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Totals Report Recording Deficiency Closing Election</p>
    <p>Ender Card Totals Report Another Copy?</p>
    <p>Totals Report Event Not logged unless NO is pressed Single appearance in the log event</p>
    <p>Effects Event is not logged</p>
    <p>Controversy on the validity of printed totals report Single appearance of the event affects</p>
    <p>Auditing Process Electoral Process</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Date recording Deficiency Deficiency</p>
    <p>Entries followed by date INITIALIZE SESSION START</p>
    <p>If &gt;24 hours elapse from the date recording without any actions occurring</p>
    <p>Cannot determine whether the next event occurred on the same date.</p>
    <p>Effects Modification of the results</p>
    <p>I.e., leave the terminal ON for a day, cast more votes and close it the next day at the expected time</p>
    <p>Did these events happen on</p>
    <p>Nov 04, 2008?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Log Audit Procedure in Practice Connecticut Nov 2008 Presidential Elections</p>
    <p>We collected Event Logs from 421 AV-OS memory cards</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings 314 out of 421 contain the expected sequences</p>
    <p>Our pre-election audit included only cards programmed until 10/26/2008</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Findings (Cont) 1 event log had ELECTION CLOSE event at 22:08.</p>
    <p>Findings Suggest No serious security problem or malicious intent Prescribed procedures are not followed uniformly</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary Proposed and Developed an Automated Procedure for Event Log Analysis</p>
    <p>Modeling AV-OS in terms of FSM Time-Sensitive Action Rules A tool to compare the actions in the logs over the defined rules</p>
    <p>Our tool may be adjusted and used with other systems</p>
    <p>Discovered some defects and deficiencies in AV-OS logging procedures</p>
    <p>Printing an Overflowed Event Log Totals Report Recording Deficiency Date recording Deficiency</p>
    <p>Used the automated tool in log analysis for CT Nov 2008 elections Findings suggest no malicious intent but reveal non-uniformity in the electoral procedures</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions Our Results Suggest</p>
    <p>Full scale event log analysis is feasible It provides information about</p>
    <p>Usage of the machines Deviation from procedures.</p>
    <p>Should included in any procedural audit Part of Post-Election Audit</p>
    <p>Event Logs should be a part of any EVoting Terminal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You.</p>
    <p>Questions?</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
