<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Development of Peer Instruction Questions for Cybersecurity</p>
    <p>Education William E. Johnson, Allison Luzader, Irfan Ahmed,</p>
    <p>Vassil Roussev, Golden G. Richard III Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>University of New Orleans</p>
    <p>Cynthia B. Lee Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>Stanford University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Peer Instruction  Introduced by Eric Mazur, a physicist at</p>
    <p>Harvard University  Tested and used in several scientific disciplines</p>
    <p>including o Physics, o Biology, and o Computer science</p>
    <p>Results of using peer instruction are promising o Improving student learning o Halving failure rates o Increasing student retention in their respective major</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Peer Instruction Methodology  Pre-class preparation by students</p>
    <p>o Reading material o Quiz</p>
    <p>In Class, a topic is covered as o A question is asked to students</p>
    <p>Conceptual  Multiple choice</p>
    <p>o Two to three minutes for reply o Group discussion of students o Students reply to the question again o Instructor may further discuss the answers</p>
    <p>Iterative</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Peer Instruction in CS  6% higher grades on final exams over</p>
    <p>traditional lecture style  61% reduction in failure rates</p>
    <p>o Theory of Computation, and Computer Architecture</p>
    <p>31% improvement in student retention  Instructors find peer instruction effective  Real learning occurs during discussions among</p>
    <p>students  Students recommend that more instructors</p>
    <p>should use peer instruction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges for Developing Questions</p>
    <p>Quiz vs. Peer Instruction Questions o Should be conceptual o Should facilitate peer discussion</p>
    <p>Plausible Incorrect Answers o Creating incorrect answers for peer instruction questions that</p>
    <p>seem plausible</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Question Development Methodology</p>
    <p>Concept Identification</p>
    <p>Concept Trigger</p>
    <p>Question Presentation</p>
    <p>Question Development</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Concept Trigger  Provoke a students thinking process  Set the desired direction of peer discussion  Examples: (Beatty et al. [1])</p>
    <p>o Deliberate ambiguity o Trolling for misconceptions o Omit necessary information o Identify a set or subset o Compare and contrast o Trap unjustified assumptions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Question Presentation  Putting concept and concept trigger together</p>
    <p>o Better presentation o Easier understanding</p>
    <p>Examples: o Scenario o Example o Diagram o Definitional o Feature</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Question # 1 An attacker deletes files on a system, denying access to system users. Which element of CIA triad is violated?</p>
    <p>a) Confidentiality b) Integrity c) Availability d) None/Other/More than one of the above</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deconstruction # 1  Concept trigger</p>
    <p>o None of the above o Identify a set or subset o Multiple defensible answers</p>
    <p>Question Presentation o Example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Question # 2 Estimate the fraction of disk blocks affected by formatting a hard disk:</p>
    <p>a) 100% b) 65% c) 20% d) Less than 5%</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Formatting Flash Drive</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deconstruction # 2  Concept Trigger</p>
    <p>o Omit necessary information o Trap unjustified assumptions o Trolling for misconceptions</p>
    <p>Question Presentation o Feature</p>
    <p>Understanding disk formatting to guess correct percentage</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Question # 3</p>
    <p>After executing these instructions while single stepping inside a debugger on an 80486 processor, what is the value of the 16-bit word at location Loc_10129+5?</p>
    <p>a) 168h, b) 152h c) 4D4Ch d) Value is unknown e) None of the above 14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deconstruction # 3  Concept Trigger</p>
    <p>o None of the above</p>
    <p>Question Presentation o Example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Question # 4 You obtain a leaked database of unsalted SHA1 password hashes. What would be the most effective way to obtain as many passwords as possible in a short amount of time?</p>
    <p>a) Brute force b) rainbow tables c) dictionary attack with a large wordlist d) passing the hash e) birthday attack</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deconstruction # 4  Concept Trigger</p>
    <p>o Interpret representations o Strategize only</p>
    <p>Question Presentation o Scenario</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis of Questions  172 questions for two cybersecurity courses</p>
    <p>o Introduction to Computer Security (93 questions) o Network Penetration Testing (79 questions)</p>
    <p>Goal of Analysis is to identify concept triggers and presentation types in the questions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation types</p>
    <p>EX A M PL E&quot;</p>
    <p>SC EN</p>
    <p>A RI O &quot;</p>
    <p>D EF IN IT IO N A L&quot;</p>
    <p>FE A TU</p>
    <p>RE &quot;</p>
    <p>D IA G RA</p>
    <p>M &quot;</p>
    <p>N o. $o f$P</p>
    <p>I$Q ue</p>
    <p>s, on</p>
    <p>s$ (%</p>
    <p>)$</p>
    <p>Presenta,on$Types$of$Ques,ons$</p>
    <p>IntroducDon&quot;to&quot;Computer&quot;Security&quot; Network&quot;PenetraDon&quot;TesDng&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation-types &amp; Topics</p>
    <p>EX A M PL E&quot;</p>
    <p>SC EN</p>
    <p>A RI O &quot;</p>
    <p>D EF IN IT IO N A L&quot;</p>
    <p>FE A TU</p>
    <p>RE &quot;</p>
    <p>D IA G RA</p>
    <p>M &quot;</p>
    <p>N o. $o f$P</p>
    <p>I$Q ue</p>
    <p>s, on</p>
    <p>s$ (%</p>
    <p>)$</p>
    <p>Presenta,on$Types$of$Ques,ons$</p>
    <p>Overview&quot; Cryptographic&quot;Tools&quot; User&quot;AuthenNcaNon&quot; Access&quot;Control&quot; Malicious&quot;SoOware&quot; Denial&quot;of&quot;Service&quot;AQacks&quot; Intrusion&quot;DetecNon&quot;System&quot; Firewall&quot; Buffer&quot;Overflow&quot; SoOware&quot;Security&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Concept Trigger - Example</p>
    <p>R E M O V E &quot;N</p>
    <p>O N E S S E N T IA LS &quot;</p>
    <p>C O M P A R E &quot;A N D &quot;C</p>
    <p>O N T R A S T &quot;</p>
    <p>E X T E N D &quot;T H E &quot;C</p>
    <p>O N T E X T &quot;</p>
    <p>R E U S E &quot;F A M IL IA R &quot;Q</p>
    <p>U E S T IO</p>
    <p>N &quot;</p>
    <p>O O P S ?G</p>
    <p>O ?B</p>
    <p>A C K &quot;</p>
    <p>IN T E R P R E T &quot;R</p>
    <p>E P R E S E N T A T IO</p>
    <p>N S &quot;</p>
    <p>ID E N T IF Y &quot;A &quot;S E T &quot;O</p>
    <p>R &quot;S U B S E T &quot;</p>
    <p>R A N K &quot;V A R IA N T S &quot;</p>
    <p>R E V E A L&quot; A &quot;B E T T E R &quot;W</p>
    <p>A Y &quot;</p>
    <p>ST R A T E G IZ E &quot;O</p>
    <p>N LY &quot;</p>
    <p>IN C LU</p>
    <p>D E &quot;E X T R A N E O U S &quot;</p>
    <p>O M IT &quot;N</p>
    <p>E C E S S A R Y &quot;I N F O &quot;</p>
    <p>A N S W E R &quot;C H O IC E S &quot;R E V E A L&quot; LI K E LY &quot;</p>
    <p>U S E &quot;&quot; N O N E &quot;O</p>
    <p>F &quot;T H E &quot;A B O V E &quot;&quot;</p>
    <p>Q U A LI T A T IV E &quot;Q</p>
    <p>U E S T IO</p>
    <p>N S &quot;</p>
    <p>A N A LY S IS &quot;A N D &quot;R E A S O N IN G &quot;</p>
    <p>M U LT IP LE &quot;D E F E N S IB LE &quot;A N S W E R S &quot;</p>
    <p>R E Q U IR E &quot;U</p>
    <p>N S T A T E D &quot;</p>
    <p>T R A P &quot;U</p>
    <p>N JU</p>
    <p>S T IF IE D &quot;A S S U M P T IO</p>
    <p>N S &quot;</p>
    <p>D E LI B E R A T E &quot;A M B IG U IT Y &quot;</p>
    <p>T R O LL IN G &quot;F O R &quot;M</p>
    <p>IS C O N C E P T IO</p>
    <p>N S &quot;</p>
    <p>N o. $o f$P</p>
    <p>I$Q ue</p>
    <p>s, on</p>
    <p>s$ (%</p>
    <p>)$</p>
    <p>Concept$Triggers$</p>
    <p>Ques,on$Presenta,on$:$&quot;Example&quot;$</p>
    <p>IntroducOon&quot;to&quot;Computer&quot;Security&quot; Network&quot;PenetraOon&quot;TesOng&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Concept Trigger - Scenario</p>
    <p>R E M O V E &quot;N</p>
    <p>O N E S S E N T IA LS &quot;</p>
    <p>C O M P A R E &quot;A N D &quot;C</p>
    <p>O N T R A S T &quot;</p>
    <p>E X T E N D &quot;T H E &quot;C</p>
    <p>O N T E X T &quot;</p>
    <p>R E U S E &quot;F A M IL IA R &quot;Q</p>
    <p>U E S T IO</p>
    <p>N &quot;</p>
    <p>O O P S ?G</p>
    <p>O ?B</p>
    <p>A C K &quot;</p>
    <p>IN T E R P R E T &quot;R</p>
    <p>E P R E S E N T A T IO</p>
    <p>N S &quot;</p>
    <p>ID E N T IF Y &quot;A &quot;S E T &quot;O</p>
    <p>R &quot;S U B S E T &quot;</p>
    <p>R A N K &quot;V A R IA N T S &quot;</p>
    <p>R E V E A L&quot; A &quot;B E T T E R &quot;W</p>
    <p>A Y &quot;</p>
    <p>ST R A T E G IZ E &quot;O</p>
    <p>N LY &quot;</p>
    <p>IN C LU</p>
    <p>D E &quot;E X T R A N E O U S &quot;</p>
    <p>O M IT &quot;N</p>
    <p>E C E S S A R Y &quot;I N F O &quot;</p>
    <p>A N S W E R &quot;C H O IC E S &quot;R E V E A L&quot; LI K E LY &quot;</p>
    <p>U S E &quot;&quot; N O N E &quot;O</p>
    <p>F &quot;T H E &quot;A B O V E &quot;&quot;</p>
    <p>Q U A LI T A T IV E &quot;Q</p>
    <p>U E S T IO</p>
    <p>N S &quot;</p>
    <p>A N A LY S IS &quot;A N D &quot;R E A S O N IN G &quot;</p>
    <p>M U LT IP LE &quot;D E F E N S IB LE &quot;A N S W E R S &quot;</p>
    <p>R E Q U IR E &quot;U</p>
    <p>N S T A T E D &quot;</p>
    <p>T R A P &quot;U</p>
    <p>N JU</p>
    <p>S T IF IE D &quot;A S S U M P T IO</p>
    <p>N S &quot;</p>
    <p>D E LI B E R A T E &quot;A M B IG U IT Y &quot;</p>
    <p>T R O LL IN G &quot;F O R &quot;M</p>
    <p>IS C O N C E P T IO</p>
    <p>N S &quot;</p>
    <p>N o. $o f$P</p>
    <p>I$Q ue</p>
    <p>s, on</p>
    <p>s$ (%</p>
    <p>)$</p>
    <p>Concept$Triggers$</p>
    <p>Ques,on$Presenta,on$:$&quot;Scenario&quot;$</p>
    <p>IntroducOon&quot;to&quot;Computer&quot;Security&quot; Network&quot;PenetraOon&quot;TesOng&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  Question development methodology allows</p>
    <p>instructors to o systematically create questions, and o smoothly transition from lecture style format to peer instruction</p>
    <p>Analysis of question set o example and scenario based questions are often used o The use of concept triggers may vary depending on the course</p>
    <p>content</p>
    <p>Contents will be available at http://www.peerinstruction4cs.org/</p>
    <p>As part of future, evaluate efficacy of peer instruction questions in cybersecurity courses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions ??</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
