<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Milo Bartk</p>
    <p>Masaryk University, Brno</p>
    <p>August 9, 2016</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ph.D. graduate in flow-based intrusion detection.</p>
    <p>Founder and head of a university CSIRT in the Czech Republic.</p>
    <p>Researcher with KYPO  academic cloud-based cyber range.</p>
    <p>Coordinator and designer of hands-on training at KYPO platform, e. g. Czech national cyber defence exercise.</p>
    <p>Who am I?</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>KYPO game  Generic module of KYPO cyber range for running CtF games</p>
    <p>Prototype game</p>
    <p>Lessons learned</p>
    <p>Extensions of KYPO game</p>
    <p>Research questions</p>
    <p>User study  setup and results</p>
    <p>Conclusion and future work</p>
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>KYPO cyber range</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>One educational use case of KYPO cyber range, implemented as a portlet.</p>
    <p>Framework for creating and running attack-only capture-the-flag games.</p>
    <p>Each game is split to several levels, players search for correct answer (flag).</p>
    <p>Each level offers hints that can be displayed in exchange for penalty points.</p>
    <p>KYPO game - design</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Prototype game for teaching penetration testing.</p>
    <p>Four levels with the ultimate objective of NTP DoS amplification attack.</p>
    <p>Each player has own sandbox with a machine under control.</p>
    <p>KYPO game  prototype</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
    <p>Sandbox topology</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lessons learned:</p>
    <p>Difficulty of levels is not balanced.</p>
    <p>Learners are hesitant whether the hints will help them.</p>
    <p>Game-related information provided outside the platform are inconvenient.</p>
    <p>Extensions:</p>
    <p>Improved hint system  Hints about hints available</p>
    <p>what tool to use, how to use the tool,</p>
    <p>Players can now choose hints in arbitrary order.</p>
    <p>Embedded level solutions  Step-by-step tutorial for each level.</p>
    <p>KYPO game  extensions I</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lesson learned:</p>
    <p>Teacher has no information about the learners performance and progress in the ongoing event.</p>
    <p>Extension:</p>
    <p>Logging the learners actions  Generic approach independent on specific game and its</p>
    <p>sandbox (hosts, network connections).</p>
    <p>Captures only the interaction of the player and KYPO portal.</p>
    <p>Does not capture any events or states from sandbox.</p>
    <p>KYPO game  extensions II</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
    <p>Aug 9, 08:00, Participant_1:</p>
    <p>Game started</p>
    <p>Aug 9, 08:00, Participant_1:</p>
    <p>Level 1 entered</p>
    <p>Aug 9, 08:05, Participant_1:</p>
    <p>Incorrect flag submitted</p>
    <p>Aug 9, 08:07, Participant_1:</p>
    <p>Hint 1 taken</p>
    <p>Aug 9, 08:15, Participant_1:</p>
    <p>Level 1 completed (correct flag)</p>
    <p>Aug 9, 08:20, Participant_1:</p>
    <p>Level 2 entered</p>
    <p>...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How do they contribute to completion of the level?</p>
    <p>What do game logs tell about the game and progress of the players?</p>
    <p>Research questions</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Experiment with a new game using the new features  More levels</p>
    <p>Used improved hint system</p>
    <p>Level solutions available.</p>
    <p>21 participants in total - a diverse mix of players  Various level of experience and work positions (students, IT staff, researchers, experts).</p>
    <p>Various European nations.</p>
    <p>Various experience with hands-on training in cyber security.</p>
    <p>Evaluation of extensions  setup I</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Self-assessment questionnaires for players  before the game,</p>
    <p>after each level,</p>
    <p>after the game.</p>
    <p>How was the level difficult?</p>
    <p>Were the hints helpful?</p>
    <p>Was the time limit sufficient?</p>
    <p>What have you learned?</p>
    <p>Would you like to play another game?</p>
    <p>Game events of all players logged  a complement to self-assessment data.</p>
    <p>Evaluation of extensions  setup II</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>New hint system used in 28 % of cases (arbitrary order of hints = green boxes).</p>
    <p>77 % of all levels where learners opted for a hint(s) were then accomplished.</p>
    <p>Mismatch of game logs and self-assessment (double checked).</p>
    <p>Evaluation of extensions  hints</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>If the hints do still not help, and participants cannot proceed further, they can access the solution of the level.</p>
    <p>Contribution of solutions to accomplishment of the level was weaker than expected  Solution displayed and then the correct flag submitted  60 % (17x)</p>
    <p>Solution displayed and then the level skipped  40 % (11x)</p>
    <p>Some participants might be frustrated and just wanted to enter the next level(s).</p>
    <p>Evaluation of extensions  level solutions</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of new features  game logs</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
    <p>Time limit</p>
    <p>Median</p>
    <p>Max</p>
    <p>Min</p>
    <p>Level</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation of new features  game logs</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
    <p>Level difficulty 1.6 2.7 3.6 4.2 3.8 4.5 1  easy, 5  very hard</p>
    <p>Time limit</p>
    <p>Median</p>
    <p>Max</p>
    <p>Min</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Logging the games events provide useful data for analysis of game sessions to make them more engaging and fun.</p>
    <p>It is also useful for teachers to monitor ongoing session.</p>
    <p>Learners did use redesigned hint system and recommended solutions.  Evidence found in collected game events and the supplemental user survey.</p>
    <p>Learners answers neither confirm nor disprove the benefit of the hints and solutions used.</p>
    <p>Other games events matched the learners assessment (level difficulty and duration).</p>
    <p>Future work: Do user surveys represent reliable tools for designing and evaluating hands-on training?</p>
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal, Masaryk University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>QUESTIONS?</p>
    <p>THANKS FOR YOUR ATTENTION!</p>
    <p>Jan Vykopal</p>
    <p>vykopal@ics.muni.cz</p>
    <p>www.kypo.cz</p>
    <p>@csirtmu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
