<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Self-efficacy in Cybersecurity Tasks: Relationships with Cybersecurity Competition and Work-Related Outcomes</p>
    <p>Presenter: Beth Strickland, PhD Student, iSchool @ Illinois Co-authors: Masooda Bashir,Colin Wee, &amp; Nasir Memon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Funding &amp; Support</p>
    <p>Project made possible by NSF funding (Early-Concept Grants for Exploratory Research)</p>
    <p>Grant supported 3-years of research</p>
    <p>Phase I: Exploratory study of cybersecurity competition participants</p>
    <p>Phase II: More focused study based on findings from Phase I</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Rationale</p>
    <p>Employee shortages in the cybersecurity field</p>
    <p>Congress passed the Cybersecurity Workforce Assessment Act to address these shortages</p>
    <p>What role might cybersecurity competitions play in these recruitment efforts?</p>
    <p>Academics: evaluate cybersecurity competitions and study the participants</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction What are Cybersecurity Competitions?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Introduction  Challenge participants to attack/defend networks/systems</p>
    <p>Educational tool to raise awareness about online threats and practice computer security skills through live exercises</p>
    <p>Recruitment platform to share cybersecurity career information</p>
    <p>Often sponsored by the US Govt. and hosted by schools</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Exploratory study (2013) to obtain a psychological profile of cybersecurity competition participants</p>
    <p>Participants of NYUs Cybersecurity Awareness Week Capture the Flag (CSAW)</p>
    <p>Found: openness to exp., interest in investigative tasks, rational decision-making styles, &amp; self-efficacy</p>
    <p>Self-efficacy was strongest predictor of whether or not participants entered cybersecurity career</p>
    <p>Phase I Research</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phase II Research</p>
    <p>Phase II: focused follow-up on Phase I</p>
    <p>RQ1: Why participants join cybersecurity competitions</p>
    <p>RQ2: The role of self-efficacy in competition and career related outcomes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phase II Research  Contacted same population of participants  survey</p>
    <p>588 past participants of Cybersecurity Awareness Week - Capture the Flag (CSAW)</p>
    <p>- One of the longest running, most established capture-the-flag competitions - Hosted annually by NYU - Access to 10 years worth of participants - Willing to release mailing lists to researchers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sample</p>
    <p>195 respondents (184M / 11F) passed the quality control questions</p>
    <p>Average age 24.28</p>
    <p>58.9% White, 30.2% Asian</p>
    <p>88 were employed in cybersecurity jobs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RQ1: Survey Question &amp; Result</p>
    <p>Top Reasons:</p>
    <p>Problem solving</p>
    <p>Skill mastery</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RQ1: Further Analysis</p>
    <p>Question: Does the reason for entering differ between firsttime and repeat participation?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RQ2: Self-Efficacy &amp; Outcomes</p>
    <p>How does self-efficacy relate to competition effectiveness and career intent?</p>
    <p>Administered established psychological measures - Rosenberg (1965) General Self-Efficacy Scale - Chen (2001) Self-Esteem Scale</p>
    <p>Also developed new measure of self-efficacy in cybersecurity-specific tasks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RQ2: Measures</p>
    <p>Cybersecurity Self-efficacy: Belief in own ability to meet demands in cybersecurity tasks  20-item measure pre-tested in university students</p>
    <p>Two classes of dependent measures: organizational outcomes; competition-related outcomes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RQ2: Results</p>
    <p>M SD Self Esteem General Self</p>
    <p>Efficacy</p>
    <p>CybersecuritySpecific Efficacy</p>
    <p>Job Satisfaction 0.72 0.4 0.29* 0.33* 0.32*</p>
    <p>Perceived Fit 3.77 0.65 0.18 0.37* 0.37*</p>
    <p>Organizational Outcomes (N = 88): Who is more likely to be satisfied with their jobs?</p>
    <p>- Individuals who are generally confident - Also those confident at cybersecurity tasks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RQ2: Results</p>
    <p>Competition-related Outcomes:</p>
    <p>Cybersecurity-specific self-efficacy was better at predicting performance within the competition</p>
    <p>Participants w/high self-esteem &amp; self-efficacy were likely to learn more &amp; be satisfied w/their performance</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>RQ2: Results Competition-related Outcomes:</p>
    <p>Participants w/higher general self-efficacy &amp; selfesteem report competition was effective at recruitment</p>
    <p>Same group thought competition increased the appeal of cybersecurity to the public</p>
    <p>No relationship found with career influence - possibly due to way question was phrased</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Limitations</p>
    <p>Sample: only CSAW capture-the-flag participants  Should study participants engaged in other competition formats</p>
    <p>Self-report; retrospective data over 10 years  Conduct future longitudinal studies on current CSAW participants</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>People with higher confidence in performing cybersecurity tasks most likely to do well and be satisfied with their competition performance</p>
    <p>No significant relationship found between competition score (low/high) and view competition is effective</p>
    <p>Explore relationships between self-efficacy &amp; job outcomes - highlight value of cybersecurity self-efficacy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  Cybersecurity career recruiters may want to target first-time participants</p>
    <p>These participants are most motivated about cybersecurity careers</p>
    <p>Need to encourage participants they are capable of handling difficult cybersecurity challenges</p>
    <p>Encouragement may enhance the recruitment rate of new cybersecurity employees from competitions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Send questions to: Masooda Bashir: mnb@illinois.edu</p>
    <p>Colin Wee: jwee2@Illinois.edu</p>
    <p>Thank You! Questions?</p>
    <p>Selected Related Research: Bashir, M., Lambert, A., Wee, J.M.C., &amp; Guo, B. (2015, 11 August). An examination of the vocational and psychological characteristics of cybersecurity competition participants. Proceedings of the USENIX Summit on Gaming, Games and Gamification in Security Education, Washington, D.C.</p>
    <p>Bashir, M., Lambert, A.D., Wee, J.M.C., Guo, B., &amp; Memon, N. (2015, 15-17 June). Exploring the vocational interests of cybersecurity competition participants. Colloquium for Information Security Education (CISSE), Las Vegas, NV.</p>
    <p>Lambert, A.D., Bashir, M., Guo, B., Memon, N., &amp; Halevi, T. (2015, May 18-20). Are competitions effective in increasing the cybersecurity workforce? Proceedings of IEEE Security &amp; Privacy, San Jose, CA.</p>
    <p>Bashir, M. &amp; Jeon, G. (2014, 11-12 Apr). An examination of psychological factors underlying the gender gap in cybersecurity. Proceedings of the 2014 Women in Cyber Security Conference (WiCyS), Nashville, TN.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
