<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Finding the Balance Between Guidance and Independence</p>
    <p>Richard Weiss The Evergreen State College</p>
    <p>Franklyn Turbak Wellesley College</p>
    <p>Jens Mache, Erik Nilsen Lewis &amp; Clark College</p>
    <p>Michael E. Locasto SRI International</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Challenge of Cybersecurity Education</p>
    <p>Our goaldevelop exercises that teach analysis skills/abilities and the security mindset.</p>
    <p>Having good exercises is half of the battle  The other half is providing the</p>
    <p>context/guidance.  Clear learning goals are important  Prerequisite background: know the audience  Formative assessment  any tool that helps to</p>
    <p>give students timely and helpful feedback (guidance)</p>
    <p>Summative assessment  need to verify that they met the learning goals.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Formative Assessment: Challenges</p>
    <p>Having the right tools: Complete/Accurate  Large class size  No TA support  Limited time  * Equitable distribution of attention *</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>An example from network security: suppose these were the goals</p>
    <p>Analyze a large address space  Explain how ping works and use it  Use efficient options in nmap  Understand CIDR addresses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is wrong with this picture? 1. Click Start in the Search Programs box, type cmd and press ENTER. 2. At the command line type nmap and press ENTER. a. observe the output b. What version of nmap are you running? 3. At the command line type nmap -sn 192.168.100.0/24 and press ENTER a. observe the output b. how many hosts did nmap find?</p>
    <p>...  Analyze a large address space  Explain how ping works and use it  Use efficient options in nmap  Understand CIDR addresses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Rubrics</p>
    <p>Students can not do the exercise without meeting the goals.</p>
    <p>If a student is stuck, you can give a hint without giving the answer.</p>
    <p>The exercise structure does not preclude reasonable ways to meet the learning goals.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Strace: essential facts</p>
    <p>Students may not know about Linux: syscalls, child processes, file permissions, etc</p>
    <p>The output can be voluminous.</p>
    <p>The student must be able to recognize what is important and what is not</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scaffolding of strace</p>
    <p>Start with the empty program, then strace -o empty1 ./empty strace -o empty2 ./empty</p>
    <p>diff empty1 empty  copy a file.  &gt; mystery foo abc</p>
    <p>writes abc to file foo  trace a known script that forks a process  Use the -e option for strace to filter output</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trojan cat</p>
    <p>&gt;cat secret</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Dynamic Analysis Example: strace</p>
    <p>Goals: students will be able to analyze a process to discover if it is reading/writing files that it should not.</p>
    <p>Trojan cat writes the contents of the file to a new file and appends all of the new filenames to a separate file.</p>
    <p>The permissions are set, so that they cannot list the directory, but they can read the files.</p>
    <p>The task is to read other students' files.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How do we provide formative assessment?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Tool for assessing student work bash history visualization</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Possible Uses for this Information</p>
    <p>Instructor can see visually if student is on the right track</p>
    <p>Student can use it after the exercise to reflect on what they did/did not do.</p>
    <p>Instructor can use it in a debrief after the exercise.</p>
    <p>Note: it gives more information than whether the student was successful or not</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Students working on EDURange</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EDURange Project</p>
    <p>What it is: a cloud-based (AWS) framework for designing and instantiating interactive cybersecurity exercises</p>
    <p>What it aims to teach: ethical hacking and cybersecurity analysis skills Variety of scenarios: networking, reverse engineering, etc</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>We need engaging exercises with clear learning goals and tools for timely, precise feedback.</p>
    <p>Backwards design can help by starting with the learning goals</p>
    <p>Identifying rubrics and level of guidance can help with design.</p>
    <p>Some parts of our strace exercise are too prescriptive  they do not conform to our rubrics</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future work</p>
    <p>How to teach students how to choose the right tools for a problem, including ones we haven't taught them.</p>
    <p>Shifting from tool-based exercises to problembased exercises.</p>
    <p>Improving our tools to give better feedback to students and instructors.</p>
    <p>Collaboration with DETER, and we want your help.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our website</p>
    <p>For general information: http://www.edurange.org to sign up cloud.edurange.org</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
