<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>2008 Andreas Haeberlen, MPI-SWS 1</p>
    <p>SatelliteLab: Adding Heterogeneity to Planetary-Scale Network Testbeds</p>
    <p>Andreas Haeberlen</p>
    <p>MPI-SWS / Rice University</p>
    <p>Marcel Dischinger MPI-SWS</p>
    <p>Ivan Beschastnikh University of Washington</p>
    <p>Krishna P. Gummadi</p>
    <p>MPI-SWS</p>
    <p>Stefan Saroiu University of Toronto</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why are testbeds so popular?</p>
    <p>Testbeds provide wide-area network paths  Realistic network paths are crucial for evaluating</p>
    <p>the performance of distributed systems</p>
    <p>Your clusterTestbeds</p>
    <p>PLANETLAB</p>
    <p>vs.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Access networks and heterogeneity</p>
    <p>Internet bottlenecks are in access networks  Studies show that most queueing, loss etc. happens there</p>
    <p>Access networks have high heterogeneity  Cable, DSL, GPRS, UMTS, EVDO, 802.11, Satellite, Dial-up...</p>
    <p>Not represented in existing testbeds</p>
    <p>Internet Backbone</p>
    <p>Access networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Growing the testbed is not enough</p>
    <p>Can we simply add more nodes?  More nodes from acad. networks do not improve heterogeneity  Nodes from the commercial Internet are much more effective</p>
    <p>Need nodes from the commercial Internet</p>
    <p>I n te</p>
    <p>rA</p>
    <p>S l in</p>
    <p>k s</p>
    <p>c o v e re</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>Node index</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A new testbed architecture</p>
    <p>Idea: Separate computation and communication  Tier 1: Powerful, well-connected nodes (from existing testbed)</p>
    <p>Contribute computation power, memory, storage...  Tier 2: Light-weight nodes</p>
    <p>Contribute &quot;just their access-network links&quot;</p>
    <p>Tier 1</p>
    <p>Tier 2</p>
    <p>&quot;Planets&quot;</p>
    <p>&quot;Satellites&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation  SatelliteLab  Evaluation  Applications  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Delegation</p>
    <p>Delegate code execution to the planets  Problem: Changes the network path  Misses the access links</p>
    <p>Solution: Send traffic through the satellites</p>
    <p>Planet A Planet B</p>
    <p>Satellite A Satellite B</p>
    <p>Application</p>
    <p>Network path</p>
    <p>Network path</p>
    <p>Adds some latency</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Detour routing</p>
    <p>Two challenges remain:  Satellites are sending traffic that may trigger complaints  NATs and firewalls may prevent connectivity</p>
    <p>Solution: Detour traffic through the planets</p>
    <p>Planet A Planet B</p>
    <p>Satellite A Satellite B</p>
    <p>Firewall</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The SatelliteLab detour path</p>
    <p>To send a packet from planet A to planet B: 1. A intercepts the data packet 2. A exchanges a probe packet with its satellite 3. A sends the data packet to B 4. B exchanges a probe packet with its satellite 5. B delivers the data packet</p>
    <p>Planet A Planet B</p>
    <p>Satellite A Satellite B</p>
    <p>Actual path</p>
    <p>&quot;Ideal&quot; path</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges revisited</p>
    <p>planet  No hassle: Sufficient to install the satellite helper once  No CPU slowdown: Planets do all the heavy lifting  No security risk: Satellite is just 118 lines of Java code</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation  SatelliteLab  Evaluation  Applications  Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation</p>
    <p>Is it feasible to recruit edge nodes?  Is the availability sufficient for</p>
    <p>experiments?  Can satellites find a nearby planet?  Does SatelliteLab preserve...</p>
    <p>the path capacity?  the queueing delay?  the jitter?  the packet loss rates?</p>
    <p>Yes.</p>
    <p>Yes. Yes.</p>
    <p>Yes.</p>
    <p>Yes. Yes.</p>
    <p>Yes.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Is it feasible to recruit edge nodes?</p>
    <p>Built a prototype testbed  Asked friends and family to install satellite software</p>
    <p>Increased heterogeneity with very little effort  Ten U.S. states, six countries, 15 commercial ISPs  Technologies: Cable, DSL, Ethernet, Wi-Fi, ISDN, BT, EVDO</p>
    <p>Canada Canada Canada Canada Canada Germany Germany Germany Germany Germany Germany Germany Germany Hungary Portugal UK</p>
    <p>Cable DSL Uni+Wi-Fi Uni+Wi-Fi Cable+Wi-Fi DSL+Wi-Fi Cable DSL DSL+Wi-Fi Cable+Wi-Fi DSL DSL+Wi-Fi ISDN+BT DSL Cable DSL</p>
    <p>no no no no yes yes no yes yes yes yes yes no yes no no</p>
    <p>Desktop Desktop Laptop PDA Laptop Desktop Desktop Desktop Laptop Laptop Desktop Desktop Laptop Laptop Laptop Laptop</p>
    <p>no no yes yes no no no no yes yes no no no yes no yes</p>
    <p>CA, USA CA ,USA CO, USA IL, USA LA, USA MA, USA MD, USA MD, USA NJ, USA NJ, USA TX, USA WA, USA WA, USA WA, USA WA, USA WA, USA</p>
    <p>DSL+Wi-Fi EVDO Cable+Wi-Fi Cable DSL Cable+Wi-Fi Uni Cable+Wi-Fi DSL+Wi-Fi Cable+Wi-Fi Cable+Wi-Fi Cable Cable Cable+Wi-Fi Cable+Wi-Fi DSL</p>
    <p>yes no yes yes yes no no yes yes yes yes yes yes yes yes yes</p>
    <p>Laptop Laptop Laptop Desktop Desktop Laptop Desktop Laptop Laptop Laptop Desktop Desktop Desktop Desktop Laptop Desktop</p>
    <p>no no no no no yes no yes no no no no no no yes no</p>
    <p># Location Access link NAT Type Mob. # Location Access link NAT Type Mob.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SatelliteLab preserves path capacity</p>
    <p>Direct path vs. interplanetary path  Large difference because bottlenecks are in access networks</p>
    <p>Detour routing preserves the path capacity</p>
    <p>Direct path</p>
    <p>SatelliteLab path PA PB</p>
    <p>SA SB</p>
    <p>Interplanetary path</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SatelliteLab preserves queueing delay</p>
    <p>Same comparison for queueing delay  Almost all the queueing is in the access networks</p>
    <p>Detour routing preserves the queueing delay</p>
    <p>Interplanetary path PA PB</p>
    <p>SA SB Direct path</p>
    <p>SatelliteLab path</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Motivation  SatelliteLab  Evaluation  Applications</p>
    <p>Network coordinate system  Overlay multicast  TCP throughput over cellular links</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Application: Network coordinates</p>
    <p>Need to measure RTT between nodes  Surprising observation (in previous work):</p>
    <p>Discarding outliers improves network coordinates on PlanetLab [NSDI'06] but not when deployed with Azureus BitTorrent client [NSDI'07]</p>
    <p>Reason: Huge RTT variance</p>
    <p>PlanetLab did not predict this observation  Could SatelliteLab have predicted it?</p>
    <p>Figures taken from [NSDI'07]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Application: Network coordinates  We ran an experiment with several Azureus</p>
    <p>nodes on SatelliteLab  We observed same effect as in [NSDI'07]</p>
    <p>SatelliteLab could have predicted this outcome!</p>
    <p>Can we also use SatelliteLab to explain it?  Yes - Measurements revealed extremely long queues on</p>
    <p>the broadband access links  Azureus downloads fill up the queues  high RTT variance!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary  Existing testbeds lack heterogeneity  SatelliteLab: A new testbed architecture</p>
    <p>for heterogeneous testbeds  Introduces satellites, a new class of light-weight nodes  Enables experimenters to improve heterogenity by</p>
    <p>recruiting end nodes as satellites  Builds on existing testbeds and preserves many of their</p>
    <p>useful properties: Ease of use, ease of management...</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>SatelliteLab is for YOU!</p>
    <p>We have a new testbed that you can use for your experiments</p>
    <p>To run an experiment, you need:  some planets (e.g., nodes from PlanetLab)  some satellites (e.g., nodes from friends or</p>
    <p>colleagues)  the SatelliteLab software</p>
    <p>http://satellitelab.mpi-sws.org/</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
