<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Teaching Computer Science with Cybersecurity Education Built-in</p>
    <p>Chuan Yue, chuanyue@mines.edu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security &amp; Privacy Vulnerabilities - The Path to Exploitation</p>
    <p>Where a threat intersects with a vulnerability, risk is present  NIST Special Publication 800-100: Information Security Handbook: A Guide for Managers</p>
    <p>Vulnerabilities are pervasive in computer &amp; network systems:</p>
    <p>Req. analysis, design, implementation, deployment, maintenance, ...</p>
    <p>Web-based, cloud-based, mobile-based, ...</p>
    <p>Application, middleware, OS, VMM, Hardware, ...</p>
    <p>Functionality related, usability related, ...</p>
    <p>Human users</p>
    <p>Security threat trends (Symantec, Gartner, SANS, etc.)</p>
    <p>targeting end users, online underground economy, rapidly adaptable attacking techniques</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Security &amp; Privacy Protection</p>
    <p>Great need and importance, much more challenging!</p>
    <p>Technical solutions</p>
    <p>Educational solutions</p>
    <p>Vulnerabilities ThreatsRisks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vision: Security-integrated CS Education</p>
    <p>Integrate (inject) relevant cybersecurity topics into nonsecurity courses  CS students have no way to escape cybersecurity education</p>
    <p>none of the top 50 CS programs in U.S. includes cybersecurity in the core of their curricula based on our survey in June 2016</p>
    <p>CS students understand the correlation and interplay between cybersecurity and other sub-areas of CS</p>
    <p>Job, career, ......</p>
    <p>Evaluate the teaching and learning effectiveness</p>
    <p>Promote the adoption of this approach</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Security Integration Approach</p>
    <p>Its necessity and importance have been emphasized for over one decade, e.g., SIGCSE 2002 (Panel on integrating security concepts into existing computer courses [3]).</p>
    <p>Unfortunately, this approach has received insufficient attention, and it still severely lags behind in adoption.</p>
    <p>(Section 2 Related Work : mainly on low level courses)</p>
    <p>Our effort complements those existing efforts by providing a new viable implementation solution and focuses more on the (limited existing) integration in upper and graduate level non-security courses.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Introduction and Background</p>
    <p>Our Integration Implementation</p>
    <p>Evaluation Results</p>
    <p>Conclusion</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Basic Idea of our Integration Implementation</p>
    <p>Leveraging the expertise of cybersecurity researchers to incorporate relevant security topics into upper and graduate level non-security courses.</p>
    <p>consult with the instructors of non-security courses</p>
    <p>identify the relevant cybersecurity topics</p>
    <p>discuss the corresponding topics in the classes</p>
    <p>A viable solution  relevant and current content, no training overhead as in [13]</p>
    <p>use travel time of non-security course instructors, thus address the concern that something else will have to be sacrificed [3]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Integration Implementation Effort So Far</p>
    <p>8 Courses (9 topics, 10 sessions)  Computer Communication (A Case Study of Heartbleed</p>
    <p>Vulnerability)</p>
    <p>Software Engineering (Engineering Your Password Security)</p>
    <p>Operating Systems (VM Introspection and the Semantic Gap)</p>
    <p>Software Testing for Mobile &amp; Embedded Systems (Cryptomisuse in Android Apps)</p>
    <p>Computer Networks (Web Security and Privacy Topics)</p>
    <p>Database Management (SQLi Attacks and Defenses)</p>
    <p>Database Management (Access Control and Database Security)</p>
    <p>Advanced High Performance Computing (Scientific Computing Integrity)</p>
    <p>Data Structures and Algorithms (Command Injection)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Computer Communication - A Case Study of Heartbleed Vulnerability</p>
    <p>SSL, TLS, and HTTPS</p>
    <p>DTLS (Datagram TLS)</p>
    <p>TLS Heartbeat Extension</p>
    <p>OpenSSL Heartbleed Vulnerability and Impact</p>
    <p>OpenSSL Heartbleed Vulnerability Security Patch</p>
    <p>Discussions  HTTPS Administration</p>
    <p>Certificate Revocation and Scalability</p>
    <p>Support for Critical Projects</p>
    <p>Vulnerability Disclosure</p>
    <p>Notification and Patching</p>
    <p>98/9/2016</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Software Engineering - Engineering Your Password Security</p>
    <p>Problems of Passwords</p>
    <p>Some Popular Solutions</p>
    <p>Password Creation</p>
    <p>Password Management</p>
    <p>Single Sign-On (SSO) Systems Security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Operating Systems - VM Introspection and the Semantic Gap</p>
    <p>Virtualization, VM, VMM</p>
    <p>Virtualization and Security</p>
    <p>Virtual Machine Introspection (VMI) can be very useful in security applications</p>
    <p>Semantic gap exists</p>
    <p>Weak semantic gap has been largely addressed</p>
    <p>Strong semantic gap is still there</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Software Testing for Mobile &amp; Embedded Systems - Crypto-misuse in Android Apps</p>
    <p>Commonly Used Crypto Primitives</p>
    <p>Common Rules in Cryptography</p>
    <p>CryptoLint --- a light-weight static analysis tool</p>
    <p>System Design and Implementation</p>
    <p>Evaluation and Results</p>
    <p>Case Studies</p>
    <p>Limitations</p>
    <p>Mitigations</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Computer Networks - Web Security and Privacy Topics</p>
    <p>Symantec Internet Security Threat Report</p>
    <p>Vulnerability Analysis of Browser-based Password Managers</p>
    <p>Automatic Detection of Information Leakage Vulnerabilities in Browser Extensions</p>
    <p>Phishing Susceptibility Measurement &amp; Analysis, Design, Education</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Class Session Information</p>
    <p>Session Symbol</p>
    <p>Course Title</p>
    <p>Course Level</p>
    <p>Institution/ Semester</p>
    <p>Class Size</p>
    <p>CC Computer Communication</p>
    <p>Grad. I / I 11</p>
    <p>ST Software Testing</p>
    <p>Grad. I / I 5</p>
    <p>SE Software Engineering</p>
    <p>Undergrad. I / I 24</p>
    <p>OS1 Operating Systems</p>
    <p>Grad. &amp; Undergrad.</p>
    <p>I / I 27</p>
    <p>OS2 Operating Systems</p>
    <p>Grad. &amp; Undergrad.</p>
    <p>I / II 23</p>
    <p>CN Computer Networks</p>
    <p>Undergrad. II / II 17</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fourteen Common Survey Questions (1~7)</p>
    <p>General Questions  S1: Learning cybersecurity knowledge &amp; skills is important for computer</p>
    <p>science students.</p>
    <p>S2: I am interested in learning cybersecurity knowledge &amp; skills.</p>
    <p>S3: Please rate your current cybersecurity knowledge &amp; skills: (clueless, beginner, intermediate, advanced, total guru)</p>
    <p>Overall Perception of the Cybersecurity Topic  S4: The cybersecurity topic discussed in todays class is interesting.</p>
    <p>S5: The cybersecurity topic discussed in todays class is difficult.</p>
    <p>S6: The cybersecurity topic discussed in todays class is useful.</p>
    <p>S7: The cybersecurity topic discussed in todays class is relevant to this course.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Fourteen Common Survey Questions (8~14)</p>
    <p>Overall Perception of the Cybersecurity Topic (cont.)  S8: The cybersecurity topic discussed in todays class improved my</p>
    <p>cybersecurity knowledge and skills.</p>
    <p>S9: The cybersecurity topic discussed in todays class is helpful for me to prepare for my career.</p>
    <p>S10: The instructor(s) effectively discussed the cybersecurity topic in todays class.</p>
    <p>S11: I effectively learned the cybersecurity topic discussed in todays class.</p>
    <p>S12: I would like to have cybersecurity topics dis-cussed in other noncybersecurity courses in the future.</p>
    <p>S13: Todays class motivates me to systematically learn cybersecurity knowledge and skills in the future.</p>
    <p>Open Comments:  S14: Please write down comments and suggestions about todays class and</p>
    <p>learning cybersecurity knowledge &amp; skills in general.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mean Ratings of Six Class Sessions to S1~S13</p>
    <p>(answer options for Likert-scale statements were converted to numeric values)</p>
    <p>The majority of students found the discussed cybersecurity topics interesting, useful, and relevant.</p>
    <p>They would like to have cybersecurity topics discussed in other noncybersecurity courses in the future.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Specific Questions and Results</p>
    <p>Each questionnaire also contains some questions specific to the cybersecurity content discussed in the class session.</p>
    <p>The questions are designed in pairs for us to evaluate the learning effectiveness in terms of the students understanding of certain details of the discussed content (B)efore the class session and (C)urrently.</p>
    <p>Students effectively learned the corresponding cybersecurity topics discussed in the class sessions.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Specific Questions for Operating Systems</p>
    <p>SS1B: I understood the basic idea of the Intrusion Detection System (IDS) before reading the paper recommended by the instructor(s) and before todays class.</p>
    <p>SS1C: Currently, I clearly understand the basic idea of IDS.</p>
    <p>SS2B: I understood that VMI can be useful in security systems such as IDS before reading the paper recommended by the instructor(s) and before todays class.</p>
    <p>SS2C: Currently, I clearly understand that VMI can be useful in security systems, especially IDS.</p>
    <p>SS3B: I understood the technical details about using VMI in security systems, especially IDS, before reading the paper recommended by the instructor(s) and before todays class.</p>
    <p>SS3C: Currently, I clearly understand the technical details about using VMI in security systems, especially IDS. SS4B: I understood the meaning of the semantic gap in VMI before reading the paper recommended by the instructor(s) and before todays class. SS4C: Currently, I clearly understand the meaning of the semantic gap in VMI.</p>
    <p>SS5B: I understood the difference between the weak semantic gap and the strong semantic gap in VMIbased security systems, especially IDS, before reading the paper recommended by the instructor(s) and before todays class. SS5C: Currently, I clearly understand the difference between the weak semantic gap and the strong semantic gap in VMI-based security systems, especially IDS.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ratings to Specific OS Questions</p>
    <p>OS1</p>
    <p>OS2</p>
    <p>Students improved their understanding of the IDS and VMI related concepts.</p>
    <p>Mean ratings for all the five paired questions are improved (statistically significant) in both class sessions.</p>
    <p>The spread for all the ratings to the current understanding are also relatively small.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Advocate to further explore the security integration approach</p>
    <p>Explored a viable implementation solution and evaluated its effectiveness</p>
    <p>Evaluated the teaching and learning effectiveness</p>
    <p>Our experience is very encouraging</p>
    <p>Thank You!</p>
    <p>(NSF DGE-1619841) Big Thanks!</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
