<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lowering the Barriers to Capture The Flag Administration</p>
    <p>and Participation Kevin Chung, CTFd LLC</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is a Capture The Flag</p>
    <p>Teams of users participate in a online/LAN competition</p>
    <p>Receive cyber security challenges</p>
    <p>By exploiting, patching, or reverse engineering each challenge, a team receives points</p>
    <p>Whoever has the most points at the end wins</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What are CTFs used for?  Games of skill</p>
    <p>CTFs began as a way of testing and teaching cyber security techniques</p>
    <p>Education &amp; Internal Training</p>
    <p>Educational institutions and companies use CTFs to teach their students and employees</p>
    <p>Recruitment</p>
    <p>Some companies leverage CTFs as a means of filtering and identifying candidates</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Future of CTF</p>
    <p>De-facto security training interface?</p>
    <p>Expand into more than just cyber security?</p>
    <p>Can a security CTF become an e-sport?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CTF as an e-sport</p>
    <p>What drives a decision?</p>
    <p>How do you add meta game to CTF?</p>
    <p>e.g. Types of units/utilities, map layouts, item economy</p>
    <p>Would someone watch a CTF for 30 mins to an hour?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Started life at CSAW CTF in 2014 and was open sourced in 2015</p>
    <p>Focuses on ease of use and extensibility</p>
    <p>Written in Python, Flask, and JavaScript</p>
    <p>CTFd comes with everything needed code-wise to run a CTF</p>
    <p>Anything additional can be implemented with a theme or plugin</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Features</p>
    <p>Team Scoring algorithm  User profiles  Graph visualizations  Challenge board interface  Content Management System  Hints and Awards</p>
    <p>Plugins  Themes  CTF backup and restoration  Automatic CTF starting and</p>
    <p>ending</p>
    <p>Mail server configuration</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CTFd gives users a clean and simple interface to access challenges</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges  Information appears</p>
    <p>when you click the associated button</p>
    <p>Descriptions are written in Markdown/ HTML</p>
    <p>When a user has found the flag they can submit it for validation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CTFd provides hints, files, solves, and associated other information</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CTFd keeps track of who solves what and when</p>
    <p>This is all rendered on a large score graph</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scoring Algorithm 1. Who has the most points</p>
    <p>Sum the value of all the challenges the team has solved 2. Apply any extra awarded points</p>
    <p>Admins can award points for good behavior 3. In the case of a tie, who was quicker to achieve the</p>
    <p>score</p>
    <p>Sort by the recorded time of the teams last solve</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CTFd also generates statistics graphs for individual teams</p>
    <p>All graphs are downloadable</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CTFds admin interface lets us change data without leaving the browser</p>
    <p>We can do the same for team information and website pages</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tags, Hints, Keys</p>
    <p>Tags - An additional way to mark challenges to be customized by themes/plugins for the end user</p>
    <p>Hints - Reveal hints to the user and optionally charge points for the hint</p>
    <p>Keys - Add and delete keys/ flags that are accepted by the challenge</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Customizability</p>
    <p>CTFd exposes plugins and themes to heavily customize a CTF</p>
    <p>Themes are written in Jinja2, HTML, CSS, and Javascript</p>
    <p>Plugins and CTFd itself are written in Python and Flask</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example CTFd Themes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Plugins</p>
    <p>CTFd will load specially written Python modules as plugins</p>
    <p>These plugins override default behavior and add additional behavior</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Plugin Examples  Private Registration - Only accept users with unique tokens</p>
    <p>https://github.com/farisv/CTFd-Private-Registration</p>
    <p>Instancing Plugin - Unique Challenges per team</p>
    <p>https://github.com/tamuctf/ctfd-instancing-plugin</p>
    <p>Competitor Shells - Web terminals for teams</p>
    <p>https://github.com/tamuctf/ctfd-shell-plugin</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CTFd supports custom challenges CTFd allows you customize</p>
    <p>how challenges are seen and solved</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Custom Challenges</p>
    <p>Based on the observation that CTFs are primarily about solving challenges, not the challenge format</p>
    <p>Challenges can define how they look to competitors and how they are edited by CTF administrators</p>
    <p>Answer acceptance can be defined with Python</p>
    <p>End result is that CTF challenges gain format diversity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Multiple Choice Questions</p>
    <p>Programming Challenges</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CTF Backups</p>
    <p>CTFd supports the export and import of backups</p>
    <p>Meant to support CTFd itself, offline analysis, &amp; archival sites</p>
    <p>The backup format is a zip file containing</p>
    <p>JSON files representing the serialized database</p>
    <p>A copy of all files uploaded to CTFd</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Installation</p>
    <p>Setup scripts provided for native installation</p>
    <p>Docker build files provided for Docker installation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Planned Improvements</p>
    <p>More documentation around CTFds feature set</p>
    <p>Fully RESTful API</p>
    <p>Attack and Defense format support</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A small sample of companies and schools using CTFd</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Managed Hosting We offer managed CTFd instances for those not</p>
    <p>interested in hosting on their own</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Questions? github.com/CTFd/CTFd</p>
    <p>ctfd.io @ctfdio /ctfdio</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
