<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Peer Instruction for Digital Forensics</p>
    <p>William E. Johnson, Irfan Ahmed, Vassil Roussev Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>University of New Orleans</p>
    <p>Cynthia B. Lee Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>Stanford University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Peer Instruction  Introduced by Eric Mazur, a physicist at</p>
    <p>Harvard University  Tested and used in several scientific disciplines</p>
    <p>including o Physics, o Biology, and o Computer science</p>
    <p>Results of using peer instruction are promising o Improving student learning o Halving failure rates o Increasing student retention in their respective major</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Peer Instruction in CS  6% higher grades on final exams over</p>
    <p>traditional lecture style  61% reduction in failure rates</p>
    <p>o Theory of Computation, and Computer Architecture</p>
    <p>31% improvement in student retention  Instructors find peer instruction effective  Students recommend that more instructors</p>
    <p>should use peer instruction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Peer Instruction Methodology  Pre-class preparation by students</p>
    <p>o Reading material o Quiz</p>
    <p>In Class, a topic is covered as o A question is asked to students</p>
    <p>Conceptual  Multiple choice</p>
    <p>o Two to three minutes for reply o Group discussion of students o Students reply to the question again o Instructor may further discuss the answers</p>
    <p>Iterative</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Elements of a Peer Instruction Question</p>
    <p>Concept Trigger  Presentation Type</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Concept Trigger  Provoke a students thinking process  Set the desired direction of peer discussion  Examples: (Beatty et al. [1])</p>
    <p>o Deliberate ambiguity o Trolling for misconceptions o Omit necessary information o Identify a set or subset o Compare and contrast o Trap unjustified assumptions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Question Presentation  Putting concept and concept trigger together</p>
    <p>o Better presentation o Easier understanding</p>
    <p>Examples: o Scenario o Example o Diagram o Definitional o Feature</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Question # 1 File Carving</p>
    <p>In which of the following situations is file carving most effective?</p>
    <p>a) The targeted drive is highly fragmented, b) The targeted drive has been recently</p>
    <p>defragmented, c) The system being used to examine the drive has</p>
    <p>low free space, d) The system being used to examine the drive has</p>
    <p>high free space, e) More than one of the above</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deconstruction # 1  Concept Trigger</p>
    <p>o identify a set or subset o trolling for misconceptions</p>
    <p>Question Presentation o example</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example Question # 2 Forensic Artifacts</p>
    <p>A USB drive with an unknown owner is found in a corporate setting. How might a forensic investigator typically determine whether that particular drive was plugged into any given Windows machine?</p>
    <p>a) Examine all ntuser.dat files to determine if a user plugged it into the machine</p>
    <p>b) Check the SYSTEM registry hive to see if it was plugged into that machine</p>
    <p>c) Check the SOFTWARE registry hive to see if it has been used by any particular piece of software</p>
    <p>d) More than one of the above e) None of the above</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Deconstruction # 2  Concept Trigger</p>
    <p>o None of the above o Identify a set or subset</p>
    <p>Question Presentation o Scenario</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Analysis of Questions  Developed 108 questions for digital forensics</p>
    <p>Goal of Analysis is to identify concept triggers and presentation types in the questions</p>
    <p>Topics # of Questions Introduction to Computer Forensics 31 Windows Registry 10 Forensic Artifacts 24 File Systems 11 Live Forensics 24 File Carving 8</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Concept Trigger</p>
    <p>R EM</p>
    <p>O V E$ N O N ES</p>
    <p>SE N TI A LS $</p>
    <p>C O M PA</p>
    <p>R E$ A N D $C O N TR</p>
    <p>A ST $</p>
    <p>EX TE</p>
    <p>N D $T H E$ C O N TE</p>
    <p>XT $</p>
    <p>R EU</p>
    <p>SE $F A M IL IA R $Q</p>
    <p>U ES</p>
    <p>TI O N $</p>
    <p>O O PS =G</p>
    <p>O =B</p>
    <p>A C K$</p>
    <p>IN TE</p>
    <p>R PR</p>
    <p>ET $R EP</p>
    <p>R ES</p>
    <p>EN TA</p>
    <p>TI O N S$</p>
    <p>ID EN</p>
    <p>TI FY $A $S ET $O</p>
    <p>R $S U B SE</p>
    <p>T$</p>
    <p>R A N K$ V A R IA N TS $</p>
    <p>R EV</p>
    <p>EA L$ A $B ET</p>
    <p>TE R $W</p>
    <p>A Y$</p>
    <p>ST R A TE</p>
    <p>G IZ E$ O N LY $</p>
    <p>IN C LU</p>
    <p>D E$ EX</p>
    <p>TR A N EO</p>
    <p>U S$ IN FO</p>
    <p>R M A TI O N $</p>
    <p>O M IT $N</p>
    <p>EC ES</p>
    <p>SA R Y$ IN FO</p>
    <p>R M A TI O N $</p>
    <p>A N SW</p>
    <p>ER $C H O IC ES $R EV</p>
    <p>EA L$ LI KE</p>
    <p>LY $</p>
    <p>U SE $&quot; N O N E$ O F$ TH</p>
    <p>E$ A B O V E&quot; $</p>
    <p>Q U A LI TA</p>
    <p>TI V E$ Q U ES</p>
    <p>TI O N S$</p>
    <p>A N A LY SI S$ A N D $R EA</p>
    <p>SO N IN G $</p>
    <p>M U LT IP LE $D EF</p>
    <p>EN SI B LE $A N SW</p>
    <p>ER S$</p>
    <p>R EQ</p>
    <p>U IR E$ U N ST</p>
    <p>A TE</p>
    <p>D $A SS</p>
    <p>U M PT</p>
    <p>IO N S$</p>
    <p>TR A P$ U N JU</p>
    <p>ST IF IE D $A SS</p>
    <p>U M PT</p>
    <p>IO N S$</p>
    <p>D EL IB ER</p>
    <p>A TE $A M B IG U IT Y$</p>
    <p>TR O LL IN G $F O R $M</p>
    <p>IS C O N C EP</p>
    <p>TI O N S$</p>
    <p>N o. $o f$P</p>
    <p>I$Q ue</p>
    <p>s, on</p>
    <p>s$ (%</p>
    <p>)$</p>
    <p>Concept$Triggers$</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation types</p>
    <p>EX A M PL E$</p>
    <p>SC EN</p>
    <p>A RI O $</p>
    <p>D EF IN IT IO N A L$</p>
    <p>FE A TU</p>
    <p>RE $</p>
    <p>D IA G RA</p>
    <p>M $</p>
    <p>N o. $o f$P</p>
    <p>I$Q ue</p>
    <p>s, on</p>
    <p>s$ (%</p>
    <p>)$</p>
    <p>Presenta,on$Types$of$Ques,ons$</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presentation-types &amp; Topics</p>
    <p>IN TR</p>
    <p>O D U CT</p>
    <p>IO N &quot;</p>
    <p>W IN D O W S&quot; RE</p>
    <p>G IS TR</p>
    <p>Y&quot;</p>
    <p>FO RE</p>
    <p>N SI C&quot; A RT</p>
    <p>IF A CT</p>
    <p>S&quot;</p>
    <p>FI LE &quot;S YS TE M S&quot;</p>
    <p>LI VE &quot;F O RE</p>
    <p>N SI CS &quot;</p>
    <p>FI LE &quot;C A RV</p>
    <p>IN G &quot;</p>
    <p>N o. $o f$P</p>
    <p>I$Q ue</p>
    <p>s, on</p>
    <p>s$ (%</p>
    <p>)$</p>
    <p>Presenta,on$Types$of$Ques,ons$ Example&quot; Scenario&quot; DefiniKonal&quot; Feature&quot; Diagram&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Workshop  Topic: Computer forensics  Participants: 12 undergrad students  Topics covered:</p>
    <p>o Introduction to Computer Forensics o File Systems o File Carving o Windows Registry</p>
    <p>Duration: 4 hours</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Pre-workshop Activities  Advertisement</p>
    <p>o Email is sent out to UNO CS Undergrad students o Registration form</p>
    <p>Reading Material: Students asked to read some material on workshop topics o Windows registry o File carving and o FAT32 and NTFS file systems</p>
    <p>Pre-workshop quiz o Students are asked to complete a quiz on the reading material o Ensures that students read the material</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Evaluation  Quizzes</p>
    <p>o Three quizzes: Carving, FAT, and Registry. o Each quiz is taken before and after the material is covered</p>
    <p>Survey on Peer Instruction Experience</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quiz Results</p>
    <p>Q.1# Q.2# Q.3# Q.4# Q.5# Q.6# Q.7# Q.8# Q.9# Q.10#Q.11#</p>
    <p>N o. $o f$C</p>
    <p>or re ct $A ns w er s$ (%</p>
    <p>)$</p>
    <p>Quiz$Ques6ons$</p>
    <p>File$Carving$</p>
    <p>Before#Covering#the#Topic## A?er#Covering#the#Topic##</p>
    <p>FAT$File$System$ Registry$</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Peer Instruction Results</p>
    <p>Q-1&quot; Q-2&quot; Q-3&quot; Q-4&quot; Q-5&quot; Q-6&quot; Q-7&quot;</p>
    <p>N o. $o f$C</p>
    <p>or re ct $A ns w er s$ (%</p>
    <p>)$</p>
    <p>Peer$Instruc5on$Ques5ons$</p>
    <p>Before&quot;Peer&quot;Discussion&quot; A;er&quot;Peer&quot;Discussion&quot;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Question 5</p>
    <p>Originally worded File carving is the most effective in which one or more of the following scenarios? o A. Drive is highly fragmented o B. Drive is recently defragmented o C. System used to examine drive has low space o D. System used to examine drive has high space o E. More than one of the above</p>
    <p>The question targets misconception about defragmentation, causing incorrect answers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion  108 peer instruction questions with variety of</p>
    <p>concept triggers  Example and scenario based questions are</p>
    <p>often used  Four-hour long workshop is used to test a</p>
    <p>subset of questions o The participants show positive response for peer instruction</p>
    <p>and clicker survey o The learning gain evaluated via quiz and peer instruction</p>
    <p>questions are 34% and 13% o 91% would recommend that other instructors use peer</p>
    <p>instruction</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Please send me any questions at</p>
    <p>irfan@cs.uno.edu</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
