<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The EDURange Framework and a Movie-themed Exercise in Network Reconnaissance</p>
    <p>Richard Weiss The Evergreen State College</p>
    <p>Jens Mache Lewis &amp; Clark College</p>
    <p>Michael E. Locasto SRI International</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Challenge of Cybersecurity Education</p>
    <p>Teaching analysis skills/abilities and the security mindset  not just knowledge.</p>
    <p>Having good exercises (half of the battle)  Providing the context/guidance (the other half), including clear learning goals.</p>
    <p>Providing prerequisite background  Formative assessment  any tool that helps to give students timely and helpful feedback (guidance)</p>
    <p>Summative assessment  need to verify that they met the learning goals.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>What is EDURange?</p>
    <p>A framework for creating cybersecurity exercises.</p>
    <p>A collection of exercises.  One of those exercises is Total Recon.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Total Recon: An example from network security</p>
    <p>Analyze a large address space  Understand how ping and TCP work  Understand CIDR addresses  Use efficient options in nmap</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demo</p>
    <p>https://cloud.edurange.org</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Total Recon: learning nmap</p>
    <p>Why not just use ping?  nmap will use ping, but if there is no response,</p>
    <p>it can try TCP.  Understanding protocols  Learning the options for nmap: scan all TCP</p>
    <p>ports? UDP ports?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Challenge of Formative Assessment</p>
    <p>Having the right tools: Complete/Accurate  Large class size  No TA support  Limited time  Equitable distribution of attention</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Possible Uses for command line history Information</p>
    <p>Instructor can see visually if student is on the right track</p>
    <p>Student can use it after the exercise to reflect on what they did/did not do.</p>
    <p>Instructor can use it in a debrief after the exercise.</p>
    <p>Note: it gives more information than whether the student was successful or not</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other EDURange Exercises</p>
    <p>strace: teaches about system calls, and dynamic analysis of processes</p>
    <p>ssh inception: understanding basics and options  Treasure hunt: command line tools, access control</p>
    <p>in Linux.  scapy hunt: more advanced network recon  elf infection: static analysis of binaries  DaVinci code: basics of codes and ciphers.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Bash History graph</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions  We need engaging exercises with clear learning goals and tools for timely, precise feedback.</p>
    <p>We used backwards design and it helped.  It is possible to use old movies as themes: students and faculty like it.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Future work</p>
    <p>How to teach students how to choose the right tools for a problem, including ones we haven't taught them.</p>
    <p>Shifting from tool-based exercises to problembased exercises, finding open ports that are filtered by a firewall.</p>
    <p>Improving our visualization tools to give better feedback to students and instructors.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our website</p>
    <p>For general information:  http://www.edurange.org  to sign up  cloud.edurange.org</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
