<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PHISHING ATTACKS: LEARNING BY DOING Tom Chothia, Stefan Paul and Michael Oultram University of Birmingham, UK</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Teaching Phishing Attacks is Hard  People fall for phishing attacks because they are stupid</p>
    <p>Id never fall for a phishing attack</p>
    <p>Phishing attacks work because people are not thinking about phishing attacks when they open their e-mail.</p>
    <p>When you teach phishing attacks the students will be thinking about phishing attacks.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our Solution  A VM framework in which students can perform their own</p>
    <p>phishing attacks.</p>
    <p>The VM contains a company website.  More information about the employees can be found on Facebook.</p>
    <p>Docker containers, running our scripts simulate each possible phishing victim.</p>
    <p>Students need to think about the employees, look at their profiles, and come up with ideas for spear phishing attacks.</p>
    <p>They must then execute these attacks on the VM using Metaspoit, Office macros, and by building fake websites.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Docker Container: Victim</p>
    <p>daemon</p>
    <p>VM</p>
    <p>Flag</p>
    <p>Docker Container: Victim</p>
    <p>daemon</p>
    <p>Docker Container: Victim</p>
    <p>daemon</p>
    <p>Flag</p>
    <p>Student nonroot account</p>
    <p>Docker Container: Web + Email servers Flag</p>
    <p>Flag</p>
    <p>E-mail client</p>
    <p>MetaSploit</p>
    <p>ooffice</p>
    <p>Web browser</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>LESSON OVERVIEW</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Typical Network</p>
    <p>Wi-Fi</p>
    <p>WebServer</p>
    <p>Comp1</p>
    <p>DataBase</p>
    <p>CEOs E-mail Server</p>
    <p>Dev.</p>
    <p>Credit Card Processing</p>
    <p>DMZ</p>
    <p>NAT Proxy</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phishing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Spear Phishing  Random phishing e-mails dont stand much chance.</p>
    <p>Spear phishing refers to very carefully crafted, targeted phishing e-mails.</p>
    <p>E.g. look on Linkedin, Facebook:  find the name of the sysadmin,  find the name of a new employee and  write an e-mail which makes the new employee fear they are going</p>
    <p>to loose out.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>from MWR infosec.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Phishing payloads  Websites,</p>
    <p>E.g. phishtank.com</p>
    <p>Executables  Run anything you want</p>
    <p>Macros  In office documents</p>
    <p>But the real question is how to get people to open the payload!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Automated flag submission  Students can be asked to write up their attacks.</p>
    <p>Give their reasoning, and say why the victim might fall for the attack.</p>
    <p>Marks can be awarded for good ideas that didnt work.</p>
    <p>Marks can also be just for flag submission  Done automatically via a website:  http://www.cs.bham.ac.uk/internal/courses/comp</p>
    <p>sec/publictokens</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Further work  Improve performance</p>
    <p>8GB VM! Some scripts can crash (e.g. on special characters in e-mails)E.g.  restart fixes this.</p>
    <p>A.I. methods to recognize tone and text for e-mail.</p>
    <p>Getting past different levels of anti-virus.</p>
    <p>More sources of information.</p>
    <p>Assessment of educational value.</p>
    <p>Please do let me know if you would like to use or help develop this.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
