<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Authenticity, Ethicality, and Motivation: A Formal Evaluation of a 10-week Computer Security</p>
    <p>Alternate Reality Game for CS Undergraduates</p>
    <p>John Morelock, Virginia Tech Zachary Peterson, Cal Poly, San Luis Obispo</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Innovating CS and Security Education</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Cal Polys CPE123</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>CPE123: Security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Alternate Reality Games</p>
    <p>Inspire counterfactual thinking Maintain engagement Provide an authentic context for course material</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Game &amp; Course Design</p>
    <p>Iterative design process Starting with KSAs, LOs, and an initial story Weekly refined and aligned topics to story Resulting in a design document</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Story</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Methods</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Answering Research Question 1</p>
    <p>What aspects of the ARG affected student experience in the course?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Qualitative Data Collection</p>
    <p>(4 female, 16 male)</p>
    <p>Interview protocol on perceptions of course,</p>
    <p>game, and security</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Qualitative Data Analysis</p>
    <p>Open coded for various aspects of student</p>
    <p>experience</p>
    <p>Categorized codes to discern general patterns</p>
    <p>across responses</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Aspects of student experience analyzed</p>
    <p>Positive and negative aspects of the course Positive and negative aspects of the ARG Suggested changes to the course and ARG Changes in students behaviors, perceptions, and understanding related to cybersecurity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: The ARG provided an authentic context to motivate problem-solving</p>
    <p>Even though we all knew exactly when [the ARG] started and exactly what was going on, it was way more engaging than just getting assignments...when youre like, Hey, were doing an attack, youre like, Oh, I know this is fake, but its exciting.</p>
    <p>-Male focus group participant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: The ARG provided an authentic context to motivate problem-solving</p>
    <p>The game, that made it more fun. And even though some things ended up taking multiple hours, it didnt feel like it was a task. It felt like it was just a fun thing to do.</p>
    <p>-Male focus group participant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Even inauthentic elements were enjoyable</p>
    <p>I think because, at least for me, I knew from the beginning [the ARG] wasnt real, that even though throughout the quarter [with the introduction of videos], it became like more obvious, I still really enjoyed the videos...I showed my family members, and it was really cool.</p>
    <p>-Female focus group participant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Authenticity often clashed with ethicality</p>
    <p>I missed the first day of this class when you said that this was not a real thing we were doing. So I actually thought we were doing a phishing attack against a person...I was like, This could so be real, and then were just going to go and do the worst possible thing? So I had that whole thing, like, No, Im not going to participate.</p>
    <p>-Male focus group participant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Authenticity often clashed with ethicality</p>
    <p>I think on the other end though, making [the ARG] more fake and not as believable I think made the [ethical] line a lot clearer...seeing this in a game and a set setting, youre not harming someone else, this is completely within [Cal Polys] system...It was nice to know that it wasnt real and we were doing it in practice, rather than I think it would have been a huge issue if like it wasnt like that.</p>
    <p>-Female focus group participant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: The course changed students perceptions of the cybersecurity profession</p>
    <p>You have to be right on defense 100% of the time. And on attack, you only have to be right once. And so, I was thinking about that, and it makes [cybersecurity] a very important profession, given how it must be a perfect system in that way. So it seems like its actually way more necessary.</p>
    <p>-Male focus group participant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: The course changed students perceptions of the cybersecurity profession</p>
    <p>Im going to get into web security. I dont know, it looks fun...I think that what this class did tell me is dont get into cryptography. Okay, Im not going to lie. I was falling asleep during the lecture because I was just, I couldnt grasp it. But web security, I was into it.</p>
    <p>-Female focus group participant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Answering Research Question 2</p>
    <p>How did students motivation-related experiences in the course differ based on gender?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quantitative Data Collection</p>
    <p>Electronic survey n = 54</p>
    <p>(14 female, 40 male)</p>
    <p>Likert-scale items on student achievement</p>
    <p>motivation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Measuring Achievement Motivation: Eccles Expectancy-Value Theory (EVT)</p>
    <p>Expectancy for Success - Confidence in ones ability to succeed Attainment Value - Importance of doing well Utility Value - Usefulness to future plans Intrinsic Interest Value - Enjoyment of participation Cost - Perceived difficulty and effort required to do well</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Quantitative Data Analysis</p>
    <p>?</p>
    <p>Comparison of male and female responses on EVT Constructs</p>
    <p>Two-sided t-test</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Women had less confidence and found the course harder and requiring more effort than men</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results: Women had less coding knowledge to start</p>
    <p>I felt like with a lot of the labs, I knew conceptually what I had to do, but I did not have the skills in writing code to actually do it, because all the lectures were conceptual, and I seemed to understand them. But then I had no tools to go in and do that in the lab.</p>
    <p>-Female focus group participant</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Discussion</p>
    <p>Ethics Gender Gap Hard Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Plans to revisit and refine coursework Increase reality Ultimately release as a package</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
