<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS, AMHERST  Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>Tian Guo, Upendra Sharma, Timothy Wood, Sambit Sahu,Prashant Shenoy</p>
    <p>University of Massachusetts Amherst, The George Washington University , IBM Research</p>
    <p>Seagull: Intelligent Cloud Bursting For Enterprise</p>
    <p>Applications</p>
    <p>Friday, June 15, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tian Guo(tian@cs.umass.edu)</p>
    <p>Cloud Computing</p>
    <p>Cloud Computing:  Pay-as-you-go service  Rent Resources  Infrastructure as a Service</p>
    <p>- Virtualization technology, rent VMs - Popular for Apps with dynamic workload</p>
    <p>Benefits  Flexible pricing model  Agile to workload changes</p>
    <p>Mon Tues Wed Thur Fri Sat Sun</p>
    <p>Private Site (5 servers)</p>
    <p>S ev</p>
    <p>er N</p>
    <p>ee de</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>Friday, June 15, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tian Guo(tian@cs.umass.edu)</p>
    <p>Cloud Bursting</p>
    <p>Enterprises own private data centers  Try to use the existing infrastructure (hybrid)</p>
    <p>Cloud Bursting  Enables Enterprise to use local data center  rents public resource upon workload changes  seamless and transparent resource sharing between local and</p>
    <p>public cloud</p>
    <p>Challenges  When to trigger cloud bursting?  Which Apps to cloud Burst?  How to balance cost and time trade-off?</p>
    <p>Seagull  Cloud Bursting Algorithm  Precopying Algorithm</p>
    <p>Mon Tues Wed Thur Fri Sat Sun</p>
    <p>Se rv</p>
    <p>er s</p>
    <p>N ee</p>
    <p>de d</p>
    <p>Private Site (5 servers)</p>
    <p>Cloud Burst</p>
    <p>Friday, June 15, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Seagull</p>
    <p>Naive 1 vcpu 1 2 vcpu 2</p>
    <p>Tian Guo(tian@cs.umass.edu)</p>
    <p>Seagull Cloud Bursting Algorithm</p>
    <p>Which applications to cloud burst?  Naive approach: move overloaded applications</p>
    <p>Incurs high cost and overhead  Seagull approach: Pick the cheapest applications</p>
    <p>Multi-resource bin packing problem  Greedy approach  Metric: App_Costs/ VM_cores to run in public cloud</p>
    <p>Seagull 1 vcpu 1 2 vcpu 2</p>
    <p>Naive 1 vcpu 1 2 vcpu 2</p>
    <p>Naive 1 vcpu 1 2 vcpu 2</p>
    <p>Friday, June 15, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tian Guo(tian@cs.umass.edu)</p>
    <p>How to Lower Migration Time ?</p>
    <p>Cloud bursting on demand  e.g 5 GB disk state, takes a long time ( ~22 mins)</p>
    <p>Opportunistic Precopying  Copys app vm state to the public cloud in the background  Benefit: Dramatically shortens the migration time  Some experiments:</p>
    <p>~120 secs</p>
    <p>Friday, June 15, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tian Guo(tian@cs.umass.edu)</p>
    <p>Seagull Precopying Algorithm</p>
    <p>How to balance cost and time trade-off?  Naive Precopying: Precopying overloaded applications</p>
    <p>- Not Necessary lower migration time  Intelligent Precopying</p>
    <p>- Intuition: Choose the apps that are most likely to be migrated</p>
    <p>Naive 1 vcpu 1 2 vcpu 2</p>
    <p>Naive 1 vcpu 1 2 vcpu 2</p>
    <p>Seagull 1 vcpu 1</p>
    <p>Friday, June 15, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tian Guo(tian@cs.umass.edu)</p>
    <p>Cloud Bursting Algorithm Evaluation</p>
    <p>Experiment Setup  3 hosts and 5 Apps  Varying workload of A for 4 hours</p>
    <p>Seagull is cost Efficient  Lowers cost by 25% over 4 hours</p>
    <p>Friday, June 15, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tian Guo(tian@cs.umass.edu)</p>
    <p>Precopying Algorithm Evaluation</p>
    <p>Experiment Setup  Emulation with 200 quad-core hosts  40 applications, 30% were overloaded  Precopying freqency: 1 hr &amp; total time: 24 hrs</p>
    <p>Seagull balances time and cost well  Spends 22% more money  Transmits 95% less data</p>
    <p>Friday, June 15, 12</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tian Guo(tian@cs.umass.edu)</p>
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Cloud Bursting  Hybrid solution for dynamic workload  Good for Enterprises with private data centers</p>
    <p>Seagull: Intelligent and automated Cloud Bursting  Determines which Apps to Cloud Burst</p>
    <p>- Lowers Cost by 25%  Determines which Apps to Precopy</p>
    <p>- Saves 95% Data Transmission</p>
    <p>Friday, June 15, 12</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
