<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Toward A Session-Based</p>
    <p>Search Engine</p>
    <p>Smitha Sriram, Xuehua Shen, ChengXiang Zhai</p>
    <p>Department of Computer Science</p>
    <p>University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign</p>
    <p>U.S.A.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Information retrieval is inherently an interactive process  A users information need is unlikely fully satisfied with just one</p>
    <p>query execution</p>
    <p>A user often needs to interact with the system several times through query reformulation and document-browsing</p>
    <p>Thus in general, a query exists in a search session</p>
    <p>A search session provides lots of contextual information for a query that can be exploited (e.g., previous queries and clickthrough data)</p>
    <p>Such contextual information is mostly ignored in existing search engines</p>
    <p>We aim at developing a session-based search engine that can exploit such contextual information to improve retrieval</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Traditional vs. Session-based Retrieval</p>
    <p>Retrieval System</p>
    <p>Traditional (1-query)</p>
    <p>Document Collection</p>
    <p>Query=IR applications</p>
    <p>Results: D1 (infrared) D2 (infrared) D3 (retrieval) D4 (infrared) D5 (retrieval)</p>
    <p>Retrieval System</p>
    <p>Session-based</p>
    <p>Query=IR applications</p>
    <p>Results: D3 (retrieval) D5 (retrieval)</p>
    <p>Previous query= retrieval systems</p>
    <p>Frequency in viewed docs:</p>
    <p>Infrared: 0 Retrieval: 5</p>
    <p>Uses more contextual information Gives more accurate results</p>
    <p>IR can mean either information retrieval</p>
    <p>or infrared</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Research Issues</p>
    <p>What is an appropriate architecture for supporting session-based retrieval?  How to manage session information?</p>
    <p>How can we detect session boundaries?  What contextual information should we exploit?  How can we exploit such contextual information to</p>
    <p>improve document ranking?</p>
    <p>How can we display search results in the context of a session?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Client-Server Architecture for Session-based IR</p>
    <p>Docs</p>
    <p>querySearch Engine</p>
    <p>Top-N</p>
    <p>Server Side</p>
    <p>User Search context</p>
    <p>User model</p>
    <p>results</p>
    <p>Personalized Agent</p>
    <p>query</p>
    <p>Client Side</p>
    <p>Local Collection</p>
    <p>Session Manager</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Advantages of Server-Side Processing</p>
    <p>Persistent user profiles (imagine if a user often uses different machines)</p>
    <p>Have access to global user information  Can exploit information about all users to identify</p>
    <p>common access patterns</p>
    <p>Can exploit information about similar users to help improve performance for any individual user</p>
    <p>Have access to all the documents  Can perform more powerful statistical analysis</p>
    <p>(e.g., to identify most frequently accessed docs)</p>
    <p>Can improve document representation over time</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Advantages of a Client-Side Agent</p>
    <p>Can capture more information about the user thus more accurate user modeling</p>
    <p>Can exploit the complete interaction history (e.g., easily capture click-through information)</p>
    <p>Can exploit a users other activities (e.g., searching immediately after reading an email)</p>
    <p>Can detect session boundary more accurately</p>
    <p>More scalable (distributed personalization)  Alleviate the problem of privacy for personalization</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Session Boundary Detection</p>
    <p>Detection is generally easier if done on the client side  More information about the user can be exploited</p>
    <p>E.g., knowing that logout and login happened between two queries</p>
    <p>Sever side has access to query co-occurrence patterns, which can help judge query coherence</p>
    <p>Possible clues for session boundary detection  Time interval between queries</p>
    <p>Query coherence (based on word relatedness and/or query log analysis)</p>
    <p>Activities in between two queries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Useful Session Context Information</p>
    <p>Previous queries in the same session  Documents viewed and not viewed so far in the</p>
    <p>current session</p>
    <p>Other user activities during the same time as the current session</p>
    <p>Context information collected in a similar session by the current user or other users</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Session-based Retrieval Models</p>
    <p>Framework: The risk minimization retrieval framework [Lafferty &amp; Zhai 01, Zhai 02] can be naturally extended to support session-based retrieval</p>
    <p>One possible model (KL-divergence model)  Retrieval = estimating a query model + estimating a doc</p>
    <p>model + computing their KL-divergence</p>
    <p>Session context information (and any other potentially useful information) can be used to estimate a better (session-based) query model</p>
    <p>arg max ( | )</p>
    <p>arg max ( | , , )</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>Q</p>
    <p>p Doc</p>
    <p>p Query User CurrentSessionContext</p>
    <p>Refinement of this model leads to specific retrieval formulas</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Session-based Result Presentation</p>
    <p>Retrieval results can be displayed in the context of the current session  Previous search results in the session can be exploited to</p>
    <p>show which document has been consistently moving up in ranking as the user is reformulating the query</p>
    <p>All the queries in the session can be combined and analyzed to generate a subtopic space for the users information need, and documents can be organized and displayed in this space</p>
    <p>Session-based result presentation can  Help a user digest the search results more effectively and</p>
    <p>more efficiently</p>
    <p>Help a user to quickly focus on the important concept/topic dimensions</p>
    <p>Help a user to figure out how to better formulate a query</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ACES: A Contextual Engine for Search  Architecture: server-side session management  Session-boundary detection: probabilistic measure of query</p>
    <p>similarity</p>
    <p>Session-based ranking: use the KL-div retrieval model and estimate a query model based on  Original query</p>
    <p>Displayed title and summary of viewed documents in the same session</p>
    <p>Previous queries in the same search session</p>
    <p>Session-based result display: show ranks of each doc w.r.t. all the previous queries</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>ACES System Architecture</p>
    <p>Query Clickthrough Data</p>
    <p>Web Browser</p>
    <p>Internet Internet</p>
    <p>Search Result Document Text</p>
    <p>Query Clickthrough Data</p>
    <p>Web/Application Server</p>
    <p>Search Profile Engine Capture</p>
    <p>Text DB RDBMS</p>
    <p>User Profile</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Details of the Ranking Algorithm</p>
    <p>Query model updating using past queries q1, q2,, qk</p>
    <p>Further query model updating using the displayed title and summary of the viewed documents s1, s2,, sk</p>
    <p>k</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>ik q</p>
    <p>qwc k i</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>k qqqwpqwp</p>
    <p>),( 21</p>
    <p>' )1( 1</p>
    <p>),...,,|()|(</p>
    <p>i</p>
    <p>k c w s k i</p>
    <p>s i</p>
    <p>p w q p w q k</p>
    <p>is a decay factor to emphasize the most recent context</p>
    <p>is a parameter to control the influence of the clickthrough data Currently all parameters are set in an ad hoc way</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Demo: Exploiting Previous Queries in ACES</p>
    <p>TREC AP data + Topics 1- 150 + judgments  Allow us to compare traditional search and</p>
    <p>contextual search</p>
    <p>ACES is still far away from a full-fledged session-based search engine</p>
    <p>Much further research needs to be done</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Architecture of Personalized System</p>
    <p>Docs</p>
    <p>querySearch Engine</p>
    <p>Top-N</p>
    <p>Server Side</p>
    <p>Search context</p>
    <p>User model</p>
    <p>results</p>
    <p>Personalized Agent</p>
    <p>query</p>
    <p>Client Side</p>
    <p>Profile Collection</p>
    <p>Session Manager</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>C</p>
    <p>U</p>
    <p>S</p>
    <p>QModel Selection</p>
    <p>Model Selection</p>
    <p>D</p>
    <p>q</p>
    <p>d</p>
    <p>Document generation</p>
    <p>Query generation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Query Clickthrough Data</p>
    <p>Web Browser</p>
    <p>Internet Internet</p>
    <p>Search Result Document Text</p>
    <p>Query Clickthrough Data</p>
    <p>Web/Application Server</p>
    <p>Search Context Engine Capturer</p>
    <p>AP Text DB RDBMS</p>
    <p>User Profile</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
