<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BISmark: A Testbed for Deploying Measurements and Applica=ons in Broadband</p>
    <p>Access Networks</p>
    <p>Srikanth Sundaresan, Sam Burne*, Nick Feamster School of Computer Science, Georgia Tech</p>
    <p>Walter de Donato University of Napoli Federico II</p>
    <p>http://projectbismark.net</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Internet is coming home</p>
    <p>1/3 of the worlds households had Internet access in 2011, compared to 1/5 in 2006. [ITU]</p>
    <p>About 200 million broadband access users in the U.S.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Internet is coming home</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Home networking research ques=ons Do ISPs perform as adverRsed?</p>
    <p>How can we improve home network troubleshooRng?</p>
    <p>Does home network usage vary across the globe?</p>
    <p>Answering these quesRons is hard in pracRce 4</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why is studying home networks difficult?</p>
    <p>Difficult to experiment with and collect data from many home networks</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Where we started: How fast is my ISP?</p>
    <p>Can I trust this measurement?  Is performance consistent?  How does wireless affect performance?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our approach: modify the home router</p>
    <p>Home Network</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>The home router sits at the center of the home network 7</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Our approach: modify the home router</p>
    <p>Home Network</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>BISmark Router</p>
    <p>Custom OpenWRT firmware  Netgear WNDR3800</p>
    <p>650 MHz processor, 128 MB RAM, 16 MB flash</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Home routers enable many kinds of research</p>
    <p>Home Network</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>Uplink and wide area</p>
    <p>Examples: Performance, reliability, accessibility</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Home routers enable many kinds of research</p>
    <p>Home Network</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>Home network behind the NAT</p>
    <p>Examples: Home network characterizaRon, troubleshooRng</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Home routers enable many kinds of research</p>
    <p>Home Network</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
    <p>Traffic that passes through the router</p>
    <p>Examples: Security, caching, bogleneck isolaRon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How to conduct research using BISmark</p>
    <p>The paper This talk</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>MoRvaRon for customized home routers  Lessons learned  Form factor ma*ers  Hardware on the criRcal path is a double-edged sword  Deployment model shapes success</p>
    <p>How you can use BISmark</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Users are wary of unfamiliar hardware</p>
    <p>No labels</p>
    <p>Metal case</p>
    <p>Lack of familiar branding</p>
    <p>First generaRon: the NOX Box</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Form factor maQers</p>
    <p>vs</p>
    <p>NOX Box Netgear WNDR3800</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Once deployed, users sRll only marginally trust</p>
    <p>familiar-looking hardware and blame it at the first sign of trouble.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>MoRvaRon for customized home routers  Lessons learned</p>
    <p>How you can use BISmark</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BISmark is on the cri=cal path</p>
    <p>Home Network</p>
    <p>Internet</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>BISmark is on the cri=cal path</p>
    <p>Advantages 1. We get a complete view, for:  Measuring access networks  Characterizing home devices  IdenRfying boglenecks</p>
    <p>Disadvantages 1. Privacy concerns</p>
    <p>User consent? 2. Users do not tolerate failure</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>AQri=on is high</p>
    <p>A majority of offline routers went offline within six months</p>
    <p>~10% never turned on at all!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Incen=ves to counteract aQri=on Network dashboard uCap</p>
    <p>hgp://networkdashboard.org</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>MoRvaRon for customized home routers  Lessons learned</p>
    <p>How you can use BISmark</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Trust rela=onships are essen=al for success</p>
    <p>Four deployment models: 1. Volunteers with hardware 2. Friends and friends-of-friends 3. Franchising (like Planetlab)  Good for internaRonal deployment (UK, Pakistan, South Africa, Tunisia)</p>
    <p>Trust in authority</p>
    <p>Delegated trust</p>
    <p>Unscalable trust</p>
    <p>No trust</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>More isnt always beQer</p>
    <p>Small deployment  We know the users  Easier to get consent  Greater tolerance for failures</p>
    <p>Easier to conduct in-depth experiments  Harder to draw general conclusions</p>
    <p>Large deployment  Good for drawing general conclusions  Good for comparing between regions, ISPs, devices, etc.  Harder to maintain</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>MoRvaRon for customized home routers  Lessons learned</p>
    <p>How you can use BISmark</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>How you can use BISmark</p>
    <p>In your home  Flash your own Netgear WNDR3700v2, Netgear WNDR3800, or TP-Link WDR3600  hgp://downloads.projectbismark.net</p>
    <p>We can mail you a free router  As a researcher  Open source and open data whenever possible  hgp://uploads.projectbismark.net</p>
    <p>Can you host a deployment?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusion</p>
    <p>Home routers are a good vantage point for conducRng research in home networks  BISmark is a global testbed for deploying measurements and applicaRons in home networks</p>
    <p>Contact us if you are interested in using BISmark for your own research Visit hgp://projectbismark.net for more informaRon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Acknowledgements</p>
    <p>BISmark could not exist without the help of many people  Many thanks to Adam Allred, Marshini Chegy, Thomas Copeland, Abhishek Jain, Aman Jain, Hyojoon Kim, Guilherme Grillo MarRns, Brian Poole, Alfred Roberts, Paul Royal, Boris de Souza, Dave Tht, Steve Woodrow, and many others  Special thanks to the many hundreds of volunteers who host BISmark routers in their homes</p>
    <p>Visit hgp://projectbismark.net for more informaRon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
