<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A Full GPU Virtualization Solution with Mediated</p>
    <p>Pass-Through</p>
    <p>Kun Tian, Yaozu Dong, David Cowperthwaite</p>
    <p>kevin.tian@intel.com,</p>
    <p>eddie.dong@intel.com,</p>
    <p>david.j.cowperthwaite@intel.com</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GPU Virtualization Approaches</p>
    <p>API Forwarding</p>
    <p>Direct Pass-Through</p>
    <p>Performance</p>
    <p>Feature</p>
    <p>Sharing</p>
    <p>Performance</p>
    <p>Feature</p>
    <p>Sharing</p>
    <p>Performance</p>
    <p>Feature Sharing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>gVirt</p>
    <p>Full GPU virtualization</p>
    <p>Mediated Pass-through  Pass-through performance critical operations</p>
    <p>Trap-and-emulate privileged operations</p>
    <p>Full-featured vGPU</p>
    <p>Up to 95% native performance</p>
    <p>Scale up to 7 VMs</p>
    <p>Run native graphics driver in VM</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>GPU Virtualization Approaches</p>
    <p>API Forwarding</p>
    <p>Direct Pass-Through</p>
    <p>Performance</p>
    <p>Feature</p>
    <p>Sharing</p>
    <p>Performance</p>
    <p>Feature</p>
    <p>Sharing</p>
    <p>Full GPU Virtualization</p>
    <p>Performance</p>
    <p>Feature</p>
    <p>Sharing</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>gVirt</p>
    <p>Open source implementation  GPL/BSD dual-license</p>
    <p>Current based on Xen (codename as XenGT)</p>
    <p>KVM support is coming</p>
    <p>Support Intel Processor Graphics built into 4th generation Intel Core processors</p>
    <p>Principles apply to different GPUs</p>
    <p>Trademarked as Intel GVT-g  Intel Graphics Virtualization Technology for virtual GPU</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Challenges</p>
    <p>Complexity in virtualizing a modern GPU</p>
    <p>Efficiency when sharing the GPU</p>
    <p>Secure isolation among the VMs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Graphics Memory Resource Partitioning</p>
    <p>Render Engine</p>
    <p>R e g is</p>
    <p>te rs</p>
    <p>GPU</p>
    <p>Display Engine</p>
    <p>Page Tables</p>
    <p>System Memory</p>
    <p>Graphics Virtual Memory</p>
    <p>CPU</p>
    <p>VM2 VM1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Address Space Ballooning</p>
    <p>(VMs view)  Reduced size  Start from address ZERO</p>
    <p>(VMs view)  Full size  Start from random address  Other VMs resource are reserved</p>
    <p>Inconsistent view due to graphics memory partition</p>
    <p>Host View</p>
    <p>VM2 View</p>
    <p>VM1 View</p>
    <p>Host View</p>
    <p>VM2 View</p>
    <p>VM1 View Ballooned</p>
    <p>Ballooned</p>
    <p>Consistent view with address space ballooning</p>
    <p>Avoid address</p>
    <p>translation!</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>A VM may map unauthorized graphics memory pages</p>
    <p>A VM may program unauthorized graphics memory addresses in registers and commands</p>
    <p>A VM may deliberately hang the GPU as a denial-of-service attack</p>
    <p>Secure Isolation in gVirt</p>
    <p>Mediated Pass-through</p>
    <p>Mediated Pass-through</p>
    <p>Audit before GPU access Audit before GPU access</p>
    <p>Detect and recover</p>
    <p>Detect and recover</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Vulnerability from Direct Execution</p>
    <p>CMDs CMDs</p>
    <p>VM Graphics</p>
    <p>Driver</p>
    <p>Mediator</p>
    <p>GPU</p>
    <p>Submit</p>
    <p>Audit</p>
    <p>Submit</p>
    <p>Execute</p>
    <p>CMDs CMDs CMDs CMDs CMDs CMDs</p>
    <p>Evil happens!</p>
    <p>Evil happens!</p>
    <p>Modify</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Smart Shadowing</p>
    <p>Utilize specific programming model</p>
    <p>Ring</p>
    <p>Buffer</p>
    <p>Batch</p>
    <p>Buffer</p>
    <p>Statically allocated</p>
    <p>Limited page number Lazy</p>
    <p>Shadowing</p>
    <p>Allocated on-demand</p>
    <p>Rare access after submission</p>
    <p>Write</p>
    <p>Protection</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lazy Shadowing</p>
    <p>VM Graphics</p>
    <p>Driver</p>
    <p>Mediator</p>
    <p>GPU</p>
    <p>Submit</p>
    <p>Submit</p>
    <p>Execute complete</p>
    <p>Copy &amp;</p>
    <p>Audit</p>
    <p>complete</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Write-Protection</p>
    <p>VM Graphics</p>
    <p>Driver</p>
    <p>Mediator</p>
    <p>GPU</p>
    <p>Submit</p>
    <p>Audit &amp;</p>
    <p>Write-Protection on</p>
    <p>Submit</p>
    <p>Execute</p>
    <p>complete &amp;</p>
    <p>Write-Protection off</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Configurations</p>
    <p>Hardware with the 4th Intel Core Processor  4 CPU cores (2.4Ghz)  8GB system memory  256GB Intel 520 series SSD  Intel Processor Graphics</p>
    <p>A 2GB global graphics memory  Multiple 2GB local graphics memory</p>
    <p>Software  Dom0/Linux VM: 64bit Ubuntu 12.04 (3.8 kernel)  Windows VM: 64bit Win7  Xen: 4.3  VM configuration</p>
    <p>4 VCPUs and 2GB system memory  Evenly partitioned global graphics memory (e.g. 512MB per VM in a 3</p>
    <p>VM configuration)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Linux VM Performance</p>
    <p>3D Benchmark: Phoronix Test Suite  LightsMark, OpenArena, UrbanTerror, Nexuiz</p>
    <p>2D Benchmark: Cairo-perf-trace  Firefox-asteroids, firefox-scrolling, midori-zommed, gnome-system-monitor</p>
    <p>Software and workloads used in performance tests may have been optimized for performance only on Intel microprocessors. Performance tests, such as SYSmark* and MobileMark*, are measured using specific computer systems, components, software, operations and functions. Any change to any of those factors may cause the results to vary. You should consult other information and performance tests to assist you in fully evaluating your contemplated purchases, including the performance of that product when combined with other products. For more information go to http://www.intel.com/performance.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Windows VM Performance</p>
    <p>Software and workloads used in performance tests may have been optimized for performance only on Intel microprocessors. Performance tests, such as SYSmark* and MobileMark*, are measured using specific computer systems, components, software, operations and functions. Any change to any of those factors may cause the results to vary. You should consult other information and performance tests to assist you in fully evaluating your contemplated purchases, including the performance of that product when combined with other products. For more information go to http://www.intel.com/performance.</p>
    <p>3D Benchmark: 3DMark06, Heaven3D  2D Benchmark: Passmark2D</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Scalability</p>
    <p>Software and workloads used in performance tests may have been optimized for performance only on Intel microprocessors. Performance tests, such as SYSmark* and MobileMark*, are measured using specific computer systems, components, software, operations and functions. Any change to any of those factors may cause the results to vary. You should consult other information and performance tests to assist you in fully evaluating your contemplated purchases, including the performance of that product when combined with other products. For more information go to http://www.intel.com/performance.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overhead Analysis</p>
    <p>Prevent power saving per HW</p>
    <p>spec</p>
    <p>Submit commands</p>
    <p>Allocate/free graphics memory</p>
    <p>The rest Unnecessary in VM!</p>
    <p>Unnecessary in VM!</p>
    <p>Software and workloads used in performance tests may have been optimized for performance only on Intel microprocessors. Performance tests, such as SYSmark* and MobileMark*, are measured using specific computer systems, components, software, operations and functions. Any change to any of those factors may cause the results to vary. You should consult other information and performance tests to assist you in fully evaluating your contemplated purchases, including the performance of that product when combined with other products. For more information go to http://www.intel.com/performance.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Optimization: Removal of PM Access</p>
    <p>Average 60% reduction of trap rate!</p>
    <p>higher performance!</p>
    <p>Software and workloads used in performance tests may have been optimized for performance only on Intel microprocessors. Performance tests, such as SYSmark* and MobileMark*, are measured using specific computer systems, components, software, operations and functions. Any change to any of those factors may cause the results to vary. You should consult other information and performance tests to assist you in fully evaluating your contemplated purchases, including the performance of that product when combined with other products. For more information go to http://www.intel.com/performance.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Graphics Memory Resource Partitioning</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Summary</p>
    <p>Full GPU virtualization + mediated pass-through</p>
    <p>Run native graphics driver in VM</p>
    <p>Good balance for performance, feature and sharing capability</p>
    <p>Publicly available patches  https://github.com/01org/XenGT-Preview-xen</p>
    <p>https://github.com/01org/XenGT-Preview-kernel</p>
    <p>https://github.com/01org/XenGT-Preview-qemu</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Q&amp;A</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Legal Disclaimer</p>
    <p>INFORMATION IN THIS DOCUMENT IS PROVIDED IN CONNECTION WITH INTEL PRODUCTS. NO LICENSE, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, BY ESTOPPEL OR OTHERWISE, TO ANY INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY RIGHTS IS GRANTED BY THIS DOCUMENT. EXCEPT AS PROVIDED IN INTEL'S TERMS AND CONDITIONS OF SALE FOR SUCH PRODUCTS, INTEL ASSUMES NO LIABILITY WHATSOEVER AND INTEL DISCLAIMS ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTY, RELATING TO SALE AND/OR USE OF INTEL PRODUCTS INCLUDING LIABILITY OR WARRANTIES RELATING TO FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR INFRINGEMENT OF ANY PATENT, COPYRIGHT OR OTHER INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY RIGHT. A &quot;Mission Critical Application&quot; is any application in which failure of the Intel Product could result, directly or indirectly, in personal injury or death. SHOULD YOU PURCHASE OR USE INTEL'S PRODUCTS FOR ANY SUCH MISSION CRITICAL APPLICATION, YOU SHALL INDEMNIFY AND HOLD INTEL AND ITS SUBSIDIARIES, SUBCONTRACTORS AND AFFILIATES, AND THE DIRECTORS, OFFICERS, AND EMPLOYEES OF EACH, HARMLESS AGAINST ALL CLAIMS COSTS, DAMAGES, AND EXPENSES AND REASONABLE ATTORNEYS' FEES ARISING OUT OF, DIRECTLY OR INDIRECTLY, ANY CLAIM OF PRODUCT LIABILITY, PERSONAL INJURY, OR DEATH ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF SUCH MISSION CRITICAL APPLICATION, WHETHER OR NOT INTEL OR ITS SUBCONTRACTOR WAS NEGLIGENT IN THE DESIGN, MANUFACTURE, OR WARNING OF THE INTEL PRODUCT OR ANY OF ITS PARTS. Intel may make changes to specifications and product descriptions at any time, without notice. Designers must not rely on the absence or characteristics of any features or instructions marked &quot;reserved&quot; or &quot;undefined&quot;. Intel reserves these for future definition and shall have no responsibility whatsoever for conflicts or incompatibilities arising from future changes to them. The information here is subject to change without notice. Do not finalize a design with this information. The products described in this document may contain design defects or errors known as errata which may cause the product to deviate from published specifications. Current characterized errata are available on request. Contact your local Intel sales office or your distributor to obtain the latest specifications and before placing your product order. Copies of documents which have an order number and are referenced in this document, or other Intel literature, may be obtained by calling 1-800-548-4725, or go to: http://www.intel.com/design/literature.htm Intel, Core, Look Inside, and the Intel logo are trademarks of Intel Corporation in the United States and other countries.</p>
    <p>*Other names and brands may be claimed as the property of others. Copyright  2014 Intel Corporation.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Risk Factors The above statements and any others in this document that refer to plans and expectations for the first quarter, the year and the future are forward-looking statements that involve a number of risks and uncertainties. Words such as anticipates, expects, intends, plans, believes, seeks, estimates, may, will, should and their variations identify forward-looking statements. Statements that refer to or are based on projections, uncertain events or assumptions also identify forward-looking statements. Many factors could affect Intels actual results, and variances from Intels current expectations regarding such factors could cause actual results to differ materially from those expressed in these forward-looking statements. Intel presently considers the following to be the important factors that could cause actual results to differ materially from the companys expectations. Demand could be different from Intel's expectations due to factors including changes in business and economic conditions; customer acceptance of Intels and competitors products; supply constraints and other disruptions affecting customers; changes in customer order patterns including order cancellations; and changes in the level of inventory at customers. Uncertainty in global economic and financial conditions poses a risk that consumers and businesses may defer purchases in response to negative financial events, which could negatively affect product demand and other related matters. Intel operates in intensely competitive industries that are characterized by a high percentage of costs that are fixed or difficult to reduce in the short term and product demand that is highly variable and difficult to forecast. Revenue and the gross margin percentage are affected by the timing of Intel product introductions and the demand for and market acceptance of Intel's products; actions taken by Intel's competitors, including product offerings and introductions, marketing programs and pricing pressures and Intels response to such actions; and Intels ability to respond quickly to technological developments and to incorporate new features into its products. The gross margin percentage could vary significantly from expectations based on capacity utilization; variations in inventory valuation, including variations related to the timing of qualifying products for sale; changes in revenue levels; segment product mix; the timing and execution of the manufacturing ramp and associated costs; start-up costs; excess or obsolete inventory; changes in unit costs; defects or disruptions in the supply of materials or resources; product manufacturing quality/yields; and impairments of long-lived assets, including manufacturing, assembly/test and intangible assets. Intel's results could be affected by adverse economic, social, political and physical/infrastructure conditions in countries where Intel, its customers or its suppliers operate, including military conflict and other security risks, natural disasters, infrastructure disruptions, health concerns and fluctuations in currency exchange rates. Expenses, particularly certain marketing and compensation expenses, as well as restructuring and asset impairment charges, vary depending on the level of demand for Intel's products and the level of revenue and profits. Intels results could be affected by the timing of closing of acquisitions and divestitures. Intel's results could be affected by adverse effects associated with product defects and errata (deviations from published specifications), and by litigation or regulatory matters involving intellectual property, stockholder, consumer, antitrust, disclosure and other issues, such as the litigation and regulatory matters described in Intel's SEC reports. An unfavorable ruling could include monetary damages or an injunction prohibiting Intel from manufacturing or selling one or more products, precluding particular business practices, impacting Intels ability to design its products, or requiring other remedies such as compulsory licensing of intellectual property. A detailed discussion of these and other factors that could affect Intels results is included in Intels SEC filings, including the companys most recent reports on Form 10-Q, Form 10-K and earnings release.</p>
    <p>Rev. 1/16/14</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
