<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Post Retraction Citations in Context Gali Halevi, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</p>
    <p>Judit Bar-Ilan, Bar-Ilan University</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>THE NUMBER OF RETRACTIONS IS ON THE RISE</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Figure 2. Proportion of journals issuing corrections or retractions amongst all journals covered by the Web of Science database, by year.</p>
    <p>Fanelli D (2013) Why Growing Retractions Are (Mostly) a Good Sign. PLoS Med 10(12): e1001563. doi:10.1371/journal.pmed.1001563 http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/article?id=info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1001563</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Background</p>
    <p>There are two types of citations to retracted articles: Citations that a retracted article received prior to its retraction and citations that are received post retraction and despite retraction notices.</p>
    <p>In this study we sought out to find the context around post-retraction citations with the main purpose of finding out whether they are negatively, positively or neutrally mentioned.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Data Collection</p>
    <p>ScienceDirect, Elseviers full text database was accessed in October 2014. The database was queried for the term RETRACTED in the article title and its retraction notice.</p>
    <p>For this study we selected the five top articles that were found to be highly cited since 2015. This ensured that the papers all cite retracted articles</p>
    <p>A total of 1,203 results retrieved from which 988 were retracted articles. The results excluded were retraction notices, duplicates and papers whose original titles included the word &quot;retracted&quot;.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Case study</p>
    <p>For each article we extracted the citing documents and analyzed the ones appearing in 2015 and 2016. Overall, we analyzed 120 citing documents.</p>
    <p>Each mention was categorized as follows:</p>
    <p>Positive: A positive citation indicates that the retracted article was cited as legitimate prior work and its findings used to corroborate the author/s current study.</p>
    <p>Negative: A negative citations indicates that the authors mentioned the retracted article as such and its findings as inappropriate.</p>
    <p>Neutral: A neutral citation indicates that the retracted article was mentioned as a publication that appears in the literature and does not include judgement on its validity.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>EXAMPLES</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sralini, G. E., Clair, E., Mesnage, R., Gress, S., Defarge, N., Malatesta, M., &amp; De</p>
    <p>Vendmois, J. S. (2012). RETRACTED: Long term toxicity of a Roundup herbicide and a Roundup-tolerant</p>
    <p>genetically modified maize. Food and chemical toxicology, 50(11), 4221-4231.</p>
    <p>This article discusses the relationship between GM foods and cancerous tumors in animals.</p>
    <p>This article, published in 2012 was the subject of a debate surrounding the validity of the findings, use of animals and even accusations of fraud.</p>
    <p>Its publication and retraction process have resulted in the Sralini affair which became a big media news item and created a social movement against GM food</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Citations in Context</p>
    <p>This article was cited 109 times since its publication in 2012 with 28 citations tracked after 2014</p>
    <p>More citations are seen to be negative, the positive and neutral ones are also present</p>
    <p>The negative citations mostly point to the media frenzy around the results.</p>
    <p>The study was republished in 2014 by Environmental Sciences Europe. The republished article received 17 citations in 2015 and 2016. The vast majority of them being positive mentions</p>
    <p>NA Negative Neutral Positive</p>
    <p>N u</p>
    <p>m b</p>
    <p>e r o</p>
    <p>f c it</p>
    <p>in g</p>
    <p>a r ti</p>
    <p>c le</p>
    <p>s 2</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Mukherjee, S., Lekli, I., Gurusamy, N., Bertelli, A. A., &amp; Das, D. K. (2009).</p>
    <p>RETRACTED: Expression of the longevity proteins by both red and white wines and their cardioprotective components, resveratrol, tyrosol, and hydroxytyrosol. Free</p>
    <p>Radical Biology and Medicine, 46(5), 573-578.</p>
    <p>This article discusses the benefits of resveratrol for longevity</p>
    <p>The leading author of the paper, Dipak Das and his lab at the University of Connecticut Health Sciences Center were the subject to an ethical investigation by the university.</p>
    <p>The results of the universitys investigation led to the retraction of all of Dr. Das' papers due to scientific misconduct and data manipulation.</p>
    <p>The article, which was retracted in 2012, received 85 citations since its publication in 2009, 21 of which occurred in 2015 through March 2016.</p>
    <p>The vast majority of citations are positive , quoting the articles findings as legitimate.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Walumbwa, F. O., Wang, P., Wang, H., Schaubroeck, J., &amp; Avolio, B. J. (2010).</p>
    <p>RETRACTED Psychological processes linking authentic leadership to follower behaviors.</p>
    <p>This article develops the concept of The authentic leadership</p>
    <p>This article was retracted in 2014 due to serious data manipulation and falsification.</p>
    <p>The article continued to be cited despite the lengthy and detailed retraction notice.</p>
    <p>A close examination of the post retraction citations (2015March 2016) shows that all citations were positive citations, meaning that the citing authors used findings from this article to support their findings.</p>
    <p>The subject of authentic leadership is popular in management studies and has seen a surge in publications since 2012. This could explain the overall positive citations of the article.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Conclusions</p>
    <p>Retracted articles continue to be cited years after retraction and despite retraction notices being posted on publishers platforms.</p>
    <p>This could be the result of general interest by the public or media.</p>
    <p>In other cases, the reason for retraction does not deter others from citing the article.</p>
    <p>We recommend that publishers use reference checks to all submitted articles to detect citations of retracted articles and remove them or at least request an explanation from the authors for citing a retracted paper in a positive or neutral manner</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank you Questions?</p>
    <p>Contact:</p>
    <p>Gali Halevi: gali.halevi@mssm.edu</p>
    <p>JuditBar-Ilan: Judir.Bar-ilan@biu.ac.il</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
