<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Identifying Trends in Enterprise Data Protection Systems</p>
    <p>George Amvrosiadis, University of Toronto</p>
    <p>Medha Bhadkamkar, Symantec Research Labs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>June 10, 2015</p>
    <p>June 24, 2015</p>
    <p>Copyright  2015 Symantec Corporation</p>
    <p>June 25, 2015 [1]</p>
    <p>[2]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We need to fix Backup Systems</p>
    <p>Too many parameters to fine-tune  Top 3 commercial products come with 1000-page admin guides</p>
    <p>Businesses experience problems recovering from backups 1 in 6 times [3]</p>
    <p>Too much data to backup  94% of businesses backup more than just mission-critical data,</p>
    <p>and 40% backup everything [4]</p>
    <p>Only 28% of businesses complete all backups on time [5]</p>
    <p>Complexity and missed goals lead to frustration  55% of businesses plan to change backup tools within 24 months</p>
    <p>Study goal: Use customer data to help researchers understand and improve data protection systems</p>
    <p>Copyright  2015 Symantec Corporation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Storage servers</p>
    <p>Data protection systems are multi-tiered domains  Master server: job scheduling,</p>
    <p>backup image metadata</p>
    <p>Clients: transmit backup data</p>
    <p>Storage servers (optional): backup storage management</p>
    <p>Backup policies specify clients backup schedules  E.g. weekly full, daily incremental backups</p>
    <p>Policy types tailored to applications</p>
    <p>e.g. Oracle, VMware, Microsoft Exchange</p>
    <p>Anatomy of Modern Data Protection Systems Master server</p>
    <p>Clients</p>
    <p>Domain</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Customer domains periodically transmit telemetry  Collected from consenting Symantec NetBackup customers</p>
    <p>Weekly reports of runtime and configuration statistics</p>
    <p>Telemetry allows us to study how domains evolve  Reports can be grouped and analyzed as time series</p>
    <p>Dataset represents large, diverse domain population  1M telemetry reports from 40,000 domains, collected over 3 years</p>
    <p>35% of domains 3-tiered, rest 2-tiered</p>
    <p>31% of domains use dedicated backup appliances</p>
    <p>Study Dataset</p>
    <p>Copyright  2015 Symantec Corporation</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
    <p>Analysis results</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Week</p>
    <p>N u m</p>
    <p>b e</p>
    <p>r o</p>
    <p>f c li e n ts</p>
    <p>Client populations rarely shrink  Client population reaches</p>
    <p>stable state after first 3 weeks</p>
    <p>93% of changes attributed to growth</p>
    <p>Clients are introduced every 3 months, in groups  Low variability across changes, growth bursts 5% of the time</p>
    <p>Domain configuration: Clients</p>
    <p>Copyright  2015 Symantec Corporation</p>
    <p>change point</p>
    <p>change size</p>
    <p>configuration period</p>
    <p>Takeaway: For resource provisioning, keep in mind that clients are added in bursts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Domain components remain unprotected at times  16% of clients spend time unprotected</p>
    <p>Only 32% of domains use a policy to protect master server state</p>
    <p>Domains typically protect fewer than 3 application types  36% of domains deploy</p>
    <p>policies targeted to a single application</p>
    <p>Number of policies stays fixed after first 3 weeks</p>
    <p>Domain configuration: Backup policies</p>
    <p>Copyright  2015 Symantec Corporation</p>
    <p>Number of policy types per domain</p>
    <p>P e</p>
    <p>rc e</p>
    <p>n ta</p>
    <p>g e</p>
    <p>o f d</p>
    <p>o m</p>
    <p>a in</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>CDF</p>
    <p>Median: 1.9 policy types</p>
    <p>Mean: 2.6 policy types</p>
    <p>Takeaway: Domains are homogeneous wrt. client policies, making policy auto-configuration a feasible goal</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Recoveries are rare and sparse  Occur in 1275 domains (3.1%)</p>
    <p>337 domains (0.8%) recover frequently as part of testing</p>
    <p>Frequent full backups are preferred to incremental ones  Full backups are rarely</p>
    <p>weekly events</p>
    <p>Only 33% of frequent full backups are complemented by incremental ones</p>
    <p>Copyright  2015 Symantec Corporation</p>
    <p>Job scheduling: Frequency</p>
    <p>Domains Recovery</p>
    <p>events Avg. event frequency</p>
    <p>Takeaway: Recoverability of images is rarely tested, and frequent full backups are preferred to incremental ones</p>
    <p>% o</p>
    <p>f d</p>
    <p>o m</p>
    <p>a in</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Full backup frequency (days)</p>
    <p>Literature assumption</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Default scheduling windows are popular</p>
    <p>Activity spikes at beginning of scheduling windows (6pm, 12am)</p>
    <p>Administrators schedule fewer jobs during the weekend</p>
    <p>M o</p>
    <p>n 0</p>
    <p>T u</p>
    <p>e 0</p>
    <p>W e</p>
    <p>d 0</p>
    <p>T h</p>
    <p>u 0</p>
    <p>F ri</p>
    <p>:0 0</p>
    <p>S a t</p>
    <p>:0 0</p>
    <p>S u</p>
    <p>n 0</p>
    <p>M o</p>
    <p>n 0</p>
    <p>Hour of the week</p>
    <p>S c h e</p>
    <p>d .</p>
    <p>p ro</p>
    <p>b a</p>
    <p>b il it y (</p>
    <p>% )</p>
    <p>M o</p>
    <p>n 0</p>
    <p>T u</p>
    <p>e 0</p>
    <p>W e</p>
    <p>d 0</p>
    <p>T h</p>
    <p>u 0</p>
    <p>F ri</p>
    <p>:0 0</p>
    <p>S a t</p>
    <p>:0 0</p>
    <p>S u</p>
    <p>n 0</p>
    <p>M o</p>
    <p>n 0</p>
    <p>Hour of the week</p>
    <p>S c h e</p>
    <p>d .</p>
    <p>p ro</p>
    <p>b a</p>
    <p>b il it y (</p>
    <p>% )</p>
    <p>Job scheduling: Timing</p>
    <p>Mon Tue Wed Thu Fri Sat Sun</p>
    <p>unless its the weekend!</p>
    <p>Takeaway: Consistently using the same/default scheduling window creates job bursts</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Incremental backups resemble full backups in size</p>
    <p>Deduplication reduces full backup sizes by 89% on average</p>
    <p>Incremental backups can be larger due to misconfigurations, timestamp modifications by maintenance tasks</p>
    <p>Backup data growth: Job sizes</p>
    <p>Average GB transferred per job</p>
    <p>P e</p>
    <p>rc e</p>
    <p>n ta</p>
    <p>g e</p>
    <p>o f</p>
    <p>d o</p>
    <p>m a in</p>
    <p>s</p>
    <p>Incremental backups</p>
    <p>Full backups</p>
    <p>Recovery operations</p>
    <p>Recovering a few files</p>
    <p>Recovering a volume</p>
    <p>Takeaway: Deduplication may obsolete incremental backups. Recovering only a few files is not uncommon.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>a y 2 3</p>
    <p>e e</p>
    <p>k 2 3</p>
    <p>o 2 3 6</p>
    <p>e a</p>
    <p>r 2 3 5</p>
    <p>Retention period</p>
    <p>P e</p>
    <p>rc e</p>
    <p>n ta</p>
    <p>g e</p>
    <p>o f jo</p>
    <p>b s</p>
    <p>Incremental backups</p>
    <p>(Mean: 25 days)</p>
    <p>Full backups</p>
    <p>(Mean: 40 days)</p>
    <p>94% of retention periods picked from preset values</p>
    <p>Retention time is proportional to backup frequency</p>
    <p>Less frequent full backups are retained longer (x,y = 0.53)</p>
    <p>Backup data growth: Retention periods</p>
    <p>Incremental backups</p>
    <p>retained for weeks</p>
    <p>Full backups retained for</p>
    <p>months</p>
    <p>Takeaway: Retention periods are selected with backup storage capacity in mind</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Outline</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>In summary: Avenues for future research</p>
    <p>Auto-configuration and self-healing backup systems  Clients are introduced in bursts, but may be left unprotected</p>
    <p>Domains are homogeneous wrt. policies protecting clients</p>
    <p>Default scheduling windows are preferred, causing job bursts</p>
    <p>Improve rehydration time of deduplicated backup images  Deduplicated full backups are preferred to incremental ones</p>
    <p>Revisit backup retention as a need-based feature  Dedicated backup appliances are widely used</p>
    <p>Retention periods are picked with storage capacity in mind</p>
    <p>Re-examine techniques for instant recovery  Recovery events made up of few files are not uncommon</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Copyright  2015 Symantec Corporation. All rights reserved. Symantec and the Symantec Logo are trademarks or registered trademarks of Symantec Corporation or its affiliates in the U.S. and other countries. Other names may be trademarks of their respective owners.</p>
    <p>This document is provided for informational purposes only and is not intended as advertising. All warranties relating to the information in this document, either express or implied, are disclaimed to the maximum extent allowed by law. The information in this document is subject to change without notice.</p>
    <p>Thank you:</p>
    <p>Symantec Research Labs, Symantec Backup and Recovery group, University of Toronto SysNet and CSL groups, Fred Douglis and anonymous reviewers</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>References</p>
    <p>[1] M. Jordan, U.S. Visa-Processing Glitch Is Partially Fixed. Wall Street Journal. Updated June 24, 2015.</p>
    <p>[2] Bureau of Consular Affairs, Technological Systems Issue. U.S. Department of State. Updated June 25, 2015.</p>
    <p>[3] Veeam Software, Virtualization Data Protection Report 2013. Analyst report, 2013.</p>
    <p>[4] Iron Mountain, Data Backup and Recovery Benchmark Report. Analyst report, 2013.</p>
    <p>[5] Dimensional Research, The state of IT recovery for SMBs. Analyst report, 2014.</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
