<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>School of Computing ScienceSchool of Computing Science Simon Fraser University, CanadaSimon Fraser University, Canada</p>
    <p>PCP: A Probabilistic Coverage Protocol for Wireless Sensor Networks</p>
    <p>Mohamed Hefeeda and Hossein Ahmadi</p>
    <p>ICNP 07</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Sensor networks have been proposed for many apps: surveillance, forest fire detection,</p>
    <p>Common in most apps: - Each sensor detects events within its sensing range</p>
    <p>- Sensors collaborate to deliver data to processing centre</p>
    <p>Many previous works assume disk sensing model</p>
    <p>MotivationsMotivations</p>
    <p>distance</p>
    <p>Prob. of sensing</p>
    <p>rs</p>
    <p>rs</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Why disk sensing model? - Easier to design and analyze coverage protocols</p>
    <p>What is wrong with it? - Not too realistic [Zou 05, Ahmed 05, Cao 05, ]</p>
    <p>- Wastes sensor capacity: signals dont fall abruptly  chance to detect events after rs</p>
    <p>- Activates more sensors  more interference, shorter network lifetime</p>
    <p>- Protocols my not function in real environments</p>
    <p>Motivations (contd)Motivations (contd)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>New coverage protocol for probabilistic sensing models (denoted by PCP) - Simple, energy efficient</p>
    <p>- Robust against clock drifts, failures, location inaccuracy</p>
    <p>One model does not fit all sensor types  - PCP is designed with limited dependence on sensing</p>
    <p>model  can be used with various sensor types</p>
    <p>PCP can use disk sensing model as well</p>
    <p>Our WorkOur Work</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Lots of coverage protocols assuming disk model - PEAS [Ye 03], OGDC [Zhang 05], CCP [Xing 05],  - We compare PCP (with disk model) vs. OGDC, CCP</p>
    <p>Analysis of probabilistic sensing models - [Liu 04] studies implications of adopting prob. models - [Lazos 06] analyzes prob. of coverage under general</p>
    <p>sensing modes and heterogeneous sensors - Neither presents distributed coverage protocols</p>
    <p>Coverage protocols using probabilistic models - CCANS [Zou 05] assumes exponential sensing model - We show that PCP (with expo model) outperforms</p>
    <p>CCANS by wide margins</p>
    <p>Related WorksRelated Works</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Several models have been proposed in literature  Our protocol can work with various models</p>
    <p>Probabilistic Sensing ModelsProbabilistic Sensing Models</p>
    <p>Expo</p>
    <p>[Zou 05] [Ahmed 05] [Liu 05]</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Def 1: An area A is probabilistically covered with threshold  if for every point x in A:</p>
    <p>Probabilistic Coverage: DefinitionsProbabilistic Coverage: Definitions</p>
    <p>n</p>
    <p>i i xpxP</p>
    <p>)(11)(</p>
    <p>- where pi(x): prob. that sensor i detects events at x</p>
    <p>That is, the collective probability of sensing events at x by all sensors is at least</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Def 2: x is called the least-covered point in A if:</p>
    <p>Probabilistic Coverage: Definitions (contd)Probabilistic Coverage: Definitions (contd)</p>
    <p>yxAyxyPxP</p>
    <p>Ex.: least-covered point by three sensors using expo model</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Activate sensors such that the least-covered point in A has prob of sensing</p>
    <p>To do this in distributed manner, we - divide A into smaller subareas,</p>
    <p>- determine location of the least-covered point,</p>
    <p>- activate sensors to meet  coverage in each subarea</p>
    <p>We choose subareas to be equi-lateral triangles - Activate sensors at vertices, others sleep</p>
    <p>- Yields optimal coverage in disk sensing model [Bai 06]</p>
    <p>Probabilistic Coverage: Basic IdeasProbabilistic Coverage: Basic Ideas</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Size of each triangle? - Stretch the separation between active sensors to the</p>
    <p>maximum while maintaining  coverage</p>
    <p>- Minimize number of activated sensors</p>
    <p>Theorem 1: Maximum Separation under the exponential sensing model is:</p>
    <p>Probabilistic Coverage: Basic Ideas (contd)Probabilistic Coverage: Basic Ideas (contd)</p>
    <p>3 11ln</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>One node randomly enters active state</p>
    <p>The node sends an activation message</p>
    <p>Closest nodes to vertices of triangular mesh activated - Using activation timers as</p>
    <p>function of proximity to vertex</p>
    <p>Activated nodes send activation messages</p>
    <p>PCP: Probabilistic Coverage Protocol PCP: Probabilistic Coverage Protocol</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PCP: Further OptimizationPCP: Further Optimization</p>
    <p>Def 3: -circle is the smallest circle drawn anywhere in A s.t. there is at least one node inside it</p>
    <p>Minimizes number of nodes in WAIT state  saves energy</p>
    <p>The diameter  is computed based on node deployment</p>
    <p>Paper shows calculations for uniform and grid distributions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theorem 2: PCP converges in at most</p>
    <p>steps with every point has a prob. of sensing</p>
    <p>- Convergence time depends only on area size (not number of sensors)  PCP can scale</p>
    <p>PCP: PCP: Convergence and Correctness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theorem 3: PCP activates at most</p>
    <p>nodes to maintain coverage, and exchanges at most that number of messages</p>
    <p>PCP: PCP: Activated Nodes and Message Complexity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Theorem 4: Nodes activated by PCP will be connected if communication range rc is greater than or equal to maximum separation s</p>
    <p>PCP: PCP: Connectivity</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>We implemented PCP - in NS-2; worked fine for up to 1,000 nodes, and - in our own packet level simulator; scaled to more than 20,000</p>
    <p>nodes deployed in a 1 km x 1 km area - Implemented Expo and Disk sensing models</p>
    <p>Used elaborate energy model (Motes) in [Zhang 05][Ye 03]  Rigorous evaluation to</p>
    <p>- Verify correctness - Show robustness - Compare PCP against the state-of-the-art protocols:</p>
    <p>Probabilistic coverage protocol : CCANS  Deterministic coverage protocols : CCP, OGDC</p>
    <p>Only sample results are presented</p>
    <p>Evaluation: SetupEvaluation: Setup</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Connectivity achieved when rc  s</p>
    <p>Significant savings can be achieved by gauging coverage threshold</p>
    <p>Evaluation: Correctness and SavingsEvaluation: Correctness and Savings</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Coverage is maintained even with large: (i) location errors, and (ii) clock drifts</p>
    <p>Cost: slight increase in number of activated sensors</p>
    <p>Evaluation: RobustnessEvaluation: Robustness</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Significant energy savings</p>
    <p>Much longer lifetime</p>
    <p>Evaluation: PCP vs. CCANS Evaluation: PCP vs. CCANS</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>PCP (with disk model) outperforms OGDC and CCP. Why? - Peak in CCP is due to many HELLO messages</p>
    <p>- OGDC takes longer time to converge</p>
    <p>Evaluation: PCP vs. OGDC, CCP Evaluation: PCP vs. OGDC, CCP</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Presented a distributed protocol (PCP) for maintaining coverage under probabilistic and deterministic sensing models - Robust, efficient, and outperforms others</p>
    <p>- More suitable for real environments than others</p>
    <p>PCP Limitation - Does not provide coverage with multiple degrees</p>
    <p>ConclusionsConclusions</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Thank You!Thank You!</p>
    <p>Questions??</p>
    <p>Details are available in the extended version of the paper at:</p>
    <p>http://www.cs.sfu.ca/~mhefeeda</p>
  </div>
</Presentation>
