<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Presentation>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Noam Nisan, Michael Schapira, Gregory Valiant, and Aviv Zohar</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Equilibrium is the basic object of study in game theory.</p>
    <p>Question: How is an equilibrium reached?</p>
    <p>In a truly satisfactory answer each players rule of behavior is simple and locally rational repeated best-response repeated better-response regret-minimization</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Motivation</p>
    <p>Repeated best-response is often employed in practice e.g., Internet routing</p>
    <p>We ask: When is such locallyrational behavior really rational?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Repeated best-response is not always best.</p>
    <p>*the game is solvable through elimination of dominated strategies.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Overview of Results</p>
    <p>We identify a small class of games for which: 1. Repeated best-response converges (quickly)</p>
    <p>from any initial point.</p>
    <p>While small, this class covers several important examples:</p>
    <p>Internet Routing, Cost Sharing, Stable Roommates, Congestion Control.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The Setting</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>The repeated best-response strategy:</p>
    <p>When a players turn arrives, it announces the best response to the latest announcements of others.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Tie Breaking Rules</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Never Best Response (NBR) Strategies</p>
    <p>-10 -15 3</p>
    <p>-3 3 -1</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>NBR-Solvability Def: A game G is NBR-solvable (under some tiebreaking rule) if there exists a sequence of eliminations of NBR strategies from the game that leaves each player with only a single strategy.</p>
    <p>There must be such a sequence for every type configuration of the players.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Clear Outcomes</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Example: Congestion Control  A crude model of TCP congestion control.</p>
    <p>[Godfrey, Schapira, Zohar, Shenker  SIGMETRICS 2010]</p>
    <p>A protocol responsible for scaling back transmission rate in cases of congestion.</p>
    <p>The network is represented by a graph with capacities on the edges.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Each player is a pair of source &amp; target nodes, connected by a simple path, and has some maximal rate of transmission.</p>
    <p>Actions of players: selecting transmission rate (up to limit).</p>
    <p>Utility: amount of flow that reaches destination.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Flow is handled as if routers use Fair Queuing:</p>
    <p>Capacity on each link is equally divided between players that use the link.</p>
    <p>Unused capacity by some player is divided equally among others</p>
    <p>Ce =9</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Adjusting rate to fit bottleneck capacity: equivalent to best reply (with certain tie breaking rules)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results for Congestion Control Thm: The Congestion Control Game with</p>
    <p>routers that follow Fair-Queueing is NBRSolvable with a clear outcome.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Ce</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Eliminate all transmission rates below e* for them.</p>
    <p>If they all transmit at least e*, none will manage to get more through. Eliminate all rates above e*.</p>
    <p>Repeat with the residual graph and remaining players.</p>
    <p>Ce</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Results for Congestion Control Thm: The Congestion Control Game with routers</p>
    <p>that follow Fair-Queueing is NBR-Solvable with a clear outcome.</p>
    <p>Corollaries:  Best-response is incentive compatible  Converges fast regardless of topology</p>
    <p>TCPs actual behavior in this setting can be seen as probing for the best-response.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Other Games</p>
    <p>Matching Uncorrelated markets, interns and hospitals</p>
    <p>Cost-sharing games</p>
    <p>BGP  interdomain routing in the internet.</p>
    <p>See the paper for more details and references!</p>
    <p>d</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page">
    <p>Open Questions:</p>
    <p>Explore other dynamics (e.g., regret minimization) and other equilibria (e.g., mixed Nash, correlated).</p>
    <p>Find an exact characterization of games where repeated best-response is rational.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="page"/>
</Presentation>
